<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhūtakoṭi</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha’</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">“the very limit of reality”</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.5 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">bhutakoti</idno>
                <date>2021-06-08</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-08T22:31:41.492Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-5">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-08T22:32:22.328Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-6">
                    <desc>Auto (knowledgebase-header)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-08T22:32:49.808Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-7">
                    <desc>Auto (knowledgebase-header)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-08T22:33:27.125Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-8">
                    <desc>Auto (knowledgebase-header)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.5" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-9">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="18">Bhūtakoṭi</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-article-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-2"/>
                    <p tid="6">The term “limit of reality”, bhūtakoṭi, appears in a number of sūtras, and frequently in the Prajñāpāramitā literature. It stands for ultimate truth and, as such, is
                        synonymous with intrinsic nature (dharmatā) and suchness (tathatā). For example, this particular equation is made in the Mahāprajñāpāramitāśāstra attributed to Nāgārjuna
                        (Lamotte 2001, p. 47). Elsewhere in his translation of this text, Lamotte cites a number of other canonical sources that provide lists of synonyms for the ultimate nature, all
                        of which include the term bhūtakoṭi (ibid. p. 52, n. 103). While a synonym for the ultimate appears to be the main significance of the term, bhūtakoṭi can also refer to the
                        awakened experience of the ultimate, or even to a quiescent state of a worthy one (arhat) to be avoided by bodhisattvas who vow to remain in cyclic existence as long as
                        suffering remains (Buswell and Lopez 2013, p. 117). In the present sūtra, the equation between the ultimate and the bhūtakoṭi is repeatedly confirmed. In the final exchange
                        concerning this term, we are told that this is not actually a limit, per se. Generally speaking, a limit must be locatable and so, since the bhūtakoṭi transcends location, it
                        is not truly a limit in the ordinary sense of the word. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">Grammatically, bhūtakoṭi is a term that can be read as both a tatpuruṣa and a karmadhāraya compound. In support of reading it as tatpuruṣa, Ratnākaraśānti, when
                        explaining the term in his Muktāvalī, glosses bhūta by tattva (reality), and koṭi by agra (edge, limit) (Tripathi 2001, p. 96). Both words in this compound are nouns. Lamotte
                        also adopted this reading in his translation of the Mahāprajñāpāramitāśāstra where, in the English translation of his work, the term is rendered “peak of existence” (2013, p.
                        47). On the other hand, Edgerton (1953, p. 410) takes bhūtakoṭi to be a karmadhāraya compound, meaning “true goal” (bhūta= true, and koṭi= goal). What may underlie these
                        different interpretations is the fact that the word bhūta can be used both in an adjectival sense of “real/true” as well as a noun, meaning “reality/truth.” In this
                        translation, we have opted to read the term as a tatpuruṣa compound. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-4"/>
                    <p tid="8">Asaṅga’s Compendium of Abhidharma </p>
                    <p tid="9">What is the suchness of auspicious phenomena? It is the two selflessnesses, emptiness, signlessness, the reality limit, the ultimate state, and the expanse of reality. </p>
                    <p tid="10">Why is suchness called suchness? Because it does not transform into something else. </p>
                    <p tid="11">Why is it called emptiness? Because it does not act as the cause of that which is thoroughly afflicted. </p>
                    <p tid="12">Why is it called signless? Because it fully pacifies signs. </p>
                    <p tid="13">Why is it called the reality limit? Because it is a focal object that lacks distortion. </p>
                    <p tid="14">Why is it called the ultimate state? Because it is the pure referent field of ārya transcendent wisdom. </p>
                    <p tid="15">Why is it called the expanse of reality? Because it is the cause of all the Dharmas of śrāvakas, [272] solitary buddhas, and buddhas. </p>
                    <p tid="16">So too you should view the suchness of inauspicious phenomena and the suchness of neutral phenomena like the suchness of auspicious phenomena. </p>
                    <p tid="17">ཆོས་དགེ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་གང་ཞེ་ན། བདག་མེད་པ་རྣམ་པ་གཉིས་དང༌། སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་དང༌། མཚན་མ་མེད་པ་དང༌། ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་དང་དོན་དམ་པ་སྟེ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱང་དེ་ཡིན་ནོ།
                        །ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ཅེས་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། གཞན་དུ་མི་འགྱུར་བ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ཅེས་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མི་རྒྱུ་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ།
                        །ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་མཚན་མ་མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། མཚན་མ་ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་མེད་པའི་དམིགས་པ་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ།
                        །ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་དོན་དམ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། འཕགས་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་དམ་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཞེས་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། ཉན་ཐོས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང༌།
                        སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་རྒྱུ་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-BHUTAKOTI-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>