<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Dhāraṇī</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.1 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-DHARANI"/>
                <idno eft:kb-id="dharani"/>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2021-06-09T21:46:26.263Z" user="mike">09/06/2021 21:46:26</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.1" date-time="2021-06-09T21:30:41.831Z" user="mike">Auto (file-created)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-DHARANI-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">From the Intro to Toh 145 </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-5"/>
                    <title xml:lang="en " dhāraṇī="note" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-6">The Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism  defines and explains dhāraṇī:1 </title>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="7">In Sanskrit “mnemonic device,” “code.” The term is derived  etymologically from the Sanskrit root √dhṛ (“to hold” or “to maintain”),  thus suggesting something that supports, holds, or retains; hence, a  verbal formula believed to “retain” or “encapsulate” the meaning of  lengthier texts and prolix doctrines, thus functioning as a mnemonic  device. It is said that those who memorize these formulae (which may or  may not have semantic meaning) gain the power to retain the fuller  teachings that the dhāraṇī “retain.” Commenting on the <hi rend="small-caps">Bodhisattvabhūmisūtra</hi> <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">[sic</foreign>], Buddhist exegetes, such as  the sixth-century Chinese scholiast <hi rend="small-caps">Jinying  Huiyuan</hi>, describe dhāraṇī as part of the equipment or  accumulation (<hi rend="small-caps">saṃbhāra</hi>) that <hi rend="small-caps">bodhisattvas</hi> need to reach full  enlightenment, and classify dhāraṇī into four categories, i.e., those  associated with (1) teachings (<hi rend="small-caps">dharma</hi>), (2)  meaning (<hi rend="small-caps">artha</hi>), (3) spells (<hi rend="small-caps">mantra</hi>) and (4) acquiescence (<hi rend="small-caps">kṣānti</hi>). The first two types are  involved with learning and remembering the teachings and intent of  Buddhist doctrine and thus function as “codes.” . . . The third type  (<hi rend="small-caps">mantradhāraṇī</hi>) helps  the bodhisattva to overcome adversity, counter baleful influences, and  bestow protection. . . . The fourth type assists the bodhisattva in  acquiescing to the true nature of dharmas as unproduced . . . , giving  him the courage to remain in the world for all sentient beings.</p> </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-8"/>
                    <p tid="8">This informative dictionary entry ends by helpfully describing the  various occurrences of dhāraṇī and suggesting that they are probably not to  be considered proto-tantric texts (contrary to one prevailing theory) but  rather belong to a pan-Buddhist context. However, the Indian Buddhist locus  classicus for a fourfold division of dhāraṇīs is not a sūtra, as stated by  that dictionary, but rather a treatise entitled the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvabhūmi</title>. The relevant passage was also discussed and  translated by Jens Braarvig,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-9">See Braarvig 1985, p. 19–20: “The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvabhūmi</title> divides dhāraṇī into four  types: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmadhāraṇī</foreign>  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">of Dharma], [arthadhāraṇī</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">of the meaning], [mantradhāraṇī</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">of mantras] and [dhāraṇī</foreign> to attain the  tolerance, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>, of a  bodhisattva. By the first type the bodhisattva acquires the power of  remembrance (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">smṛti</foreign>) and  insight (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñā</foreign>) into  the Dharma, and thus is able to retain in memory for endless time any  book merely by hearing it once. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arthadhāraṇī</title> is the same, only here one retains the meaning  of the book, not just the words, as in the first. . . . The third,  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mantradhāraṇī</foreign>, at  first seems to justify the translation ‘magical formula.’ Here, the  bodhisattva acquires the power of concentration, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samādhivaśitā</foreign>, and he  employs the mantras magically to alleviate the sufferings of living  beings . . . the fourth, the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhisattvakṣāntilabhāya dhāraṇī</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī for attaining  the bodhisattva’s tolerance][ . . . </foreign>consists in pondering a mantra until one understands its  meaning, namely that it is without meaning, and accordingly understands  all dharmas as being beyond expression. The bodhisattva’s <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign> is the tolerance of  this state of things, that dharmas are unborn, empty and so on.”</note>  who renders this fourfold classification of dhāraṇī as (1) dhāraṇī of  Dharma, (2) dhāraṇī of the meaning, (3) dhāraṇī of mantras, and (4) dhāraṇī  to attain tolerance. Braarvig also cites the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣaya­matinirdeśa</title>, which characterizes dhāraṇī as both  remembrance itself and the faculty or means of retaining in memory the  teachings of the buddhas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-10">Braarvig 1985, p. 18. </note> Braarvig thus  observes that dhāraṇī became connected with concentration (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samādhi</foreign>), remembrance or  recollection (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">smṛti</foreign>), and  meditation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhyāna</foreign>),  concluding that “dhāraṇī and samādhi naturally belong together; to retain  something in memory, concentration is needed, and remembrance may produce  concentration.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-11">  Braarvig 1985, p. 22.</note>  </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-12"/>
                    <p tid="9">It should be noted that J. S. Negi in his dictionary entry for the  phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">don gyi gzungs</foreign>  (dhāraṇī of the sense) quotes the same fourfold enumeration of dhāraṇī from  the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvabhūmi</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-13">See J. S. Negi 1993–2005, vol. 6,  p. 2318: (1) dhāraṇī of the Dharma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi gzungs</foreign>,<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term"> dharmadhāraṇī</foreign>), (2) dhāraṇī of the sense  (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">don gyi gzungs</foreign>,  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arthadhāraṇī</foreign>), (3)  dhāraṇī of mantras (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gsang sngags  kyi gzungs</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mantradhāraṇī</foreign>), and (4) bodhisattva’s dhāraṇī for gaining  of forbearance, (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byang chub sems  dpa’ bzod pa ’thob par byed pa’i gzungs</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhisattvakṣāntidhāraṇī</foreign>).</note> In a standard modern  Tibetan–Chinese dictionary, moreover, the same four <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzungs kyi sgo</foreign> (access to the  dhāraṇī) appear, but in a different order, while the third one is called  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshig gi gzungs</foreign>  (dhāraṇī of words), instead of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos  kyi gzungs</foreign> (dhāraṇī of Dharma).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-14">See Krang Dbyi-sun 1985, p.  2506.</note> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-15"/>
                    <p tid="10">The topic of dhāraṇī has also received notable attention from Janet  Gyatso, who provides a rich semiotic analysis focusing on the work of the  Tibetan author Dodrupchen Jikten Tenpai Nyima<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-16">This is the phonetic rendering of the  Tibetan name <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo grub chen ’jigs med bstan  pa’i nyi ma</foreign>.</note> (1865–c. 1926). Drawing on the  theories of Charles Sanders Peirce, Gyatso argues that dhāraṇī function as  “iconic signifiers” that represent their signified objects by virtue of  being similar to them.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-17">See Gyatso 1992, p. 179.</note> Noting  common examples of iconic signifiers such as pictures, diagrams, and  metaphors, she argues that dhāraṇīs are analogous to these since—following  the explanation of Dodrupchen—their lack of any conventional meaning is in  fact their meaning: “Again, as the mantric formula itself has no  linguistically expressible meaning, it resembles the thusness that it is  signifying, and so it can be employed as an iconic sign.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-18">Gyatso 1992, p. 191.</note> Here  the idea is that dhāraṇī qua iconic signs can free practitioners from their  own deluded conventions, functioning as “reminders” of inexpressible  emptiness. The assumption is that deluded sentient beings forget the  “profound situation” of emptiness, and gradually may become accustomed to  indexical and symbolic signs that come to be understood as “icons of that  birthless truth.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-19">  Gyatso 1992, p. 195.</note> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-20"/>
                    <p tid="11">Ronald Davidson<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-21">On the different meanings of dhāraṇī and  the Western scholarly reception of the term, see Davidson 2009.</note>  argues that dhāraṇī are “codings” for different elements of Buddhist  tradition including doctrines, syllables, scriptures, ritual powers, the  elimination of negative karma, the destruction of unwholesome psychological  states, essential elements of the Buddhist path, and even the path in its  entirety. In this regard, he criticizes his predecessors for limiting their  analyses of dhāraṇī to intellective and mnemonic functions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-22">Davidson 2009, p. 106.</note> He  also recognizes dhāraṇī as a scriptural genre, describing it as an extremely  diverse phenomenon: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-23"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="12">Dhāraṇīs are phrases/statements/texts that operate in the same  manner as dhāraṇīs as syllables/letters or as mantras, from coding  elements of doctrine to the entire canon to acting as a vehicle for  final liberation. This function yields dhāraṇīs as a genre, which often  includes prayers, aspirations, ritual programs and concluding summaries  of benefits. It is indicative, though, that texts in the genre can have  their mantradhāraṇīs abstracted elsewhere with no sense that there is a  loss of the meaning, just what we might expect for coded  information.[](note id:UT22084-057-004-24)</p> </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-25"/>
                    <p tid="13">Davidson prefaces these characterizations of dhāraṇī by cautioning  that the volume and proliferation of dhāraṇī scriptures and dhāraṇī-related  rites necessitate that any statement concerning dhāraṇīs “requires  qualification almost before it is written.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-26">Davidson 2009, p. 141.</note> He notes that  this situation is exacerbated by the fact that Mahāyāna sūtras “sometimes  contradict each other and, occasionally, themselves.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-27">Davidson 2009, p. 141.  </note> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-28"/>
                    <p tid="14">In his second article on dhāraṇī, Davidson takes a different  approach, using the linguistic tools of historical pragmatics. Drawing on  the work of John Searle, Davidson explores how dhāraṇī texts might be  fruitfully analyzed as consisting of illocutionary acts. He finds nine forms  of such acts in his sources: (1) precipitating assertives that articulate a  problem condition or a miraculous event, (2) directives to speak or perform  the dhāraṇī, with the verb in the imperative or optative, (3) commissive  statements promising to communicate a dhāraṇī, (4) assertives in the forms  of precedent or predictive statements extolling the use of the given dhāraṇī  by a/some/many previous buddhas, (5) assertives as benefit statements that  usually concern the dhāraṇī’s power to ward off disease, poison, possession,  or enemies, or that affirm health, welfare, or soteriological efficacy, (6)  assertive hybrid warning statements, (7) ubiquitous expressives such as  praise, homage, confession, and condemnation, (8) perlocutionary expressives  or assertives about the joy and amazement of the audience who received the  dhāraṇī under discussion, and (9) the mantradhāraṇī itself.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-29">See Davidson 2014, p. 11.</note>  By identifying these nine types of illocutionary acts across his source  texts, Davidson concludes that the dhāraṇī genre is highly formalized—and to  some degree formulaic—working in recognizable pragmatic patterns.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-30">Davidson 2014, p.  52.</note> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-004-31"/>
                    <p tid="15">Gyatso’s and Davidson’s characterizations of dhāraṇī are relevant to  <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Jewel Torch</title>, in which we  find frequent references to the ultimate reality of emptiness and the  various codings and speech acts that Davidson outlines. </p>
                    <p tid="16">10)   Gyatso 1992, p. 195. </p>
                    <p tid="17">11) On the different meanings of dhāraṇī and  the Western scholarly reception of the term, see Davidson 2009. </p>
                    <p tid="18">12) Davidson 2009, p. 106. </p>
                    <p tid="19">13) See Davidson 2009, p. 142. </p>
                    <p tid="20">14) Davidson 2009, p. 141. </p>
                    <p tid="21">15) Davidson 2009, p. 141.  </p>
                    <p tid="22">16) See Davidson 2014, p. 11. </p>
                    <p tid="23">17) Davidson 2014, p.  52. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-DHARANI-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-DHARANI-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a
                        link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh
                            46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>