<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Erroneous Views</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">erroneous-views</idno>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-09T21:37:06.338Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-28">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-29">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">Sixty-Two Erroneous Views from Toh 113 Glossary</head>
                    <list type="section">
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-14"/>
                            <p tid="7">A. Eighteen views based upon the past, which are comprised of: </p>
                            <list type="bullet" rend="letters">
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="8"><!--(a)--> Two views that everything is eternal as a result of clairvoyantly remembering as far back as thirty
                                        intermediate kalpas: </p>
                                    <p tid="9">(1) The belief that the self is eternal, and (2) the belief that the world is eternal.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="10"><!--(b)--> Two views that everything is eternal as a result of clairvoyantly remembering rebirths as far back
                                        as sixty to ninety intermediate kalpas: </p>
                                    <p tid="11">(3) The belief that the self is eternal, and (4) the belief that the world is eternal.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="12"><!--(c)--> Four views of annihilation: </p>
                                    <p tid="13">(5) The belief that apart from Mahābrahmā the world and the other devas are impermanent on seeing clairvoyantly
                                        the demise of other devas in his paradise; (6) the belief that devas in the desire realm who become angered are
                                        impermanent but other devas are eternal, on seeing clairvoyantly the demise of angered devas in in the Trāyastriṃśa
                                        paradise; (7) the belief that devas in the desire realm who are distracted by pleasures are impermanent but other devas
                                        are eternal, on seeing clairvoyantly the demise of devas in in the Trāyastriṃśa paradise because in their enjoyment of
                                        pleasures they forget to eat; and (8) the belief that the four elements are impermanent but mind and mental events are
                                        eternal, on seeing clairvoyantly the cessation of the elements in the formless realm. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="14"><!--(d)--> Four beliefs in the existence and non-existence of limits: </p>
                                    <p tid="15">(9) The belief that self and the world have a limit, on seeing clairvoyantly from the hells to the four dhyānas
                                        only; (10) the belief that self and the world have no limit, on seeing clairvoyantly as far as certain boundaries and
                                        deciding there is more beyond; (11) the belief that there is and there is not a limit, on seeing clairvoyantly the limit
                                        of the human world but not that of the world of Brahmā, and (12) the belief that there neither is nor is not a limit, on
                                        seeing the world of Brahmā and not being able to see that there is a limit or that there is not a limit. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="16"><!--(e)--> Four beliefs of not abandoning the view of immortality when it is argued against: </p>
                                    <p tid="17">(13) because of little wisdom, (14) because of not being trained in their tradition, (15) because of being
                                        trained but <!--Comment:-->(not?) having definite knowledge, and (16) because of being proud thinking there is no answer
                                        to the questions they are asked. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="18"><!--(f)--> The beliefs that there are no causes on the basis of dhyāna and knowledge: </p>
                                    <p tid="19">(17) The belief that all worlds arise without a cause; because having left the existence that is a state of
                                        meditation without perception,
                                        they<!--Comment: Who does “they” refer to? It’s the first time it’s turned up, and doesn’t seem to have an
                     antecedent.--> do not see that there is a subtle basis and believe that senses arise from nothing
                                        and also because they cannot see the atoms that combine to create the world, and (18) the belief that there is no cause
                                        because the wind and clouds appear spontaneously. </p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-15"/>
                            <p tid="20">B. Forty-four views based upon the future, which are comprised of:</p>
                            <list type="bullet" rend="letters">
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="21"><!--(a)--> Sixteen beliefs that there are perceptions: </p>
                                    <p tid="22">(19) The self has perception with form perception <!--Comment:-->(delete "perception"?); (20) the self has
                                        perception without form; (21) the self has perception that has form and is formless; and (22) the self has perception
                                        that has neither form nor is formless. (23) The self has perception that has a limit; (24) the self has perception that
                                        has no limit; (25) the self has perception that both has and does not have a limit; and (26) the self has perception
                                        that is neither with nor without limit. (27) The self has perception that has bliss; (28) the self has perception that
                                        has suffering; (29) the self has perception that has both bliss and suffering; and (30) the self has perception that has
                                        neither bliss nor suffering. (31) The self has a single perception; (32) the self has various perceptions; (33) the self
                                        has small perception; and (34) the self has vast perception.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="23"><!--(b)--> Eight beliefs in the absence of perception: </p>
                                    <p tid="24">(35) The self that has form has no perception, like hair and nails; (36)
                                        a<!--Comment: Should 35 and 39 also begin
                     with “A”?--> self without form has no perception, like space; (37) that which is both has no
                                        perception; and (38) that which is neither has no perception. (39) The self that has a limit has no perception; (40) a
                                        self without limit has no perception; (41) that which is both has no perception; and (42) that which is neither has no
                                        perception. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="25"><!--(c)--> Eight beliefs in there being neither existence nor non-existence of perception: </p>
                                    <p tid="26">(43) The perception of a self that has form is not existent; (44) it is not non-existent; (45) it is not both;
                                        and (46) it is not neither. (47) The perception of a self that has limit is not existent; (48) it is not non-existent;
                                        (49) it is not both; and (50) it is not neither. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="27"><!--(d)--> Seven nihilistic beliefs: </p>
                                    <p tid="28">(51) The humans in the desire realm have no previous or future lives, suffer while alive, and after death there
                                        is oblivion. It is the same for (52) the devas of the desire realm; (53) the devas of the form realm; (54) the devas of
                                        the formless realm of infinite space; (55) the devas of the formless realm of infinite consciousness; (56) the devas of
                                        the formless realm of nothingness; and (57) the devas of the formless realm that is the summit of existence. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="29"><!--(e)--> The belief in nirvāna: </p>
                                    <p tid="30">(58) The devas of the desire realm have no previous or future life, but in this life they have the nirvāna of
                                        the pleasures of their existence. It is the same for (59) the first dhyāna’s meditation on samādhi, and (60) for the
                                        second dhyāna, (61) the third dhyāna, and (62) the fourth dhyāna.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="31">The Three Hundred and Sixty Classes of Heretical Texts and their Teachers</head>
                    <p tid="32">Fifth, the three hundred and sixty classes of heretical texts and their teachers may also be presented in terms of the eleven
                        categories (13.1.2.5). On this [it says in the root verses]: </p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="33">And there are eleven specific categories of heretical texts.</p>
                    </q>
                    <p tid="34">There are three hundred notions concerning the limits of present time (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">da ltar gyi mtha’
                            la rtog pa sum brgya</foreign>), starting with the ten imitators (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mgo snyoms pa
                        bcu</foreign>), which, along with the [aforementioned] eighteen notions concerning the limits of past time and the forty-two notions
                        concerning the limits of future time, add up to three hundred and sixty.</p>
                    <p tid="35">Among them, first of all, those concerning the limits of present time [may be subsumed in the following eleven categories]: </p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-16"/>
                            <p tid="36">The ten imitators which include: (i) conventional extremists who imitate the pious attendants (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nyan thos la mgo snyoms pa mu rtegs tha snyad pa</foreign>); (ii) consumers (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhakṣaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">za ba pa</foreign>) who imitate the
                                hermit buddhas; (iii) atomists (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sūkṣmaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra ba pa</foreign>) who imitate the Cittamātrins, (iv) great atomists (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahāsukṣamaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra ba chen po</foreign>) who imitate the Mādhyamika, (v)
                                ritualists (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs byed pa</foreign>) who imitate Action Tantra, (vi) practitioners
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs spyod pa</foreign>) who imitate Conduct Tantra, (vii) yogins (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs sbyor ba</foreign>) who imitate Union Tantra, (viii) practitioners of intense ascetic
                                discipline (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtul zhugs cher spyod pa</foreign>) who imitate Father Tantra, (ix)
                                appraisers of spiritual triumph (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jaimini</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyal dpogs</foreign>) who imitate Mother Tantras, and (x) acquirers of spiritual triumph (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jayalabdha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyal thob pa</foreign>) who
                                imitate Non-dual Tantra. These [imitators] are held to number one hundred when subdivided according to the five material
                                elements and the sensory elements associated with the five quidities.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-2"> The
                                    source for this passage is Longchen Rabjam’s <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, p. 357. Our text misreads
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’byung ba lnga dang chen po lnga dang khams las las phye ba</foreign>, but
                                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title> offers the more accurate reading of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’byung ba lnga dang chen po lnga yi khams las phye ba</foreign>. That said, the expression <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chen po lnga</foreign> surely implies the five quidities (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">de tsam lnga</foreign>) on which see below, p. XXX. </note>
                                <!-- Footnote is unfinished - missing page number -->
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-17"/>
                            <p tid="37">The nine propounding coherent eternalism (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtag pa ther zug dgu</foreign>) which
                                include: (i) those upholding eternalism in general (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyir rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>),
                                and in particular, (ii) those holding chance and mighty Īśvara to be an eternal creator (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phyva dang dbang phyug byed pa po rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>), (iii) those holding the words of the Vedas to be eternal
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig byed kyi tshig rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>), (iv) those holding an inexpressible
                                soul to be eternal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brjod du med pa’i bdag rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>), (v) those holding
                                objects of knowledge to be eternal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig bya rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>), (vi) those
                                holding attributes to be eternal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yon tan rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>), (vii) those
                                holding primal matter and the soul to be eternal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gtso bdag rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>),
                                (viii) those holding the nine categories [of phenomena] to be eternal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshig gi don dgu
                                    rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>) and (ix) those holding states of knowledge to be eternal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig pa’i gnas rtag par ’dod pa</foreign>). These may number one hundred and one when each of them is appraised in terms of
                                the following eleven aspects: (i) eternal nature (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtag pa’i rang bzhin</foreign>), (ii)
                                soul (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bdag</foreign>), (iii) primal matter (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gtso
                                    bo</foreign>), and in terms of its threefold modification (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam ’gyur
                                gsum</foreign>), (iv) the objects of cognition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig bya</foreign>), (v) the process of
                                cognition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig byed</foreign>), (vi) the states of cognition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig yul</foreign>), (vii) their activation (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyod tshul</foreign>),
                                (viii) their action (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">las</foreign>), (ix) their generic state (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyi</foreign>), (x) their interaction (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’brel ba</foreign>), and (xi) the
                                force of their combined impact (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’bad ’du’i shugs</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-3"> The source for this passage is again <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, pp.
                                    357-358. Some of these key terms are discussed below, in the context of Sāṃkhya. There are some discrepancies between that
                                    source and our text and also the corresponding entry in Nordrang Orgyan 2008, p. 3840, regarding the way in which the eleven
                                    subcategories are tallied. Note also that our text reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’grel pa</foreign> for
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’brel ba</foreign>.</note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-18"/>
                            <p tid="38">The six propounding irrationality (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smyon par smra ba drug</title>) who include: (i) the
                                followers of Jaimini who would establish silence as a reason for the proof of omniscient beings; (ii) the Naiyāyika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig pa can pa</foreign>) who would establish that the attributes of the soul, including
                                happiness and suffering, are objectifiable in all things in order to prove that the soul is present in all things; (iii) the
                                Mīmāṃsika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyod pa ba</foreign>) who would establish that sound is uncreated in order to
                                prove that it is eternal; (iv) the Digambara (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nam mkha’i gos can</foreign>) who would
                                establish the fact that leaves die during the night and that peeled bark will wither in order to prove that wood is animate; (v)
                                the Sāṃkhya (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">grangs can pa</foreign>) who would establish the fact that bark which has
                                been peeled will die as a reason in order to prove that matter is animate; and (vi) the Vaiśeṣika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bye brag pa</foreign>) who would establish that living beings possess life in order to prove that the body of
                                living beings is endowed with a soul. These may number eighteen since in terms of the understanding of compatible factors
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sapakṣa</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mthun phyogs</foreign>)
                                each seeks to prove that their (i) premise (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dam bca’</foreign>), (ii) reason (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hetu</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gtan tshigs</foreign>) and (iii)
                                example (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upamā</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe</foreign>) are
                                    discernible.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-4"> See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, p. 358.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-19"/>
                            <p tid="39"> The seven with faith in meditative concentration (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sgom pa bsam gtan la dad pa
                                    bdun</foreign>) who include: (i) the Bārhaspatya (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phur bu pa</foreign>) who meditate
                                that even relative appearances are non-existent; (ii) the Sāṃkhya (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">grangs can
                                    pa</foreign>) who meditate on emptiness devoid of modifications; (iii) the Saura (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nyi
                                    ma pa</foreign>) who meditate on emptiness by rejecting light; (iv) the followers of Jayadhara (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dzA ya dha ri ba</foreign>) who meditate with one-pointed non-conceptualization, regarding the six aspects of
                                consciousness and their sense objects as defective; (v) the Vaiśeṣika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bye brag
                                    pa</foreign>) who meditate with one-pointed non-recollection, regarding recollection as defective; (vi) the Śaiva (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhi ba pa</foreign>) who meditate without distraction on the nature of mind, considering that
                                all things are mind; and (vii) the Vaidika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig byed pa</foreign>), who meditate in a
                                manner similar to space, having rejected all [dichotomies of] happiness and suffering, or of conceptualization and
                                non-conceptualization. These may also number twenty-eight since each of them may be considered in terms of (i) the essential
                                nature of their focus on meditative stability, (ii) their categories, (iii) their experiences, and (iv) their fruits.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-5"> See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, pp. 358-359. </note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-20"/>
                            <p tid="40">The six teachers propounding nihilism (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chad par smra ba’i ston pa drug</foreign>)
                                who are the aforementioned teachers, starting with Purāṇakāśyapa. Their tenets may also be held to number thirty-two since they
                                seek to understand: (i) past and future lives, (ii) actions, cases and results; (iii) release and liberation, and (iv) an
                                indiscernible soul which does not move, by means of: (i) the single approach, (ii-iv) the three examples and (v-viii) the four
                                modalities. The single approach (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyu gcig</foreign>) is so called because none of these
                                is discerned within the perceptual range of one’s own sense faculties. </p>
                            <p tid="41">The three examples (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe gsum</foreign>) comprise: (i) the example of
                                non-causation, which is the bursting forth of mushrooms on the grasslands; (ii) the example of non-fruition which is the
                                scattering of dust by the wind; and (iii) the example of natural emergence which corresponds to the verse: ‘waterfalls at
                                sunrise, peas that are round, thorns with tips that are long and sharp, princesses who are lovely to behold—all these appear
                                naturally, uncreated by anyone!’<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-6"> A similar quotation also occurs in the
                                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Grub mtha mdzod</title>, p. 54, on which see Barron 2007: 65; and also in the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gSang snying spyi don yid kyi mun sel</title>, p. 30.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p tid="42">The four modalities (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshul bzhi</foreign>) comprise: (i) the modality through
                                which happiness, suffering and so forth exist here in the present life, although there are no past or future lives; (ii) the
                                modality through which suddenly arising corporeal forms are naturally present of their own accord when they take shape, even
                                though the soul and primal matter are [supposed to be] unchanging through past and future lives; (iii) the modality through
                                which living beings are formed from the suddenly arising material compositions of the five material elements, including earth,
                                that enable awareness to develop;<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-7"> Our text appears to be corrupt in reading
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">la sogs</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sa sogs</foreign>,
                                    and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">grol ba grub pa’i tshul</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’gro ba grub pa’i tshul</foreign>. See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, p. 359.</note> and (iv) the
                                modality through which, when one understands the fact that there is no cause and effect, since beings are not released through
                                the austerities of refining the path, but they are released naturally, there will be no need to rely on hardships in this life
                                and so the textual tradition of the Lokāyatika will not be rendered meaningless—when beings pass away, they all abide in an
                                identical state of release. Accordingly, various sources (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ra ma ra rnams</foreign>)
                                    assert:<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-8"> See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, pp. 359-360.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <q>
                                <lg tid="54">
                                    <l>Owing to the three examples and the four modalities,</l>
                                    <l>All things are definitively established in the single approach.</l>
                                    <l>Since entities are entirely without cause,</l>
                                    <l>How could the release of liberation be possible!</l>
                                </lg>
                            </q>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-21"/>
                            <p tid="47">The six ministers (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">blon po drug</foreign>) including the masters: (i)
                                Abhayaprāpta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’jigs med thob</foreign>); (ii) Somabhāskarakīrti (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nyi zla grags</foreign>), (iii) Sāraprāpta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snying po
                                    thob</foreign>); (iv) Satyaprāpta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bden pa thob</foreign>); (v) Jñānavāda (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shes par smra</foreign>); and (vi) Maṅgalaprāpta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bkra
                                    shis thob</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-9"> The Sanskrit names given here are all unattested
                                    reconstructions. On this passage, see <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, p. 360. </note> They claim that
                                whatever is active and present in the world is true, contrary to the Buddhists and the extremists. For this reason, they esteem
                                six repositories of knowledge (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig pa’i mdzod drug</foreign>), namely: the planets, the
                                constellations, the seasons, the gods, topics of scrutiny (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtag pa’i gnas</foreign>) and
                                rituals (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid bsrung ba</foreign>); and they emphasize positive and negative ideas with
                                regard to the present alone. In terms of their practical application, these six fields [of knowledge] may be reduced to three.
                                That is to say, there are astrologers who disclose the positive and negative impacts of the planets, constellations, and
                                calendar days; kings who protect their subjects by knowing the laws that derive from the lineage of universal monarchs and so
                                forth who maintain the righteousness (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos lugs</foreign>) of the gods; merchants who
                                engage in distinctive topics of scrutiny, of horses, elephants, oceans and so forth; priests who differentiate matters of state,
                                such as [the prospects for] victory and defeat; and ordinary citizens who engage in their seasonal livelihood. But these may be
                                subsumed in the three categories of kings, scientists and citizens, so that the priests,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-10"> Our text (Sichuan ed. p. 697) and <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, p. 360
                                    both read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">blon po</foreign> (“ministers”) for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdun na ‘don</foreign> (“priests”) at this point. </note> merchants and ordinary citizens are rolled into one. Their
                                fields of knowledge may also number thirty-six since there are six common [fields of knowledge] and then these six may be
                                [differently] understood by kings, ministers [or priests], scientists, merchants, and ordinary citizens.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-11"> This would surely engender an enumeration of thirty rather than thirty-six. Nordrang
                                    Orgyan 2008: 3841 is similarly perplexed.</note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-22"/>
                            <p tid="48">The four types of incidental extremists (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhar byung gi mu stegs bzhi</foreign>),
                                including: (i) the aspirant (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mos pa</foreign>), (ii) the attached (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chags pa</foreign>), (iii) the distracted (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yengs
                                    pa</foreign>), and (iv) the perceptive who are being distracted (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gYeng ba’i ’du shes
                                    can</foreign>). They all hold that by indulging in the happiness of this life they will attain liberation. They are four in
                                number because they respectively: aspire to the desirable attributes of the senses, they are attached to them, they have been
                                distracted by them and they are being distracted by them.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-23"/>
                            <p tid="49"> There are six exponents of sophistry (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tarka sde drug</foreign>), namely: (i)
                                those whose [rambling] reasoning resemble a breeze driving a donkey (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ser bu bong ’ded gyi
                                    sde</foreign>), (ii) those whose [absurd] reasoning resembles eating the skin and flesh of a wall (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsig lpags sha zan gyi sde</foreign>), (iii) those whose [incredible] reasoning resembles the
                                sight of a fox’s head (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">va mgo re thong gi sde</foreign>), (iv) those who are materialists
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">‘jig rten rgyan ’phen pa’i sde</foreign>), (v) those who always deny causality
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyu ’bras gtan med kyi sde</foreign>), and (vi) those who espouse meaningless
                                apathy (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phyal pa don med kyi sde</foreign>). These six modes derive from their [common
                                belief in] the non-existence of causes.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-12"> See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma
                                        dkar po</title>, p. 361. </note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-24"/>
                            <p tid="50"> The four false views regarding causes (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyur lta ba bzhi</foreign>), namely: (i)
                                the false view of nature as a cause (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rang bzhin rgyur lta ba</foreign>); (ii) the false
                                view of a creator [Brahmā divinity] as a cause (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byed po rgyur lta ba</foreign>); (iii)
                                the false view of Īśvara as a cause (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang phyug rgyur lta ba</foreign>); and (iv) the
                                false view of time as a cause (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dus rgyur lta ba</foreign>). These four are established as
                                such because they derive from the false view of eternalism.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-25"/>
                            <p tid="51">The two [pre-eminent] preceptors [propagating such views] (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkhan po
                                    gnyis</foreign>), namely Śaṅkara (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dung ’dzin</foreign>), the master of the
                                eternalists; and Bṛhaspati, the master of the nihilists. These two are respectively the primary [exponents] of eternalism and
                                nihilism.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-26"/>
                            <p tid="52"> The Vedāntaupaniṣadika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs byed kyi mtha’ gsang ba pa</foreign>) who are
                                included among the Mīmāṃsika.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-27"/>
                    <p tid="53">So it is that there are one hundred imitative philosophical systems (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mgo snyoms pa’i grub
                            mtha’ brgya</foreign>), one hundred and one eternalist views (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtag pa ba’i brgya rtsa
                            gcig</foreign>), eighteen irrational views (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">smyon par smra ba’i bco brgyad</foreign>),
                        twenty-eight false views of meditators (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsam gtan pa’i nyi shu rtsa brgyad</foreign>), thirty-six
                        false views of [nihilistic] ministers (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">blon po drug gi sum cu rtsa drug</foreign>), four
                        incidental false views (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhar byung gi bzhi</foreign>), six exponents of sophistry (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tarka sde drug</foreign>), four false views regarding causes (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyur lta ba bzhi</foreign>), two [primary] preceptors (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkhan po gnyis</foreign>), and the
                        Aupaniṣadika (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gsang ba pa</foreign>). Together these comprise the three hundred [false views]
                        which depend on the limit of present time.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-13"> This calculation of three hundred and
                            sixty omits the fifth of the eleven categories, comprising the six teachers who espouse nihilism and their thirty-two views. That
                            same group is also excluded from the list found in the source text, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Padma dkar po</title>, p. 361,
                            presumably because the immediately following list of the thirty-six ministers is reckoned to subsume both. </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-ERRONEOUS-VIEWS-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>