<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Foremost Qualities of Śrāvaka Disciples</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.1 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-FOREMOST-QUALITIES-SRAVAKA-DISCIPLES"/>
                <idno eft:kb-id="foremost-qualities-sravaka-disciples"/>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2021-06-23T16:14:31.818Z" user="john">23/06/2021 16:14:31</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.1" date-time="2021-06-09T22:17:16.216Z" user="mike">Auto (file-created)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-FOREMOST-QUALITIES-SRAVAKA-DISCIPLES-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">The Śrāvaka Disciples </head>
                    <head type="nonStructuralBreak" tid="7">from the Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra: </head>
                    <p tid="8">The list is incidental to the main narrative in this passage, in which Maitreya demonstrates his mastery of the śūraṃgamasamādhi by manifesting, to all the bodhisattvas in the assembly, in all kinds of forms in all the worlds of the trichiliocosm, including those of the ten foremost śrāvakas: </p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="9">Ānanda – the Tathāgata’s attendant (upasthāyaka, de bzhin gshegs pa’i g.yog byed). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="10">Śāriputra – foremost of those with great wisdom (mahāprajñāvatām agryaḥ, shes rab che). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="11">Maudgalyāyana – foremost of those with great supernormal powers (ṛddhimatām agryaḥ, rdzu ’phrul che). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="12">Mahākāśyapa – foremost of those who observe the ascetic practices (dhūtaguṇavādinām agryaḥ, sbyangs pa smra). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="13">Pūrṇa – foremost of those who expound the Dharma (dharmakathikānām agryaḥ, chos smrar ba por gyur). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="14">Rāhula – foremost of those who like to train themselves (śikṣākāmānām agryaḥ, bslab pa ’dod par gyur). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15">Upāli – foremost of those who hold the vinaya (vinayadharāṇām agryaḥ, ’dul ba ’dzin). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="16">Aniruddha – foremost of those who have the divine eye (divyacakṣukānām agryaḥ, lha’i mig dang ldan). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">Revata – foremost of those in meditative absorption (dhyāyinām agryaḥ, bsam gtan par gyur). </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p tid="18">10. Subhūti – foremost of those staying without kleśas (araṇavihāriṇām agryaḥ, nyon mongs pa med par gnas pa’i mchog tu gyur). </p>
                    <p tid="19">Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra (Toh 132), Degé Kangyur vol. 55 (mdo sde, da), F.305.b. </p>
                    <head type="nonStructuralBreak" tid="20">nyan thos mchog brgyad </head>
                    <head type="nonStructuralBreak" tid="21">from Dungkar: </head>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="22">Śāriputra – Great wisdom (shes rab can) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="23">Maudgalyāyana – great supernatural powers (rdzu ’phrul can) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="24">Subhūti – interest in the profound (zab mo la mos pa) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="25">Aniruddha – having the divine eye (lha’i mig ldan) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="26">Dravya Mallaputra (gyad nor bu) – assigner of lodgings (mal stan bgo ba, vaiyāpṛtyakara) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="27">Udāyin – arousing faith in householders (khyim bdag dad pa skyes pa) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="28">Ānanda – learning (mang du thos pa) </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="29">Rāhula – respect for training (bslab pa la gus pa) </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p tid="30">Mahākāśyapa was known as “the foremost among the upholders of the ascetic practices” (dhūtaguṇavādinām agraḥ) and was the Buddha’s successor as leader of the saṅgha after the parinirvāṇa. </p>
                    <p tid="31">Śāriputra—foremost of the wise, “second only to the Buddha in his knowledge of the Dharma”—attained the state of arhat two weeks after going forth, after hearing the Dīrghanakaparivrājakaparipṛcchā </p>
                    <p tid="32">Maudgalyāyana / Mahāmaudgalyāyana – foremost in supranormal powers (ṛddhi) – attained the state of arhat seven days after going forth </p>
                    <p tid="33">Ānanda (from email sent 5/9/2020): he had no less than five “foremost in…” distinctions (no-one else had more than two): as well as that of “foremost attendant" (upaṭṭhakānaṁ), he was foremost in having “heard much” (bahussutānaṁ), “good memory” (satimantānaṁ), “mastery of the structure of the teachings” (gatimantānaṁ), and “steadfast in study” (dhitimantānaṁ) (all from Bodhi/ Nyanaponika/Hecker, Great Disciples of the Buddha). </p>
                </div>
    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-FOREMOST-QUALITIES-SRAVAKA-DISCIPLES-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="34">Pali Souces </head>
                    <p tid="35">See https://84000.org/tipitaka/english/metta.lk/20i146-e.php </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-FOREMOST-QUALITIES-SRAVAKA-DISCIPLES-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-FOREMOST-QUALITIES-SRAVAKA-DISCIPLES-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>