<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<tei:TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Khotan and Khotanese</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.1 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE"/>
                <idno eft:kb-id="khotan-khotanese"/>
                <date>2021-06-29</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2021-06-29T19:58:34.542Z" user="celso">29/06/2021 19:58:34</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.1" date-time="2021-06-29T09:53:09.893Z" user="mike">Auto (file-created)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="47">Khotan</head>
                    <p tid="5">The once great city-state of Khotan, called <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">li yul </foreign>in Tibetan,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-3"> Another
                        name by which Khotan is known in some Tibetan texts is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha sha</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha sa</foreign>, which may be related to the Indic name <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Kaṃsadeśa</foreign>. It is not clear where the Tibetan rendering <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">li</foreign> might have
                        come from, and at some periods of Tibetan history not all scholars seem to have been clear about the country to which that name
                        referred, some assuming it sometimes or always meant Nepal. Dungkar’s dictionary devotes no less than two columns to a discussion of
                        different scholars’ views on the subject; see Dungkar 2002, pp. 1956-7. See also Introduction x.xx, n.3, and Stein 1907, p. 153.</note>
                    is today called Hotan (or Hetian) and is located in China’s Xinjiang province. An oasis kingdom on the southwest edge of the vast
                    Taklamakhan desert that fills the Tarim Basin, Khotan lies to the north of the Kunlun mountain range, which divides it from present-day
                    Ladakh to the southwest and from Western Tibet to the southeast. It was an important trade center on the southern branch of the Silk Route,
                    which from Kashgar followed the southern side of the desert through Khotan and Shanshan to Lop Nor and Dunhuang, while the more important
                    northern Silk Route reached Dunhuang from Kashgar along the northern edge of the desert through Kucha and Karashahr. </p>
                
                <p tid="6">During the last few centuries before the Christian Era and the first millennium CE, the Silk Route as a whole—almost the only conduit for
                    high value trade between China and the rest of East Asia and the classical civilizations of Europe, the Arab world, Turkey, Persia, and
                    India—gave rise to unparalleled wealth in the small countries, kingdoms, and city states along it, allowing agriculture to be sustained by
                    complex irrigation schemes as well as the funding of artistic, literary, and spiritual pursuits, all favoring a high level of cultural
                    diversity and exchange.</p>
                
                <p tid="7">The earliest cultural influence on Khotan may have been Iranian.</p>
                
                <p tid="8">Indian Buddhist sources, including the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aśokāvadāna</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kunālāvadāna</title>, give
                    differing accounts of a son of Aśoka named Kunāla (or Kustana in the Kharoṣṭhī manuscripts, but according to Brough 1948, p. 334 n.6,
                    following Lévi and Bailey, the indigenous form in Khotanese was Gostana), who—after either having been blinded as a child by a jealous
                    stepmother, or banished by Aśoka himself as a threat to his reign, or appointed as governor of Gandhāra—settled in Khotan as a founding
                    ruler. His name constitutes one postulated origin of the name Khotan, and he is identified with Suckler of the Earth Breast in this and the
                    other Tibetan texts on Khotan. </p>
                
                <p tid="9">According to <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li’i yul lung bstan
                    pa</title>, Toh 4202) the wandering Kustana / Gostana had been adopted, at Vaiśravaṇa’s behest, by the king of China, who wanted thereby to
                    add to his 999 sons and round up the number to 1,000. According to some versions of the story, therefore, Gostana arrived in Khotan as
                    representing China along with some Chinese subjects, while from India came the minister Yaśa with his own contingent of dissident subjects
                    of Aśoka; they joined forces and this constituted the population of Khotan.</p>
                
                <p tid="10">Whatever historical facts may have given rise to the legends, at some time during or following the rule of Aśoka in India, Khotan became an
                    outpost of Indian culture and gradually, during the first millennium <hi rend="small-caps">CE,</hi> a place where Chinese merchants, monks,
                    and scholars encountered Indian Buddhist doctrine, practices, and texts. It therefore had an important role in the transmission of Buddhism
                    to China and the rest of east Asia.</p>
                
                <p tid="11">Tibetans, too, may have encountered some aspects of the Indian Buddhist traditions in Khotan. Khotan was invaded by the Tibetans a little
                    after the mid seventh century <hi rend="small-caps">CE</hi> at a time when, in the reigns of Songtsen Gampo and his successors, Tibetan
                    political and military power were expanding. Khotanese accounts of the time saw the arrival of the Tibetans as destructive of Buddhist
                    institutions there, and although the Tibetan court had recently begun to adopt Buddhist culture it is likely that its influence had not yet
                    reached the far-flung army commanders. However, soon afterwards it appears that Tibetan occupation had proved relatively benign to Khotan’s
                    Buddhists, and for the next three centuries while Khotan was twice subject to Tibetan administration (rule by China, lasting from the late
                    seventh to late eighth century CE, intervened between the two periods of Tibetan administration) the cultural ties between Tibet and Khotan
                    grew stronger.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-10"> See van Schaik 2016, pp. 50-52.</note> Indeed, some scholars attribute considerable importance to Khotan in
                    the establishment of Buddhism in Tibet. Khotanese monks seem to have been welcomed in Tibet in the early eighth century by the Chinese queen
                    of Tridé Tsukten, father of Trisong Deutsen, and for several centuries even after the collapse of the Tibetan imperial power in the mid
                    ninth century Tibetan and Khotanese monks and scholars were in frequent contact in Dunhuang and other cultural centers in Central Asia.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-11"> See Snellgrove 1987, vol. 2, pp. 331-43; van Schaik 2016, pp. 51-61.</note>
                </p>
                
                <p tid="12">Of the many oasis kingdoms on both sides of the Tarim Basin, Khotan was among the most prosperous and orderly, and sustained large
                    communities of monks and nuns, as described by both Faxian and Xuanzang, the great Chinese monk travellers of the early fifth and seventh
                    centuries, respectively. Later, wealth came from jade, washed down in the rivers from deposits in the mountains; Khotanese jade was highly
                    valued in China.</p>
                
                <p tid="13">Military conflicts, successive invasions, and the gradual evolution of alternative, maritime trade routes between the Western and Eastern
                    worlds led to dwindling importance of the Silk Routes and concomitant decline of the cultures that had been sustained by them.</p>
                
                <p tid="14">Buddhist texts in Khotan until the sixth century seem to have been in Gāndhārī, written in the Kharoṣṭhī script, but from the sixth century
                    CE onward in Khotanese, a Middle Iranian form of Indo-European that developed from the vernacular of the region and was written in Brāhmī
                    script. A considerable range of Buddhist literature in Khotanese, mostly Mahāyāna texts and many represented only by fragmentary
                    manuscripts, has been identified. Many such texts must have circulated in Tibet as Buddhism took root there, alongside texts in other
                    Central Asian languages, Chinese, and increasingly—as the great imperial period of translations gathered pace—in Sanskrit. </p>
                
                <p tid="15">The standard Tibetan rendering of Khotan is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">li yul</foreign>.</p>
                
                <p tid="16">In Toh 257 (see below) it seems to be referred to as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha sha</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha sha’i yul</foreign>, (or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha za</foreign>) which may correspond to Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khāṣya</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khaśa</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khasa</foreign> as referring to a people (see Edgerton).</p>
                </div>
                
               <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-2"> 
                   <head type="section" tid="48">Khotanese</head>
                
                <p tid="18">Buddhist texts in Khotan until the sixth century seem to have been in Gāndhārī, written in the Kharoṣṭhī script, but from the sixth century
                    CE onward in Khotanese, a Middle Iranian form of Indo-European that developed from the vernacular of the region and was written in Brāhmī
                    script. A considerable range of Buddhist literature in Khotanese, mostly Mahāyāna texts and many represented only by fragmentary
                    manuscripts, has been identified. Many such texts must have circulated in Tibet as Buddhism took root there, alongside texts in other
                    Central Asian languages, Chinese, and increasingly—as the great imperial period of translations gathered pace—in Sanskrit. </p>
                
                <p tid="19">A written script or language called Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khāsyalipi</foreign> may be early Khotanese, i.e.
                    Kharoṣṭhī.</p>
                
                <p tid="20">See Negi qv <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kha sha’i yi ge</foreign>: khāśyalipiḥ (khāsyalipiḥ, khāṣyalipiḥ), lipiviśeṣaḥ — katamāṃ
                    me bho upādhyāya lipiṃ śikṣāpayasi | brāhmīkharoṣṭīpuṣkarasārimaṅgalipim…daradalipiṃ khāṣya(khāsya)lipiṃ cīnalipim…| āsāṃ bho upādhyāya
                    catuṣṣaṣṭilipīnām la.vi.66kha/88; dra. ཁ་ཤའི་ལུང་པ khaśadroṇiḥ ma.mū.199ka/214.</p>
                
                <p tid="21">For written communications and texts, Khotan probably used a Gāndhārī Prakrit written in Kharoṣṭī script until after the 6th century, when
                    vernacular Khotanese, a Middle Iranian branch of the Indo-European language family, and written in the Brāhmī script used all over Northern
                    India, became more prominent. </p>
                
                <p tid="22">Texts in Khotanese have been found in several Central Asian sites including Dunhuang, including the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aparimitāyurjñānasūtra</title> (Toh 675).</p>
                
                <p tid="23">Canonical texts related to Khotan</p>
                
                <p tid="24">Toh 168 <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhāparipṛcchā</title>
                </p>
                
                <p tid="25">Toh 257 <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sūryagarbha-mahāvaipulya</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu rgyas pa chen po’i sde nyi ma’i snying
                        po</title>)</p>
                
                <p tid="26">Toh 357 <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>)</p>
                
                <p tid="27">Toh 4201 <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa dge 'dun 'phel gyis lung bstan pa</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arhatsaṅghavardhanavyākaraṇa</title>)</p>
                
                <p tid="28">Toh 4202 <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li’i yul lung bstan pa</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kaṃsadeśavyākaraṇa</title>)</p>
                
                <p tid="29">In <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Vimalaprabhā</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhāparipṛcchā</title>, Toh 168), the
                    princess Vimalaprabhā, bodhisattva daughter of King Ajātaśatru of Magadha, receives a detailed prophecy of her future lives as a series of
                    important and powerful female figures in Khotan, including one as the powerful rakṣasī Xxxx and especially a life as the formidable lady
                    Rabngé, sister of the king of one neighboring country (Skardo), widow of the king of another (The Gold Country), Buddhist nun, and
                    protectress of Khotan at the time of an invasion by the Tibetans. Other figures in Vimalaprabhā’s family, as well as Vaiśravaṇa and others,
                    are prophesied in various supporting roles.</p>
                
                <p tid="30">In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sūryagarbha-mahāvaipulya</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu rgyas pa chen po’i sde nyi ma’i snying
                        po</title>, Toh 257), a passage of the text summarizes the story of the Buddha’s visit to Khotan to bless the landscape that is told in
                    detail in <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357).</p>
                
                <p tid="31">In <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357), the Buddha,
                    toward the end of his life, flies from Rajgṛha to Khotan, where he blesses the landscape, causes the lake covering the country to be drained
                    away, and predicts the sites of stūpas and monasteries that will be founded as the Dharma takes root and spreads there.</p>
                
                <p tid="32">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arhatsaṅghavardhanavyākaraṇa</title> (Toh 4201) is structured along the lines of the descriptions of the decline
                    of the Dharma in India as told in a number of texts, but goes into considerable detail regarding the future expulsion of Buddhist monks from
                    Khotan and the difficulties they will encounter as they travel through Tibet to India. </p>
                
                <p tid="33">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li’i yul lung bstan pa</title>, Toh
                    4202)</p>
                
                <p tid="34">From Chomden Rikpai Raltri’s text catalogue (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan rigs pa’i ral gri</title>):</p>
                
                <p tid="35">(p. 150) “And translated by other lotsāwas who knew many different languages, translators from Khotanese included Khotanese Khenpo
                    Surendrākaraprabha, and the editor-lotsāwa Gelong Namkha.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-36"> Is this the same translator as Nam mkha’ translator of the Heart
                        Sūtra? See also Toh 3818.</note>
                </p>
                
                <p tid="36">Khotan is situated behind the snow mountains of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chags po</foreign> (?? <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">chags po gangs kyi rgyab na</foreign>), and the [texts] translated from [Khotanese] are:</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-3">
                    <head type="section" tid="49">Western Interest in Khotan and its Literature</head>
                    
                    <p tid="38">The first scholar in the West to take an interest in Khotan seems to have been the nineteenth century French Sinologist, Abel Rémusat in
                        1820 with a study of Chinese texts about Khotan. W. Woodville Rockhill drew attention to the Tibetan texts on Khotan in his <title xml:lang="en">Life of the Buddha</title>, published in 1884, while Édouard Chavannes and Sylvain Lévi published articles mentioning
                        Khotanese texts in 1903 and 1905. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="39">A few years earlier, in 1900, following the first discoveries of Kharoṣṭhī manuscripts on birch-bark in Kuchā and Khotan by other
                        expeditions and the studies of them by Émile Senart and Rudolf Hoernle, the great explorer of Central Asia, Sir Aurel Stein, had already
                        set out on his expedition to Chinese Turkestan. In 1907, Stein published a full account of his archaeological findings together with a
                        wealth of geographical, historical, and linguistic observations, identifying and describing the sacred geography and architecture
                        mentioned in this sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-40"> See Stein 1907, in particular pp. 185–90. </note>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p tid="40">Stein’s initial work on the Tibetan texts was subsequently developed further by Frederick Thomas, culminating in the publication in 1935
                        of complete English translations of the and of the other most closely associated texts mentioned above, <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Questions of Vimalaprabhā</title> (Toh 168), <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of the Arhat Saṅghavardhana</title> (Toh 4201) and
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> (Toh 4202), along with extracts from some other related
                            works.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-42"> Thomas 1935, in particular pp. 1–38.</note>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p tid="41">More recently, in 1967, Ronald Emmerick published translations of the two parts of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land
                            of Khotan</title> (Toh 4202). He has also published translations from Khotanese of works, and a guide to Khotanese literature. A
                        useful article by van Schaik published in 2016 summarizes studies of the Khotanese literature in general and on Khotanese works among
                        the texts found in Dunhuang, including those by Karashima, Kumamoto, Skjaervø, van Schaik, and Zhang and Rong. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="42">This English translation was prepared based on the Tibetan translation in the Degé Kangyur in consultation with the Comparative Edition
                        (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and the Stok Palace Kangyur. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="43">Jan Nattier, in <title xml:lang="en">Once Upon a Future Time: Studies in a Buddhist Prophecy of Decline</title> (1991), traces the
                        development of the Buddhist “prophetic history” literature including a detailed account and analysis of the Khotanese texts mentioned
                        here.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="44">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="46">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-listBibl-1">
                  
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-46"> (see many articles in Indo-Iranian Journal)</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-47">Brough, John. “Legends of Khotan and Nepal,” in <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies,
                            University of London</title>, vol. 12, no. 2, pp. 333–9. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1948. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-48">Chopel, Gendun. <title xml:lang="en">Grains of Gold: Tales of a Cosmopolitan Traveler</title>. Translated by Thupten Jinpa and Donald
                        S. Lopez. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-49">Emmerick, Ronald E. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Texts Concerning Khotan</title>. London: Oxford University Press, 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-50">————. The Book of Zambasta, a Khotanese poem on Buddhism (London Oriental Series 21), Oxford University Press: London, 1968, pp. xxii
                        + 455.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-51">————. <title xml:lang="en">The Book of Zambasta: A Khotanese Poem on Buddhism</title>. London: Oxford University Press. 1968. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-52">————. <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Golden Light, being a translation of the Suvarṇabhāsottamasūtra</title> (Sacred Books of the
                        Buddhists XXVII). London: Luzac and Company Ltd, 1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-53">————. <title xml:lang="en">The Khotanese Śūraṅgamasamādhisūtra</title> (London Oriental Series 23), Oxford University Press: London
                        1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-54">————. <title xml:lang="en">A Guide to the Literature of Khotan</title>. Tokyo: The International Institute for Buddhist Studies, 1992. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-55">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten
                            buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-56">Hoernle, A. R Rudolf. <title xml:lang="en">A Report on the British Collection of Antiquities from Central Asia</title>. Part I (Extra
                        number to <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal</title>). Calcutta: Baptist Mission Press, 1899. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-57">————. ————. Part 2 (Extra number to <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal</title>, vol. LXX, 1901).
                        Calcutta, 1902. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-58">Karashima, Seishi. “An Old Tibetan Translation of the Lotus Sutra from Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Annual Report of The
                            International Research Institute for Advanced Buddhology</title>, 8: pp. 105–90, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-59">Kumamoto, Hiroshi. “The Khotanese in Dunhuang,” in <title xml:lang="it">Cina e Iran: Da Alessandro Magno alla Dinastia
                            Tang</title>, Orientalia Venetiana 5, pp. 79–101. Florence: Leo S Olschiki Editore, 1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-60">————. “Textual Sources for Buddhism in Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Buddhism across Boundaries: Chinese Buddhism and the Western
                            Regions</title>, pp. 345–360. Taipei: Fo Guang Shan Foundation for Buddhist &amp; Culture Education, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-61">————. “A St. Petersburg Bilingual Document and Problems of the Chronology of Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Inner Asian
                            Art and Archaeology</title> 3: pp. 149–56, 75–82. 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-62">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">Once Upon a Future Time: Studies in a Buddhist Prophecy of Decline</title>. Berkeley: Asian Humanities Press, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-63">Rockhill, W. Woodville. <title xml:lang="en">The Life of the Buddha</title>. London: Trübner &amp; Co., 1884.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-64">Skjaervø, P.O. “Khotan: An Early Center of Buddhism in Chinese Turkestan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Buddhism across Boundaries: Chinese
                            Buddhism and the Western Regions</title>, pp. 265–344. Taipei: Fo Guang Shan Foundation for Buddhist &amp; Culture Education,
                        1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-65">————. <title xml:lang="en">Khotanese Manuscripts from Chinese Turkestan in The British Library</title>. London: The British Library,
                        2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-66">————. <title xml:lang="en">This Most Excellent Shine of Gold, King of Kings of Sutras. The Khotanese Suvarṇabhāsottamasūtra</title>.
                        Cambridge, MA: Harvard University, Dept. of Near Eastern Languages and Civilizations, 2004a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-67">————. “Iranians, Indians, Chinese and Tibetans: The Rulers and the Ruled of Khotan in the First Millenium,” in Susan Whitfield (ed.),
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Silk Road: Trade, Travel, War and Faith</title>. London: The British Library, 2004b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-68">Stein, M. Aurel. <title xml:lang="en">Ancient Khotan: Detailed Report of Archaeological Explorations in Chinese Turkestan</title>,
                        vol. 1. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1907.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-69">Thomas, Frederick W. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Literary Texts and Documents Concerning Chinese Turkestan, Part I</title>. London:
                        The Royal Asiatic Society, 1935.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-70">————. “An Old Name of the Khotan Country,” in <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and
                            Ireland</title>, April 1938, no. 2, pp. 281–2. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1938.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-71">van Schaik, Sam. “Red Faced Barbarians, Benign Despots and Drunken Masters: Khotan as a Mirror to Tibet,” in <title xml:lang="fr">Revue d’Etudes Tibétaines</title>, no. 36, pp. 45-68, October 2016. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-72">Zhang, Guangda and Rong, Xinjiang. “On the Dating of the Khotanese Documents from the Area of Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal
                            of Inner Asian Art and Archaeology</title> 3: pp. 149–156, 2009.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-listBibl-2"/>
            </div>
          
        </back>
    </text>
</tei:TEI>