<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Khotan and Khotanese</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li yul</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.2.4 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">khotan-khotanese</idno>
                <date>2023-08-22</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-29T09:53:09.893Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-115">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-116">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-08-22T08:26:20.078Z" type="publication-status" status="1" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-117">
                    <desc>1</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-08-22T08:26:31.093Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-118">
                    <desc>1.1.1</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-09-30T22:27:47.998Z" type="text-version" status="1.2.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-375">
                    <desc>Substantial revisions and additional material added, still in progress.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-09-30T22:28:33.814Z" type="text-version" status="1.2.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-376">
                    <desc>Titles updated</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-02T19:14:20.775Z" type="text-version" status="1.2.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-377">
                    <desc>Further revision and material added.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-11T14:57:40.187Z" type="text-version" status="1.2.4" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-378">
                    <desc>Changes following update to figure configuration.</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="99">Khotan and Khotanese</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="50">Khotan: the Country, its Legends and History</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-80"/>
                    <p tid="5">The once great city-state of Khotan, called <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">li yul </foreign>in Tibetan,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-3">See “Names” below.</note> is today called Hotan (or Hetian) and is located in China’s Xinjiang province. An oasis
                        kingdom on the southwest edge of the vast Taklamakhan desert that fills the Tarim Basin, Khotan lies to the north of the Kunlun mountain range, which
                        divides it from present-day Ladakh to the southwest, Aksai Chin to the south, and Western Tibet to the southeast. It was an important trade center on the
                        southern branch of the Silk Route, which from Kashgar followed the southern side of the desert through Khotan and Shanshan to Lop Nor and Dunhuang, while
                        the more important northern Silk Route reached Dunhuang from Kashgar along the northern edge of the desert through Kucha and Karashahr. 
                        <media mimeType="image/png" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/5f/Moghulistan.PNG/512px-Moghulistan.PNG" source="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Moghulistan.PNG">
                            <desc>Ro4444 at en.wikipedia, CC BY-SA 3.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0, via Wikimedia Commons</desc>
                        </media>
                        <media mimeType="image/png" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3e/Kingdom_of_Khotan.png/800px-Kingdom_of_Khotan.png" source="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kingdom_of_Khotan.png">
                            <desc>en.wikipedia, CC BY-SA 3.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0, via Wikimedia Commons</desc>
                        </media>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-81"/>
                    <p tid="6">During the last few centuries before the Christian Era and the first millennium CE, the Silk Route as a whole—almost the only conduit for high value
                        trade between China and the rest of East Asia and the classical civilizations of Europe, the Arab world, Turkey, Persia, and India—gave rise to unparalleled
                        wealth in the small countries, kingdoms, and city states along it, allowing agriculture to be sustained by complex irrigation schemes as well as the funding
                        of artistic, literary, and spiritual pursuits, all favoring a high level of cultural diversity and exchange.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-82"/>
                    <p tid="7">The earliest cultural influence on Khotan may have been Iranian, but by the time of the Mauryan empire (third century BCE) trade routes were bringing increasing contact with India, Bactria, other nearby city states, and China.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-83"/>
                    <p tid="8">In Indian Buddhist sources, Khotan is said to have been covered by a great lake until the Buddha Śākyamuni flew there to bless it as a site for the
                        future implantation of the Dharma, and miraculously drained the lake; this is the narrative of the sūtra <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount
                            Gośṛṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357), see below. Other canonical works, including the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aśokāvadāna</title> and one of its chapters, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kunālāvadāna</title>,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-76">A
                            Tibetan translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kunālāvadāna</title> is found in the Degé Tengyur (Toh 4145), and in some Kangyurs (e.g. Stok Palace
                            Kangyur 311).</note> give differing accounts of a later period in which a son of Aśoka named Kunāla (or Kustana in the Kharoṣṭhī manuscripts, but
                        according to Brough 1948, p. 334 n.6, following Lévi and Bailey, the indigenous form in Khotanese was Gostana), after either having been blinded as a child
                        by a jealous stepmother, or banished by Aśoka himself as a threat to his reign, or appointed as governor of Gandhāra, settled in Khotan as a founding ruler.
                        His name constitutes one postulated origin of the name Khotan, and he is identified with Suckler of the Earth Breast in <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh357.html">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</ref>
                        </title> (Toh 357) and the other Tibetan texts on Khotan. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-84"/>
                    <p tid="9">According to <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li’i yul lung bstan pa</title>, Toh
                        4202) the wandering Kustana / Gostana had been adopted, at Vaiśravaṇa’s behest, by the king of China, who wanted thereby to add to his 999 sons and round up
                        the number to 1,000. According to some versions of the story, therefore, Gostana arrived in Khotan as representing China along with some Chinese subjects,
                        while from India came the minister Yaśa with his own contingent of dissident subjects of Aśoka; they joined forces and this constituted the population of
                        Khotan.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-85"/>
                    <p tid="52">Whatever historical facts may have given rise to the legends, at some time during or following the rule of Aśoka in India, Khotan became an outpost
                        of Indian culture and gradually, during the first millennium <hi rend="small-caps">CE,</hi> a place where Chinese merchants, monks, and scholars encountered
                        Indian Buddhist doctrine, practices, and texts. It therefore had an important role in the transmission of Buddhism to China and the rest of east Asia.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-86"/>
                    <p tid="53">Historical accounts do not allow precise dating of the first establishment of monastic and lay communities practicing pre-Mahāyāna forms of
                        Buddhism. Even from the traditional histories, it does not seem to have been as early as the Mauryan period in India. It is possible that Buddhism had
                        reached Khotan during the first century BCE, even if it was not widely adopted there, since the southern Silk Route was the probable conduit for the
                        transmission of Buddhism to China in the early first century CE.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-13">See Maggi 2009, p. 340.</note>
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> mentions the presence of Mahāsāṅghika and Sarvāstivāda Nikāyas in Khotan when the
                        Khotanese king defeated Kashgar and converted its ruler and people to Buddhism in about 100 CE, and speaks of monasteries of the adherents of both Nikāyas
                        during the reign of King Vijaya Dharma I (which might, very speculatively, be dated to the third or fourth century CE). There is as yet no archaeological
                        evidence for stūpas or residential monasteries before the late third and early fourth century, although archaeological investigations are ongoing. In terms
                        of texts, a kharoṣṭhī recension of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmapada</title> in a Gāndhāri Prākrit, dated to between the first and third century, was
                        discovered in Khotan in 1892 by Jules-Léon Dutreuil du Rhins. While this single manuscript is so far the only concrete evidence of Āgama-related literature
                        at an early period, it is known from several Chinese accounts that the transmission of texts (both vinaya and sūtra) prior to the introduction of the
                        Mahāyāna was largely oral, with an active bhāṇaka tradition seemingly the norm over the entire Tarim basin and not only in the more northerly centers that
                        remained faithful to the non-Mahāyāna traditions for longer. Indeed, it may only have been the advent of the Mahāyāna, with its sūtras making explicit
                        reference to the merit of copying the scriptures in writing, that stimulated across the region the production of texts and translations—of both Mahāyāna and
                        non-Mahāyāna works.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-45">See Sander 1991, p. 142, and Martini 2013, pp. 15–17.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-87"/>
                    <p tid="54">If Khotan had hitherto been a predominantly non-Mahāyāna Buddhist community, early evidence of Mahāyāna influence comes from the transmission to
                        China of <title xml:lang="en">The Transcendent Perfection of Wisdom in Twenty-Five Thousand Lines</title>. Both of the early Chinese translations, made in
                        the late third century, were of manuscripts originating in Khotan. The story begins with the account of the travels of the Chinese monk Zhu Shixing, who had
                        studied Lokakṣema’s early translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Transcendent Perfection of Wisdom in Eight Thousand Lines</title> (Taishō 224) in Luoyang
                        and had set out westward to find the “more complete” text that had been heard about in China but had not been seen. He had determined to travel all the way
                        to India if necessary, but did not have to go that far as he found the text in Khotan, probably in 260 CE. After various trials and tribulations he sent his
                        Khotanese disciple Puṇyadhana with a copy to China, but himself remained in Khotan for the rest of his life. Puṇyadhana set out from Khotan with the
                        manuscript in 282 but it was only some five years later that he arrived in Cangyuan, where Mokṣala, who was also Khotanese, undertook its translation
                        (Taishō 221) in 291. Another Sanskrit manuscript translated into Chinese (Taishō 222) slightly earlier, in 286 CE by Dharmarakṣa, who was born in Dunhuang,
                        had been brought to Chang’an, also from Khotan, by a Khotanese monk, Gītamitra, who assisted Dharmarakṣa in its translation. It included only the first
                        twenty-seven chapters, while Mokṣala’s more complete translation included all ninety chapters.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-77">See the
                            Introduction to <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in Twenty-Five Thousand Lines</title>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh9.html#UT22084-026-001-28">i.11 et seq</ref>. See also Zürcher 2007, pp.
                        61–63.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-88"/>
                    <p tid="55">Other accounts of Chinese visitors to Khotan include those of Faxian, who in 401 spent three months there. He describes the large Buddhist community
                        consisting of tens of thousands of priests, most of whom belonged to the Mahāyāna. And Zhi Faling found there in the early fifth century the text of the
                        smaller recension of the Avataṃsaka (Taishō 278). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-89"/>
                    <p tid="11">Tibetans, too, may have encountered some aspects of the Indian Buddhist traditions in Khotan. Khotan was invaded by the Tibetans a little after the
                        mid seventh century <hi rend="small-caps">CE</hi> at a time when, in the reigns of Songtsen Gampo and his successors, Tibetan political and military power
                        were expanding. Khotanese accounts of the time saw the arrival of the Tibetans as destructive of Buddhist institutions there, and although the Tibetan court
                        had recently begun to adopt Buddhist culture it is likely that its influence had not yet reached the far-flung army commanders. However, soon afterwards it
                        appears that Tibetan occupation had proved relatively benign to Khotan’s Buddhists, and for the next three centuries while Khotan was twice subject to
                        Tibetan administration (rule by China, lasting from the late seventh to late eighth century CE, intervened between the two periods of Tibetan
                        administration) the cultural ties between Tibet and Khotan grew stronger.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-10"> See van Schaik 2016, pp.
                            50-52.</note> Indeed, some scholars attribute considerable importance to Khotan in the establishment of Buddhism in Tibet. Khotanese monks, banished
                        from Khotan during a period of rule hostile to Buddhism, seem to have been welcomed in Tibet in the early eighth century by the Chinese queen of Tridé
                        Tsukten, father of Trisong Deutsen, and may have been responsible for the establishment of the first Buddhist monasteries in Tibet. For several centuries
                        even after the collapse of the Tibetan imperial power in the mid ninth century, Tibetan and Khotanese monks and scholars were in frequent contact in
                        Dunhuang and other cultural centers in Central Asia.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-11"> See Snellgrove 1987, vol. 2, pp. 331-43; van
                            Schaik 2016, pp. 51-61.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-90"/>
                    <p tid="12">Of the many oasis kingdoms on both sides of the Tarim Basin, Khotan was among the most prosperous and orderly, and sustained large communities of
                        monks and nuns, as described by both Faxian and Xuanzang, the great Chinese monk travellers of the early fifth and seventh centuries, respectively. Later,
                        wealth came from jade, washed down in the rivers from deposits in the mountains; Khotanese jade was highly valued in China.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-91"/>
                    <p tid="59">Military conflicts, successive invasions, and the gradual evolution of alternative, maritime trade routes between the Western and Eastern worlds led
                        to dwindling importance of the Silk Routes and concomitant decline of the cultures that had been sustained by them. By the twelfth century, little was left
                        of Khotan’s Buddhist past. The power of China had waxed and waned several times, Tibet’s imperial reach had long ago collapsed, and waves of Turkic and
                        Iranian influence, eventually bringing Islam, had surged through the region. Mongol power was increasing. Many scholars and historians in Tibet seemed
                        already to have become ignorant of Khotan’s contribution to their culture a few centuries earlier. Some were so ill-informed that they were not even sure
                        what country was designated by the Tibetan name for Khotan, Liyül, let alone where it was. Others, familiar perhaps with the legends of the draining of the
                        lake that was the site of Svayambhu in the Kathmandu Valley, identified the Khotan sūtras confidently with Nepal, as evidenced by specific refutations of
                        that notion by early figures like the Kadampa master Drolungpa Lodro Jungne and the great Sakya scholars Sakya Pandita and Rendawa Zhonnu Lodro. In the
                        thirteenth century, Chomden Rikpai Raltri saw the need to specify Liyül as being “on the other side of the Chakpo snow-mountains” (see below <ptr target="#EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-112"/>) and, in another work, to write a stanza on the subject:</p>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="60">
                            <l>That Liyül of “Sustained by the Earth Breast”<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-113">The “earth breast” refers to the legend of a
                                    breast appearing from the earth from which, according to <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357) <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh357.html">1.14</ref> and similar accounts in other
                                    texts, Aśoka’s son was nourished and hence became known as Suckler of the Earth Breast. “Sustained by the Earth Breast” is presumably a variant
                                    of this name, although in some works it seems to refer more to a geographical site in Khotan.</note>
                            </l>
                            <l>Is not the Nepal on the border of India and Tibet,</l>
                            <l>Because there the features of Li, as described </l>
                            <l>By the Buddha himself, are not to be found.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-114">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa nus bzung ba’i li yul de/ rgya bod mtshams kyi bal po min/ gang phyir de la sangs rgyas kyis/ gsungs pa’i li yi
                                        mtshan nyid med</foreign> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab bya gsum rgyan gyi me tog</title> F.54.a.)</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <p tid="61">Even in the twentieth century, the renowned Tibetan traveler and scholar Gendun Chopel (1903–1951) found it necessary to point out to his countrymen
                        that to identify Liyül with Nepal was wrong, and that the features of the country, as mentioned in the Kangyur texts, are those of Khotan.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-135">
                            <title xml:lang="en">Grains of Gold</title> p. 56.</note> Dungkar’s dictionary devotes no less than two columns to a discussion of different scholars’
                        views on the subject; see Dungkar 2002, pp. 1956-7. See also Stein 1907, p. 153.</p>


                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-1-1">
                        <head type="section" tid="51">The Names Identifying Khotan</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-93"/>
                        <p tid="15">The standard Tibetan rendering of Khotan is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">li yul</foreign>. It is not clear where the Tibetan rendering
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">li</foreign> might have come from, and at some periods of Tibetan history not all scholars seem to have been
                            clear about the country to which that name referred, some assuming it sometimes or always meant Nepal (see <ptr target="#EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-91"/>). </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-94"/>
                        <p tid="16">Another name by which Khotan is known in some Tibetan texts (e.g. Toh 257, see below) is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha
                                sha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha sa</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha za</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kha sha’i yul</foreign>, Tibetan renderings which may correspond to Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khāṣya</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khaśa</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khasa</foreign> as referring
                            to a people (see Edgerton) or to the Indic name <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Kaṃsadeśa</foreign>. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-95"/>
                        <p tid="17">The name Khotan may have evolved from the variants Kustana and Gostana of the name of Aśoka’s son Kunāla in Khotan’s Buddhist founding myths
                            (see above).</p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="73">The Khotanese Language</head>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-2.1">
                        <head type="section" tid="74">Texts in Khotanese</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-96"/>
                        <p tid="18">Buddhist texts in Khotan until the mid fifth century CE seem to have been in the Indic Gāndhārī language, written in the Kharoṣṭhī script, and
                            were not translated into the vernacular. A written script or language called Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khāsyalipi</foreign> may be
                            early Khotanese, i.e. Kharoṣṭhī.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-97"/>
                        <p tid="62">See Negi qv <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kha sha’i yi ge</foreign>: </p>
                        <q>
                            <p tid="63">khāśyalipiḥ (khāsyalipiḥ, khāṣyalipiḥ), lipiviśeṣaḥ — katamāṃ me bho upādhyāya lipiṃ śikṣāpayasi |
                                brāhmīkharoṣṭīpuṣkarasārimaṅgalipim…daradalipiṃ khāṣya(khāsya)lipiṃ cīnalipim…| āsāṃ bho upādhyāya catuṣṣaṣṭilipīnām la.vi.66kha/88; dra.
                                ཁ་ཤའི་ལུང་པ khaśadroṇiḥ ma.mū.199ka/214.</p>
                        </q>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-98"/>
                        <p tid="56">From around the start of the sixth century, or possibly the mid fifth century, both texts and written communications in “Khotanese” became more
                            prominent. This was a Middle Iranian form of Indo-European that developed from the vernacular of the region and was written in the Brāhmī and Gupta
                            scripts used all over Northern India (but in forms specific to Central Asia). It was only at this time that Buddhist scriptures were actually translated
                            into Khotanese.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-99"/>
                        <p tid="57">The formal varieties of the Brāhmī scripts used for religious texts can be grouped into four stages of development, according to Sander: (1)
                            Early Turkestan Brāhmī, type b (with two subtypes, one with knots, especially at the end of the verticals, and another without knots), “about the fifth
                            century A.D.”; (2) Early South Turkestan Brāhmī, “end of the sixth to the seventh century”; (3) South Turkestan Brāhmī (the main type), “between the
                            seventh and the ninth century”; and (4) Late South Turkestan Brāhmī, “tenth century”.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-12">Sander 1989,
                                pp. 112–18.</note>
                        </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-92"/>
                        <p tid="14">In the early centuries of the millennium, there may have been separate monastic communities in Khotan following Śrāvakayāna and Mahāyāna
                            doctrine. A considerable range of Buddhist literature in Khotanese, mostly Mahāyāna texts and many represented only by fragmentary manuscripts, has been
                            identified. Many such texts must have circulated in Tibet as Buddhism took root there, alongside texts in other Central Asian languages, Chinese, and
                            increasingly—as the great imperial period of translations gathered pace—in Sanskrit. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-100"/>
                        <p tid="64">Texts in Khotanese, found in Dunhuang and several other Central Asian sites, include the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aparimitāyurjñānasūtra</title>
                                (<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh674.html#UT22084-091-072-413">Toh 674</ref> and <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh675.html#UT22084-091-073-413">Toh 675</ref>), <title xml:lang="en">The White Lotus of the Good
                                Dharma</title> or “Lotus Sūtra” (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmapuṇḍarīka</title>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-051-001.html#UT22084-051-001-49">Toh 113</ref>), and <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the
                                Tathāgata Jñānolka</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-088-016.html#UT22084-088-016-8">Toh 522</ref>).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-2.2">
                        <head type="section" tid="75">Canonical Texts Translated from Khotanese into Tibetan</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-112"/>
                        <p tid="65">A number of Kangyur texts are known to have been translated into Tibetan from Khotanese, while others may have been translated initially from
                            Khotanese but subsequently retranslated or revised from Sanskrit manuscripts as they became available to Tibetans. The thirteenth century inventory of
                            canonical translations compiled by the scholar Chomden Rikpai Raltri (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan rig pa’i ral gri</foreign>) with the title
                                <title xml:lang="en">Ornamenting Sunlight of the Teachings’ Spread</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan pa rgyas pa rgyan gyi nyi ’od</title>)
                            lists twenty-one texts as having been translated from Khotanese, under the heading:
                        </p>
                        
                        <q>
                            <p tid="35">(p. 150) “Those that were translated from Khotanese were translated by the Khotanese Khenpo Surendrākaraprabha, the chief editor-lotsāwa
                                Gelong Namkha,<!--<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-36"> Is this the same translator as Nam
                            mkha’ translator of the Heart Sūtra? See also Toh 3818.</note>--> and others. Khotan is situated behind the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chags po</foreign> snow mountains,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-109"> Translated according to
                                    the reading in the two versions available on BDRC, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">li ni chags po gangs kyi rgyab na yod pa
                                        ste</foreign>, while Schaeffer and van der Kuijp’s diplomatic edition from two manuscripts instead reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">li ni chags so gang gyi rgyab nas yod pa te</foreign>. Whichever the case, it is significant that even in Chomden Rikral’s time
                                    it seemed necessary to ensure that Tibetan readers knew where Khotan was situated.</note> and the [texts] translated from [Khotanese] are as
                                follows:...”</p>
                        </q>
                        <figure>
                            <media mimeType="image/png" url="/images/khotan-bstan_pa_rgyas_pa_rgyan_gyi_nyi_od_f26a.png"/>
                            <figDesc>Page 26a from Chomden Raltri's inventory</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                            <media mimeType="image/png" url="/images/khotan-bstan_pa_rgyas_pa_rgyan_gyi_nyi_od_f26b.png"/>
                            <figDesc>Page 26b from Chomden Raltri's inventory</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-121"/>
                        <p tid="76">Most of the works listed by Chomden Rigpai Raltri can be at least tentatively identified as matching the following extant Kangyur and Tengyur
                            texts:</p>
                        <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                            <item>
                                <p tid="66">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh168.html">The Questions of
                                        Vimalaprabhā</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhāparipṛcchā</title>, Toh 168)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="67">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh357.html">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="68">“<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyangs pa’i yon tan bshad pa</title>” [probably <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam grol lam las sbyangs pa’i yon
                                        tan bstan pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimuktimārgadhutaguṇanirdeśa</title>, Toh 306)]</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="69">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh206.html">Pure Sustenance of Food</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zas kyi ’tsho ba rnam par dag pa</title>, Toh 206)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="70">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh335.html">The Sūtra on the Ringing Staff</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khar gsil gyi mdo</title>, Toh 335)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="77">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh336.html">The Rite for the Protocols Associated with Carrying
                                            the Ringing Staff</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khar gsil ’chang ba’i kun spyod pa’i cho ga</title>, Toh 335)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="78">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh137.html">The Supreme Samādhi</ref>
                                    </title>
                                        (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Samādhyagrottama</title>, Toh 137)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="79">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh351.html">The Sūtra of Prince
                                        Arthasiddhi</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Jinaputrārthasiddhisūtra</title>, Toh 351)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="80">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh355.html">Teaching the Ripening of Virtuous and Nonvirtuous
                                            Actions</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dge ba dang mi dge ba’i las kyi rnam par smin pa bstan pa</title>, Toh 355) or possibly
                                    another similar but distinct text, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi rnam par smin pa’i ’bras bu</title> in Lhasa (H342) and Qianlong (Q1004)
                                    Kangyurs</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="81">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh691.html" rend="pending">The Dhāraṇī of the Thousand-Armed, Thousand-Eyed
                                            Avalokiteśvara</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs phyag stong spyan stong gzungs</title>, Toh 691 and 897) or
                                    possibly another similar but distinct text, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug phyag stong du sprul pa rgya chen po
                                        yong su rdzogs pa thogs pa med par thug rje chen po dang ldan pa’i gzungs</title> in Lithang (J681) and Qianlong (Q368) Kangyurs</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="82">Vasubandhu’s <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3995.html">An Explanation of The
                                            Fundamental Exposition and Detailed Analysis of Dependent Arising</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Pratītyasamutpādādi­vibhaṅga­nirdeśa</title>, Toh 3995)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="83">Guṇamati’s <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3996.html">Extensive Explanation of
                                            Teaching the Fundamental Exposition and Detailed Analysis of Dependent Arising</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Pratītyasamutpādādi­vibhaṅga­nirdeśaṭīkā</title>, Toh 3996)</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p tid="93">Others in his list, however, are difficult to identify with any certainty:</p>
                        <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                            <item>
                                <p tid="85">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rta skad byang chub sems dpa’i mdo</title>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="86">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan gyi mdo</title>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="87">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon lam gyi mdo</title>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="88">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mo’u ’gal ma tshol ba’i mdo</title>
                                    <note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-180">Reading from the
                                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu med</foreign> MS version (b), which is clearly readable. Schaeffer and van der Kuijp have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">le’u ’gal mi tshol ba’i mdo</foreign>, which seems unlikely.</note> [The presumed theme of Maudgalyāyana seeking his
                                    mother, reborn in the preta realms, suggests a possible relationship to the Ullambana (or Yulanpen) sūtras in Chinese, Taishō 685 and 686, or
                                    similar narratives not always involving Maudgalyāyana himself in the Avadāna literature.]</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="89">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rta ’grin gnam sa bkod pa’i mdo</title>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="90">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge’ ba bcu dang du blang pu’i(?) mdo</title>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="91">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snang brgyad rigs bzhi</title>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="92">
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lang kar gshegs pa’i ti ka</title> (in three <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bam po</foreign>)</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p tid="94">The following two works that appear (somewhat mysteriously) in the Epistles section of the Degé Tengyur are not mentioned by Chomden Rikral, but
                            were also presumably translated from Khotanese. They are described briefly in the next section below and should no doubt be added as a supplement to
                            Chomden’s list:</p>
                        <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                            <item>
                                <p tid="95">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of the Arhat Saṅghavardhana</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arhatsaṅghavardhanavyākaraṇa</title>,
                                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa dge 'dun 'phel gyis lung bstan pa</title>, Toh 4201) </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="96">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kaṃsadeśavyākaraṇa</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li’i yul lung bstan pa</title>, Toh 4202) </p>
                            </item>
                        </list>

                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-2.3">
                        <head type="section" tid="58">Canonical Texts With Content Related to Khotan</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-101"/>
                        <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                            <item>
                                <p tid="72">In <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Vimalaprabhā</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhāparipṛcchā</title>, Toh 168), the
                                    princess Vimalaprabhā, bodhisattva daughter of King Ajātaśatru of Magadha, who in the past was the powerful rakṣasī Husha, receives a detailed
                                    prophecy of her future lives as a series of important and powerful female figures in Khotan, including one as the formidable lady Rabngé, sister
                                    of the king of one neighboring country (Skardo), widow of the king of another (The Gold Country), Buddhist nun, and protectress of Khotan at the
                                    time of an invasion by the Tibetans. Other figures in Vimalaprabhā’s family, as well as Vaiśravaṇa and others, are prophesied in various
                                    supporting roles.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="30">In <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh257.html">The Quintessence of the Sun</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sūryagarbha-mahāvaipulya</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu rgyas pa chen po’i sde nyi ma’i snying po</title>, Toh
                                    257), a passage of the text (<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh257.html#UT22084-066-015-1130">12.30 et seq.</ref>) summarizes
                                    the story of the Buddha’s visit to Khotan to bless the landscape that is told in detail in <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount
                                        Gośṛṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357).</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="31">In <title xml:lang="en">
                                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh357.html">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</ref>
                                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gośṛṅgavyākaraṇa</title>, Toh 357), the Buddha, toward the end of his life, flies from Rajgṛha to Khotan, where he blesses
                                    the landscape, causes the lake covering the country to be drained away, and predicts the sites of stūpas and monasteries that will be founded as
                                    the Dharma takes root and spreads there.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="97">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of the Arhat Saṅghavardhana</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arhatsaṅghavardhanavyākaraṇa</title>,
                                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa dge 'dun 'phel gyis lung bstan pa</title>, Toh 4201) is structured along the lines of the descriptions
                                    of the decline of the Dharma in India as told in a number of texts, but goes into considerable detail regarding the future expulsion of Buddhist
                                    monks from Khotan and the difficulties they will encounter as they travel through Tibet to India. </p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="98">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of Khotan</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kaṃsadeśavyākaraṇa</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li’i yul lung bstan pa</title>, Toh 4202), contains material that partly overlaps the content of <title xml:lang="en">The
                                        Prophecy of the Arhat Saṅghavardhana</title>, and also includes accounts of the rulers of Khotan and other historical details set out as
                                    prophecies. </p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-article-3">
                    <head type="section" tid="49">Western Interest in Khotan and its Literature</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-110"/>
                    <p tid="38">The first scholar in the West to take an interest in Khotan seems to have been the nineteenth century French Sinologist, Abel Rémusat in 1820 with a
                        study of Chinese texts about Khotan. W. Woodville Rockhill drew attention to the Tibetan texts on Khotan in his <title xml:lang="en">Life of the
                            Buddha</title>, published in 1884, while Édouard Chavannes and Sylvain Lévi published articles mentioning Khotanese texts in 1903 and 1905. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-111"/>
                    <p tid="39">A few years earlier, in 1900, following the first discoveries of Kharoṣṭhī manuscripts on birch-bark in Kuchā and Khotan by other expeditions and
                        the studies of them by Émile Senart and Rudolf Hoernle, the great explorer of Central Asia, Sir Aurel Stein, had already set out on his expedition to
                        Chinese Turkestan. In 1907, Stein published a full account of his archaeological findings together with a wealth of geographical, historical, and linguistic
                        observations, identifying and describing the sacred geography and architecture mentioned in this sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-40"> See Stein 1907, in particular pp. 185–90. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-132"/>
                    <p tid="40">Stein’s initial work on the Tibetan texts was subsequently developed further by Frederick Thomas, culminating in the publication in 1935 of complete
                        English translations of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</title> (Toh 357) and of the other most closely associated texts mentioned above, 
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Vimalaprabhā</title> (Toh
                        168), <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of the Arhat Saṅghavardhana</title> (Toh 4201) and <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of
                            Khotan</title> (Toh 4202), along with extracts from some other related works.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-42"> Thomas 1935, in
                            particular pp. 1–38.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-133"/>
                    <p tid="41">More recently, in 1967, Ronald Emmerick published translations of the two parts of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning the Land of
                            Khotan</title> (Toh 4202). He has also published translations from Khotanese of works, and a guide to Khotanese literature. A useful article by Sam van
                        Schaik published in 2016 summarizes studies of the Khotanese literature in general and on Khotanese works among the texts found in Dunhuang, including those
                        by Karashima, Kumamoto, Skjaervø, van Schaik, and Zhang and Rong. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-134"/>
                    <p tid="43">Jan Nattier, in <title xml:lang="en">Once Upon a Future Time: Studies in a Buddhist Prophecy of Decline</title> (1991), traces the development of
                        the Buddhist “prophetic history” literature including a detailed account and analysis of the Khotanese texts mentioned here.</p>
                </div>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="44">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="46">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-46"> (see many articles in Indo-Iranian Journal)</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-47">Brough, John. “Legends of Khotan and Nepal,” in <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African
                            Studies, University of London</title>, vol. 12, no. 2, pp. 333–9. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1948. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-120">Chomden Rigpai Raltri (bcom ldan rig pa'i ral gri). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan pa rgyas pa rgyan gyi nyi
                            ’od</title> [<title xml:lang="en">Ornamenting Sunlight of the Teachings’ Spread</title>]. (a) In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung ’bum</title> vol. 1.
                        Lhasa: khams sprul bsod nams don grub, 2006. BDRC: MW00EGS1017426. (b) In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung gsung thor bu</title> vol. 2 pp. 3–158
                        (manuscript). BDRC MW1CZ1041. (c) See Schaeffer and van der Kuijp. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-141">————. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab bya gsum rgyan gyi me tog</title> [<title xml:lang="en">Ornamenting Flowers of
                            the Three Trainings</title>]. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung ’bum</title> vol. 1. Lhasa: khams sprul bsod nams don grub, 2006. BDRC: MW00EGS1017426. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-48">Chopel, Gendun. <title xml:lang="en">Grains of Gold: Tales of a Cosmopolitan Traveler</title>. Translated by Thupten
                        Jinpa and Donald S. Lopez. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-49">Emmerick, Ronald E. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Texts Concerning Khotan</title>. London: Oxford University Press,
                        1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-50">————. The Book of Zambasta, a Khotanese poem on Buddhism (London Oriental Series 21), Oxford University Press: London,
                        1968, pp. xxii + 455.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-51">————. <title xml:lang="en">The Book of Zambasta: A Khotanese Poem on Buddhism</title>. London: Oxford University
                        Press. 1968. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-52">————. <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Golden Light, being a translation of the Suvarṇabhāsottamasūtra</title>
                        (Sacred Books of the Buddhists XXVII). London: Luzac and Company Ltd, 1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-53">————. <title xml:lang="en">The Khotanese Śūraṅgamasamādhisūtra</title> (London Oriental Series 23), Oxford University
                        Press: London 1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-54">————. <title xml:lang="en">A Guide to the Literature of Khotan</title>. Tokyo: The International Institute for
                        Buddhist Studies, 1992. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-55">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten
                            buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-56">Hoernle, A. R Rudolf. <title xml:lang="en">A Report on the British Collection of Antiquities from Central
                        Asia</title>. Part I (Extra number to <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal</title>). Calcutta: Baptist Mission Press, 1899. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-57">————. ————. Part 2 (Extra number to <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal</title>, vol.
                        LXX, 1901). Calcutta, 1902. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-58">Karashima, Seishi. “An Old Tibetan Translation of the Lotus Sutra from Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Annual Report
                            of The International Research Institute for Advanced Buddhology</title>, 8: pp. 105–90, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-59">Kumamoto, Hiroshi. “The Khotanese in Dunhuang,” in <title xml:lang="it">Cina e Iran: Da Alessandro Magno alla Dinastia
                            Tang</title>, Orientalia Venetiana 5, pp. 79–101. Florence: Leo S Olschiki Editore, 1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-60">————. “Textual Sources for Buddhism in Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Buddhism across Boundaries: Chinese Buddhism
                            and the Western Regions</title>, pp. 345–360. Taipei: Fo Guang Shan Foundation for Buddhist &amp; Culture Education, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-61">————. “A St. Petersburg Bilingual Document and Problems of the Chronology of Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal
                            of Inner Asian Art and Archaeology</title> 3: pp. 149–56, 75–82. 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-73">Maggi, Mauro. “Khotanese Literature.” Chapter 7 in Emmerick, Ronald E. and Maria Macuch (eds.), <title xml:lang="en">The Literature of Pre-Islamic Iran</title>, companion vol. 1 to <title xml:lang="en">A History of Persian Literature</title>. London: I. B. Tauris and
                        Co Ltd., 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-78">Martini, Giuliana (a.k.a. Dhammadinnā). “Bodhisattva Texts, Ideologies and Rituals in Khotan in the Fifth and Sixth
                        Centuries.” In de Chiara, Matteo, Mauro Maggi, and Giuliana Martini (eds.), <title xml:lang="en">Buddhism Among the Iranian Peoples of Central Asia</title>,
                        vol. 1 of <title xml:lang="en">Multilingualism and History of Knowledge</title>. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-62">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">Once Upon a Future Time: Studies in a Buddhist Prophecy of Decline</title>.
                        Berkeley: Asian Humanities Press, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-63">Rockhill, W. Woodville. <title xml:lang="en">The Life of the Buddha</title>. London: Trübner &amp; Co., 1884.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-74">Sander, L. “The earliest manuscripts from Central Asia and the Sarvāstivāda mission.” In Emmerick, R.E. and D. Weber
                        (eds.), <title xml:lang="en">Corolla Iranica: papers in honour of Prof. Dr. David Neil MacKenzie on the occasion of his 65th birthday on April 8th,
                            1991.</title> Frankfurt am Main, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-79">————. “Remarks on the Formal Brāhmī of Gilgit, Bamīyān and Khotan.” In Jettmar, K. (eds.), <title xml:lang="en">Antiquities of Northern Pakistan: Reports and Studies.</title> Vol. 1: <title xml:lang="en">Rock Inscriptions in the Indus Valley,</title> pp. 107–130.
                        Mainz, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-374">Schaeffer, Kurtis and Leonard van der Kuijp. <title xml:lang="en">An Early Tibetan Survey of Buddhist Literature: The
                            Bstan pa rgyas pa rgyan gyi nyi ’od of Bcom ldan ral gri</title>. Harvard Oriental Series vol. 64. Cambridge and London: Harvard University Press,
                        2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-64">Skjaervø, P.O. “Khotan: An Early Center of Buddhism in Chinese Turkestan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Buddhism across
                            Boundaries: Chinese Buddhism and the Western Regions</title>, pp. 265–344. Taipei: Fo Guang Shan Foundation for Buddhist &amp; Culture Education,
                        1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-65">————. <title xml:lang="en">Khotanese Manuscripts from Chinese Turkestan in The British Library</title>. London: The
                        British Library, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-66">————. <title xml:lang="en">This Most Excellent Shine of Gold, King of Kings of Sutras. The Khotanese
                            Suvarṇabhāsottamasūtra</title>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University, Dept. of Near Eastern Languages and Civilizations, 2004a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-67">————. “Iranians, Indians, Chinese and Tibetans: The Rulers and the Ruled of Khotan in the First Millenium,” in Susan
                        Whitfield (ed.), <title xml:lang="en">The Silk Road: Trade, Travel, War and Faith</title>. London: The British Library, 2004b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-68">Stein, M. Aurel. <title xml:lang="en">Ancient Khotan: Detailed Report of Archaeological Explorations in Chinese
                            Turkestan</title>, vol. 1. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1907.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-69">Thomas, Frederick W. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Literary Texts and Documents Concerning Chinese Turkestan, Part
                            I</title>. London: The Royal Asiatic Society, 1935.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-70">————. “An Old Name of the Khotan Country,” in <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great
                            Britain and Ireland</title>, April 1938, no. 2, pp. 281–2. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1938.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-71">van Schaik, Sam. “Red Faced Barbarians, Benign Despots and Drunken Masters: Khotan as a Mirror to Tibet,” in <title xml:lang="fr">Revue d’Etudes Tibétaines</title>, no. 36, pp. 45-68, October 2016. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-72">Zhang, Guangda and Rong, Xinjiang. “On the Dating of the Khotanese Documents from the Area of Khotan,” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Inner Asian Art and Archaeology</title> 3: pp. 149–156, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KHOTAN-KHOTANESE-75">Zürcher, Erik. <title xml:lang="en">The Buddhist Conquest of China: The Spread and Adaptation of Buddhism in Medieval
                            China</title>, 3rd ed. [1st ed. 1959] with a foreword by S. F. Teiser. Leiden: Brill (Sinica Leidensia 11), 2007.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>