<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Kīla</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-KILA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">kila</idno>
                <date>2021-06-08</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-08T23:01:45.171Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-KILA-2">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-KILA-3">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KILA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">Kīla </head>
                    <head type="nonStructuralBreak" tid="7">Indrakīla </head>
                    <p tid="8">30 Aug 2020: </p>
                    <p tid="9">Dear all, </p>
                    <p tid="10">Is it me who is missing something here, or is there some misunderstanding in the way some translators translate the Sanskrit śaṅku or kīla synonyms — nail or spike — as
                        “dagger”? Is it possible that these translators do so based on the association of the Tibetan translation of the Sanskrit word — phur pa / phur ba / phur bu — with the ritual
                        object of the same name used in Tibetan rites that indeed has an elaborate form of a dagger? </p>
                    <p tid="11">While it can’t be ruled out with certainty that kīlas or śaṅkus took a form of ritual daggers also in the Indian context when used for ritual purposes I would be
                        grateful if somebody could point me to any textual or archaeological evidence for this, it seems a bit out of place to call them “daggers” in non-ritual contexts, for example
                        when they are used to oppress beings in hell where the ground is studded with spikes / nails, and the same fall from the sky. Also in contexts when some villagers arm
                        themselves with “rods, spikes, and canes,” it is unlikely that these spikes <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śaṅku</foreign> are daggers. </p>
                    <p tid="12">Translating śaṅku / kīla as “dagger” in the description of hells in the early sūtras could be planting Tibetan content in texts where it doesn’t historically belong. </p>
                    <p tid="13">I also recently saw the word triśaṅku translated as “triple dagger.” The term, synonymous, with triśūla, most likely means a three-forked spike or trident, so common in
                        India. I find it difficult to visualize it as a dagger. </p>
                    <p tid="14">Best wishes, </p>
                    <p tid="15">Wiesiek </p>
                    <p tid="16">see other emails from that string </p>
                    <p tid="17">See Mayer on kīla </p>
                    <p tid="18">Mt Meru as kīla </p>
                    <p tid="19">Indrakīla may not be a foundation stone but a sort of pillar implanted at the gates of royal cities </p>
                    <p tid="20">see Boord’s book and article </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-KILA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-KILA-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>