<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Mahāsūtras</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.0 <date>2025</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s
                    words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">mahasutras</idno>
                <date>2024-06-14</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#john" when="2025-01-04T19:46:45.503Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.0" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-66">
                    <desc>Several edits and additions.</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="main-subject">Mahāsūtra</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-article">
                <head type="article" tid="1">Mahāsūtra</head>
                
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-article-1">
                        <head tid="2">Overview</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-1"/>
                        <p tid="3">The Mahāsūtras, or “Great Discourses,” collectively comprise a corpus of texts extracted from the Āgama literature
                            of the Sarvāstivādin and Mūlasarvāstivādin Vinaya, defined not so much by their subject matter, which is diverse, as by
                            the way they were used—that is, they were recited for the protection conferred by the resounding of the Buddha’s words,
                            perhaps representing the whole Āgama canon in a short anthology. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-2"/>
                        <p tid="4">More generally, they constitute a set of works from a foundational layer of Buddhist literature and have many
                            parallels across a wide range of canonical corpora in Sanskrit, Pali, Chinese, and other languages. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-3"/>
                        <p tid="5">The epithet <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā</foreign> (“great”) applied to them as a group and in their titles
                            seems to denote their power, importance, and efficacity rather than their length; some are relatively short texts.
                            While some of them set out the basic doctrinal principles of the Buddha’s teachings, others are oriented more to providing
                            protection from the vicissitudes his followers might face as they pursue a life of putting those teachings into practice.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-4"/>
                        <p tid="6">In all Kangyurs, there are ten sūtras whose titles identify them as belonging to the corpus of Mahāsūtras:</p>
                        <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                            <item>
                            <p tid="7">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh288.html">The Mahāsūtra “Illusion’s Net”</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyājālamahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen sgyu ma’i dra ba</title>, Toh 288), a teaching on how to train in wisdom by examining one’s perceptions and reactions to them 
                                    in order not to be taken in by various kinds of harmful delusion.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="8">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref rend="pending" inst="endnote not needed" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh289.html">The Mahāsūtra “Bimbisāra’s Going Out to Meet the Buddha”</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bimbisārapratyudgamanamahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po gzugs can
                                        snying pos bsu ba</title>, Toh
                                        289), an account of King Bimbisāra’s first audience with the Buddha after his awakening that includes
                                    teachings on the aggregates, non-self, and impermanence.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="9">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref rend="pending" inst="endnote not needed" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh290.html">The [Lesser] Mahāsūtra on Emptiness</ref>
                                </title> ([<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Cūḍa-</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūnyatāmahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po stong
                                        pa nyid</title>, Toh 290), a
                                    teaching to Ānanda on the experience of emptiness.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="10">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref rend="pending" inst="endnote not needed" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh291.html">The [Greater] Mahāsūtra on [Great] Emptiness</ref>
                                </title>
                                <note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-5"> The Sanskrit title and especially its rendering in Tibetan has—in at least one
                                        commentary—seemingly allowed one of the two instances of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chen po</foreign> (“great” or “greater”) to be interpreted as referring to the greatness
                                        of emptiness, although the most common and likely interpretation is that it refers to the text’s length
                                        (compared to that of the preceding text in the list). See Skilling <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II,
                                        p. 368. </note> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāśūnyatāmahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po
                                        stong nyid chen po</title>, Toh
                                        291), a teaching to monks in Kapilavastu on living in solitude, meditating on emptiness, and respecting
                                    the teacher.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="11">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh292.html">The Mahāsūtra “The Crest Insignia” [1]</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhvajāgramahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po rgyal mtshan mchog</title>, Toh 292), a teaching to traveling
                                    merchants on the protective benefits of recollecting the Three Jewels.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="12">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh293.html">The Mahāsūtra “The Crest Insignia” [2]</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhvajāgramahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po rgyal mtshan dam pa</title>, Toh 293), a teaching to monks on
                                    the protective benefits of recollecting the Three Jewels.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="13">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref rend="pending" inst="endnote not needed" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh294.html">The Mahāsūtra on the Five and Three [Views]</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañcatrayamahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po lnga gsum pa</title>, Toh 294), a teaching to monks on the different
                                    views about what it is of a person that survives in future.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="14">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref rend="pending" inst="endnote not needed" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh653.html">The Mahāsūtra, the Sūtra of the Great Assembly</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsamājasūtramahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po ’dus pa chen po’i mdo</title>, Toh 653/1062), an account of the many different kinds of
                                    gods, goddesses, and other supernatural beings who come to Kapilavastu to pay homage to the Buddha.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="15">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref rend="pending" inst="endnote not needed" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh656.html">The Mahāsūtra, the Āṭānāṭīya Sūtra</ref>
                                </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āṭānāṭīyasūtramahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen kun tu rgyu dang / kun tu rgyu ma yin pa
                                        dang mthun pa’i mdo</title>, Toh 656/1061), an account in which Vaiśravaṇa, the divine guardian of the North,
                                    provides the Buddha with a protective ritual text that monks and nuns should recite to prevent the various
                                    nonhuman beings who might harm them, particularly yakṣas, from doing so.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="16">
                                <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh312.html">The Mahāsūtra on Entering the City of Vaiśālī</ref>
                                </title>, (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśālīpraveśamahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yangs pa’i grong khyer du ’jug pa’i mdo chen
                                        po</title>, Toh 312/Toh 698/Toh 1093), the mantras and blessing verses the
                                    Buddha uses to dispel the great epidemic of Vaiśālī.</p>
                        </item>
                        </list>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-6"/>
                        <p tid="17">Of these ten texts, eight titles are listed in the Tibetan translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="en">The Detailed Explanations of Monastic Discipline</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba rnam ’byed</title>, <ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh3.html"/>Toh 3) as texts to be recited for protection. Since one of the eight titles in that list is the
                            identical title shared by two different sūtras (5 and 6 above), the list in practice covers the nine texts (1–9). The same nine texts are
                            listed as Mahāsūtras in the ninth-century Denkarma inventory, and all ten texts are known to have been translated into
                            Tibetan in the early, imperial translation period. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-7"/>
                        <p tid="18">The tenth, a slight outlier in the corpus, is not included in any lists but has affiliations with the others in
                            terms of both its sources and its uses.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-8"> Its inclusion is suggested by
                                Skilling (see below).</note>
                        </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-9"/>
                        <p tid="19">In most Kangyurs, seven of the texts (1–7) are found grouped together in the General Sūtra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</foreign>) section. Two (8 and 9) are found in the Action Tantra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ba’i rgyud</foreign>) section, and one (10) is duplicated in both the General Sūtra and Action Tantra sections. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-10"/>
                        <p tid="20">Further copies of 8, 9, and 10 are also found in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs
                                ’dus</foreign>) section in those Kangyurs that include such a compendium.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-article-2">
                        <head tid="21">Origins and History</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-11"/>
                        <p tid="22">Much of our current understanding of the Mahāsūtras comes from the work of Peter Skilling, who has published a
                            two-volume study of this important early Buddhist corpus, including critical editions of the ten Tibetan texts along with
                            their available Pali and Sanskrit counterparts.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-12"> Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, pp. 9–12. For Skilling’s complete list of Mahāsūtras that were translated
                                into Tibetan, see p. 12. For charts of the variations of Mahāsūtras across Buddhist textual lineages, see pp. 54–61.
                                For charts of the distribution and mention of the Mahāsūtras in Tibetan sources, see pp. 209–20. </note>
                    </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-13"/>
                        <p tid="23">As Skilling notes, the Mahāsūtras are broadly defined, first of all, as a small, selected set of texts from the
                            Āgamas. The Āgamas (and their Pali counterparts) are four (or five) collections of works considered to have been among
                            those teachings of the Buddha that were recited at the First Council.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-14"> The
                                Āgamas (Pali: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nikāyas</foreign>) of the Mūlasarvāstivāda are divided into four sections:
                                the Long Discourses (<foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dīrghāgama</foreign>), the Middle-Length Discourses (<foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Madhyamāgama</foreign>), the Connected Discourses, (<foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Saṃyuktāgama</foreign>), and the Numbered Discourses (<foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Ekottarāgama</foreign>).
                                Skilling (<title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, p. 17) notes that “the sūtras in question were transmitted
                                orally for several centuries before being written down; during both the oral and written periods they would have been
                                amplified, edited, and revised any number of times, translated from an original Prakrit or Prakrits into a ‘Buddhist’
                                and finally a more standard Sanskrit, and then further revised.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-15"/>
                        <p tid="24">The Sarvāstivāda and Mūlasarvāstivāda vinaya traditions each had their own selection of texts that they termed
                            Mahāsūtras. Each tradition listed them in texts that prescribed their recitation under particular circumstances (set out
                            below). The Sarvāstivāda lists eighteen texts in this way,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-16"> Skilling
                                provides a list of the Sarvāstivādin Mahāsūtra titles in Table 1, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, p. 54.
                            </note> while the Mūlasarvāstivāda lists six or eight.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-17"> See <ptr target="#EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-12"/><!--note 3--> and
                                Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, pp. 4–8.</note> These lists mention only the titles, and we do
                            not know what differences there may have been in the actual content of the texts in the two lists. Indeed, more generally,
                            we do not know with certainty if there were differences between the Sarvāstivāda and Mūlasarvāstivāda Āgamas, since the
                            Āgama collection of neither school has survived in full; the Chinese translations are of mixed or unknown origins.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-18"/>
                        <p tid="25">References in <hi rend="bold">Sanskrit</hi> to the Mahāsūtras, whether in the vinaya literature of the
                            Sarvāstivādins or that of the Mūlasarvāstivādins, are lost. However, fragments of the Sarvāstivādin recensions of the
                            Mahāsūtras have been found among a number of Sanskrit manuscript collections recovered in Central Asia.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-19"> Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, p. 18. Skilling notes that six of
                                these texts correspond to the Mūlasarvāstivādin list and ten correspond to the Sarvāstivādin list. </note>
                    </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-20"/>
                        <p tid="26">For the <hi rend="bold">Sarvāstivādin Vinaya</hi>:</p>
                        <list type="bullet">
                            <item>
                            <p tid="27">references are preserved only in <hi rend="bold">Chinese translation</hi> (dated to the early fifth
                                    century): eighteen titles of Mahāsūtras are listed in the section on keeping the rains retreat.</p>
                        </item>
                        </list>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-21"/>
                        <p tid="28">For the <hi rend="bold">Mūlasarvāstivādin Vinaya</hi>:</p>
                        <list type="bullet">
                            <item>
                            <p tid="29">references are preserved in <hi rend="bold">Chinese translation</hi> (dated to the very first years of
                                    the eighth century): six titles of Mahāsūtras are listed twice, in the sections on the taking of human life (the
                                    third <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">pārājika</foreign>) in the two <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title>
                                    texts (the one for monks and the one for nuns).</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="30">references are also preserved in <hi rend="bold">Tibetan translation</hi> (dated to the early ninth
                                    century): eight titles of Mahāsūtras are listed, also in the sections on the taking of human life (the third
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">pārājika</foreign>), also in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title>
                                (Toh 3)<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh3.html"/>, in passages under the rubric of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ro langs</foreign>
                                    (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vetāḍa</foreign>, “zombies”).</p>
                        </item>
                        </list>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-22"/>
                        <p tid="31">The Mahāsūtras were not translated into Chinese as a known corpus of texts, but a number of the texts are
                            preserved in Chinese translation as independent works belonging to the various Āgamas.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-23"> Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, pp. 105–9.</note>
                    </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-24"/>
                        <p tid="32">The eight titles mentioned in the Tibetan translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> match
                            those of the nine Tibetan Mahāsūtra texts in the Kangyur (two of the nine, numbers 5 and 6 in the list above, have the
                            same Sanskrit title, although rendered slightly differently in Tibetan). The six mentioned in the Chinese <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> match seven of the nine Tibetan Mahāsūtra texts (again because two of the
                            latter have the same title); the two titles that appear in the Tibetan list but not in the Chinese are the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsamāja</title> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āṭānāṭīya</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-25"> See Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, pp. 13–14.</note>
                    </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-26"/>
                        <p tid="33">Based on the lists of Mahāsūtras in the Chinese and Tibetan translations of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title>, the Tibetan affiliation with the Mūlasarvāstivādin pratimokṣa lineage to which this work
                            belongs, and the integral role that the Kashmiri scholar Jinamitra played in transmitting the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya to
                            Tibet, Skilling has pointed out that the Mahāsūtra collection that Jinamitra, Prajñāvarman, and the Tibetan translator
                            Yeshé Dé translated into Tibetan in the early ninth century probably represents a short corpus of discourses that were
                            important to the Kashmiri Mūlasarvāstivādin textual community. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-27"/>
                        <p tid="34">The Denkarma<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-28"> Denkarma, folio 300.a.3. See also Herrmann-Pfandt
                                2008, p. 128, no. 241.</note> and Phangthangma<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-29"> Phangthangma (2003), p.
                                20. </note> royal Tibetan catalogs indicate that the set of nine Mahāsūtras was originally considered an independent
                            corpus. The same set of nine is also mentioned in Chomden Rikpai Raldri’s thirteenth-century inventory of translated texts
                            under the heading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po</foreign>, but a tenth text with the title <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen po stong nyid brten cing ’brel par ’byung ba</title> is added to the list; it is difficult
                            to identify this title with any extant work.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-30"> Chomden Rikpai Raldri, folio
                                16.a–b; his inventory is thought to have been composed around 1270. See also Schaeffer and van der Kuijp 2009, pp.
                                135–36.</note> The tradition of classifying all the Mahāsūtras as discourses belonging to the “Lesser Vehicle” or
                            Hīnayāna is in accordance with their Mūlasarvāstivādin provenance and is seen in Chomden Rikpai Raldri’s inventory as well
                            as in the Tibetan scholar Butön’s (1290–1364) <title xml:lang="en">History of Indian Buddhism</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya gar chos ’byung</title>, ca. 1322–23).<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-31"> Butön,
                                    <title xml:lang="en">History</title>, folio 144.a. </note> Nevertheless only a decade or two later, in the
                            mid-fourteenth-century Tshalpa Kangyur, two of the Mahāsūtras began to be classified as Action (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kriyā</foreign>) tantras.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-32"/>
                        <p tid="35">That the status of the Mahāsūtras as a set of important works was maintained during the centuries of canon
                            formation in Tibet is reflected in their grouping—at least of the first seven—in a prominent position among the first
                            works in the Hīnayāna subdivision of the General Sūtra section, following only the massive and important <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh287.html">Application of Mindfulness of the Sacred
                                    Dharma</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmasmṛtyupasthāna</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam pa’i
                                chos dran pa nye bar gzhag pa</title>, Toh 287). </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-33"/>
                        <p tid="36">It is Skilling who suggests including in the corpus the tenth text, <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh312.html">The Mahāsūtra on Entering the City of Vaiśālī</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśālīpraveśamahāsūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yangs
                                pa’i grong khyer du ’jug pa’i mdo chen po</title>, Toh 312/698/1093), although it is a slight outlier. It is not
                            mentioned in the list of nine Mahāsūtras given in the Tibetan royal catalogs, but its title (like those of the other nine)
                            includes the appellation <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsūtra</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo chen
                            po</foreign>. It also has a clear affiliation with the Mūlasarvāstivādin school and has uses similar to the other
                            nine.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-article-3">
                        <head tid="37">Uses</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-34"/>
                        <p tid="38">Many of the sūtras in the group are versions of texts widely recited in a range of Buddhist traditions for their
                            efficacy in warding off evil circumstances and protecting what is good and positive (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rakṣa</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parītta</foreign>, Pali <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">paritta</foreign>). </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-35"/>
                        <p tid="39">The likelihood that this specific corpus was put to similar protective use by monastic and lay communities
                            affiliated with the Sarvāstivāda and Mūlasarvāstivāda traditions is supported by the contexts in which the lists of
                            Mahāsūtras occur in their vinaya literature. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-36"/>
                        <p tid="40">In the <hi rend="bold">Sarvāstivādin</hi> Vinaya the list of Mahāsūtras occurs in the section on the rules
                            governing the rains retreat vow that address various circumstances under which, for a period that is not to exceed seven
                            days, a monk is allowed to break his vow to remain in the same dwelling for three lunar months. The passage lists the
                            various discourses that are classified as Mahāsūtras by the Sarvāstivādins and then notes that a monk is permitted to
                            break the rains retreat vow for up to seven nights if a learned layperson has requested him to teach or recite the
                                Mahāsūtras.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-37"> Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, p.
                                20. Skilling provides an English rendering of Sylvain Lévi’s French translation of the original Chinese (Lévi 1915).
                                The passage opens with the Sarvāstivādin list of Mahāsūtras and then reads, “If this layman has not yet learned them
                                and wishes to do so, or if he has learned them and then forgotten them, and wishes to recite them, and if he sends
                                someone to a monk (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</foreign>) with this message: ‘The <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhadanta</foreign> is very learned, well versed in the Great Sūtras... I have not yet learned them and wish to do
                                so, or I have forgotten them and wish to recite them. May the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhadanta</foreign> come so
                                that I may receive instruction, study, recite, and inquire about the meaning’: in this case, he [the monk] should
                                accept and go for [up to] seven nights.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-38"/>
                        <p tid="41">The <hi rend="bold">Mūlasarvāstivādin</hi> Vinaya list of Mahāsūtras appears in a quite different context. In the
                            section on the rains retreat equivalent to the Sarvāstivāda passage just described, there is a reference to the four
                            Āgamas, but not to the Mahāsūtras. However, in a section of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> on the
                            third of the serious offenses that a monk may commit entailing “defeat” (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pārājika</foreign>, Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pham pa</foreign>), that of “taking a life,” one topic is a
                            discussion of what happens when a monk reanimates a corpse as a zombie (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vetāḍa</foreign>,
                            Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ro langs</foreign>) and instructs it to kill a victim—an event somewhat esoteric to a
                            modern audience but by no means unfamiliar in popular culture. Here the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title>
                            lists the Mahāsūtras, almost incidentally, among a number of protective circumstances and measures that may have been
                            taken by a potential victim that will cause the zombie’s murderous attack to fail:</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-39"/>
                        <q>
                        <p tid="42">“If some kind of protection measure has been taken—such as hanging garlands of beads made of
                            forest flowers at the entrance door, setting out a vase filled with water, tying a cow or a calf, tying a sheep, setting
                            out a mortar, laying a threshold slab at the door, or keeping a fire burning; if a victor, someone appointed by a victor,
                            a universal monarch, a woman pregnant with a universal monarch, a bodhisattva, or a woman pregnant with a bodhisattva is
                            present; or if someone recites, silently or aloud elaborately, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prātimokṣasūtra</title>, one
                            of the four Āgama collections, or the great Mahāsūtras—the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cūḍaśūnyatāmahāsūtra</title>, the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāśūnyatāmahāsūtra</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañcatrayamahāsūtra</title>, the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyājālamahāsūtra</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bimbisārapratyudgamanamahāsūtra</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhvajāgramahāsūtra</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āṭānāṭīyasūtramahāsūtra</title>, and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsamājasūtramahāsūtra</title>—the zombie, its mission having failed, might decide to kill the very monk behind it.
                            Were the zombie to kill the monk, that monk would have committed a grave fault. Were the monk to kill the zombie, he
                            commits a double grave fault: one because of killing the zombie, and the other because of his initial act.”<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-40">
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> (Toh 3), folio 143.a, here translated from 84000’s forthcoming
                                    translation.<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh3.html"/><!--Reference Toh 3 F.143.a--> The passage is also translated and discussed in Skilling 2007.</note>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-41"/>
                        <p tid="43">The Mūlasarvāstivādin <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhikṣunīvinayavibhaṅga</title> in its Tibetan translation does make
                            brief mention of zombies in the summary for the equivalent section<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-42">
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhikṣunīvinayavibhaṅga</title> (Toh 5), folio 51.b. 84000 translation forthcoming.<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh5.html"/><!--Reference Toh 5 F.51.b-->
                        </note> but does
                            not contain a passage matching the citation above. The eighth-century Chinese translations of both <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> texts (for bhikṣus and bhikṣunīs) by Yijing, however, both include almost
                            identical passages that closely match the Tibetan of the (bhikṣus’) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> and
                            mention the Mahāsūtras.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-43"/>
                        <p tid="44">The Mūlasarvāstivādin parallel to the Sarvāstivādin passage mentioning the Mahāsūtras in the context of the rules
                            for the rains retreat does not explicitly mention the Mahāsūtras. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-44"/>
                        <p tid="45">Extrapolating from the way the Mahāsūtras are mentioned in two different contexts in these two related vinaya
                            traditions, Skilling concludes that they were used as protective texts (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rakṣā</foreign>),<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-45"> Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, pp. 63–88. </note>
                            probably in a wide variety of situations and contexts other than the occasions mentioned in these passages. Some of the
                            Mahāsūtras (notably nos. 5, 6, 9, and 10 in the list above) have an explicit protective function, but others do not. It is
                            likely that the use of the group as protection was one among other, wider applications of their function as a “practical
                            canon” that represented in shortened form the entirety of the four Āgamas,<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-46">
                                Skilling, <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> II, p. 27. Skilling writes, “A complete set of the four Āgamas would
                                be somewhat unwieldy, difficult both to master and to prepare in manuscript form: it may be that the Mahāsūtras were
                                extracted in order to make a collection that would be easier for diligent monks, nuns, or lay-followers to study. This
                                might explain their arrangement according to the sequence of Āgamas, with the internal sequence of some sūtras intact
                                (at least Mahāsūtras 2, 3, and 4 for the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dīrghāgama</title>; Mahāsūtras 8 and 9 for the
                                    <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Madhyamāgama</title>; and the first three sections of the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Saṃyuktāgama</title>).” Skilling does not employ the formal/practical canon distinction here, but the phenomenon
                                he describes here certainly fits this approach to Buddhist “canonicity”; see Blackburn 1999. </note> which in turn
                            represent the entirety of the Buddha’s words—the resounding of which would have fulfilled many applications including
                            transmission, instruction, recollection, and protection.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-article-4">
                        <head tid="46">Parallels and Related Collections</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-47"/>
                        <p tid="47">Representing as they do an ancient layer of Buddhist tradition and practices used widely across Asia, the
                            individual Mahāsūtras all have numerous parallels. There are texts related to almost all of them in the Pali Theravādin
                            tradition, as well as works in the Chinese Sarvāstivādin corpus and in some cases Sarvāstivādin texts (or fragments of
                            them) that have survived in Sanskrit. Skilling’s <title xml:lang="en">Mahāsūtras</title> volume II<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-48">Skilling 1994–97, vol. 2, p. 442.</note> provides full lists for each text.</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-49"/>
                        <p tid="48">As a collection recited for protection, the Mahāsūtras are comparable in their uses (as well as, in part, in their
                            content) to the book known in Sri Lanka as the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Maha Pirit Pota</title> (“Great Book of
                            Protection”) or the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catubhāṇavārapāli</title> (“Text of the Four Recitals”).<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-50"> See Pemaloka 2018.</note>
                    </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-51"/>
                        <p tid="49">Within the Kangyur are two other collections that have similar uses, one more explicitly formalized as a group
                            than the other, and content that is comparable to varying degrees:</p>
                        <list type="bullet">
                            <item>
                            <p tid="50">The “<ref target="https://read.84000.co/knowledgebase/thirteen-late-translated-sutras.html">Thirteen
                                        late-translated sūtras</ref>” (Toh 31–43), a set of Theravāda texts translated from Pali, two of which, Toh 33
                                    and 34, are the Theravāda equivalents of two of the Mahāsūtras, numbered 8 and 9 in the list above (Toh 656/1061
                                    and Toh 653/1062) respectively; all are recited for protection.</p>
                        </item>
                            <item>
                            <p tid="51">The works related to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañcarakṣa</title>, five protective dhāraṇīs and the
                                    goddesses personifying them, Toh 558–563 and 587–588 in the Action Tantra section. They are not defined as a
                                    distinct collection in Tibetan but are in widespread use and popular today in Nepal.</p>
                        </item>
                        </list>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-52"/>
                        <p tid="52">To these one could add the entirety of the <ref target="https://read.84000.co/knowledgebase/compendium-dharanis.html">Compendium of Dhāraṇīs</ref>; although of course
                            its numerous texts have a considerably wider range of applications than the Mahāsūtras, it also represents a set of works
                            compiled specifically for their practical and protective functions.</p>
                    </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="53">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="54">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-53">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba rnam
                            ’byed</title>). Toh 3, Degé Kangyur vol. 5 (’dul ba, ca), folio 21.a–vol. 8 (’dul ba, nya), folio 269.a. Translation by
                        84000 forthcoming.<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh3.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-54">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhikṣunīvinayavibhaṅga</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong
                            ma’i ’dul ba rnam par ’byed pa</title>). Toh 5, Degé Kangyur vol. 9 (’dul ba, ta), folios 25.b–328.a. Translation by 84000
                            forthcoming.<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh5.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-55">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan dkar gyi chos kyi ’gyur ro cog gi
                            dkar chag</title>). Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-56">Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ʼphang thang ma</title>). Beijing: mi rigs
                        dpe skrun khang, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-57">Butön Rinchen Drup (bu ston rin chen grub). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’byung</title>
                            [<title xml:lang="en">History</title>] (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa’i bstan pa’i gsal byed chos kyi ’byung
                            gnas gsung rab rin po che’i gter mdzod</title>). In <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Works of Bu-Ston</title>, vol. 24
                        (ya), folios 1.b–212.a (pp. 633–1055). New Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture, 1965–71. <ref target="https://library.bdrc.io/show/bdr:MW22106_ECEBF8">BDRC W22106</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-58">Chomden Rikpai Raldri (bcom ldan rig pa’i ral gri). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan pa rgyas pa
                            rgyan gyi nyi ’od</title> [<title xml:lang="en">Ornamenting Sunlight of the Teachings’ Spread</title>]. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung gsung thor bu</title>, 2:3–158 (manuscript). <ref target="https://library.bdrc.io/show/bdr:MW1CZ1041">BDRC MW1CZ1041</ref>. See also Schaeffer and van der Kuijp
                        2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-59">Blackburn, Anne. “Looking for the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya</title>: Monastic Discipline
                        in the Practical Canons of the Theravāda.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of Buddhist
                            Studies</title> 22, no. 2 (1999): 281–310.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-60">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins
                            Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften,
                        2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-61">Lévi, Sylvain. “Sur la récitation primitive des textes bouddhiques.” <title xml:lang="fr">Journal Asiatique</title> (May–June 1915): 401–47.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-62">Pemaloka, Kotawila Sri Nayaka Thera. <title xml:lang="en">The Great Book of Protection: The
                            Text of the Four Recitals (Catubhāṇavārapāli): Sinhala – Maha Pirit Pota, with Translation into English</title>. Colombo:
                        Samayawardhana, 2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-63">Schaeffer, Kurtis R., and Leonard W. J. van der Kuijp. <title xml:lang="en">An Early Tibetan
                            Survey of Buddhist Literature: The Bstan pa rgyas pa rgyan gyi nyi ’od of Bcom ldan ral
                            gri</title>. Harvard Oriental Series 64. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-64">Skilling, Peter (1994–97). <title xml:lang="en">The Mahāsūtras: Great Discourses of the
                            Buddha</title>. 2 vols. Oxford: Pali Text Society, 1994–97.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-65">———(2007). “Zombies and Half-Zombies: Mahāsūtras and Other Protective Measures.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the Pali Text Society</title> 29 (2007): 313–30.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary" status="excluded" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASUTRAS-glossary">
                <list type="glossary"/>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>