<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">mahāsattva</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="bo">sems dpa’ chen po</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.3 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="3"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">mahasattva</idno>
                <date>2022-08-04</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#andre" when="2022-08-04T14:59:06.089Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-11">
                    <desc>Auto (knowledgebase-header)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-12">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="20">Overview</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-1"/>
                    <p tid="24">An epithet of advanced bodhisattvas. The term can be understood to mean “great courageous one” or "great hero,” or (from the Sanskrit) simply “great
                        being,” and is almost always found as an epithet of “bodhisattva.” The qualification “great” in this term, according to the majority of canonical
                        definitions, focuses on the generic greatness common to all bodhisattvas, i.e. the greatness implicit in the bodhisattva vow itself in terms of outlook,
                        aspiration, number of beings to be benefited, potential or eventual accomplishments, and so forth. In this sense the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā-</foreign> is closer in its connotations to the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā-</foreign> in “Mahāyāna” than to the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā-</foreign> in “mahāsiddha.” While individual bodhisattvas described as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsattva</foreign> may in many cases also be
                        “great” in terms of their level of realization, this is largely coincidental, and in the canonical texts the epithet is not restricted to bodhisattvas at
                        any particular point in their career. Indeed, in a few cases even bodhisattvas whose path has taken a wrong direction are still described as bodhisattva
                        mahāsattva.</p>
                    <p tid="28">Later commentarial writings do nevertheless define the term—variably—in terms of bodhisattvas having attained a particular level (bhūmi) or
                        realization. The most common qualifying criteria mentioned are attaining the path of seeing, attaining irreversibility (according to its various
                        definitions), or attaining the seventh bhūmi.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="21">In the Prajñāpāramitā sūtras</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-2"/>
                    <p tid="25">Perhaps the most detailed explanations of the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsattva</foreign> are found in the long Prajñāpāramitā
                        sūtras. In them, in answer to a question put by Subhūti, four distinct discussions follow. The first is the Buddha’s own explanation; there is then
                        discussion of further statements by Śāriputra, Subhūti himself, and Pūrṇa Maitreyāṇīputra.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-5">
                    <head type="section" tid="22">In: <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in Twenty-Five Thousand Lines</title>, vol. ka, F.188.b<ref rend="hidden" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh9.html">ka F.188.b</ref> (Toh 9)</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-5"/>
                    <p tid="26">Then the venerable Subhūti asked the Blessed One, “Blessed Lord, why, in the term bodhisattva great beings, are bodhisattvas called great beings?” </p>
                    <p tid="29">“Subhūti,” replied the Blessed One, “they are called bodhisattva great beings because they will lead the great category of sentient beings with
                        certainty of progress to their consummation.”</p>
                    <p tid="31">“Blessed Lord, what is the great category of sentient beings with certainty of progress that bodhisattva great beings will lead to their
                        consummation?”</p>
                    <p tid="33">“Subhūti,” replied the Blessed One, “that great category of sentient beings includes those on the level of the spiritual family, those on the
                        eighth-lowest level, those who have entered the stream to nirvāṇa, those who are destined for one more rebirth, those who will no longer be reborn, those
                        who are arhats, those who are pratyekabuddhas, those beings who have initially set their minds on enlightenment, and [other beings], up to and including
                        bodhisattva great beings who dwell on the level at which progress has become irreversible. Subhūti, these constitute the great category of sentient beings
                        with certainty of progress, and it is to their corresponding consummation that bodhisattva great beings will lead them. In that regard, when bodhisattva
                        great beings give rise to the vajra-like setting of the mind on enlightenment, one speaks of the consummation of the definite great category of sentient
                        beings with certainty of progress.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-3">
                    <head type="section" tid="23">In: <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in Eighteen Thousand Lines</title>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh10.html/#UT22084-031-002-915">7.30–7.31</ref> (Toh 10)</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-3"/>
                    <p tid="27">Then the venerable Śāradvatī­putra said to the Blessed One, “Reverend Lord! I am inspired to say in what sense bodhisattvas are called ‘great
                        beings.’” </p>
                    <p tid="30">The Blessed One asked, “Śāradvatī­putra, are you inspired to say that?”</p>
                    <p tid="32">“Yes, Reverend Lord,” he replied, “I am inspired to say that.”</p>
                    <p tid="34">“Well then, how is it?”</p>
                    <p tid="8">“Reverend Lord! The enlightened mind of the bodhisattvas is equal to the unequaled, and it is not shared in common with any śrāvakas or
                        pratyekabuddhas. In that sense a bodhisattva is called a ‘great being.’ If one were to ask why, Reverend Lord, bodhisattvas are called ‘great beings,’ it is
                        because [F.72.b] they are even unattached to the mind endowed with omniscience, which is uncontaminated and not included within the three world
                        systems.”</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-4">
                    <head type="section" tid="10">In: <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in Eighteen Thousand Lines</title>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh10.html/#UT22084-029-001-6371">84.18–84.20</ref> (Toh 10)</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-4"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>Why then are they called a great being?</l> 
                        <l>They will become foremost in a great mass of beings. </l>
                        <l>They chop down the many views of a mass of beings.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, they get called a great being.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>Greatly generous, with great intellect and great power, </l>
                        <l>They have set out in the supreme Great Vehicle of the victors, </l>
                        <l>And buckled on the great
                            armor to conquer Māra’s deceit. </l>
                        <l>Therefore, they are called a great being.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>As when a magician at a crossroads conjures </l>
                        <l>The illusion of many people and severs ten million heads,</l> 
                        <l>The bodhisattvas know that, like those
                            victims, all beings </l>
                        <l>Are like illusions, and so have no fear.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-6">
                    <head type="section" tid="38">In: <title xml:lang="en">The White Lotus of Compassion</title> (Toh 112), <ptr target="#UT22084-050-003-1333"/>  </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-6"/>
                    <p tid="39">In chapter 4 of this text the Buddha Ratnagarbha states that bodhisattvas who have vowed 
                        to attain awakening under relatively easy circumstances do not deserve the title 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsattva</foreign>, which should be reserved for those like 
                        Mahākāruṇika (the bodhisattva who, in the past lives narrative, is a previous life of Śākyamuni) who have vowed to 
                        attain awakening only in the most degenerate and difficult times and places. </p>
                    <p tid="40">However, this 
                        statement is best taken as highlighting a specific point of perspective rather than as a general gloss, 
                        since elsewhere throughout the text the term is nevertheless used—just as it is in most Mahāyāna sūtras—as an 
                        epithet for bodhisattvas in 
                        general regardless of their individual status, qualities, or aspirations. 
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-7">
                    <head type="section" tid="41">In: <title xml:lang="en">The Absorption of the Miraculous Ascertainment of Peace</title>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh129.html/#UT22084-055-003-132">1.119</ref> (Toh 129) </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-7"/>
                    <p tid="15">“Mañjuśrī, there are also four qualities that, when practiced, make one a bodhisattva great being. What are these four qualities? They are (1)
                        extending timely generosity, (2) being free from deceit and pretense, (3) not taking breaks from engendering the mind of awakening with an altruistic
                        attitude, and (4) being deeply respectful toward even a bodhisattva who has just begun engendering the mind of awakening. When practicing these four
                        qualities, one is called a bodhisattva great being.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-article-8">
                    <head type="section" tid="16">According to Mipham’s commentary on Maitreya’s Mahāyānasūtrālaṃkāra, (citing below Padmakara’s translation “A Feast of Nectar of
                        the Supreme Vehicle”, page 787; (in Dharmachakra’s translation it's in page 852)): </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-8"/>
                    <p tid="17">“ “Great Heroes” designates those who have mastered great magical powers, such as displaying in a single pore of their bodies a kalpa of formation
                        and destruction of a third-order great universal system of one thousand million worlds. Alternatively, because they wish to attain unsurpassable
                        enlightenment themselves, they are called Heroes of Enlightenment, and because they wish to liberate all sentient beings from the sufferings of saṃsāra and
                        set them in nirvānạ, they are called Great Heroes. Again, from the point of view of their being, on account of their great wisdom, untainted by the faults
                        of saṃsāra even while staying in saṃsāra, they are Heroes of Enlightenment; and because, through their great compassion, they strive endlessly for the
                        welfare of sentient beings, they are referred to as Great Heroes. And again, those who have aroused the mind intent on accomplishing unsurpassable
                        enlightenment are Heroes of Enlightenment, and those who possess that which has the seven forms of greatness as explained above are Great Heroes.
                        <note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-10">
                            The greatness of its reference,/ And likewise of its twin accomplishment,/ Its gnosis, diligent application,/ Its skill in means, (XX, 59)/ Its
                            great consummation,/ And great buddha activities—/ It is because it possesses these forms of greatness/ That the Great Vehicle is so described. (XX, 60)
                        </note>
                        Apart from these comparative distinctions, there is no difference between a Hero of Enlightenment and a Great Hero, both being general names for a
                        bodhisattva. </p>
                    <p tid="18">From the point of view of different levels, those on the earlier levels are Heroes of Enlightenment and those on the later ones are Great Heroes.
                        Those on the level of earnest aspiration, who have aroused the mind intent on enlightenment, are Heroes of Enlightenment, while those who have attained the
                        noble levels are Great Heroes of Enlightenment. Those on the seven impure levels are Heroes of Enlightenment, while those dwelling on the pure levels are
                        Great Heroes. Whichever the case, it is because they are courageous and undaunted in practicing boundless transcendent perfections, the causes of
                        unsurpassable enlightenment that are so difficult to practice, and in attaining unsurpassable enlightenment, the result that is so difficult to attain, that
                        they are called Heroes of Enlightenment."</p>
                </div>
            </div><!--Add descriptions from Toh 263, in which mahāsattva seems to have a specific meaning like the statement in Toh 112-->
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="3">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" rend="default-text" tid="4">Bibliography Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl rend="default-text" xml:id="EFT-KB-MAHASATTVA-9">This is a sample bibliographic reference with a <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">link example</ref>. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary"/>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>