<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Medicine Buddha texts in the Kangyur </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">medicine-buddha-texts-in-kangyur</idno>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-09T22:31:33.163Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-20">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-21">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">Medicine Buddha texts in the Kangyur (Bhaiṣajyaguruvaiḍūryaprabharāja)</head>
                    <p tid="7">notes by JC July 2018</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-2"/>
                    <p tid="8">For the medicine Buddha sūtras, I have looked at the Degé texts and dkar chag, skimmed through Schopen’s 1978 thesis on the Gilgit MSS
                        (very informative on a wide range of topics), looked at what little is online, . The following is incomplete but :</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-3"/>
                    <p tid="9">The “Medicine Buddha” Bhaiṣajyaguru-vaiḍūryaprabharāja is often seen or depicted as the seventh of seven or eight “medicine buddhas;”
                        when there are eight, the eighth is Śākyamuni (NB these seven are not the usual “seven buddhas of the past”). The canonical texts about
                        him (or them in the case of the seven or eight) focus largely on the detailed vows they took, as bodhisattvas, to relieve the sufferings
                        of beings in various ways. Not all of these vows, or even a majority, are directly concerned with illness or healing, but many are
                        related to dying and all to the karmic causes of sufferings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-4"/>
                    <p tid="10">Toh 503 is sometimes called (in Tibetan) the “larger Medicine Buddha sūtra” and Toh 504 “the smaller.”  503 is a bit over twice as long
                        as 504.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-5"/>
                    <p tid="11">Toh 503, the larger (it has two <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bam po</foreign>), details the past vows of all seven “medicine
                        buddhas;” those of the first six fill the first <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bam po</foreign> and the 12 great vows of the
                        seventh, Bhaiṣajyaguruvaiḍūryaprabharāja himself, most of the second <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bam po</foreign>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-6"/>
                    <p tid="12">Toh 504, the smaller, focuses on the 12 vows of Bhaiṣajyaguru-vaiḍūryaprabharāja alone. Much of it seems to be very close, or even
                        identical, to the second <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bam po</foreign> of 503 (this would need more careful checking than I
                        have done, and might mean a reduction in per-page costs), but it does contain a page or two of additional material at the beginning and
                        end.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-7"/>
                    <p tid="13">Both were translated from Sanskrit in the early period by the same team of Indian-Tibetan translators (Jinamitra, Dānaśīla,
                        Śīlendrabodhi, and Yeshé Dé), and despite the considerable overlapping were always treated as separate texts (they are both listed in
                        the Denkarma inventory). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-8"/>
                    <p tid="14">In terms of how they correspond to the Chinese translations, I haven’t looked into it much, but this is from Wikipedia:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-9"/>
                    <p tid="15">“There are two popular Chinese translations of this sutra: one by Xuanzang and the other by <ref target="HYPERLINK">Yijing</ref> both
                        translated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tang_dynasty">Tang dynasty</ref>. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taisho_Tripitaka">Taisho Tripitaka</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qianlong_Emperor">Qianlong</ref> Tripitaka (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_Chinese_characters">Chinese</ref>: <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">乾隆大藏經</foreign>) each have three translations of the sutra:</p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="16">By Dharmagupta in 615 CE (Taisho: vol. 14, no. 449; Qianlong: no. 166)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">By Xuanzang in 650 CE (Taisho: vol. 14, no. 450; Qianlong: no. 167)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="18">By Yijing in 707 CE (Taisho: vol. 14, no. 451; Qianlong: no. 168)</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-10"/>
                    <p tid="19">These three versions have different titles:</p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="20">Dharmagupta: <title xml:lang="en">Sutra of the Vows of the Medicine Buddha</title>
                                <lb/>
                                <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_Chinese_characters">Chinese</ref>: <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">藥師如來本願經</foreign>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="21">Xuanzang: <title xml:lang="en">Sutra of the Vows of the Medicine Buddha of Lapis Lazuli Crystal Radiance</title>
                                <lb/>
                                <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_Chinese_characters">Chinese</ref>: <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">藥師琉璃光如來本願功德經</foreign>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="22">Yijing: <title xml:lang="en">Sutra of the Vows of the Medicine Buddha of Lapis Lazuli Crystal Radiance and Seven Past
                                    Buddhas</title>
                                <lb/>
                                <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_Chinese_characters">Chinese</ref>: <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">藥師琉璃光七佛本願功德經</foreign> (no. 168, two scrolls).</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-11"/>
                    <p tid="23">The version translated by Yijing includes not only the vows of the Medicine Buddha but also the vows of the Seven Past Buddhas.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-12"/>
                    <p tid="24">In other words, I presume that Toh 503 corresponds more to Taisho 449 and 450, while Toh 504 seems to be similar to Taisho 451, but this
                        would need to be checked. Toh 504 exists in Sanskrit, as several manuscripts found in Gilgit, and a large excerpt in the
                        Śikṣāsamuccaya.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-13"/>
                    <p tid="25">Coming now to Toh 505, this shorter (5 page) text doesn’t seem to correspond to a Chinese text. It is a teaching by the Buddha Śākyamuni,
                        in answer to Mañjuśrī, in which people are advised to recite homages to the eight medicine buddhas and then a number of bodhisattvas and
                        others, then a dhāraṇī. It was translated from Sanskrit by the same Indian-Tibetan team. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-14"/>
                    <p tid="26">Some or all three of these texts seem to have been revised into the “new terminology”, and for Toh 505 the colophon mentions that Atiśa
                        did that.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-15"/>
                    <p tid="27">In fact just after Toh 505 there is a separate short text that we should probably call Toh 505a, not mentioned in the Tohoku catalog,
                        just one and a half lines, giving a short version of the Bhaiṣajyaguru mantra for dispensing medicines.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-16"/>
                    <p tid="28">All three (/four) texts are classified as tantras in the Degé, under Action Tantra belonging to the principal deity of the Tathāgata
                        family, but in some other Kangyurs are treated as sūtras. There isn’t anything very tantric about them. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-17"/>
                    <label tid="53">The Seven/Eight Tathāgatas</label>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="30">Suparikīrtitanamaśrīrāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="term">མཚན་ལེགས་པར་ཡོངས་བསྒྲགས་དཔལ་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་</foreign>) 8 vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="31">Svaraghoṣarāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="quote">རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང༌། ཟླ་བ་དང༌།
                                    པད་མས་རབ་ཏུ་བརྒྱན་པ་མཁས་པ་གཟི་བརྗིད་སྒྲང་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་་་་རྒྱལ་པོ་</foreign>) 8 vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="32">Suvarṇabhadravimalaratnaprabhāsarāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="quote">གསེར་བཟང་དྲི་མེད་རིན་ཆེན་སྣང་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་གྲུབ་པ་</foreign>) 4 vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="33">Aśokottamaśrīrāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="quote">མྱ་ངན་མེད་མཆོག་དཔལ་</foreign>) 4 vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="34">Dharmakīrtisāgaraghoṣarāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="quote">ཆོས་བསྒྲགས་རྒྱ་མཚོའི་དབྱངས་</foreign>) 4 vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="35">Abhijñarāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="quote">ཆོས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་མཆོག་གི་བློས་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་</foreign>) 4
                                vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="36">Bhaiṣajyaguruvaiḍūryaprabharāja (<foreign xml:lang="bo" type="quote">སྨན་གྱི་བླ་བཻ་ཌཱུ་ཪྻའི་འོད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་</foreign>) 12
                                vows</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="37">[Śākyamuni]</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-18"/>
                    <p tid="38">For their vows (Gavin Kilty) see also <ref target="http://landofmedicinebuddha.org/about-medicine-buddha/vows-of-medicine-buddhas/">http://landofmedicinebuddha.org/about-medicine-buddha/vows-of-medicine-buddhas/</ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="39">The Twelve Vows</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-19"/>
                    <p tid="40">The Twelve Vows of the Medicine Buddha upon attaining Enlightenment, according to the Medicine Buddha Sutra (Chinese
                        translation) are:</p>

                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="41"><!--1.--> I vow that my body shall shine as beams of brilliant light on this infinite and boundless world, showering on all
                                beings, getting rid of their ignorance and worries with my teachings. May all beings be like me, with a perfect status and
                                character, upright mind and soul, and finally attaining enlightenment like the Buddha.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="42"><!--2.--> I vow that my body be like crystal, pure and flawless, radiating rays of splendid light to every corner, brightening
                                up and enlightening all beings with wisdom. With the blessings of compassion, may all beings strengthen their spiritual power
                                and physical energy, so that they could fulfil their dreams on the right track.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="43"><!--3.--> I vow that I shall grant by means of boundless wisdom, all beings with the inexhaustible things that they require,
                                and relieving them from all pains and guilt resulting from materialistic desires. Although clothing, food, accommodation and
                                transport are essentials, it should be utilised wisely as well. Besides self-consumption, the remaining should be generously
                                shared with the community so that all could live harmoniously together.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="44"><!--4.--> I vow to lead those who have gone astray back to the path of righteousness. Let them be corrected and returned to the
                                Buddha way for enlightenment.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="45"><!--5.--> I vow that I shall enable all sentient beings to observe precepts for spiritual purity and moral conduct. Should
                                there be any relapse or violation, they shall be guided by repentance. Provided they sincerely regret their wrong-doings, and
                                vow for a change with constant prayers and strong faith in the Buddha, they could receive the rays of forgiveness, recover their
                                lost moral and purity.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="46"><!--6.--> I vow that all beings who are physically disabled or sick in all aspects be blessed with good health, both physically
                                and mentally. All who pays homage to Buddha faithfully will be blessed.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="47"><!--7.--> I vow to relieve all pain and poverty of the very sick and poor. The sick be cured, the helpless be helped, the poor
                                be assisted.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="48"><!--8.--> I vow to help women who are undergoing sufferings and tortures and seeking for transformation into men. By hearing my
                                name, paying homage and praying, their wishes would be granted and ultimately attain Buddhahood.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="49"><!--9.--> I vow to free all beings from evil thoughts and its control. I shall lead them onto the path of light through
                                inculcating them with righteousness and honour so that they will walk the Buddha way.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="50"><!--10.--> I vow to save prisoners who have genuinely repented and victims of natural disasters. My supreme powers will bless
                                those who are sincere and be freed from sufferings.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="51"><!--11.--> I vow to save those who suffer from starvation and those who committed a crime to obtain food. If they hear my name
                                and faithfully cherish it, I shall lead them to the advantages of Dharma and favour them with the best food and eventually lead
                                a tranquil and happy life.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="52"><!--12.--> I vow to save those who suffer from poverty, tormented by mosquitoes and wasps day and night. If they come across my
                                name, cherish it with sincerity and practise dharma to strengthen their merits, they will be able to achieve their
                            wishes</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-MEDICINE-BUDDHA-TEXTS-IN-KANGYUR-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>