<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Pūrṇa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Puṇṇa</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.1 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">purna</idno>
                <date>2020-08-13</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-7">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-02T19:21:17.655Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-8">
                    <desc>Ready to publish October 2023.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-02T19:21:17.655Z" type="publication-status" status="1" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-9">
                    <desc>1</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <!--<profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>Purna</term>
                </keywords>
                <catRef scheme="knowledgeBase" target="k"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <!-\-SEE TEI GUIDELINES FOR:
          •  TAXONOMY ELEMENT:
          https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-taxonomy.html
          •  TEXT CLASSIFICATION:
          https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD43
          -\->
                <taxonomy xml:id="taxonomy-84000">
                    <category xml:id="persons.human.disciples.pūrṇa">
                        <catDesc>Persons / Human / Disciples / Pūrṇa</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>-->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="25">Pūrṇa</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="12">Disciples named Pūrṇa</head>
                    <p tid="13">A common name in the canonical literature, and a word with a range of literal meanings: full, fulfilled, complete, whole, abundant, accomplished, rich, contented, etc. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-5"/>
                    <p tid="14">At least five of the Buddha Śākyamuni’s disciples with this name are mentioned in the Kangyur: </p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15">Pūrṇa Maitrāyaṇīputra, a brahmin from Kapilavastu; his mother, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitrāyanī</foreign>, was the sister of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauṇḍinya</foreign>, and Pūrṇa was ordained by his uncle when the latter (by then known as Ājñātakauṇḍinya) returned to Kapilavastu soon after the Buddha’s first
                                teaching; Pūrṇa attained the state of arhat in Kapilavastu and only met the Buddha himself later, in Śrāvastī. This is the Pūrṇa who was “foremost in teaching” among
                                the ten principal disciples, and is mentioned in many sūtras including <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh61.html">The Questions of
                                        Pūrṇa</ref>
                                </title> (Toh 61), <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh176.html#UT22084-060-005-126">The Teaching of
                                        Vimalakīrti</ref>
                                </title> (Toh 176), and <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh138.html">The Ratnaketu Dhāraṇī</ref>
                                </title>
                                (Toh 138). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="16">The Pūrṇa who was one of the second group of five monks ordained by the Buddha, the “five friends” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye lnga sde</foreign>), all
                                Vārāṇasī merchants’ sons (headed by Yaśas and, following his lead, Pūrṇa, Vimala, Gavāṃpati, and Subāhu). First, the Buddha’s former companions in asceticism (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lnga sde</foreign>), followed by these five, together constituted the first ten bhikṣus to receive
                                ordination. This Pūrṇa is the one mentioned in <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh1-1.html">The Chapter on Going
                                Forth</ref>
                                </title>, and in many of the lists of śrāvaka disciples that figure in the scene-setting introductions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nidāna</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gleng gzhi</foreign>) of sūtras. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">The Pūrṇa of <title xml:lang="en">The Deeds of Pūrṇa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇāvadāna</title>)<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-1">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇāvadāna</title> is one of the stories included in Sanskrit <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>, thought to date to the
                                    seventeenth century as a compendium but containing works that are much earlier (see bibliography). For English translation see Rotman (2008). </note>, is the son of
                                a wealthy merchant and his slave girl in the Aparāntaka (Western India) seaport of Sūrpāraka. He was a successful maritime expedition leader and heard of the Buddha
                                from some merchants from Śrāvasti whom he accompanied on a sea voyage. He then went to meet the Buddha, went forth as a monk, and later returned to the south-west,
                                building a sandalwood temple near Sūrpāraka to which he invited the Buddha; the Buddha and his monks arrive flying through the sky. This Pūrṇa is almost certainly also
                                the protagonist in <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh99.html">The Precious Discourse on the Blessed One’s Extensive Wisdom That
                                        Leads to Infinite Certainty</ref>
                                </title> (Toh 99); he is known as Puṇṇa Suppāraka in the Pali texts. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="18">An older Pūrṇa, the “Elder Pūrṇa from Kuṇḍopadāna,” who is also mentioned in <title xml:lang="en">The Deeds of Pūrṇa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇāvadāna</title>) as one of the monks in the Buddha’s airborne entourage coming to visit the Pūrṇa above (3). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="19">A very rich and generous brahmin called Pūrṇa from the Mountains of the South who invites the Buddha and receives a prediction of enlightenment, but is not
                                ordained; he is the subject of the first story in <title xml:lang="en">The Hundred Accounts of Noble Deeds, Beginning with That of Pūrṇa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇapramukhāvadānaśataka</title>, Toh 343), and also of “<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-073-001.html#UT22084-073-001-3893">The Story of Pūrṇa</ref>,” a section in Part Eight of <title xml:lang="en">The
                                    Hundred Deeds</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmaśataka</title>, Toh 340). This Pūrṇa will become a buddha also named Pūrṇa, according to the prediction. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="20">Another disciple is sometimes called Pūrṇa but this should probably more correctly be Pūraṇa, since the Tibetan of his name is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzogs
                                    byed</foreign> and not <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po</foreign>, He is the sickly and short-lived Pūraṇa of Śrāvasti, attendant of Aniruddha, who became an
                                arhat just before he died and is the subject of “<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-073-001.html#UT22084-073-001-173">The Story of Pūraṇa</ref>” in
                                Part One of <title xml:lang="en">The Hundred Deeds</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmaśataka</title>, Toh 340). </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-6"/>
                    <p tid="23">There are other individuals named Pūrṇa in the Kangyur, including both a māra and a future tathāgata in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇāpuṇḍarīka</title> (Toh
                        112).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="24">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="22">Main Section </head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-3">Vaidya, L (ed.). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>
                        <ref target="http://gretil.sub.uni-goettingen.de/gretil/1_sanskr/4_rellit/buddh/divyav_u.htm">Sanskrit edition]. Buddhist Sanskrit Texts 20. Mithila Institute (1959). Also
                            online at [GRETIL</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-PURNA-4">Rotman, Andy (tr.). “The Story of Pūrṇa,” in <title xml:lang="en">Divine Stories: Divyāvadāna</title> Part I. Somerville: Wisdom Publications (2008),
                        pp. 71–118. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>