<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Sugata</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa, bde gshegs</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="zh">善逝 (shan shi), 善來 (shan lai)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">sugata</idno>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-09T21:58:26.437Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-16">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-17">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">Overview </head>
                    <p tid="7">One of the many epithets of a buddha, and frequently used as a synonym (but perhaps less often than <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign>).</p>
                    <p tid="8">The English renderings “one who has well gone” or “well-gone one” are approximate, but serviceable if it is understood that they are renderings in English of this
                        specific epithet. It is also acceptable in some cases to leave the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> in Sanskrit. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="9">Etymology and Meaning</head>
                    <p tid="10">The Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">su</foreign> means, in general, “good” or “well,” and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gata</foreign> means
                        “gone,” the past passive participle of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">√gam</foreign>, “go”; <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gata</foreign> here does not denote
                        physical movement as much as changing state, “become.” </p>
                    <p tid="11">In essence, the meaning is “one who has gone well,” in three main senses: (1) excellently, (2) irreversibly, and (3) completely. </p>

                    <p tid="12">These three meanings are outlined in the entry for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> in the ninth century <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Drajor Bampo
                            Nyipa</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title>)<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-2"> Toh 4347 in the Tengyur, vol. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sna tshogs</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co</foreign>, F.133.b.3. The <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title> (“Two
                            Fascicles on Lexical Usage”) is the companion work to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye brag tu rtogs par byed pa chen
                                po</title>, or “Great Handbook of Comprehensive Learning,” Toh 4346), both constituting the specifications for the state-sponsored translation work of the early
                            translation period.</note> as follows, to expand on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>’s specified Tibetan rendering, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde bar gshegs pa</foreign>:</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="13">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sugata ces bya ba gcig tu na | śobhanagata sugata surūpavat ces bya ste | legs par gshegs pas na legs par gshegs pa ste | gzugs legs
                                pa bzhin | apunar āvṛtyagata sunaṣṭajvarvat ces bya ste | phyir mi ldog ba gshegs pas na legs par gshegs pa ste | rims nad legs par byang ba bzhin | yāvad
                                gantavyagamanāt sugata | supūrṇaghaṭavat ces bya ste | ji tsam du ’gro bar bya ba ma lus par phyin pas na legs par gshegs pa ste | bum pa legs par gang bzhin pa zhes
                                ’byung | yang na gcig tu na | dharmmaskandha las ’byung ba sugata iti sukhito bhagavān | svargita avyathitadharmmasamanvāgata | tad ucyate sugata ces ’byung ste | bcom
                                ldan ’das bde bar gyur cing mtho ris kyi bde ba dang ldan la | gnod ba mi mnga’ zhing gnod pa med pa’i chos dang ldan pas na bde bar gshegs pa ’am bde ba brnyes pa la
                                yang bya ste | ’dir sngar grags ba dang | dharmmaskandha las ’byung ba dang sbyar te bde bar gshegs pa zhes btags |</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </q>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-4"/>
                    <p tid="41">Translation:</p>
                    <p tid="14">[A.] <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Sugata</foreign> according to one definition means:</p>

                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15"><!--(1)-->
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śobhanagata sugata surūpavat</foreign> — “well gone” because he has gone excellently, as in “well formed.” </p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="16"><!--(2)-->
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">apunar āvṛtyagata sunaṣṭajvarvat</foreign> — “well gone” because he has gone irreversibly, as in “an epidemic has been well
                                cleared away.” </p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="17"><!--(3)-->
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yāvad gantavyagamanāt sugata | supūrṇaghaṭavat</foreign> — “well gone” because he has gone as far as there is to go, as in “the
                                vase has been well filled.”</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-5"/>
                    <p tid="18">[B.] According to another definition from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmaskandha</title>:<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-3">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmaskandha</title> here refers not to the sūtra of that name, which contains no mention of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign>, but probably to the *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmadharmaskandhapādaśāstra</title>, an Abhidharma treatise of the Sarvāstivādin school
                            attributed in the Indian tradition to Śāriputra but in the Chinese tradition to Maudgalyāyana. It was never translated into Tibetan and now exists in full only as a Chinese
                            translation by Xuanzang, and in the form of fragments of a Mūlasarvsāstivardin recension in Sanskrit found in Gilgit.</note>
                    </p>

                    <p tid="19">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">sugata iti sukhito bhagavān | svargita avyathitadharmmasamanvāgata | tad ucyate sugata</foreign>” — “because the Blessed One is in
                        wellbeing, and has the wellbeing of the higher realms, and because he is not subject to harm and has the dharmas of the absence of harm, he [can either be said to have] ‘well
                        gone’ or, also, to have ‘attained wellbeing.” </p>

                    <p tid="20">A combination of the former definitions with the latter from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmaskandha</title> was used to designate the [Tibetan rendering] <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde bar gshegs pa</foreign>.</p>

                    <p tid="21">The three shades of meaning [A. 1–3] of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> set out in the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Drajor Bampo Nyipa</title> entry
                        are found quite widely in the Sanskrit literature. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-6"/>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="22"><!--1)--> To express the sense of “gone/become perfect,” <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> is glossed using phrases such as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">praśastaṃ gataḥ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śobhanaṃ gataḥ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">suṣṭhurūpeṇa gataḥ</foreign>, etc. When the three main meanings are listed together, this one comes first, perhaps suggesting that this meaning of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> is the most important.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="23"><!--2)--> To express the sense of irreversibility, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> is glossed as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">apunarāvṛttyā gataḥ</foreign>.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="24"><!--3)--> To express the sense of “gone/become completely,” <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> is glossed using phrases such as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">atiśayena gataḥ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niḥśeṣaṃ gataḥ</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">suṣṭhugataḥ</foreign>.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-7"/>
                    <p tid="25">There are also other interpretive phrases that fall somewhere between the above three interpretations such as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nikhilasavāsanāśeṣakleśajñeyāvaraṇāni prahāya gataḥ</foreign>, meaning “gone having abandoned all the kleśas and cognitive obscurations along with all the habitual
                        tendencies,” or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nairātmyadvayamārgeṇa samyag gataḥ</foreign>, meaning “gone properly on the path of the two [types of] no-self.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-8"/>
                    <p tid="26">The rendering in Tibetan, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde bar gshegs pa</foreign>, has led to different interpretations in other languages because <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde bar</foreign> can be taken either adverbially (gone “well” or “easily”), or as a dative (gone “to happiness” or “to bliss”). The adverbial
                        interpretation is closer to the original Sanskrit and conforms to the first part [A.] of the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Drajor Bampo Nyipa</title> entry. However, the second part
                        [B.] of that entry (derived from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmaskandha</title>) potentially leads to some blurring of this distinction and supports the dative
                        interpretation, as it seems to refer to the happiness, wellbeing, or bliss to which the Buddha has gone.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-9"/>
                    <p tid="27">The Tibetan rendering <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde bar gshegs pa</foreign>, as decreed in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>, seems to
                        have been universally used. There appear to have been no alternative renderings of the term in Tibetan translations even prior to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>’s establishment.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-article-3">
                    <head type="section" tid="28">Details of Usage </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-10"/>
                    <p tid="29">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Sugata</foreign> is a very widespread epithet for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">buddha</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign> found in a wide variety of genres of literature.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-11"/>
                    <p tid="30">The Buddha Śākyamuni refers to himself as “the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign>” but not as “the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign>.” When others talk about him or address him, however, both are used, sometimes even in adjacent sentences.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-12"/>
                    <p tid="31">
                        <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sugata</foreign> is most commonly used alone; when a whole sequence of epithets are used to name or otherwise mention a buddha, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign> is more common than <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign>. Both <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign> do not seem to be used together in the same sequence, with the notable exception of the
                        phrase </p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="32">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de bzhin gshegs pa dgra bcom pa yang dag par rdzogs pa’i sangs rgyas rig pa dang zhabs su ldan pa/ bde bar gshegs pa/ ’jig rten
                                mkhyen pa/ skyes bu ’dul ba’i kha lo sgyur ba bla na med pa/ lha dang mi rnams kyi ston pa/ sangs rgyas bcom ldan ’das de </foreign>
                        </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <p tid="33">“…the thus-gone, worthy, fully and truly awakened buddha, perfect in knowledge and conduct, a blissful one, a knower of the world, an unsurpassed leader of those to
                            be trained, a teacher of gods and humans, that blessed buddha…”</p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-13"/>
                    <p tid="34">Whereas <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign> can be used for buddhas of the past, present, and future, the use of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> seems to be mainly confined to the past and present—with one exception, perhaps confirming this unwritten rule, in the common phrase about a
                        future buddha “after that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign> has passed away…”.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-14"/>
                    <p tid="35">As a compound, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugatagarbha</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde gshegs snying po</foreign>) is used as a
                        synonym for buddha-nature at a roughly equal frequency as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgatagarbha</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">de gshegs
                            snying po</foreign>), with no apparent difference in shades of meaning.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-article-4">
                    <head type="section" tid="36">Other terms:</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-15"/>
                    <list rend="dots" type="bullet">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="37">Sugatas of the Five Families: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde gshegs rigs lnga</foreign> — mainly in Vajrayāna contexts, the sugatas of the five
                                families: Vairocana for the Sugata (or Buddha) family; Akṣobhya for the Vajra family; Ratnasambhava for the Ratna (Jewel) family; Amitābha for the Padma (Lotus) family;
                                and Amoghasiddhi for the Karma (Activity) family. They are also associated with the five skandhas, five directions, and so forth.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="38">Eight Sugatas: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde gshegs mched brgyad</foreign> — the eight sugatas of the Medicine Buddha tradition including the
                                Medicine Buddha himself, Bhaiṣajyaguru.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="39">Eight Sugata Stūpas: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde gshegs mchod rten brgyad</foreign> — the traditional set of eight stūpas built in different
                                places to commemorate different events of the Buddha Śākyamuni’s life.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="40">Thirty-Five Sugatas: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde gshegs so lnga</foreign> — the thirty-five sugatas invoked in the confession ritual of the
                                “three heaps” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">triskandhaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phung po gsum</foreign>), although in the text
                                itself (see Toh 68) they are termed <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgata</foreign>.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-SUGATA-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>