<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Ten Powers / Strengths</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bcu</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">ten-powers</idno>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-09T22:31:45.206Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-2">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-3">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">[preliminary notes]</head>
                    <head type="section" tid="7">[List from Toh 99 Introduction]:</head>
                    <label>(<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jñānabala</foreign>):</label>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="8">Knowing what is possible and what is impossible (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sthānāsthāna</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="9">Knowing the ripening of karma (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmavipāka</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="10">Knowing the various inclinations (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nānādhimukti</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="11">Knowing the various elements (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nānādhātu</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="12">Knowing the supreme and lesser faculties (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">indriyaparāpara</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="13">Knowing the paths that lead to all destinations (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sarvatragāminīpratipad</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="14">Knowing the concentrations, liberations, absorptions, and attainments (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhyānavimokṣasamādhisamāpatti</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15">Knowing the recollection of past existences (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūrvanivāsānusmṛti</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="16">Knowing death and rebirth (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cyutyupapatti</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">Knowing the exhaustion of the defilements (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āsravakṣaya</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="18">The list above is only one of many variants and it would be fair to point this out, as does Lamotte (see below). We have ourselves already published at least two canonical lists, </p>
                    
                    <p tid="19">in the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khri pa</foreign> (<ref target="http://direct-read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-031-002.html#UT22084-031-002-245">http://direct-read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-031-002.html#UT22084-031-002-245</ref>) </p>
                    
                    <p tid="20">and in the <title xml:lang="en">Play in Full</title> (<ref target="http://direct-read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-046-001.html#UT22084-046-001-2236">http://direct-read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-046-001.html#UT22084-046-001-2236</ref>). </p>
                    
                    <p tid="21">We also have glossary entries for </p>
                    
                    <p tid="22">Toh 186 <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-061-006.html#UT22084-061-006-148">http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-061-006.html#UT22084-061-006-148</ref>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p tid="23">and Toh 127 <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-055-001.html#UT22084-055-001-5179">http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-055-001.html#UT22084-055-001-5179</ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="24">From Lamotte’s <foreign xml:lang="fr">
                            <ref target="https://www.wisdomlib.org/buddhism/book/the-treatise-on-the-great-virtue-of-wisdom-volume-iii/d/doc82365.html">Traité</ref>
                        </foreign>:</head>
                    
                    <p tid="25">[JC: Chapter 39 presents the Abhidharma point of view, with many more points discussed after the following excerpt. The Mahāyāna point of view is presented in the middle of chapter 40, of which part is excerpted below, but which continues with more detailed discussion].</p>
                    
                    <p tid="26">Chapter XXXIX - The Ten Powers of the Buddha according to the Abhidharma</p>
                    
                    <p tid="27">PRELIMINARY NOTE</p>
                    
                    <p tid="28">In chapter XVII to chapter XXX, the six perfections (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pāramitā</foreign>) to be fulfilled completely (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paripūrayitavya</foreign>) by the bodhisattva were discussed. They constitute the essentials of his career provided that he fulfills them by ‘the method of non-dwelling’ (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asthānayogena</foreign>), without grasping the characteristics (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">na nimittodgraheṇa</foreign>).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="29">Chapters XXXI to XXXVIII dealt with the Path of nirvāṇa, its auxiliaries and its aids. The dharmas of the Path belong to adepts of both Vehicles but under different headings. The śravakas aspire to nirvāna, whereas the bodhisattvas delay their nirvāṇa in order to dedicate themselves to the welfare and happiness of all beings. The result is that the dharmas of the Path ‘must be realized’ (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sākṣātkartavya</foreign>) by the śrāvakas but merely completely ‘fulfilled’ (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paripūrayitavya</foreign>) or ‘cultivated’ (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhāvitavya</foreign>) by the bodhisattvas. The intention of the bodhisattva is to convert beings and introduce them into the Greater Vehicle, the Vehicle of the Buddhas. They consider the dharmas of the Path as inefficacious or even non-existent (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupalabdha</foreign>) and propose a new method of liberation. But how can they divert the śrāvakas from the dharmas of the Path if they have not themselves cultivated them? Someone will certainly say to them: “You criticize the old method because you are unable to use it!” It is, therefore, important for the bodhisattvas to be aware of both the theory and practice of things of the Path in order that they can discuss them in a valid manner.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="30">In chapter XXXIX to the beginning of chapter XLII, it will be a matter not only of the perfections of the bodhisattva or the dharmas of the Path but also of the great attributes of the Buddhas. Since the bodhisattva does not yet possess them, it is not a matter of his completely fulfilling them or developing them; he can simply formulate the ‘desire to know them’ (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñatukāma</foreign>), the ‘desire to attain them’ (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prāptukāma</foreign>).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="31">In the present chapter, the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> limits itself to presenting the Abhidharmic theories concerning the ten powers of the Buddha; it is in the next chapter that it will present the Mahāyāna point of view. </p>
                    
                    <label>I. THE DAŚABALASŪTRA</label>
                    
                    <p tid="33">Pāli recension. – Anguttara, V,p. 32–36; Majjhima, I, p. 69–71; Paṭisambhida, II, p. 174–176.</p>
                    
                    <q>
                        <p tid="34">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dasa yimāni bhikkhave tathāgathassa tathāgatabalāni yehi balehi samannāgato tathāgāto āsabhaṇ ṭhānaṃ … sacchikatvā upasampajja viharati … yam pi bhikkhave tathāgato …</foreign>
                    </p>
                    </q>
                    
                    <p tid="35">Sanskrit recension (attesting to many variations) cited in Kośavyākhyā, p. 641, l. 14–642, l. 26. Add numerous fragments of Central Asian provenance: S. Lévi. <title xml:lang="fr">Textes sansrits de Touen-houang</title>, Jour. Asiatique, X, 16 (1910), p. 440–444; L. de La Vallée Poussin, <title xml:lang="fr">Documents sanscrits de la Seconde Collection M.A. Stein</title>, Jour. Roy. Asiatic Soc., 1911, p. 1063–1064; E. Waldschmidt, <title xml:lang="de">Bruchstücke buddhistischer Sūtras aus dem zentralasiatischen Sanskritkanon</title>, Leipzig, 1932, 207–225; <title xml:lang="de">Ein zweites Daśabalasūtra</title>, Mitteilungendes Instituts für Orientforschung. VI, 1958, p. 382–405.</p>
                    
                    <q>
                        <p tid="36">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Daśemāni bhikṣavas tathāgatasya balāni yaiḥ samanvāgatas tathāgato ‘rhan samyaksaṃbuddha udāram ārṣabhaṃ …karaṇīyaṃ nāparam asmād bhāvaṃ prajñānānīti. yat tathāgaḥ …</foreign>
                    </p>
                    </q>
                    
                    <p tid="37">Translation of the Sanskrit. – These, O monks, are the ten powers of the Tathāgata, endowed with which the holy One, the fully and completely enlightened One who claims the noble place, the place of the bull, turns the wheel of Brahmā and utters the true Lion’s Roar in the assembly. What are these ten?</p>
                    
                    <p tid="38">1. First, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the possible as possible and the impossible as impossible.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="39">That the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the possible as possible and the impossible as impossible is the first power of the Buddha, endowed with which, the Tathāgata, the holy One, the fully and completely enlightened One who claims the noble place, the place of the bull, turns the wheel of Brahmā and utters the true Lion’s Roar in the assembly.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="40">2. Furthermore, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, actions of the past, future and present according to their place, their cause, their object and their retribution. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="41">3. Furthermore, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the defilement, the purification, the types and the purity of the trances, liberations, concentrations and absorptions. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="42">4. Furthermore, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the degree of the moral faculties of other beings, other individuals. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="43">5. Furthermore, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the diverse aspirations of other beings, other individuals. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="44">6. Furthermore, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the world with its various acquired dispositions, with its many acquired dispositions. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="45">7. Furthermore, the Tathāgata cognizes, in accordance with reality, the route that leads to the various destinies. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="46">8. Furthermore, the Tathāgata remembers many previous abodes, for example, one lifetime, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty lifetimes, one hundred lifetimes, one thousand lifetimes, one million lifetimes, one hundred million lifetimes, several hundred lifetimes, several thousand lifetimes, several hundreds of thousands of lifetimes, one period of disappearance, one period of creation, one period of disappearance-creation, several periods of disappearance, several periods of creation, several periods of disappearance-creation, several periods of creation, several periods of disappearance-creation. He thinks: “I had such and such a name, such and such a family, such and such a clan, such and such food among beings at that time; I experienced such and such happiness and such and such pain. I had such and such longevity, such and such a duration, such and such a life-span. When I left that place, I was reborn in that other place. And from that other place I was born here.” Thus the Tathāgata remembers his many previous abodes with their aspects, their origins and their details. That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="47">9. Furthermore, the Tathāgata, with his divine eye, purified, surpassing that of men, sees beings dying and being born and recognizes them in reality as beautiful, ugly, lowly or excellent, going towards a good or a bad destiny, according to the results of their actions. He thinks: “These beings laden with bodily misdeeds, laden with misdeeds of speech and mind, slandering the saints, having false views, acting wrongly out of their wrong views, for this cause and this reason, at the dissolution of the body after death are born in a miserable state, in a bad destiny, in the hells. On the other hand, these beings endowed with good bodily actions, endowed with good actions of speech and mind, not slandering the saints, having right views, acting well due to their right views, for this cause and this reason, at the dissolution of the body after death are born in a good destiny, the heavens, among the gods.” That the Tathāgata…</p>
                    
                    <p tid="48">10. Furthermore, the Tathāgata, by the cessation of the impurities, having realized in the present existence by means of his own wisdom the pure liberation of mind and the pure liberation by wisdom, takes his stand and knows: “Birth is exhausted by me, the religious life has been practiced, that which had to be accomplished has been accomplished, I see no further existence for myself.” That the Tathāgata… .</p>
                    
                    <label>II. LISTS OF JÑĀNABALAS</label>
                    
                    <p tid="50">Lists of the ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñanabalas</foreign> ‘powers consisting of wisdoms’ have been prepared on the basis of this sūtra. They do not all follow the same order and numerous variations may be found. Here I [Lamotte] mention only a few:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="51">1. Mahāvastu, I, p. 159, l. 10–160, l. 5: verse list (see notes by É. Senart, p. 502–505.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="52">2. Lalitavistara, p. 433.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="53">3. Vibhaṅga, p. 335–3444 (with a long commentary).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="54">4. Kathāvatthu, p. 228–238.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="55">5. Mahāvibhāṣā, T 1545, k. 30, p. 156c seq.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="56">6. Kośa, VII, p. 67–72; Kośavyākhyā, p. 641, l. 10–14.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="57">7. Nyāyānusāra, T 1562, k. 75, p. 746a seq.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="58">8. Abhidharmadīpa, p. 382 seq. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="59">9. Pañcaviṃśati, p. 210, l. 11–23; Satasāhasrikā, p. 1446, l. 16–1448–l. 5.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="60">10. Āloka, p. 455, l. 15–19.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="61">11. Saṃgaha, p. 286.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="62">12. Abhidharmasamuccaya, rec. Pradhan, p. 98, l. 1–5..</p>
                    
                    <p tid="63">13. Bodh. bhūmi, p. 384.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="64">14. Mahāvyut. no. 120–129.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="65">15. Arthaviniścaya, p. 577–579.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="66">Here is the list from Kośa (l.c.): 1. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sthānāsthāna</foreign>-, 2. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karmavipāka</foreign>-, 3. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyānavimokṣasamādhisamāpatti</foreign>-, 4. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriyaparāpara</foreign>-, 5. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nānādhimukti</foreign>-, 6. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nānādhātu</foreign>-, 7. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvatragāminīpratipad</foreign>-, 8. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūrvanivasānasmṛti</foreign>-, 9. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cyutpapāda</foreign>-, 10. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsravakusayajñānabala</foreign>. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-article-3">
                    <head tid="67" type="section">From Lamottes’ <foreign xml:lang="fr">Traité</foreign>, chapter 40:</head>
                    
                    <label>SECOND PART: THE TEN POWERS AND THE FOUR FEARLESSNESSES ACCORDING TO THE MAHĀYĀNA</label>
                    
                    <label>PRELIMINARY NOTE</label>
                    
                    <p tid="70">In the preceding chapter and in the first section of the present chapter, the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> has spoken of the ten powers (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</foreign>) and the four fearlessnesses (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradya</foreign>) of the Buddha according to the doctrine of the Sūtras and the Abhidharma. Now it will discuss the conceptions of the Mahāyāna in regard to the same subject.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="71">It will position itself successively from the absolute truth point of view (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paramārthasatya</foreign>) and the relative truth point of view (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samvṛtisatya</foreign>).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="72">1. From the absolute point of view, the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</foreign>s and the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradyas</foreign> are without distinctive natures and, like all other dharmas, come within the emptiness of non-existence (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupalambhaśūnyatā</foreign>) in terms of which “dharmas, whether past, future of [present, do not exist at all” (Pañcaviṃśati, p. 197, l. 15–16: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ye dharmā atītānāgatapratyutpannās te nopalabhyante</foreign>).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="73">Bala and Vaiśāradya fall under the judgment of the Prajñāpmaramitāsūtras (Pañcaviṃśati, p. 146, l. 9–20; Śatasāhastikā, p. 839, l. 13–842, l. 17):</p>
                    
                    <p tid="74">“The bodhisattva does not grasp (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nopalabhate</foreign>) the ātman, whatever the names by which it is designated: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sattva</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jīva</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">poṣa</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puruṣa</foreign>,<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pudgala</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manuja</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mānava</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kmaraka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vedaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jānaka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paśyaka</foreign>. He does not grasp things, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">skandha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</foreign>, or their<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratītyasamutpāda</foreign>. He does not grasp the noble truths, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samudaya</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirodha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mārga</foreign>. He does not grasp the threefold world, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāma-</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpa</foreign>- and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārūpyadhātu</foreign>. He does not grasp the levels of concentration, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apramāṇa</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārūpyasamāpatti</foreign>. He does not grasp the thirty-seven auxiliaries of enlightenment, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛtyupasthāna</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyakpradhāna</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyaṅga</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mārga</foreign>. He does not grasp the Buddha attributes, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśabala</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturvaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭādaśāveṇika</foreign>. He does not grasp the categories of saints, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">srotaāpanna</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sakṛdāgamin</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anāgamin</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattva</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddha</foreign>. If he does not grasp them, it is because of their absolute purity (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">atyantaviśuddhitā</foreign>). What is this purity? Non-production (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpāda</foreign>), non-manifestation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aprādurbhāva</foreign>), non-existence (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupalambha</foreign>), non-activity (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anabhisaṃskāra</foreign>).”</p>
                    
                    <p tid="75">2. From the relative or conventional point of view, it is permissible to consider things and to find their distinctive characteristics for, just as empty space (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ākāśa</foreign>) does not oppose matter, so “the emptiness of non-existence is not an obstacle to any dharma.”</p>
                    
                    <p tid="76">Provided that he is not attached at all to his mind – in other words, provided that he recognizes its fundamental non-existence – the bodhisattva can, for the purpose of saving beings, discourse very well on the various attributes of the Buddha: the ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</foreign>s, the four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśaradya</foreign>s, the four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvids</foreign> and the eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikabuddhadharmas</foreign>. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="77">The sūtras and the Hīnayāna Abhidharmas make no distinction between Buddha attributes and bodhisattva attributes for the valid reason that the bodhisattva is a future Buddha and between the former and the latter there can be only a difference of degree and not of nature.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="78">The Prajñāpāramitāsūtras have remained at this stage. Thus the Pañcaviṃśati (p. 203–212), setting out to define the Mahāyāna, suggest twenty-one practices to be completely fulfilled (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paripūrayitavya</foreign>) or to be imitated (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śikṣitavya</foreign>). The first seventeen are dharmas of the śrāvaka: 1) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛtyupasthānas</foreign>, 2) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyakpradhānas</foreign>, 3) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipādas</foreign>, 4) five <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriyas</foreign>, 5) five <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</foreign>s, 6) seven <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyaṅgas</foreign>, 7) eight <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mārgāṅgas</foreign>, 8) three <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhis</foreign>, 9) eleven <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñānas</foreign>, 10) three <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya</foreign>s, 11) three <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhis</foreign>, 12) ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anusmṛtis</foreign>, 13) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyānas</foreign>, 14) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apramānas</foreign>, 15) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samāpattis</foreign>, 16) eight <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimokṣas</foreign>, 17) nine <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupūrvavihāras</foreign>). The last four are Buddha dharmas: [18) ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgatabalas</foreign>, 19) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradyas</foreign>, 20) four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvids</foreign>, 21) eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikabuddhadharmas</foreign>]. Nowhere is there any mention made of dharmas belonging strictly to the bodhisattva.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="79">But in a later approach, other Mahāyānasūtras have deemed it proper to propose, apart from these Buddha attributes, a series of bodhisattva attributes distinct from the preceding, but also including ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">balas</foreign>, four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradyas</foreign>, four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvids</foreign> and eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikadharmas</foreign>.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="80">Although the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> presents itself simply as a faithful commentary on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitāsūtra</title>, it does not hesitate to borrow these lists of bodhisattva dharmas from the more recent Māhayānasūtras. Its or their authors want to appear as knowledgeable of the latest progress in scholasticism with the result that, from the scholastic point of view, an important Mahāyanist production has been intercalated between the Prajñāpāramitasūtras and the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title>.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="81">With the exception of the eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikabuddhadharmas</foreign> which the old texts do not mention, the lists of Buddha attributes, namely, the ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">balas</foreign>, four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradyas</foreign> and the four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvids</foreign>, have been fixed since the time of the canonical sūtras (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nikāya</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āgama</foreign>) and are maintained practically without any change throughout the later literature.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="82">It was not the same for the lists of bodhisattva dharmas, the elaboration of which has given room for hesitation and alteration. Here I [Lamotte] will examine only the Mahāyānasūtras with which the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> was familiar and which make up its sources and I will designate them by the following:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="83">Ś = Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra.<lb/>V = Vikurvaṇarājaparipṛcchasūtra<lb/>A = Buddhāvataṃsaka.<lb/>R = Ratnameghasūtra.<lb/>Vyut = Mahāvyutpatti, dependent on the preceding ones.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="84">1. First list of ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvabalas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="85">Ś. – T 642, k. 2, p. 643a25–b3 (p. 254–255 in my [Lamotte’s] translation of the Ś<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ūraṃgamasamādhi</foreign>). – Tib. Trip., vol. 32, vol. 32, no. 800, fol. 330b2–4.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="86">V. – T 420, k. 2, p. 932c13–27. – T 421, k. 2, p. 945b8–25. – Tib. Trip., vol. 33, no. 834, p. 263, fol. 213b1–214a2.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="87">It is this first list that the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> will adopt here. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="88">2. Second list of ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvabala</foreign>s:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="89">A. – T 278, k. 39, p.649c5–14. – T 279, k. 56, p. 295b29–c10; Tib. Trip., vol. 26, no. 761, p. 84, fol. 204b1–8.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="90">R. – T 660, k. 4, p. 301b14–17. – T 489, k. 7, p. 722b7–11. – Tib. Trip., vol. 35, no. 897, p. 192, fol. 50b6–7.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="91">Vyut., no. 760–769.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="92">List I List II<lb/>1. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dṛḍhādhyāśayabala</foreign> 1. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āśayabala</foreign>
                        <lb/>2. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvasattvāparityāgabala</foreign> 2. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhyāśayabala</foreign>
                        <lb/>3. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahākaruṇābala</foreign> 3. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prayogabala</foreign>
                        <lb/>4. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāvīryabala</foreign> 4. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñābala</foreign>
                        <lb/>5. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhibala</foreign> 5. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">praṇidhānabala</foreign>
                        <lb/>6. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñābala</foreign> 6. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yānabala</foreign>
                        <lb/>7. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāraparikhedabala</foreign> 7. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caryābala</foreign>
                        <lb/>8. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattikadharmakṣāntibala</foreign> 8. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvaṇabala</foreign>
                        <lb/>9. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimuktibala</foreign> 9<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">. bodhibala</foreign>
                        <lb/>10. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvidbala</foreign> 10. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvidbala</foreign>
                        <lb/> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmacakrapravartanabala</title>.) ?</p>
                    
                    <p tid="93">3. List of four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvavaiśāradyas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="94">V. – T 420, k. 2, p. 932c27–933a7. – T 421, k. 2, p. 945b–c10.– Tib.Trip., vol. 33, no. 834, p. 263, fol. 214a2–8.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="95">R.- T 660, k. 4, p. 301b17–25. – T 489, k. 7, p. 722b11–19. – Tib. Trip., vol. 35, no. 897, p.192, fol. 50b7–51a3.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="96">Vyut., no. 782–785.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="97">This is the list adopted by the <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> here.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="98">4. List of ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvavaiśāradyas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="99">A. – T 278, k. 39, p. 649c16–650b24. – T 279, k. 56, p. 295c11–296b17.- Tib. Trip., vol. 26, no. 761, p. 84–85, fol. 204b8–207b1.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="100">5. First list of eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikabodhisattvadharmas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="101">V. – T 420, k. 2, p. 933a7–934b3. – T 421, k. 2, p. 945c11–947b4. – Tib. Trip., vol. 33, no. 834, fol. 214b1–218b4.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="102">6. Second list of eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikabodhisattvadharmas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="103">R. – T 660, k. 4, p. 301b25–c12. – T 489. k. 7, p. 722b19–c4. – Tib. Trip., vol. 35, no. 897, p. 192, fol. 51a3–51b2.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="104">Vyut., no. 787–804.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="105">7. List of ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇikabodhisattvadharmas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="106">A. – T 278, k. 40, p. 650c4–651b21. – T 279, k. 56, p. 296b20–297b1. – Tib. Trip., vol. 26, no. 761, p. 85–86, fol. 207b2–210b2.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="107">8. List of ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvasamādhis</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="108">R. – T 660, k. 4, p. 301a11–17. – T 489, k. 7, p. 722a7–12. – Tib. Trip., vol. 35, no, 897, p. 192, fol. 50a1–3.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="109">Vyut., no. 737–745. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="110">9. List of twelve bodhisattvadhāraṇīs:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="111">R. – T 660, k. 4, p. 301a18–25. – T 489, k. 7, p. 722a12–17. – Tib. Trip., vol 35, no. 897, p. 192, fol50a3–6.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="112">Vyut., no. 747–758.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="113">10. List of six <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvābhijñā</foreign>s:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="114">R. – T 660, k. 4, p. 301a25–28. – T 489, k. 7, p. 722a17–20. – Tib. Trip., vol. 35, no. 897, p. 192, fol. 50a6–7.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="115">11. List of ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattvavaśitas</foreign>:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="116">R. – T 660, k. 4, p. 301a28–b14. – T 489, k. 7, p. 722a20–b7. – Tib. Trip., vol 35, no. 897, p. 192, fol. 50a7–50b5.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="117">Vyut. – no. 771–780.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="118">It may be noted that the lists of bodhisattva dharmas given here do not appear in the two oldest Chinese translations of the Ratnameghasūtra: the Pao yun king (T658) made by Mandrasena in 503, and the Ta tch’eng pao yun king (T 659) made by Mandrasena and Seng k’ie p’o lo. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="119">[k. 25, p. 245c]</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-TEN-POWERS-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>