<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Thousand Buddhas of the Fortunate Kalpa</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.1 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA"/>
                <idno eft:kb-id="thousand-buddhas-fortunate-kalpa"/>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2021-06-10T19:17:13.922Z" user="celso">10/06/2021 19:17:13</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.1" date-time="2021-06-09T22:30:57.116Z" user="mike">Auto (file-created)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">The Thousand Buddhas of the Fortunate Kalpa</head>
                    
                    <p tid="7">Various origin stories</p>
                    
                    <p tid="8">A. The story comes in the fifth chapter of Toh 47, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatācintyaguhyanirdeśa</title>, F.117.b – 125.b:</p>
                    
                    <p tid="9">Eon “Beautifully Illuminating” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdzes par snang ba</foreign>) </p>
                    
                    <p tid="10">Universe “Fully Adorned” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par brgyan pa</foreign>)</p>
                    
                    <p tid="11">Buddha “King Set with Jewels of Infinite Qualities” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yon tan mtha’ yas rin chen sna tshogs bkod pa’i rgyal po</foreign>)</p>
                    
                    <p tid="12">Intermediate 4-continent world “Beautifully Illuminating” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdzes par snang ba</foreign>)</p>
                    
                    <p tid="13">Central city and palace: “The Pure” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par dag pa can</foreign>)</p>
                    
                    <p tid="14">King Dhṛtarāṣṭra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yul ’khor srung</foreign>) has 700,000 queens (all bodhisattvas) and 1,000 sons (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bu stong du tshang ba</foreign>).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="15">Two are born miraculously, Dharma Mind (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sems pa</foreign>) and Dharmamati (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi blo gros</foreign>) and receive teaching on the nature of phenomena.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="16">The king puts all the names of his sons in a precious vase and makes offerings for seven days, then pulls out names.</p>
                    
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">1. Prince Pure Intelligence (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhon nu rnam par dag pa’i blo gros</foreign>), who is predicted to be Krakucchanda.</p>
                        </item>
                    
                    <item>
                            <p tid="18">2. Victorious Army (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhon nu rnam par rgyal ba’i sde</foreign>) – Kanakamuni</p>
                        </item>
                    
                    <item>
                            <p tid="19">3. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang po zhi ba</foreign> – Kāśyapa</p>
                        </item>
                    
                    <item>
                            <p tid="20">4. Sarvārthasiddha – Śākyamuni</p>
                        </item>
                    
                    <item>
                            <p tid="21">5. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ska rags can</foreign> – Maitreya (etc. F.123.b)</p>
                        </item>
                    
                    <item>
                            <p tid="22">…and so forth up to 21 Tathāgatas (note that after 6, seng ge, the names are not the same as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title>).</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <p tid="23">last Matyananta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thams cad kyi tha chungs</foreign> ] <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">blo gros mtha’ yas</foreign>) – Adhimukta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mos pa</foreign>)</p>
                    
                    <p tid="24">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sems pa</foreign> vows to become Vajrapāṇi for all of them, and Dharmamati will request all of them to turn the wheel of Dharma, as Mahābrahmā.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="25">Dhṛtarāstra was previous life of Buddha Dīpaṃkara.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="26">This is mentioned in the “empowerment of the thousand buddhas” for Ratnalingpa’s <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thugs rje chen po gsang ba ’dus pa</title> (Rin chen gter mdzod new Shechen edition vol. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’a</foreign>, p. 291) which lists their names, ending in snang mdzad (Roca) rather than Adhimukta.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="27">B. In Toh 94, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title> -- beginning of 2nd chapter (F.17.a-b), a Dharmabhāṇaka called <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rin po che’i lus mtha’ yas par grags pa spyod pa’i mdzod</foreign>, teaches the teachings (in particular the samādhi being described in this sūtra) of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gser sdug mdzes pa rnam par nges pa’i ’od kyi gzi brjid kyi rgyal po</foreign> to a cakravartin king called <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skye bo mang po mngon par dga’ zhing mya ngan med pa’i nga ro</foreign>. The Dharmabhāṇaka, the King, the king’s 1,000 sons, and a whole group of attendants then practise and accumulate virtue for 80 kalpas. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="28">The Dharmabhāṇaka was none other than Amitāyus in a previous life; the King becomes Akṣobhya; and the 1,000 princes become the 1,000 buddhas of the Fortunate Eon. These are listed by name from F.86b – 101.b.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="29">see Skilling ARIRIAB XIII (2010)</p>
                    
                    <p tid="30">C. Also comes in the final chapter of Toh 176, 
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh176.html#UT22084-060-005-446">Vimalakīrtinirdeśa</ref>
                        </title>, 12.6-18</p>
                    
                    <p tid="31">But in this version the origin takes place in an eon called Vicaraṇa, a universe called Mahāvyūha, featuring a buddha Bhaiṣajyarāja and King Ratnacchattra, one of whose sons Candracchattra, who became the next buddha after Bhaiṣajyarāja and taught for ten short eons. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="32">Ratnacchattra was a previous life of the Tathāgata Ratnārcis (buddha of a western buddhafield acc to PP); the thousand sons, of the buddhas of the Fortunate Eon; and in particular Candracchattra, of Śākyamuni.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="33">The last buddha is mentioned as Roca (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snang mdzad</foreign>).</p>
                    
                    <p tid="34">Peter: see also Karuṇapuṇḍarika?</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>