<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Thousand Buddhas of the Fortunate Kalpa</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.3 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">thousand-buddhas-fortunate-kalpa</idno>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-09T22:30:57.116Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-2">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2021-11-23T14:33:43.862Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-3">
                    <desc>Auto (knowledgebase-header)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-4">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">The Thousand Buddhas of the Fortunate Kalpa</head>

                    <p tid="7">Various origin stories</p>

                    <p tid="27">A. In Toh 94, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title>
                        <lb/> -- beginning of 2nd chapter (F.17.a-b), a Dharmabhāṇaka called <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rin po che’i lus mtha’ yas par grags pa spyod pa’i mdzod</foreign>,
                        teaches the teachings (in particular the samādhi being described in this sūtra) of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gser sdug mdzes pa rnam par nges pa’i ’od
                            kyi gzi brjid kyi rgyal po</foreign> to a cakravartin king called <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skye bo mang po mngon par dga’ zhing mya ngan med pa’i nga
                            ro</foreign>. The Dharmabhāṇaka, the King, the king’s 1,000 sons, and a whole group of attendants then practise and accumulate virtue for 80 kalpas. </p>

                    <p tid="28">The Dharmabhāṇaka was none other than Amitāyus in a previous life; the King becomes Akṣobhya; and the 1,000 princes become the 1,000 buddhas of the Fortunate Eon. These
                        are listed by name from F.86b – 101.b.</p>

                    <p tid="29">see Skilling ARIRIAB XIII (2010)</p>
                    <lb/>

                    <p tid="8">B. In Toh 47, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatācintyaguhyanirdeśa</title>
                        <lb/> -- fifth chapter, F.117.b – 125.b:</p>

                    <p tid="9">Eon “Beautifully Illuminating” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdzes par snang ba</foreign>) <lb/> Universe “Fully Adorned” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par brgyan pa</foreign>)<lb/> Buddha “King Set with Jewels of Infinite Qualities” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yon tan mtha’ yas rin chen sna
                            tshogs bkod pa’i rgyal po</foreign>)<lb/> Intermediate 4-continent world “Beautifully Illuminating” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdzes par snang
                        ba</foreign>)<lb/> Central city and palace: “The Pure” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par dag pa can</foreign>)</p>

                    <p tid="14">King Dhṛtarāṣṭra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yul ’khor srung</foreign>) has 700,000 queens (all bodhisattvas) and 1,000 sons (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bu stong du tshang ba</foreign>). Two are born miraculously, Dharma Mind (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sems pa</foreign>) and Dharmamati
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi blo gros</foreign>) and receive teaching on the nature of phenomena. The king puts all the names of his sons in a precious
                        vase and makes offerings for seven days, then pulls out names.</p>

                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">1. Prince Pure Intelligence (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhon nu rnam par dag pa’i blo gros</foreign>), who is predicted to be
                            Krakucchanda.</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="18">2. Victorious Army (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhon nu rnam par rgyal ba’i sde</foreign>) – Kanakamuni</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="19">3. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang po zhi ba</foreign> – Kāśyapa</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="20">4. Sarvārthasiddha – Śākyamuni</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="21">5. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ska rags can</foreign> – Maitreya (etc. F.123.b)</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="22">…and so forth up to 21 Tathāgatas (note that after 6, seng ge, the names are not the same as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title>).</p>
                        </item>

                        <item>
                            <p tid="23">last Matyananta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thams cad kyi tha chungs</foreign> ] <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">blo gros mtha’
                                    yas</foreign>) – Adhimukta (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mos pa</foreign>)</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>

                    <p tid="24">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sems pa</foreign> vows to become Vajrapāṇi for all of them, and Dharmamati will request all of them to turn the wheel of
                        Dharma, as Mahābrahmā.</p>

                    <p tid="25">Dhṛtarāstra was previous life of Buddha Dīpaṃkara.</p>

                    <p tid="26">This is the version mentioned in the “empowerment of the thousand buddhas” for Ratnalingpa’s <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thugs rje chen po gsang ba ’dus pa</title> (Rin
                        chen gter mdzod new Shechen edition vol. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’a</foreign>, p. 291) which lists their names, ending in snang mdzad (Roca) rather than Adhimukta. There are
                        (?) other rituals and empowerments based on the theme in the Tibetan literature.</p>

                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="10"> C. In the Karuṇapuṇḍarika (Toh 112) <lb/> -- the best known version? The story of Samudrareṇu and his sons: most of the sūtra’s narrative takes place in the distant
                        past and concerns the cakravartin king Araṇemin, his thousand sons, his chief court priest Samudrareṇu, and Samudrareṇu’s eighty-one sons and his disciples. One of
                        Samudrareṇu’s eighty-one sons is the Buddha Ratnagarbha, who prophesies the buddhahood of all these individuals. He states that King Araṇemin will become the Buddha Amitābha,
                        Samudrareṇu will become Śākyamuni in our fortunate eon, and 999 of Samudrareṇu’s disciples plus his five attendants will become the other 1,004 buddhas of our eon.</p>
                    <lb/>


                    <p tid="30">D. In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh176.html#UT22084-060-005-446">Vimalakīrtinirdeśa</ref>
                        </title>, (Toh 176)<lb/> --
                        in the final chapter, 12.6-18.</p>

                    <p tid="31">In this version the origin takes place in an eon called Vicaraṇa, a universe called Mahāvyūha, featuring a buddha Bhaiṣajyarāja and King Ratnacchattra, one of whose
                        sons Candracchattra, who became the next buddha after Bhaiṣajyarāja and taught for ten short eons. <lb/> Ratnacchattra was a previous life of the Tathāgata Ratnārcis (buddha of
                        a western buddhafield acc to PP); the thousand sons, of the buddhas of the Fortunate Eon; and in particular Candracchattra, of Śākyamuni.</p>

                    <p tid="33">The last buddha is mentioned as Roca (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snang mdzad</foreign>).</p>
                    <lb/>

                    <p tid="34">E. In the <title xml:lang="en">Prajñāpāramitā in Twenty-five Thousand Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi khri</title>, Toh 9) <lb/> -- end of chapter 33:
                        20,000 bodhisattvas are prophesied as buddhas in the Fortunate Eon.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-THOUSAND-BUDDHAS-FORTUNATE-KALPA-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh
                            46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>