<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Thus have I heard</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-THUS-HAVE-I-HEARD"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">thus-have-i-heard</idno>
                <date>2021-06-09</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-09T21:59:35.494Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-THUS-HAVE-I-HEARD-2">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-THUS-HAVE-I-HEARD-3">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-THUS-HAVE-I-HEARD-article-1">
                    <p tid="6">This issue has puzzled a lot of people. There is no shortage of material on it. If you want to see the major publications on this issue, see p. 200, n. 2 of Jeffrey
                        Schoening, The 'Saalistamba Suutra and its Indian Commentaries, Volume 1, Wiener Studien zur Tibetologie und Buddhismuskunde 35.1, Vienna 1995. There we have references to
                        several publications that explicitly or in passing concern the question of placing ekasmin samaye (dus gcig na) "at one time" with the phrase "Thus... heard" or with the
                        following phrase "Bhagavaan ... resided". </p>
                    <p tid="7">I think modern scholars would agree that the key article was that of John Brough "Thus Have I Heard...", which he published in the Bulletin of the School of Oriental and
                        African Studies in 1950. It was reprinted in John Brough, Collected Papers, Ed. Minoru Hara and J.C. Wright. University of London, School of Orient. and African Studies, 1996,
                        p. 63-73. This is the starting point if we don't want to go round in circles with competing linguistic intuitions, authorities, and so forth. </p>
                    <p tid="8">The textual data is complicated, and what a Sanskritist or Chinese reader feels as an intuitive or natural way to read the text is only a part of the picture. Brough
                        surveys the arguments for and against and comes out in favor of "Thus Have I Heard at One Time" on the balance of the evidence. That said, there is evidence to the contrary. It
                        is a matter of weighing things. </p>
                    <p tid="9">Here's a summary of some of Brough's points: </p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="numbers">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="10">The Chinese texts followed the Skt word order, but of course did not mark punctuation. It is natural that Chinese would generally feel that the words "one
                                time" belonged to the following phrase. But this doesn't prove very much. It is just a natural reading of a construction that is complicated to Chinese readers because
                                of the Skt word order. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="11">Buddhaghosa, commenting on the Pali eka.m samaya.m, recognizes both possibilities. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="12">Haribhadra in his Abhisamayaala.mkaaraaloka (ed. U.Wogihara, Tokyo, 1932-5) p. 6 et sq. also recognizes both, but comes out initially and fairly strongly for
                                the placing "one time" with "Thus I have heard" rather than with "The Buddha resided ..." In arguing for placing "one time" with "Thus I have heard", Haribhadra reasons
                                that the teaching "was all heard at one single instant and hence is not readily forgotten" (ekasmin k.sa.ne sarva.m 'sruta.m ity artha.h ... na ca vismaryate) That
                                said, subsequently, he goes on to say atha vaa ... and spells out the other position! </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="13">The Tibetan dus gcig na is followed by a shad, and this punctuation is not a later addition (as it is in the Pali, Chinese and Sanskrit, where it is due to
                                the editor). It tends to support "Thus I have heard at one time." </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="14">A strong argument for "Thus I have heard at one time" was already given by E. Burnouf and A. Staël-Holstein: we fairly often (e.g. in avadaana literature)
                                find the whole phrase "Thus I have heard..." omitted. Instead the text begins with the phrase "The Bhagavaan resided..." It does NOT state "Once, the Bhagavaan resided
                                ..." We have evidence from the Mahaavastu too on this: bhagavaan samyaksambuddho ... 'sraavastiiya.m viharati "The B., the Perfectly Enlightened One, resided in
                                'Sraavastii." There is no "Once" tacked on to the sentence. There are other texts that are similar. As Brough rightly concludes (. p 418): "It may therefore be taken as
                                a general rule that the texts proper do not commence with the words ekasmin samaye (or eka.m samaya.m)." </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p tid="15">Here is my personal take on the question. The commentarial evidence is not decisive. You can find commentators that go either way and many that suggest both ways.
                        "Natural" readings are also not decisive on this matter. From my point of view, John Brough's 5th point is the most telling. It does (as Brough stresses) tend to corroborate
                        the Tibetan placement of ekasmin samaye=dus gcig na with "Thus I have heard" </p>
                    <p tid="16">Now some people have tried to "split the difference", by taking ekasmin samaye as going with both. I think that this doesn't really clarify much and it's awkward to
                        capture this ambiguity in translation. Although, I'm completely aware that some people are strong believers in having ekasmin samaye go with Bhagavaan ... viharati sma(reside),
                        I think that currently a lot of the top scholars are placing it with "Thus I have heard." To take a recent publication, Michael Zimmermann, in his Tathaagatagarbhasuutra, The
                        Earliest Exposition of the Buddha-Nature Teaching in India (Tokyo, 2002), is a good example. See his p. 94 "At one time I heard the following". See his n. 2. </p>
                    <p tid="17">There are many other scholars we can cite. However, we need to standardize here. It's not only a matter of what is right/wrong philologically -- there the jury may well
                        go on deliberating -- but what is consistent. Having the opening line of suutras differ repeatedly according to the translators' positions will just look pretty bad and sloppy. </p>
                    <p tid="18">So, in short, I think 84000 has to go consistently with the best call on this, i.e., "Thus did I hear at one time". The understanding of this phrase is not just a
                        matter that will be decided by "linguistic intuitions". It's a quite complicated philological problem. I think it's pretty impressive how much there is on this. That said,
                        after quite some research people have, at most, a rather tentative position. It's the best we can do. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-THUS-HAVE-I-HEARD-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-THUS-HAVE-I-HEARD-1">Here's a sample bibliographic reference with a link to <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">Toh 46</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>