<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Tīrthika</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthya, tīrthakara, tīrthaṅkara</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu stegs pa, mu stegs can</title>
                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">s.a. nirgrantha</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="2.a"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">tirthika</idno>
                <date>2021-06-08</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#mike" when="2021-06-08T23:36:00.579Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-2">
                    <desc>Auto (file-created)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-3">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">Mahāvyutpatti</head>
                    
                    <p tid="7">
                        <ref target="http://www2.hf.uio.no/polyglotta/index.php?page=source&amp;mid=485951&amp;tvid=2433&amp;kid=435">Sakaki 3512</ref> tīrthikāḥ </p>
                    
                    <p tid="8">mu stegs pa la ya mtshan can gyi miṅ la</p>
                    
                    <p tid="9">
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">具希有等名目</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">外道師</foreign>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p tid="10">tīrthaka ni tirthyaṃ vidyate tīrthaka źes bya ste | mtsho’i ’gram nas mtshor ’jug pa’i stegs ’cha’ ba daṅ ’dra bar dka’ thub (2)daṅ rnal ’byor la sogs pa chos sna tshogs spyod ciṅ mya ṅan las ’das pa’i mtshor ’jug pa’i stegs ’cha’ bas na mu stegs can źes bya | </p>
                    
                    <p tid="11">Sakaki 3513 tīrthyakaraḥ </p>
                    
                    <p tid="12">mu stegs byed pa</p>
                    
                    <p tid="13">
                        <ref target="http://www2.hf.uio.no/polyglotta/index.php?page=source&amp;mid=485953&amp;tvid=2433&amp;kid=435">Sakaki 3514</ref> tīrthikaḥ</p>
                    
                    <p tid="14">mu stegs can</p>
                    
                    <p tid="15">
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">具外道</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">外道師</foreign>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="16">Edgerton</head>
                    
                    <p tid="17">(also paratīrthika;; see prec. and next items; prob. Sktized from MIndic (Pali) titthiya, see tīrthya;; both are very common in prose as well as vss), (1) heretic; like its relatives, pejoratively used; there is one seeming exception, tīrthikā vā bhavanti bhavasūdanāḥ Mv i.106.8 (vs), where if the text is correct it seems to be said of Bodhisattvas in the 8th bhūmi that they become religious prophets (or the like), destroying (the states of normal) existence. I suspect a corruption, and cannot explain the text as it stands any more than Senart (his doubtful suggestion based on LV Calc. 313.19 falls now with the reading of that text, which in Lefm. 250.1 is replaced by ... tīrthyāḥ, heretics, kurvante). However, it is barely possible that this one Mv passage preserves the original neutral mg., adherent (or founder) of (any) religion. A trace of this may also remain in the not infrequent prefixation of anyato t~, other (than Buddhist) sectarian, LV 268.12; Mv iii.49.12 (anyatīrthikapūrvo, formerly a member of another sect); 412.7; or parat~;, q.v.; cf. kutīrthikā(ḥ) LV 12.10, members of base (heretical) sects. Otherwise, and very often, tīrthika alone means heretic simply: SP 272.10; LV 250.21; 258.1; 260.9; Mv i.45.10; 69.17; ii.135.12; iii.892.7 (śramaṇa-brāhmaṇa-tīrthika-gaṇikā, apparently implying that brahmans were not included among tīrthikas; this cpd. appears in some of the other passages listed); Mvy 3514; Divy 146.19; 152.5; 275.9; Av i.2.6; 16.3 etc., common; Bhad 52; Bbh 173.11 etc.; yat kiṃcit tīrthikaliṅgaṃ ... LV 409.17; Mv iii.329.11, whatever (external) mark (dress etc.) of heretics (was borne by converts, all magically disappeared and they wore the aspect of Buddhist monks); tīrthikāvakrāntaka, see avakrāntaka;; (2) n. of a nāga: Mvy 3320; (3) see s.v. samatīrthika;.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-article-3">
                    <head type="section" tid="18">Jaini, Padmanabh S. </head>
                    
                    <p tid="19">Considerable interest attaches to the Jain term Tīrthaṅkara, for it is still used by the Jains to designate their teacher Mahāvīra (the great hero), as it was used by the Buddhists in the days of the Buddha to describe all ‘heretic’ <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śramaṇas</foreign>. According to the Jains, a Tīrthaṅkara (literally one who makes a ford, as it were, to cross the flood of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra</foreign>) is a person who having completely eradicated all passions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vītarāga</foreign>) and all possessions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirgrantha</foreign>), and consequently having attained omniscience (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sarvajña</foreign>) preaches the norm until he enters <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirvāṇa</foreign> or emancipation from the cycle of transmigration. Such was, according to the Jains, Mahāvīra, whose claim to omniscience is also attested by the Buddhist texts. A similar claim was made, according to the Jain texts, by Makkhali Gosāla, leader of the Ājivakas. … Mahāvīra …. is identical with Nātaputta (son of the Nātṛ clan) the Nigaṇṭha (free from bonds) of the Pali canon. The Nigaṇṭhas, the present day Jains, … consider him to be the last of the twenty-four Tīrthaṅkaras of the present age, his immediate predecessor being Pārśva, who is believed to have attained Nirvāṇa some 250 years earlier at the famous Pārasnath hills, in Bihar.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="20">[The first Tīrthaṅkara was Ṛṣabha at the beginning of the kalpa. Other Tīrthaṅkaras: Neminaatha, Pārśvanātha.]</p>
                    
                    <p tid="21">JC Dec 2020: Worth noting that the term <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrtha</foreign> seems quite well known in Hindu writings as referring to a sacred place, usually a place of pilgrimage. E.g. see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tirtha_(Hinduism)">Wikipedia on Tīrtha</ref>. The meaning is linked to ford, crossing place, or confluence, and this (perhaps an interpretation) is also applied metaphorically to significant steps on the spiritual path. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="22">Isn’t this the obvious reason for the use of the term in Buddhist writings about practitioners we would now call “Hindus”?</p>
                    
                    <p tid="23">See also Sircar, D.C. <title xml:lang="en">Studies in the Geography of Ancient and Medieval India</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 2nd ed. 1971. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="24">From Sircar: tīrthas can be Śaiva or Śākta (p. 77). “Buddhist tīrthas” e.g. Bodhgaya (p.219). The Ganges and especially the Gaṅga-Sāgara confluence as tīrtha (pp. 220-224). Gayā and surrounding area as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrtha</foreign> in chapter 21 (pp. 282-288), see also my notes on Gayā / Gayāsirsa.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="4">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="5">New Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-TIRTHIKA-1">Jaini, Padmanabh S., “Śramaṇas: Their Conflict with Brāhmaṇical Society,” in Elder, J.W. (ed.), <title xml:lang="en">Chapters in Indian Civlization</title>, Vol. I, pp 40-81. Dubuque, Iowa, 1970: Kendall/Hunt. Reprinted in Jaini, Padmanabh S., <title xml:lang="en">Collected Papers on Buddhist Studies</title>, Ch. 3, pp 47-96. Delhi, 2001: Motilal Banarsidass.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>