<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/knowledgebase.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Uṣṇīṣa</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="en">uṇhīsa</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Uṣṇīṣa</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.3 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name>
                </publisher>
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">usnisa</idno>
                <date>2023-08-22</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#sameer" when="2023-08-22T09:51:02.134Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-4">
                    <desc>Titles updated</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#sameer" when="2023-08-25T05:46:36.292Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-82">
                    <desc>added material converted from word doc</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#sameer" when="2023-08-25T14:58:27.077Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-83">
                    <desc>Titles updated</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#sameer" when="2023-08-25T14:58:27.077Z" type="publication-status" status="2.a" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-84">
                    <desc>2.a</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-02T22:15:09.55Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.1" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-109">
                    <desc>Published but could still do with improvement and the addition of illustrations.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-02T22:15:09.55Z" type="publication-status" status="1" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-110">
                    <desc>1</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-02T22:24:13.675Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.2" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-111">
                    <desc>Minor improvements</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-03T11:10:29.151Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.3" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-171">
                    <desc>Illustrations added, further edits and updated cross-reference links.</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="75">Uṣṇīṣa</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="70">Overview</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The uṣṇīṣa is one of the thirty-two physical marks of a great being. It is a feature
                        of the head, and in its simplest form it
                        seems to refer to the shape of the head as being “like a turban,” the
                        original meaning of the Sanskrit, indicating a majestic, raised cranial
                        vault, perhaps of increased convexity or with an apical point. More
                        elaborately it refers to a dome-shaped extension of the top of the head, a
                        crest that is either anatomical (bone or flesh) or made of hair.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-7"/>
                    <p tid="81">There is an additional characteristic of the uṣṇīṣa unique to
                        tathāgatas, mentioned in a number of texts and narratives and included in at
                        least one atypical list of the eighty minor signs: that its top, or its
                        extent, is “invisible” or “out of sight.” <media mimeType="image/png" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/0c/The_Buddha_teaching._Kushan_period._National_Museum%2C_Delhi._2004.jpg/800px-The_Buddha_teaching._Kushan_period._National_Museum%2C_Delhi._2004.jpg" source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Buddha_teaching._Kushan_period._National_Museum,_Delhi._2004.jpg">
                            <desc>en.wikipedia, CC BY-SA 3.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0, via Wikimedia Commons</desc>
                        </media>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-107"/>
                    <p tid="82">The way that the uṣṇīṣa has been understood as a sign of buddhahood
                        may well have been influenced by how artists attempted to represent it
                        as sculpture and painting came to be used to depict the Buddha’s physical appearance. 
                        Perhaps more than any of his other features, the uṣṇīṣa remains
                        the one that makes depictions of the Buddha instantly recognizable to most people 
                        everywhere, regardless of culture. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-108"/>
                    <p tid="83">As an aspect of the Buddha’s rūpakāya and hence of the physical fruition 
                        of his vast accumulated merit, the uṣṇīṣa is said in particular to result from the respect
                        he has shown to parents, teachers, and other worthy persons using his head by bowing down,
                        touching his head at their feet, prostrating himself to them, and similar gestures.
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">The Buddha’s uṣṇīṣa is also mentioned as the source of protective dharaṇīs 
                        and of a number of deities related to those dhāraṇīs in works generally classified among the Action
                        Tantras (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kriyā</foreign>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="71">Etymology</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">The Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣa</foreign> in general
                        usage (e.g. in the Brāhmaṇas) denotes a turban, headband, or other cloth
                        wound around the head. But in the context of the thirty-two marks of a great
                        being (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāpuruṣalakṣaṇa</foreign>), and in
                        reference to the Buddha’s physical characteristics, it specifically refers
                        to one of the physical features of his head. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-3">
                    <head type="section" tid="72">Place in the List of Thirty-Two Marks</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">The many lists of the thirty-two marks in canonical texts do not all follow the same order. Among them, the 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣa</foreign> takes different places in the order and is listed as follows: </p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="14">first in the list given in <title xml:lang="en">The Play in
                                    Full</title> (Toh 95) <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh95.html#UT22084-046-001-475">chapter 7</ref>, (but thirty-first in <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh95.html#UT22084-046-001-2233">chapter 26</ref>), and first in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh172.html#UT22084-060-001-73"> Mañjuśrīparipṛcchā</ref>
                                </title> (Toh 172). </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15">twenty-third in the lists given in the three long <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitāsūtras</title>, the 
                                <title xml:lang="en">Hundred Thousand</title> (Toh 8), <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh9.html#UT22084-026-001-5836">Twenty-Five Thousand</ref>
                                </title> (Toh 9), and <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh10.html#UT22084-029-001-5641">Eighteen Thousand</ref>
                                </title> (Toh 10) line sūtras,
                                and in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhisamayālaṃkāra</title> (Toh
                                3786, VIII.16);</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="16">twenty-eighth in the list in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnagotravibhāgottaratantraśāstra</title> (Toh 4024);</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">thirty-first in the lists in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅghabhedavastu</title> (Toh 1, ch. 17, F.284.a) and in
                                Asaṅga’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvabhūmi</title> (Toh
                                4037, III.5.5);</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="18">last in the Pali <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lakkhaṇasutta</title> (DN 30), in <title xml:lang="en">The Good Eon</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title>, Toh 94) at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh94.html#UT22084-045-001-411">2.164 et seq.</ref>, and in the list in
                                    <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh11.html#UT22084-031-002-291"> The Transcendent Perfection of Wisdom in Ten Thousand
                                        Lines </ref>
                                </title> (Toh 11);</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-13"/>
                    <p tid="19">In most of these texts the mark is indicated by the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣaśīrṣa</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣaśiraskatā</foreign> (Pali <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṇhīsasīso</foreign>), in Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu gtsug
                            tor dang ldan pa</foreign>. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-4">
                    <head type="section" tid="73">The Uṣṇīṣa’s Meritorious Causes</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-15"/>
                    <p tid="21">Some of these texts include explanations of the Buddha’s specific
                        past meritorious actions that have caused each of the marks to appear, and
                        in the case of the uṣṇīṣa this is said to be through his having respected
                        parents, teachers, and other worthy persons by bowing his head to their
                        feet. Outside accounts of the thirty-two marks as a whole, the Buddha’s
                        statement in <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Dīrghanakha the Wandering
                            Mendicant</title> (Toh 342) at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh342.html#UT22084-074-003-69">1.22</ref> 
                        follows the same pattern. A passage in <title xml:lang="en">The Good Eon</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title>, 
                        Toh 94) at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh94.html#UT22084-045-001-446">2.193</ref> enumerates the
                        different features of the uṣṇīṣa brought about as the fruition of the six
                        perfections (see below).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-16"/>
                    <p tid="22">The uṣṇīṣa seems to be among the highest valued of the thirty two
                        marks. Regarding the proportional amounts of merit the different marks
                        represent, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnameghasūtra</title> at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh231.html#UT22084-064-001-311">1.234</ref> lists an increasing order of magnitude for one of the
                        Buddha’s hair follicles, then the first twenty-nine marks in general, then
                        the urṇa hair, and then the uṣṇīṣa, each requiring immense multiplications
                        of the preceding amount of merit to appear, and only finally outdone by the
                        Buddha’s voice. This gradation of merit is reiterated by Asaṅga in his
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvabhūmi</title> (Toh 4037), III.5.5.
                        That the Buddha’s voice is accorded such importance is no great mystery,
                        given what he can accomplish with it. But if such gradations in terms of
                        merit are correlated with importance in terms of Buddha-activity, the fact
                        that the uṣṇīṣa comes in second place only to his voice would suggest that
                        its functions go far beyond a distinguishing mark, and this may be related
                        to the aspects mentioned below of its emanation of lights and protective
                        deities.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-5">
                    <head type="section" tid="74">Descriptions and Interpretations of the
                        Uṣṇīṣa</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-118"/>
                    <p tid="84">For two or three centuries after the Buddha’s lifetime, there seems 
                        to have been little direct artistic representation of his physical appearance, 
                        which was evoked only in images of footprints, and of symbolic objects like 
                        the tree of awakening or the doctrinal wheel. The earliest known depictions 
                        of the Buddha’s body are second century BCE sculptures from Gandhāra, produced 
                        perhaps with cultural influence coming from, or shared with, the Greeks. In these, the uṣṇīṣa
                        is commonly depicted as a raised, rounded area of his luxuriant hair, or as a bound chignon.<media mimeType="image/png" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b8/Gandhara_Buddha_%28tnm%29.jpeg/463px-Gandhara_Buddha_%28tnm%29.jpeg" source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Gandhara_Buddha_(tnm).jpeg">
                            <desc>en.wikipedia, CC BY-SA 3.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0, via Wikimedia Commons</desc>
                        </media>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-18"/>
                    <p tid="85">While the artistic iconography, starting with those first Gandhāran images, has
                        no doubt influenced what the uṣṇīṣa is understood to look like and what it might be made of, 
                        oral and textual descriptions are probably much older than the earliest depictions by artists. 
                        Yet different texts interpret the uṣṇīṣa in a range of different ways. To begin with, depictions 
                        suggesting long hair would be misleading if, as most textual accounts suggest, the Buddha’s head was shaven. 
                        No texts suggest that he ever again grew the long hair that, as Prince Siddhartha, he had cut off 
                        after renouncing the kingdom. It seems more likely that instead he had short, tightly curled 
                        ringlets of bluish-black dark hair. Details of its color, thickness, smoothness and so forth 
                        are given in no less than six items in the list of eighty minor signs often found 
                        together with the thirty-two major marks. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-19"/>
                    <p tid="25">In the Pali tradition, the statement for this mark in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lakkhaṇasutta</title>, “<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāpuriso uṇhīsasīso hoti</foreign>,” is taken, reasonably enough, to
                        mean “The great being has a head shaped like a turban” (Bhikkhu Sujato’s
                        translation) or “His head is like a royal turban” (Rhys Davids). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-20"/>
                    <p tid="26">Hence, Edgerton: </p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="27">“…according to Pali Dīghanikāya commentary ii.452.1 ff. having a
                            head the size and shape of which makes it seem turbanned.”<media mimeType="image/png" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/8e/Seated_Buddha_MET_DP-15581-052.jpg/633px-Seated_Buddha_MET_DP-15581-052.jpg" source="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Seated_Buddha_MET_DP-15581-052.jpg">
                            <desc>en.wikipedia, CC BY-SA 3.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0, via Wikimedia Commons</desc>
                        </media> </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-22"/>
                    <p tid="28">Rhys Davids (1910, 16, n. 4) says “This expression, says the Cy.,
                        refers to the fullness either of the forehead or of the cranium. In either
                        case the rounded highly-developed appearance is meant, giving to the
                        unadorned head the decorative dignified effect of a crested turban, and the
                        smooth symmetry of a water-bubble.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-23"/>
                    <p tid="29">Textually, therefore, the Pali tradition follows commentaries in
                        predominantly noting the symbolic significance of this mark regarding
                        leadership without emphasizing anything abnormal about it as describing the
                        particular shape of the Buddha’s head. Nevertheless, 
                        sculpted and painted images of the Buddha Śākyamuni in South-East Asia
                        almost universally show a pronounced uṣṇīṣa in the form of a protuberance at
                        the crown of his head (this is often surmounted by a long, pointed finial in the
                        shape of a flame or jewel, representing spiritual power, and not strictly part of the uṣṇīṣa).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-24"/>
                    <p tid="30">In the (early) Mahāyāna tradition, the long Prajñāpāramitā sūtras
                        all contain lists of the thirty-two marks including the uṣṇīṣa but without
                        detailed descriptions. The commentaries appear to follow the simpler
                        interpretations of the uṣṇīṣa, as in the Pali texts, as a description of the
                        shape of the head, or the intermediate interpretations describing a fleshy
                        crest extending over the head from one ear to the other. Thus in <title xml:lang="en">The Long Explanation 
                            of the Noble Perfection of Wisdom in One Hundred Thousand, Twenty-Five Thousand, and Eighteen Thousand 
                            Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitābṛhaṭṭīkā</title>, Toh 3808), 
                        at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3808.html#UT23703-093-001-21157">5.1327</ref>: 
                        </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-25"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="31">“…Have an <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣa</foreign> on the top
                            of their head. Take this as a head like a bound turban.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-26">
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu ze’u ka bcings pa</foreign>. This is
                                a conjectural translation of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ze’u ka
                                </foreign>as “turban.” <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ze</foreign> is a
                                word for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rngog ma</foreign> (a “mane”)
                                and a <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ze’u ka</foreign> is perhaps a
                                diminutive. Jäschke, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ze</foreign>
                                cites <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ze ka</foreign> from Czoma di
                                Korosi’s <title xml:lang="en">Dictionary</title> as meaning a
                                “hump.” </note> It is explained that the heads of others are not
                            fully developed, are elongated or squashed and are not symmetrical. The
                            heads of great persons are arranged evenly like a turban, spherical,
                            completed, well-shaped, and well developed. </p>
                        <p tid="32">Others say this major sign is to teach that the forehead is
                            fully developed in size. The flesh in between and above the right ear
                            and the left ear of the foreheads of great persons is well shaped; the
                            size of the forehead is fully completed and beautiful like a royal
                            golden turban that has been bound on.</p>
                        <p tid="33">“Again, the former action [resulting in this sign] is that they were the first, they were chief,
                            at performing all wholesome actions, making parks, assembly halls, places to
                            quench thirst and so on, therefore they have a build like a fig tree;
                            and an uṣṇīṣa on the top of their head because, having become chief in
                            the assembly they raised their head uncowed, and fearlessly enjoined
                            these actions on others. Hence these are signs that presage holding the
                            highest office.”</p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-29"/>
                    <p tid="34">Likewise, a mention of the uṣṇīṣa in <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Questions of Dīrghanakha the Wandering Mendicant</title> (Toh 342) at
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh342.html#UT22084-074-003-69">1.22</ref> uses the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor ’phags
                            pa </foreign>, “raised uṣṇīṣa,” for which the attested Sanskrit is
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣonnata</foreign>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-30"/>
                    <p tid="35">There are nevertheless more elaborate interpretations. As Edgerton
                        continues: <media mimeType="image/png" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b3/Amohaasi_Bodhisattva%2C_Mathura.jpg/581px-Amohaasi_Bodhisattva%2C_Mathura.jpg" source="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Amohaasi_Bodhisattva,_Mathura.jpg">
                            <desc>en.wikipedia, CC BY-SA 3.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0, via Wikimedia Commons</desc>
                        </media>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-31"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="36">“But in Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit (and Pali) interpreted as having
                            a head surmounted by an excrescence, whether a top-knot of hair, or a
                            growth in the skull. So Tibetan regularly (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣa</foreign> = <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor</foreign>),
                            e.g. in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> 236 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣa-śiraska-tā</foreign>. Confirmed by <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title> 401.26 ff. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mūrdhni cāsyoṣṇīṣam abhinirvṛttam abhūt, sujātaṃ
                                samantaparimaṇḍalaṃ madhyābhinyastakeśālaṃkāraṃ
                                koṭīśatasahasrapattraratnapadmasaṃdarśitaṃ samantāt
                                samabhāgapratiṣṭhitam
                            aparimitamahārghyatāpradhānamadhyam</foreign>.”</p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-32"/>
                    <p tid="37">This mention in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title> of
                        which the Sanskrit is cited by Edgerton is a description of the uṣṇīṣa as
                        twenty-seventh of the thirty-two marks enumerated by Gopā as being seen on
                        Prince Tejodhipati, found in <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh44-45.html#UT22084-037-007-4418">Chapter 43</ref> (43.93):</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-33"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="38">“There was an uṣṇīṣa formed on the crown of his head: it was well
                            formed, perfectly round, central, an adornment of the hair, resembling a
                            precious lotus with a trillion petals, perfectly symmetrical, and
                            cherished as a priceless crest adornment.”</p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-34"/>
                    <p tid="39">Another more detailed description is found in <title xml:lang="en">The Good Eon</title> 
                        (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title>, Toh 94) at 
                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh94.html#UT22084-045-001-446">2.193</ref>), 
                        where (as for all the thirty-two marks of a great being)
                        six features of a buddha’s uṣṇīṣa are listed as the fruits of the six
                        perfections practiced by him as a bodhisattva: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-35"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="40">“What are the bodhisattvas’ six perfections that bring about his
                            possessing the uṣṇīṣa on his head? As the ripening of the perfection of
                            generosity it is a deep blue coil. As the ripening of discipline, it
                            coils to the right. As the ripening of patience it is untouched by dust.
                            As the ripening of diligence its summit cannot be seen. As the ripening
                            of concentration it is an object of constant gaze. As the ripening of
                            the perfection of insight it is unaffected by rain or wind. It is in
                            these ways that the six perfections of the bodhisattvas bring about his
                            possessing the uṣṇīṣa on his head.”</p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-36"/>
                    <p tid="41">Among the various kinds of relics to which pilgrims in Gandhāra
                        could pay their respects in the middle of the first millennium, as witnessed
                        by the great Chinese travelers Faxian and Xuanzang, were the Buddha’s
                        “uṣṇīṣa bone,” suggesting that in at least some Buddhist communities of the
                        time it was seen as a distinctive anatomical feature of the cranium.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-37"> See Falk 2005, p. 445.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-6">
                    <head type="section" tid="76">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anavalokitamūrdhatā</title>, the Vertex that is Out of Sight</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-39"/>
                    <p tid="43">An additional characteristic of the uṣṇīṣa (perhaps attributable
                        only to tathāgatas and not to other kinds of great being) is found in many
                        Mahāyāna texts, as exemplified by the phrase regarding diligence in the
                        passage <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh94.html#UT22084-045-001-446">2.193</ref> from <title xml:lang="en">The Good Eon</title> 
                        (Toh 94) cited above. The most common formulation in Sanskrit is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anavalokitamūrdhatā</foreign> (literally “the head /
                        top of the head is not looked upon / beheld”), rendered almost constantly in
                        Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyi gtsug bltar mi mthong ba</foreign>
                        or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyi gtsug bltar mi mngon pa</foreign> (“the
                        crown of the head looked at is not seen”). It is often translated “the
                        invisible crown” or “invisible cranial summit.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-40"/>
                    <p tid="44">This feature is included as seventy-first in the lists of the eighty
                        supplementary signs in <title xml:lang="en">The Transcendent Perfection of
                            Wisdom in Ten Thousand Lines</title> (Toh 11) at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh11.html#UT22084-031-002-394">2.69</ref> (unusually, with the alternative formulation <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gūḍhaśikhatā</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyi gtsug bltar mi mngon pa</foreign>) and at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-031-002.html#UT22084-031-002-2413">29.57</ref> (with the usual rendering), but the lists in the other
                        Prajñāpāramitā sūtras<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-41"> According
                            to Lamotte, <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> vol. III, ch. 26 part
                            2.1, it is included in the list of the eighty supplementary signs listed
                            in the <title xml:lang="en">Hundred Thousand</title> and <title xml:lang="en">Twenty-Five Thousand Line Prajñāpāramitā</title>
                            sūtras. This is not so in the Tibetan translations of the sūtras but may
                            possibly be so in their Chinese translations.</note> and most such lists
                        in other canonical texts do not include it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-42"/>
                    <p tid="45">According to Lamotte’s <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title>:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-43"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="46">This is what the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvabhūmi</title>
                        says, p. 381: tatroṣṇīṣaśiraskatānavalokitamūrdhatā caikamahāpuruṣalakṣaṇaṃ
                        veditavayaṃ tadvyatirekeṇānupalaṃbhāt (“the two make up a single mark of the
                        Great Man; there is no difference between them.”)</p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-44"/>
                    <p tid="47">The <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anavalokitamūrdhata</foreign> is
                        mentioned as third in a list of ten superiorities (of which the first two
                        are the major marks and supplementary signs respectively) in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnacūḍaparipṛcchā</title> (Toh 91, F.228.b), and as
                        a mark of the tathāgatas requiring even more merit than the thirty-two marks
                        in <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching of Akṣayamati</title> (Toh 175, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh175.html#UT22084-060-004-130">1.103</ref>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-45"/>
                    <p tid="48">Elsewhere in the sūtras, it is at times mentioned in association
                        with the uṣṇīṣa itself, as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title> (Toh 94, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh94.html#UT22084-045-001-446">2.193</ref>), <title xml:lang="en">The Play in Full</title> (Toh 95) at
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh95.html#UT22084-046-001-2233">26.174</ref> and in <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of
                            Gaganagañja</title> (Toh 148, F.263.a); but more often on its own, as in
                            <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Roots of Virtue</title> (Toh 101,
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-348">4.21</ref>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-419">4.75</ref>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-1652">8.61</ref>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-1961">10.136</ref>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-2316">13.91</ref>), the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratyutpannabuddhasaṃmukhāvasthitasamādhisūtra</title> (Toh 133,
                        F.24.a), <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Great Compassion of the
                            Tathāgata</title> (Toh 147, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh147.html#UT22084-057-006-440">2.263</ref>), <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Generosity</title>
                        (Toh 182, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh182.html#UT22084-061-002-134">2.74</ref>), <title xml:lang="en">The Seal of Engagement in Awakening
                            the Power of Faith</title> (Toh 201, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh201.html#UT22084-062-001-506">1.423</ref> and <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh201.html#UT22084-062-001-549">1.464-5</ref>, see below), and other sūtras. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-46"/>
                    <p tid="49">Its significance may sometimes be understood as metaphorical in
                        nature—that because of the Tathāgata’s uniquely superior qualities no other
                        living being may look down upon him from above. With regard to depictions of
                        the Buddha and Avalokiteśvara, Schopen adopts that interpretation.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-47"> See Schopen 2005, pp.
                            285-6.</note> This may also be seen as a prohibition, the sanctions for
                        breaking which are one of the themes investigated by Durt. Another
                        interpretation mentioned by Durt as found in Chinese Mahāyāna sources is
                        that the uṣṇīṣa emits light so bright that it cannot be looked at.<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-48"> See Durt 1967, p. 450.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-49"/>
                    <p tid="50">But <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anavalokitamūrdhata</foreign> appears
                        more often to be presented as a more literal description of how the uṣṇīṣa
                        extends upwards, physically, to a height so vast that most kinds of beings
                        either cannot see its top, or cannot see it at all. In <title xml:lang="en">The Seal of Engagement in Awakening the Power of Faith</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śraddhābalādhānāvatāramudrāsūtra</title>, Toh 201) at
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh201.html#UT22084-062-001-549">1.464-5</ref>, Samantabhadra’s explanation to Mañjuśrī makes it clear
                        that the mention of the term refers to the physical height of a tathāgata,
                        even if the imagery of that passage may also, no doubt, convey a
                        metaphorical message regarding stature.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-50"/>
                    <p tid="51">The impossibility of the top of the uṣṇīṣa being seen—again, in
                        contrast to some sort of prohibition—is so much a law of nature that it is
                        used as an example of something “untenable” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnas
                            med</foreign>) in <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Great
                            Compassion of the Tathāgata</title> (Toh 147, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh147.html#UT22084-057-006-440">2.263</ref>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-51"/>
                    <p tid="52">In some texts the uṣṇīṣa is said to extend upwards so that even when
                        the Buddha is on earth in the human realm, the top of his uṣṇīṣa is in the
                        realm of the gods.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-52"/>
                    <p tid="53">The most complete example is found in the seventh chapter, on the
                        mysteries of the Tathāgatas’ body, of <title xml:lang="en">The Secrets of the Realized Ones</title> 
                        (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatācintyaguhyanirdeśa</title>, Toh 47) where 
                        (<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh47.html#UT22084-039-003-422">7.14 et seq.</ref>) the
                        story is told of a bodhisattva from another buddhafield who came to venerate
                        the Buddha soon after his enlightenment, and using his supernatural powers
                        tried to see the top of the Buddha’s crown by travelling upwards. But even
                        travelling upwards through countless other buddhafields was not enough for
                        him to be able to do so. However, the story ends more on a note of the
                        inconceivability of a tathāgata’s body than of any more physical
                        dimensionality.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-53"/>
                    <p tid="54">Lamotte’s <title xml:lang="fr">Traité</title> adds several examples
                        of stories that imply the physical impossibility of the top of the uṣṇīṣa
                        being seen, some evidently from the Pali—significant, as the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anavalokitamūrdhatā</foreign> is usually said to be a
                        purely Mahāyāna notion. The passage quoted here is from Gelongma Karma Migme
                        Chödrön’s English translation (ch. 26, appendix 2):</p>
                    <q>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-54"/>
                        <p tid="55">“When the Traité says here that nobody can see the top of the
                            Buddha’s cranium and that nobody among gods and men can surpass him, it
                            should be taken literally: the uṣṇīṣa of the Buddha is invisible and
                            nobody can go above it. This explains several mysterious episodes in the
                            Buddha’s life. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-55"/>
                        <p tid="56">“When the recluse Asita wanted to examine the new-born Buddha,
                            the baby’s feet turned upside-down and placed themselves on the chignon
                            of the recluse (<foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">bodhisattvassa pādā
                                parivattitvā tāpasassa jaṭāsu patiṭṭhajiṃsu</foreign>). (cf. <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Nidānakathā</title> in Jātaka, I, p. 54, l.
                                25–26.)<note place="end" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-56"> This aspect of
                                the story of Asita’s encounter with the infant Siddhartha does not
                                feature in the versions of the story in either <title xml:lang="en">The Play in Full</title> (Toh 95) or the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅghabhedavastu</title> (Toh 1 chapter
                                17).</note>
                        </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-57"/>
                        <p tid="57">“ ‘When Gautama travels, heavenly gifts, precious parasols and
                            flowers rain down like snow. The devas, nāgas and flying birds do not
                            dare to fly above him for, among beings of the threefold world, none can
                            see the summit [of his cranium]’; (cf. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmāyuḥsūtra</title>, T 76, p. 884a16–18.)</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-58"/>
                        <p tid="58">“Sātāgira and Hemavatā who were flying to an assembly of yakṣas
                            were stopped in full flight and forced to land because, if they had
                            continued on their route, they would have passed above the Buddha. (cf.
                            Comm. on the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Suttanipāta</title>, I, p.
                            221–223; Comm. on the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Hemava</title>, p.
                            64.)</p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-59"/>
                        <p tid="59">“Near Rājagṛha, at Yaṣṭivana ‘Perch Forest’: ‘Once a Brahmin,
                            having heard that the Buddha’s body was sixteen feet high, persisted in
                            doubting and did not believe it. He wanted to measure the Buddha with a
                            bamboo rod sixteen feet long, but the Buddha’s body constantly rose
                            above the top of the rod and surpassed sixteen feet. He continued
                            growing so that the Brahmin, quite unable to reach the true height,
                            threw away his stick and went away. As a result of this event, the
                            bamboo stick remained planted in the ground and took root there.’ This
                            anecdote is told by Hiuan-tsang in the <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Si-yu-ki</title>, T 2087, k. 9, p. 920a7–12, and is represented on
                            the bas-reliefs at Gandhāra (Foucher, Agb. p. 505, pl. 251b; p. 522, pl.
                            256c) but has left no trace in the texts. However, a canonical passage
                            should be noted where the Teacher forbade everyone except himself to
                            measure a pudgala: <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Mā puggalesu pamāṇikā
                                ahuvatthu … yo vā pan’assa madiso</foreign>, “Do not be one of those
                            who measure men, for the person who takes the measure of men wounds
                            himself. It is I who am able to take the measure of men, or someone like
                            me.” (<title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Anguttara</title>, III, p. 350, 351; V,
                            p. 140, 143; <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Tsa a han</title>, T 99, k. 35, p.
                            258a23–25; 258c7–8; <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgamasamādhi</title>,
                            p. 208; <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>, p. 92). … </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-60"/>
                        <p tid="60">“For other comments, see H. Durt, Note sur l’origine de
                            l’Anavalokitamūrdhatā, Indian and Buddhist Studies, XVI, p. 1967, p.
                            443–450.”</p>
                    </q>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-7">
                    <head type="section" tid="77">The Uṣṇīṣa and the Buddha’s Smile</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-62"/>
                    <p tid="86">When the rays of light emanated by the Buddha from his smile return
                        to him from the realms and world-systems they have permeated, if they vanish
                        into the uṣṇīṣa it is a sign that he is about to prophesy the unsurpassed
                        perfect awakening of a future buddha.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-162"/>
                        <p tid="87">Two of many examples in Kangyur sūtras can be seen in <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Roots
                            of Virtue</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kuśala­mūla­saṃparigraha</title>, Toh 101) at 
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-1733">9.64</ref> and 
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-048-001.html#UT22084-048-001-4010">11.48</ref>.
                            Outside the Kangyur, this is a common theme in the Avadāna literature; see for example the <title xml:lang="en">Divyāvadāna</title>
                            volume 1 (Rotman 2008, p. 247).
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-8">
                    <head type="section" tid="78">The Source of Rays of Light</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-65"/>
                    <p tid="64">In some texts, e.g. in <title xml:lang="en">The Jewel Cloud</title>
                        (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnamehga</title>, Toh 231) at <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh231.html#UT22084-064-001-50">1.8</ref>, 
                        rays of light streaming from the Buddha’s uṣṇīṣa illuminate other buddhafields
                        and invite buddhas and bodhisattvas, or arouse their curiosity, as a prelude
                        to teachings.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-9">
                    <head type="section" tid="79">The Source of Deities </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-67"/>
                    <p tid="66">In the Kriyātantras and dhāraṇī-sūtras, as well as in the Kalacakra,
                        the uṣṇīṣa is described as the source (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung
                            gnas</foreign>) of certain deities, mainly protective. However, we have not so
                        far identified a clear and explicative founding narrative for this trope. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-68"/>
                    <p tid="67">In both <title xml:lang="en">The Root Manual of the Rites of
                            Mañjuśrī</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrīmūlakalpa</title>,
                        Toh 543) and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā</title> (Toh 845),
                        uṣṇīṣa deities include Vijayā, Sitātapatra, and the cakravartin deities.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-article-10">
                    <head type="section" tid="80">In Titles of Texts</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-70"/>
                    <p tid="88">The words <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uṣṇīṣa</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor</foreign> 
                        appear as elements of the full title of some canonical texts. In some cases, this is directly
                        linked to the uṣṇīṣa being the source of the deity or dhāraṇī concerned, e.g. for Uṣṇīṣavijayā or Uṣṇīṣasitātapatrā
                        (see above). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-170"/>
                    <p tid="89">In other cases, the term may perhaps be used as a metaphor for importance or unsurpassability. For example, 
                        the long title in Tibetan of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgamasūtra</title> is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das kyi 
                            gtsug gtor chen po de bzhin gshegs pa’i gsang ba sgrub pa’i don mngon par thob pa’i rgyu byang chub sems dpa’ thams cad 
                            kyi spyod pa dpa’ bar ’gro ba’i mdo</foreign>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="3">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="4">Bibliography Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-71">Durt, Hubert. “Note sur l’origine de
                        l’Anavalokitamūrdhatā,” in <title xml:lang="en">Indian and Buddhist
                            Studies</title>, XVI, p. 1967, p. 443–450.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-72">Edgerton, F. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist
                            Hybrid Sanskrit Dictionary</title>. New Haven, 1953. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-73">Falk, Harry. “The Buddha’s Begging Bowl.” In
                            <title xml:lang="en">South Asian Archaeology 2001: Volume II, Historical
                            Archaeology and Art History</title>. Paris: Éditions Recherche sur les
                        Civilisations, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-74">Jäschke, H.A. <title xml:lang="en">A
                            Tibetan-English Dictionary</title>. London 1881; reprint edition Dover
                        Publications, 2003. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-75">Lamotte, Étienne. <title xml:lang="fr">Le Traité
                            de la Grande Vertu de Sagesse de Nāgārjuna</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāprajñā-pāramitā-śāstra</title>). Vol. I and II:
                        Bibliothèque du Muséon, 18. Louvain: Institut Orientaliste, 1949; reprinted
                        1967. Vol III, IV and V: Publications de l'Institut Orientaliste de Louvain,
                        2, 12 and 24. Louvain: Institut Orientaliste, 1970, 1976 and 1980. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-76">Rhys Davids, T.W. and C.A.F. <title xml:lang="en">Dialogues of the Buddha Part II</title>. Oxford University
                        Press, 1910.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-77">Schopen, Gregory. <title xml:lang="en">Figments
                            and Fragments of Mahāyāna Buddhism in India: More Collected
                            Papers</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawai’i Press, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-78">Vasubandhu/Daṃṣṭrāsena. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa ’bum dang / nyi khri lnga
                            sgong pa dang / khri brgyad stong pa rgya cher bshad pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryaśatasāhasrikāpañcaviṃśatisāhasrikāṣṭādaśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitābṛhaṭṭīkā</title>).
                        Toh 3808, Degé Tengyur vol. 93 (shes phyin, pha) folios 1.b-291.b. English
                        translation: Sparham, Gareth. <title xml:lang="en">Long Explanation of the
                            Noble Perfection of Wisdom in One Hundred Thousand, Twenty-five
                            Thousand, and Eighteen Thousand Lines</title> (Toh 3808). 84000:
                        Translating the Words of the Buddha, forthcoming.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-79">
                            <term type="translationMain">Supplementary signs [of a great
                                being]</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dpe byad bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དཔེ་བྱད་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anuvyañjana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-80">
                            <term type="translationMain">Marks of a great being</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">skye bu chen po’i mtshan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྐྱེ་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāpuruṣa¬lakṣaṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="EFT-KB-USNISA-81" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term type="translationMain">invisible crown</term>
                            <term type="translationAlternative">the crown of his head is out of
                                sight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedSource">anavalokitamūrdhatā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1">spyi gtsug bltar mi
                                mthong ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1">སྤྱི་གཙུག་བལྟར་མི་མཐོང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>