<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="articleTitle" xml:lang="en">Heap of Jewels (Kangyur Section)</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Heap of Jewels</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon brtsegs/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.1 <date>2024</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">heap-jewels</idno>
                <date>2024-07-05</date>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="8">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC12924"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.1" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-8">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#konchog" when="2024-07-05T13:38:06.7Z" type="text-version" status="1.0.0" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-9">
                    <desc>Various fixes to bring into current conventions.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#celso" when="2024-07-05T17:27:09.626Z" type="text-version" status="1.0.1" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-15">
                    <desc>corrected typos</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <tei:div xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Forty-nine selected sūtras (Toh 45–93) on a range of themes, compiled as a separate collection also found in the
                    Chinese Tripiṭaka.</p>
            </tei:div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <tei:div xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="10">Heap of Jewels</head>
                <tei:div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-article-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This is a compilation of forty-nine heterogeneous sūtras, present in both the Kangyur and the
                        Chinese Tripiṭaka.</p>
                    <p tid="3">The Heap of Jewels—like the other distinct collection preceding it in the Kangyur, the Ornaments of
                        the Buddhas (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title>)—is often described as a sūtra, its full
                        Sanskrit title being <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāratnakūṭasūtra</title> (“The Sūtra of the Great Heap of
                        Jewels”), and in Tibetan <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dkon mchog brtsegs pa chen po’i chos kyi rnam
                            grangs le’u stong phrag brgya pa</title> (“The Noble Dharma Discourse of the Great Heap of Precious
                        Jewels with a Hundred Thousand Chapters”). Unlike the Ornaments of the Buddhas, however, its component
                        texts or chapters are explicitly presented as independent works. Many of them are individually cited in
                        the treatises of the great Indian masters and are known to have circulated as sūtras in their own right;
                        only five are still extant in Sanskrit.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-2"/>
                    <p tid="4">Although the name <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> (“heap of jewels” or, more exactly,
                        “piled-up jewels”) seems quite appropriate for such a compilation of precious scriptural works, it is in
                        fact the name by which just one of the texts in the collection, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapaparivarta</title> (<title xml:lang="en">The Discourse for Kāśyapa</title>, Toh 87) was originally known, and seems to have been applied to the whole
                        collection only later. Citations from a <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭasūtra</title> in works by
                        Asaṅga, Śāntideva, and other authors all refer to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapaparivarta</title>,
                        which is sometimes therefore designated the “old” <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-3"/>
                    <p tid="5">The history of the Heap of Jewels remains unclear. Tibetan historical tradition, as mentioned
                        briefly in the Degé Kangyur catalog and recounted more fully by Tāranātha, tells us that the originally
                        much larger collection (with a thousand chapters, or even the hundred thousand of the full title) was
                        reduced to its current forty-nine texts by an arson attack on the library at Nālandā. The date of this
                        event, said to have been responsible for the decimation of many other scriptures, too (including the
                        Buddhāvataṃsaka), is placed sometime before the lives of Asaṅga and Vasubandhu, along with accounts of
                        other calamitous episodes during a period of political turbulence and unstable patronage for Buddhist
                        institutions in India.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-4"/>
                    <p tid="6">According to modern historical methods, while the Heap of Jewels’ component texts can be traced
                        back in some cases to dates early in the appearance of Mahāyāna texts, evidence that the collection as a
                        whole existed in India (i.e., before it appeared in China) is present but sparse. The earliest mention of
                        it is in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Daśabhūmikavibhāṣa</title>, attributed to Nāgārjuna and translated
                        into Chinese by Kumārajīva in the early fifth century. The sixth-century Gandhāran translator Jñānagupta seems
                        to have spoken of it, and the famous Chinese traveler Xuanzang was asked to translate it in 664, although
                        he only made a start. It was Bodhiruci who collected and translated it into Chinese in the first decade of
                        the eighth century, using twenty-three texts already circulating in Chinese and adding twenty-six new translations of his own;
                        it is reasonable to assume that he was using an Indian (or perhaps central Asian) prototype. The Tibetan
                        collection follows the Chinese closely in structure and composition, but most of the texts were evidently
                        translated directly from Sanskrit originals (with a few exceptions, namely <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching of the Armor Array</title>, <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching to Venerable Nanda on Dwelling in the Womb</title>, <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching to Venerable Nanda on Entry into the Womb</title>, and <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Girl Vimalaśraddhā</title>—Toh 51, 57, 58, and 84, respectively—which
                        are known to have been translated from the Chinese). The Tibetan translation is mentioned with a full list
                        of its present component texts in the early ninth-century Denkarma catalog,
                        though surprisingly the other early inventory, the Pangthangma (which is
                        thought to be of a slightly later date) lists only nine works under that heading (the other forty being
                        listed in more general size-ranked categories), and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>
                        names some of the Ratnakūṭa sūtras without any mention of the collection’s name.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-5"/>
                    <p tid="7">The sūtras in the collection cover a wide range of subjects and have diverse origins. Two (<title xml:lang="en">The Teaching to Venerable Nanda on Dwelling in the Womb</title>, Toh 57, 
                        and <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching to Venerable Nanda on Entry into the Womb</title>, Toh 58) are Śrāvakayāna works from the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya; one (<title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in Seven Hundred Lines</title>, Toh 90) is a Prajñāpāramitā sūtra;
                        and two (<title xml:lang="en">The Array of Amitābha</title>, Toh 49, and <title xml:lang="en">The Array of the Tathāgata Akṣobhya</title>, Toh 50) are Pure Land works. The majority are Mahāyāna sūtras dealing with classic themes
                        such as emptiness, compassion, wisdom, and the bodhisattva’s vows and path. The very variety of its works
                        suggests that it may have been deliberately compiled as an anthology representing many topics.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-6"/>
                    <p tid="8">Jonathan Silk (1994) has argued in his study of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnarāśisūtra</title>
                        (<title xml:lang="en">The Mass of Jewels</title>, Toh 88), a text in the collection with affinities to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapa­pari­varta</title>, that the shared features of these two texts point toward the
                        characteristics of a specific kind of “textual community,” perhaps one of many such textual communities
                        influential in the rise of the Great Vehicle. Three of the defining features of this proposed textual
                        community that can be gleaned from the work of Silk and others (Nattier 2003, Boucher 2008) are an absence
                        of discernible antagonism between śrāvaka (hearer) and bodhisattva practitioners; an emphasis on monastic
                        ideals; and a concomitant valorization of renunciation and the ascetic life. While helpful as a starting
                        point, this hypothesis does not seem to be supported fully by all the texts in the collection, however,
                        and the possible basis upon which the collection was compiled remains to be explored.</p>
                    <lb/>
                </tei:div>
            </tei:div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="11">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-14">Boucher, Daniel. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattvas of the Forest and the Formation of the Mahāyāna: A Study and Translation of the Rāṣṭrapāla­paripṛcchā-sūtra</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawai’i Press, 2008</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-12">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men: the Bodhisattva Path According to The Inquiry of Ugra</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ugraparipṛcchā</title>). Honolulu: University of Hawai’i Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-10">Pedersen, K. Priscilla, “Notes on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> collection,” JIABS 3, no. 2 (1980): 60–67.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-13">Silk, Jonathan. “The Origins and Early History of the Mahāratnakūta Tradition: Traditions of Mahāyāna Buddhism with a Study of the Ratnarāśisūtra and related Materials” PhD diss., University of Michigan, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-11">Tāranātha, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam pa’i chos rin po che ’phags
                        pa’i yul du ji ltar dar ba’i tshul gsal bar ston pa dgos ’dod kun ’byung</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya gar chos ’byung</title>, from Degé xylographs), Tezu, A.P., India: Tibetan
                        Nyingma Monastery (1974), folios 47.a–48.b. Translation in Chimpa, L. et al. (trans.). <title xml:lang="en">Tāranātha’s History of Buddhism in India</title>, 140–43. Atlantic Highlands, N.J.: Humanities Press, 1981.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <tei:div xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary"/>
            </tei:div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>