<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="articleTitle" xml:lang="en">Yoga tantras (Kangyur Section)</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Yoga tantras</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yogatantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor gyi rgyud/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.3 <date>2024</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">yoga-tantras</idno>
                <date>2024-09-02</date>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="14">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20565"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
            
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.1" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-2">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2024-08-30T18:13:01.227Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.2" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-64">
                    <desc>Revision and amplification especially of section content and classification.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2024-09-02T17:18:03.586Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.3" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-103">
                    <desc>Further extensive revision with historical section, expanded descriptions, note, and added bibliography.</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Tantras of the Yoga class based mainly on meditational practices, including those emphasizing skillful means
                    followed by those emphasizing wisdom (Toh 479-493).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="warning">
                <p tid="2">
                    <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there
                    are restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                    translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                    or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="10">Yoga Tantras</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-article-1">
                <head type="section" tid="823">Overview</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-3"/>
                    <p tid="824">The Yoga Tantras are the highest of the three groups of so-called “outer” tantras. They are characterized by 
                        consecration and ritual, the detailed practice of deity yoga, the deployment of a fivefold maṇḍala structure, 
                        and the use of mantras and mudrās. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-31"/>
                    <p tid="825">Compared to the two lower groups, the Yoga Tantras place more emphasis on the cultivation of internal meditative practices than on
                        external, ritual purity. These internal practices combinate the relative,
                        the method or skillful means (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</foreign>, 
                        <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign>) of the practice of visualizing oneself as the deity, with the
                        ultimate, the state of non-conceptual wisdom (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>,
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab</foreign>) inseparable from the deity’s appearances.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-32"/>
                    <p tid="826">Rather than the three families featuring in some tantras of the lower groups, the Yoga Tantras 
                        make use of maṇḍalas in which all five of the families found in the higher tantras are present, presided over by
                        the Tathāgata family. The principal deity at the center is therefore Vairocana, or Mahāvairocana as the primordial buddha.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-article-11">
                        <head type="section" tid="827">History</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-33"/>
                    <p tid="828">From a historical point of view, the Yoga Tantras are seen as forming the earliest cohesive 
                        corpus of texts to emerge from a mature system of tantric practice in India in the late seventh century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>,
                        even if their categorization as “Yoga Tantra” only came a century or so later. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-34"/>
                    <p tid="829">Early though they may be compared to the Mahāyoga and Yoganiruttara systems, the Yoga Tantras represent the last developments 
                        of tantra in India that were transmitted to Central Asia and China by Vajrabodhi and Amoghavajra in the eighth century, 
                        and subsequently to Japan, where they became and remain influential. Traces of their practice can be found as widely as Sri Lanka and parts of Southeast Asia. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-35"/>
                    <p tid="830">Several of the Yoga Tantras were first transmitted and translated in Tibet during the early, imperial period of
                    translation in the late eighth and early ninth centuries. Although some sections seem to have been kept hidden or left untranslated, 
                    these tantras were perhaps more openly propagated than the Mahāyoga tantras introduced in the same period. Among other reasons, this
                    may have been due to the funerary rites they provided. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-36"/>
                    <p tid="831">During the later dissemination period under the patronage of the kings of Western Tibet,
                    a new transmission lineage of the Yoga Tantras was introduced from Kashmir, and along with some newly translated works and commentaries some of the 
                    tantras translated earlier were revised, replaced, or supplemented by new versions, notably by Rinchen Zangpo and several Indian scholars.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-37"/>
                    <p tid="832">Many of the elements and features of
                        tantric practice first found in the Yoga Tantras seem to have been adopted and further developed in 
                        the tantra cycles belonging to the higher, later doxographical categories of Mahāyoga or Yoganiruttara, 
                        which were not taken up in China but only transmitted and studied in Tibet and Mongolia. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-article-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="802">The Works in This Section and Their Classification</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-4"/>
                    <p tid="4">The tantras in this section tend to be composite works with several subdivisions, some of which are briefly detailed
                        in the entries in the Degé Kangyur catalog (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-41">Situ Paṇchen, folios 144.a–145.a.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-42"/>
                    <p tid="833">The relatively small number of tantras of this class (fifteen, Toh 479-493) are subdivided into two main
                        groups: those emphasizing method or skillful means, and those emphasizing wisdom. Two additional works not included in this
                        section of the Kangyur are often taken as belonging to it from certain perspectives.</p>
                
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-5"/>
                    <p tid="834">
                        <label>I. Eight tantras emphasizing skillful means</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs gtso bor ston
                            pa’i rgyud</title>)</p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-6"/>  
                            <p tid="803">The <label>root tantra</label> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtsa rgyud</foreign>):</p>
                                <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                    <item>
                                        <p tid="804">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattva­saṃgraha</title> (Toh 479), the main tantra
                                of this group and an important early tantric work very influential in the development of tantra in
                                China and Japan as well as in Tibet. It comprises an introduction, a main body with four parts, 
                                and an appended section containing the supplementary and further supplementary tantras. Among other
                                significant elements it narrates the subjugation of Maheśvara (or Mahādeva) by Vajrapaṇi, a 
                                keystone of the tantric literature as a whole.</p>
                                </item>                        
                                </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-7"/>
                            <p tid="7">Three <label>explanatory tantras</label> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bshad rgyud</foreign>), all
                                translated in the later translation period:</p>
                            <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="805">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajra­śekhara</title> (Toh 480), the explanations 
                                        in which cover the whole of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattvasaṃgraha</title>, is 
                                        nevertheless though to be incomplete;</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="806">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­rahasya</title> (Toh 481), which covers the 
                                        first part (the Vajra­dhātu section) of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattva­saṃgraha</title>’s main body; and</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="807">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trailokyavijaya</title> (Toh 482), which covers the 
                                        similarly titled second part of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattva­saṃgraha</title>’s main body.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-8"/>
                            <p tid="8">The <label>supporting tantras</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cha mthun gyi rgyud</title>):</p>
                            <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="808">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­durgati­pari­śodhana</title>, often referred to in Tibetan as the 
                                        “purification tantra” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyong rgyud</foreign>) and widely used in funeral rites, represented
                                        by three texts:</p>
                                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="809">Toh 483, the main part of the eighth century translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­durgati­pari­śodhana</title>;</p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="810">Toh 484, a brief section from the same eighth century translation that initially had been deliberately omitted
                                                due to its content detailing the rites for “coercive activities” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon spyod kyi las</foreign>); and</p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                        <p tid="811">Toh 485, the thirteenth century translation of the same work (in the rather different form it had taken 
                                        in India some five centuries later).</p>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            <item>
                                <p tid="812">Toh 486, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Supratiṣṭha­tantra</title>.</p>    
                            </item>
                            </list>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-9"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                                <label>II. Seven tantras emphasizing wisdom</label> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab gtso bor ston pa’i
                        rgyud</foreign>), a tantric sub-corpus of the Prajñā­pāramitā literature known as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramādya</title> cycle,
                        of which the different works share similar content in different form, and mostly feature Vairocana and Vajrapaṇi as the principal interlocutors. 
                        The first five of these works are closely related and are often considered to be expanded or contracted versions of 
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in One Hundred and Fifty Lines</title>, nominally represented here as Toh 489. 
                        The parallels of these tantras are of particular importance in the Shingon tradition of Japan and its Chinese antecedents.</p>
                            <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                <item>
                                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-61"/>  
                                    <p tid="813">The two parts into which the Tibetan translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī­paramādya</title> 
                                        itself is divided, being by different translators, although in the Indian textual tradition the work was seen as
                                        a single text:</p>
                                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="814">Toh 487, the initial section of the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Paramādi­kalpa</title>; and</p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="815">Toh 488, the (considerably longer) section consisting mainly of ritual prescriptions.</p>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-62"/>  
                                    <p tid="816">A set of three works, two identified by their titles as Prajñā­pāramitā sūtras and one closely related to them:</p>
                                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="817">Toh 489, <title xml:lang="en">The Principles of the Perfection of Wisdom in One Hundred and Fifty Lines</title>
                                                (the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñā­pāramitā­naya­śata­pañca­śatikā</title> or 
                                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Adhyardha­śatikā</title>), a Prajñā­pāramitā text also found as Toh 17 
                                                in the Perfection of Wisdom section of the Kangyur; the existence of seven successive
                                            Chinese translations of this work suggests that it may have evolved from a shorter non-tantric version;</p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="818">Toh 490, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajra­maṇḍālaṃkāra</title>, an extended <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramādya</title> version featuring
                                            Mañjuśrī rather than Vajrapaṇi; and</p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="819">Toh 491, the <title xml:lang="en">The Twenty-Five Entrances to the Perfection of Wisdom</title> 
                                                (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañca­viṃśatikā­prajñā­pāramitā­mukha</title>), a short Prajñā­pāramitā text 
                                                featuring part of the content of Toh 489, and also found as Toh 20 
                                                in the Perfection of Wisdom section of the Kangyur.</p>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-63"/>  
                                    <p tid="820">Two further works in this category:</p>
                                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="835">Toh 492, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhyālaṃkāra­vyūha­tantra</title>; and</p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p tid="822">Toh 493, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­maṇi­tilaka­sūtra</title>.</p>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                
                </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-71"/>
                    <p tid="836">
                        <label>III. Two tantras also sometimes classified as Yoga Tantras</label> </p>
                    <list type="bullet" rend="dots">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="837">Toh 360, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­nāma­saṃgīti</title> 
                            (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">'jam dpal mtshan brjod</title>), placed in the Degé Kangyur
                            with the Unexcelled Yoga Tantras, but interpreted by some commentaries as a Yoga Tantra; and</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="838">Toh 466, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyā­jāla­tantra</title> 
                            (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu 'phrul dra ba</title>), also placed more usually
                            with the Unexcelled Yoga Tantras.</p>
                        </item>
                </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="11">Bibliography and Further Reading</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-listBibl-1">
                    <p tid="839">Works in Tibetan</p>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-10">Butön Rinchen Drup (bu ston rin chen grub). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor rgyud kyi rgya
                        mtshor ’jug pa’i gru gzings</title>. In Collected Works of Bu-ston, Part 11 (da). Lhasa: Zhol Printing House, 1990, 1a.1-92b.2; 
                        photographic reproduction Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture, 1968.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-101">Kongtrül Yönten Gyatso (skong sprul yon tan rgya mtsho). “rnal ’byor rgyud kyi rnam gzhag bshad pa.” 
                        In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes bya kun khyab</title>, pp. 595–600. Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang [Minorities Publishing House], 2002.
                        English translation in Jamgön Kongtrul, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-11">Situ Paṇchen Chökyi Jungné (si tu pan chen chos kyi ’byung gnas). 
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</title> [Degé Kangyur Catalog]. Toh 4568.
                    Degé Kangyur, vol. 103 (dkar chag, la k+sh+mI), folios 1.a–172.a.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="840">Works in English</p>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-1">Astley-Kristensen, Ian. <title xml:lang="en">The Rishukyō: The 
                        Sino-Japanese Tantric Prajñā­pāramitā in 150 Verses (Amoghavajra’s Version)</title>. Buddhica Britannica, 
                        Series Continua III. Tring: Institute of Buddhist Studies, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-102">Jamgön Kongtrul; Guarisco, Elio, and Ingrid McLeod (trs.). <title xml:lang="en">Systems of Buddhist Tantra</title>. 
                        Treasury of Knowledge Series, Book Six, Part Four. Ithaca and Boulder: Snow Lion, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-12">Tomabechi, Toru (ed.). <title xml:lang="en">Adhyardha­śatikā Prajñā­pāramitā: 
                        Sanskrit and Tibetan texts</title>. Beijing-Vienna: China Tibetology Publishing House and Austrian Academy of Sciences Press, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413-13">Weinberger, Steven Neal. <title xml:lang="en">The Significance of Yoga Tantra 
                        and the Compendium of Principles (Tattva­saṃgraha Tantra) within Tantric Buddhism in India and Tibet</title>. 
                        University of Virginia, PhD dissertation, 2003.</bibl>
            </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary"/>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>