<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="articleTitle" xml:lang="en">Compendium of Dhāraṇīs (Kangyur Section)</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Compendium of Dhāraṇīs</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇīsaṃgraha</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs 'dus/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.3 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">compendium-dharanis</idno>
                <date>2023-08-02</date>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="23">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14717"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
            
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.1" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-3">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-08-02T18:22:09.052Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.2" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-14">
                    <desc>Added material including bibliography.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-10-06T10:40:42.727Z" type="text-version" status="1.1.3" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-32">
                    <desc>Edited with changes</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The actual collection of 250 dhāraṇī texts (Toh 846-1093).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="9">Compendium of Dhāraṇīs</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-article-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">The 250 texts in this section all belong to the genre sometimes known as “incantations,” a somewhat 
                        unsatisfactory translation of the Sanskrit 
                        term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> (Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs</foreign>). 
                        This term can mean “memory” or “retention” as well as designating a
                        formulaic sequence of syllables or words (of the kind that characterizes these texts) understood to 
                        have a power greater than their mere semantic content.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇī</foreign> in the sense of “retention” refers to a 
                        quality of mind or accomplishment said to be attained by arhats and
                        bodhisattvas that allows them to memorize long teachings and instructions, one method 
                        of so doing being to compress them into a few words or syllables which then provide a key
                        or mnemonic for their later recall. These words or syllables therefore contain all the 
                        potency of the material of which they are the quintessence, and can be deployed in
                        rituals for a wide variety of purposes. Although such <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> 
                        are often taken to be of a tantric nature (and many of them are
                        indeed of tantric origin), their use is widespread in many Buddhist traditions outside any 
                        tantric influence. The term is thus distinct from the related term “mantra.” But as well as referring 
                        to the retentive qualities of mind in general, specific instances of it, and the spoken or written 
                        formulae that may result from deploying a process of that kind, the term  
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> is also used to designate entire works that are about,
                        or include, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> formulae.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-31"/>
                    <p tid="4">Works of this genre almost always include more than simply such a formula or set of 
                        formulae (usually in Sanskrit). Typically, an introductory narrative may explain
                        their history and the reasons for their being taught, and a concluding section may describe 
                        how they should be used and what results and benefits will ensue.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">A total of 108 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> texts are listed in the 
                        early 9th century Denkarma catalogue, including a set headed the “Five
                        Great Dhāraṇīs,” a miscellaneous group of 103 other works, and a set of nine works centered 
                        on the recital of the 108 names of a deity or bodhisattva.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">The slightly later Phangthangma inventory lists the same “Five Great Dhāraṇīs,” 13 
                        miscellaneous dhāraṇī texts with rituals, a set of 89 dhāraṇīs ranked in order
                        of their different size, a group of nine “essence” mantra-dhāraṇīs extracted from larger texts 
                        elsewhere, and a final mixed group of 34 texts, some with 108 names, some
                        praises, expressions of auspiciousness, or aspiration prayers.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-6"/>
                    <p tid="10">In most Kangyurs, works categorized as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> are 
                        to be found scattered in the General Sūtra section 
                        and in a subdivision of the Tantra Collection, almost exclusively among the Action Tantras (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kriyātantra</foreign>). 
                        But in addition, most Kangyurs of the Tshalpa tradition contain all the dhāraṇī texts gathered in one place, too, 
                        either as a separate and distinctly named Compendium of Dhāraṇīs (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus</foreign>), as in 
                        the Degé and Urga Kangyurs, or as a self-contained but unnamed set of largely duplicated or triplicated texts in the later volumes of the tantra section, 
                        as in the Peking-Qianlong, Lithang, and Choné Kangyurs. The Narthang and Lhasa Kangyurs, along with the manuscript Kangyurs 
                        of the Themphangma tradition, do not gather these texts into a distinct set of copies.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">As well as works conforming to the usual structure of a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign>, 
                        the section also includes texts containing the 108
                        names of the Buddha (Toh 873), the Eight Bodhisattvas (Toh 874-881), Tāra (Toh 1000), and the wealth god 
                        Jambhala (Toh 972); sūtras recited for ritual and protective purposes,
                        including three of the Mahāsūtras (Toh 1061-2 and 1093); texts that essentialize much longer works, 
                        whether sūtra or tantra (Toh 932-934 and 939-945); and a number of praises
                        and invocations.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-8"/>
                    <p tid="11">In the Degé Kangyur, the vast majority of the 250 works contained in this section are duplicates 
                        or triplicates of works in other divisions of the 
                        Kangyur (as mentioned above in <ptr target="O1JC114941JC20568-6"/>), even if—in some cases—the version 
                        of a text reproduced in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs differs slightly from 
                        the version of that same text found elsewhere in the Kangyur. There are, however, twelve works in this 
                        section that are unique to this part of the Kangyur: 
                        Toh 846, 846a, 862, 865, 891, 953, 987, 1024, 1059, 1066, 1067, 1090, and 1091. It seems likely
                    that these twelve works found their way into the Kangyurs of the Tshalpa lineage not from more generalized
                    earlier collections of canonical translations but as a result of their inclusion in the pre-existing independent collections
                    of dhāraṇīs (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇīsaṃgraha</foreign>) described below.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-9"/>
                    <p tid="13">The contents of the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs, unlike all the other sections of the canon, is not 
                        listed and described in full in Situ Panchen’s official 
                        catalog (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign>) of the Degé Kangyur. It is only mentioned in 
                        the following brief note 
                        following the end of the catalog of the Tantra Collection:</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="21">Out of these [preceding sections], a collection of the short dhāraṇī-texts, gathered together in one 
                        place on account of their benefit for beings and known nowadays 
                        as the <title xml:lang="en">Compendium of Dhāraṇīs</title>, has been placed, as it is in Kangyurs 
                        of the Tshalpa text lineage, after the tantras; it is found in the two volumes labeled
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">e</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">waM</foreign>. (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</title> F.156.b).</p> 
                    </q> 
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-10"/>
                    <p tid="14">Although the majority of duplicated texts have clearly been edited to conform to the versions found elsewhere, 
                        it also appears that the content and order of the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs may have been created following the 
                        model of earlier, independent collections, several of which are known to have existed from similar 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇīsaṃgraha</foreign> collections in Sanskrit and among the finds
                        in Dunhuang. At what point they began to be added as an appendix to the main volumes of the Kangyur 
                        in the Tshalpa (but not the Themphangma) Kangyurs remains unknown.  
                        (see Hidas 2021, p. 7, n. 56.  See also Dalton 2016 and Dalton and van Schaik 2006 on the dhāraṇīsaṃgraha collections 
                        preserved at Dunhuang. See Hidas 2021 for the catalogues of eighteen Sanskrit dhāraṇīsaṃgraha collections.) </p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="15">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-11">Hidas, Gergely. <title xml:lang="en">Powers 
                        of Protection: The Buddhist Tradition of Spells
                        in the Dhāraṇīsaṃgraha Collections</title> (vol. 9 of <title xml:lang="en">Beyond Boundaries: 
                            Religion, Region, Language, and the State</title>). Berlin and Boston: de Gruyter, 2021 
                        (<ref target="https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/9783110713367/html">open access</ref>).
                    </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-12">Dalton, Jacob P. “How Dhāraṇīs WERE Proto-Tantric. Liturgies, Ritual Manuals, and the
                    Origins of the Tantras.” In Gray, David B. and Ryan R. Overbey (eds.) <title xml:lang="en">Tantric Traditions 
                        in Transmission and Translation</title>, 199–229. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-13">Dalton, Jacob, and Sam van Schaik. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Tantric Manuscripts 
                    from Dunhuang: A Descriptive Catalogue of the Stein Collection at the British Library</title>. Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2006.
                </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary"/>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>