<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Tantra</title>
            <title type="articleTitle" xml:lang="en">Tantra (Tengyur Section)</title>
                </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.1 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <availability status="1"/>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704"/>
                <idno type="eft-kb-id">tantra-tengyur</idno>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W23703" sort-index="3">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC7630"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
            
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.1.1" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-6">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Commentaries, instructions, and liturgical works on the tantras (Toh 1180-3785)</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head type="article" tid="6">Tantra</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-article-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This is by far the largest division of the Tengyur, containing no less than 2,626 works.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">Traditionally it is presented as one undivided collection. Here, however, it has been subdivided—not only
                        for easy reference, but also for technical reasons, to enable slower computer systems to load the
                        extensive title data rapidly and without timing out.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The subdivisions follow the structure set out by Zhuchen Tsültrim Rinchen, the 18th century editor of the
                        Degé Tengyur, in his catalog to the collection (Toh 4569). He classifies the divisions and their works
                        from “higher” to “lower.” The initial division is into the four principal classes of tantra, together with
                        a fifth section for works he classifies as common to all four, or with no definite affinity to a single
                        class. The first (and very large) Unexcelled Yoga tantra class is further subdivided into four main
                        groups, with further subdivision in some of them, and the fifth section is subdivided into the collections
                        of which it is largely composed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The Degé Tengyur's system of classifying the tantras is by no means the only possible one, and Tsültrim
                        Rinchen frequently notes diverging opinions put forward by other scholars and editors. There are even
                        differences between his classification and that of Situ Paṇchen Chökyi Jungné in the Degé Kangyur. Many of
                        Tsültrim Rinchen’s choices were, he says, dictated by tradition and by past precedent, notably that of
                        Butön Rinchen Drup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bu ston rin chen grub</foreign>, 1290-1364), although the
                        latter’s system is far from being fully reproduced in the Degé Tengyur.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="7">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="8">Bibliography Section Heading</head>
                    <bibl rend="default-text" xml:id="O1JC76301JC7704-5">This is a sample bibliographic reference with a <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh46.html">link example</ref>.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary"/>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>