<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sher phyin khri brgyad stong pa/ \(khri
                    brgyad/\)</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭādaśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">The Perfection of Wisdom in Eighteen Thousand
                    Lines</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">’phags pa shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa
                    khri brgyad stong pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">Āryāṣṭādaśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">般若波羅蜜多一萬八千頌 · (大正藏：大般若波羅蜜多經第三會)</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-60"/>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-211">Dr. Gareth
                    Sparham</author>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-289">Nathaniel
                    Rich</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-211">Dr. Gareth
                    Sparham</consultant>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <sponsor ref="sponsors.xml#sponsor-25">Matthew Yizhen Kong, Steven Ye Kong and
                    family</sponsor>
                <sponsor ref="sponsors.xml#sponsor-25">An Zhang, Hannah Zhang, Lucas Zhang, Aiden
                    Zhang, Jinglan Chi, Jingcan Chi, Jinghui Chi and family, Hong Zhang and
                    family</sponsor>
                <sponsor ref="sponsors.xml#sponsor-182">Mao Guirong, Zhang Yikun, Chi
                    Linlin</sponsor>
                <sponsor ref="sponsors.xml#sponsor-197">Joseph Tse, Patricia Tse and
                    Family</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.12 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to
                    make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-029-001"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means
                    that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2021-07-16</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh10" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 10</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 29 (shes phyin, ka), folios 1.a–300.a; vol. 30
                        (shes phyin, kha), folios 1.a–304.a; vol. 31 (shes phyin, ga), folios
                        1.a–206.a.</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="1611">
                        <volume number="29" start-page="2" end-page="599"/>
                        <volume number="30" start-page="2" end-page="607"/>
                        <volume number="31" start-page="2" end-page="412"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14665" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11523" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2021-07-16T22:54:46.663Z" user="admin">16/07/2021 22:54:46</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-11-20T08:51:58.292Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2019-12-12T18:49:53.683Z" user="john">2.f</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2020-01-27T13:06:18.593Z" user="mike">2.g</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.h" date-time="2020-02-24T08:13:40.798Z" user="andreas">2.h</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2020-03-20T08:34:56.675Z" user="line-tofte">2.g</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-07-06T07:41:16.554Z" user="line-tofte">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.2" date-time="2020-10-13T12:19:22.704Z" user="amy">Auto (update-sponsorship)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.3" date-time="2020-12-31T08:28:58.951Z" user="amy">Auto (update-sponsorship)</note>

                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2021-02-18T07:48:47.144Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2021-02-18T07:48:47.144Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.5" date-time="2021-02-24T07:45:10.042Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.6" date-time="2021-03-16T16:49:48.298Z" user="amy">Auto (update-sponsorship)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.7" date-time="2021-03-17T02:14:23.075Z" user="amy">Auto (update-sponsorship)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.8" date-time="2021-03-17T02:14:47.847Z" user="amy">Auto (update-sponsorship)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2021-03-22T14:29:53.569Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.9" date-time="2021-03-22T14:29:53.569Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2021-03-29T10:36:11.334Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.10" date-time="2021-03-29T10:36:11.334Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.11" date-time="2021-04-22T16:47:33.266Z" user="amy">Auto (update-sponsorship)</note>
            
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.12" date-time="2021-07-16T22:54:43.454Z" user="celso">Sample section for crossref test, status"2.a" is false, actual status="2.d"</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-1"/>
                <p tid="2">[Summary to be entered here]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-2"/>
                <p tid="4">[Acknowledgements to be added here.]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-introduction-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="6">Main Section</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">This is a test sample of the first chapter of the 18 Thousand Line
                        Perfection of Wisdom Sūtra applied on 7/16/2021 for the purposes of testing
                        its cross-referencing with Toh 3808. All off the sections including the
                        first chapter will be replaced by the later proofed version. Please
                        disregard any current grammatical issues in the translation. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="8"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="9">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="10">The Perfection of Wisdom in Eighteen Thousand
                    Lines</head>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-chapter-1">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="11">Chapter 1: Introduction</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-4"/>
                    <p tid="12">[B1]</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-5"/>
                    <p tid="13">We prostrate to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-6"/>
                    <p tid="14">Thus did I hear at one time. The Lord dwelt at Rājagṛha on
                        Gṛdhrākūṭa Hill together with a great community of monks, numbering<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-7"> Here and below “numbering”
                            renders <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mātra</foreign> (from root <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mā</foreign> “to measure”). D
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsam</foreign> means “just” (in a limiting sense).</note> five
                        thousand monks, all worthy ones with the exception of one single
                        person––that is, venerable Ānanda––with outflows dried up, without
                        afflictions, fully controlled, with their minds well freed and their wisdom
                        well freed, thoroughbreds, great bull elephants, with their work done, their
                        task accomplished, with their burden laid down, with their own goal
                        accomplished, with the fetters that bound them to existence broken, with
                        their hearts well freed by perfect understanding, in perfect<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-8"> “Perfect” is the MDPL rendering
                            of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">paramapārami</foreign>
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dam pa’i pha rol tu son
                                pa</foreign>). Seton (Appendix I, 36) says Ratnākaraśānti dissolves
                            the compound more fully to mean “because they have gone and are in a
                            state that has gone to the limit of mental mastery.”</note> control of
                        their whole mind; [F.2.a] with nuns numbering five hundred––Yaśodharā,
                        Mahāprajāpatī, and so on—and with a great many laymen and laywomen, all of
                        them with a vision of the Dharma; and with an unbounded, infinite number of
                        bodhisattva great beings, all of whom had acquired the dhāraṇīs, were
                        dwellers in emptiness, their range the signless, and who had not fashioned
                        any wishes, had acquired forbearance for the sameness of all dharmas, had
                        acquired the dhāraṇī of nonattachment, with imperishable clairvoyant
                        knowledges, and with speech worth listening to; who were not hypocrites, not
                        fawners, with thoughts that had left behind all desire for reputation and
                        gain; who were Dharma teachers without thought of compensation, with perfect
                        forbearance for the deep dharmas, who had obtained the fearlessnesses, and
                        who had transcended all the works of Māra, who had cut the continuum of
                        karmic obscuration, were skillful in expounding the analysis of
                        investigations into phenomena, with the prayers they made during
                        incalculable eons really fully answered, with smiling countenances, forward
                        in addressing others, without a frown on their faces, skillful in
                        communicating with others in chanted verse, without feelings of depression,
                        without losing the confidence giving a readiness to speak, and endowed with
                        fearlessness when surpassing endless assemblies; who were skilled in going
                        forth during an endless one hundred million eons, understanding phenomena to
                        be like an illusion, a mirage, a reflection of the moon in water, a dream,
                        an echo, an apparition, a reflection in the mirror, and a magical creation;
                        who were skillful in comprehending the thoughts, conduct, and beliefs of all
                        beings and subtle knowledge, [F.2.b] with unobstructed thoughts, and endowed
                        with extreme patience; who were skilled in causing entry into reality just
                        as it is, having appropriated all the endless arrays of the buddhafields
                        through prayer and setting out, with the meditative stabilization
                        recollecting buddhas in an infinite number of world systems constantly and
                        always activated; who were skillful in soliciting innumerable buddhas; who
                        were skillful in eliminating the various views, propensities, obsessions,
                        and defilements; and who were skillful in accomplishing a hundred thousand
                        feats through meditative concentration. That is, he was together with the
                        bodhisattva great beings Bhadrapāla, Ratnākara, Ratnagarbha,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-9"> H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen snying po</foreign>.</note> Ratnadatta, Susārthavaha,
                        Varuṇadeva, Guhyagupta, Indradatta, Uttaramatin, Viśeṣamatin,
                        Vardhamānamatin, Anantamatin, Amoghadarśin, Anāvaraṇamatin, Susaṃprasthita,
                        Suvikrāntamin, Anantavīrya, Nityodyukta, Nityaprayukta, Anikṣiptadura,
                        Sūryagarbha, Anupamamatin, and Avalokiteśvara, Mahāsthāmaprāpta, Mañjuśrī
                        Kumārabhūta, Mārabalapramardin, Vajramatin, Ratnamudrāhasta,
                        Nityotkṣiptahasta, Mahākaruṇācinta, Mahāvyūha, Vyūharāja, and Merukūṭa, the
                        bodhisattva great being Maitreya, and many hundreds of thousands of one
                        hundred million billion other bodhisattvas as well. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-10"/>
                    <p tid="15"> Thereupon the Lord, having himself arranged the lion throne, sat
                        down with his legs crossed, holding his body erect, intent on fixing
                        mindfulness, and entered into the meditative stabilization, [F.3.a]
                            <distinct>samādhirāja</distinct> by name, in which all meditative
                        stabilizations are included, encompassed, and come to meet.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-11"/>
                    <p tid="16"> Then the Lord, mindful and self-possessed, emerged from this
                        meditative stabilization and surveyed with his divine eye all world systems.
                        Having done so, he beamed with his whole body. From the wheels with a
                        thousand spokes on the soles of his feet issued sixty sixty-one hundred
                        thousand one hundred million billion rays, from the ten toes of his feet
                        issued sixty sixty-one hundred thousand one hundred million billion rays,
                        and similarly from his ankles, legs, knees, thighs, hips, and navel, from
                        his two sides, and from the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śrivatsa</foreign> mark of a great person in his heart issued sixty
                        sixty-one hundred thousand one hundred million billion rays. From his ten
                        fingers issued sixty sixty-one hundred thousand one hundred million billion
                        rays. Similarly, from his two forearms, two shoulders, neck, four eyeteeth,
                        all forty teeth, two nostrils, ears and eyes, the soft, long, fine, coiled
                        white hair between his eyebrows, the naturally formed turban of hair on the
                        top of his head, and from the opening of his mouth issued sixty sixty-one
                        hundred thousand one hundred million billion rays. All these sixty sixty-one
                        hundred thousand one hundred million billion rays pervaded the world systems
                        in their entirety with a great illumination and lit them up. This great
                        illumination from the light rays spread out through as many world systems in
                        the eastern direction as there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River.
                        Similarly, this great illumination from the light rays spread out through
                        each of as many world systems as there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River
                        to the south, west, and north, in the intermediate directions to the
                        northeast, southeast, southwest, northwest, below and above, and lit them
                        up. And all the beings [F.3.b] that saw that light, that were touched by the
                        illumination of those light rays, became irreversible from unsurpassed,
                        perfect, complete awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-12"/>
                    <p tid="17"> Thereupon all the Lord’s hair pores became radiant. From each of
                        the hair pores sixty sixty-one hundred thousand one hundred million billion
                        rays issued forth, and these rays pervaded all the world systems in the
                        great billionfold world system with a great illumination. This great
                        illumination from the light rays spread out through as many world systems as
                        there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River to the east, pervading them with
                        a great illumination and lighting them up. Similarly, this illumination from
                        the light rays spread out through each of as many world systems as there are
                        sand particles in the Gaṅgā River to the south, west, and north, in the
                        intermediate directions to the northeast, southeast, southwest, and
                        northwest, below and above, and lit them up. And all the beings that saw
                        that light, that were touched by the illumination of those light rays,
                        became irreversible from unsurpassed, perfect, complete awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-13"/>
                    <p tid="18"> Then the Lord, with the light from the natural splendor of a
                        tathāgata, pervaded the great billionfold world system with a great
                        illumination. He pervaded as many world systems as there are sand particles
                        in the Gaṅgā River to the east with this great illumination, and similarly,
                        pervaded each of as many world systems as there are sand particles in the
                        Gaṅgā River to the south, west, and north, in the intermediate directions to
                        the northeast, southeast, southwest, and northwest, below and above, with
                        this great illumination. And all the beings that saw that light, that were
                        touched by the illumination of those light rays, became irreversible from
                        unsurpassed, perfect, complete awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-14"/>
                    <p tid="19"> Thereupon the Lord extended his tongue and with it covered the
                        great billionfold world system in its entirety. [F.4.a] Having pervaded the
                        great billionfold world system with his tongue, he smiled, and from his
                        tongue again many hundred thousand one hundred million billion variously
                        colored rays issued forth, and on all the light rays stood lotuses made of
                        manifold precious stones, shining like gold, each with a thousand petals,
                        variegated, beautiful, captivating, brilliant, fragrant, and soft, all
                        completely like the kācalindika,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-15"> MW, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kācalindi</foreign> says <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kācalindi</foreign> is a different spelling of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kācaciñcika</foreign>, the <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">Arbus precatorius</foreign>,
                            an herbaceous flowery plant with deadly poisonous bright red seeds
                            prized as beads for use in rosaries and jewelry. Each has almost exactly
                            the same weight, so they were used in weighing gold.</note> pleasing to
                        the touch. On the lotuses, furthermore, were seated many embodied
                        tathāgatas, teaching Dharma—this very teaching of Dharma associated with the
                        perfection of wisdom. They went to as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River to the east and taught Dharma—this very
                        teaching of Dharma associated with the perfection of wisdom—and similarly,
                        to each of as many world systems as there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā
                        River to the south, west, and north, in the intermediate directions to the
                        northeast, southeast, southwest, and northwest, below and above, and
                        demonstrated Dharma—this very teaching of Dharma associated with the six
                        perfections. And all the beings who listened to that Dharma became
                        irreversible from unsurpassed, perfect, complete awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-16"/>
                    <p tid="20"> Then the Lord, seated on that very lion throne, entered into the
                        meditative stabilization called <distinct>siṃhavikrīḍita</distinct>. He
                        enacted such a performance with his miraculous power that his performance of
                        miraculous power shook the great billionfold world system in six ways: it
                        shook, shook greatly, and shook violently; it quaked, quaked greatly, and
                        quaked violently; it stirred, stirred greatly, and stirred violently; it
                        became disturbed, greatly disturbed, and violently disturbed; [F.4.b] it
                        roared, roared greatly, and roared violently; and it resounded, resounded
                        greatly, and resounded violently. At the edges it rose up and it sank down
                        in the middle; in the middle it rose up and at the edges sank down. It
                        became soft and oily, producing benefit and ease for all beings. Thereupon,
                        at that moment, minute, and second, in the great billionfold world system
                        the continuums of the hells and the animal world, and the world of Yama,
                        were all cut. And all the places that preclude a perfect human birth
                        disappeared. All those beings were reborn among humans, and also among the
                        Cāturmahārājika, Trāyastriṃśa, Yāma, Tuṣita, Nirmāṇarati, and
                        Paranirmitavaśavartin gods.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-17"/>
                    <p tid="21"> Thereupon, in their great joy and rejoicing these humans and gods
                        recalled their former lives, and having recalled them approached the Lord,
                        bowed to his feet with their heads, cupped their palms together in a gesture
                        of prayerful supplication, and bowed forward. And so too in each of the ten
                        directions, in as many world systems as there are sand particles in the
                        Gaṅgā River to the east, to the south, west, and north, in the intermediate
                        directions, and below and above, the continuums of the hells, animal worlds,
                        and the worlds of Yama in as many world systems as there are sand particles
                        in the Gaṅgā River were all cut too. And all the places precluding a perfect
                        birth disappeared. All those beings were reborn among humans and the gods.
                        Thereupon these humans and gods recalled their former lives. In their great
                        joy and rejoicing they then approached the buddhas in their respective
                        buddhafields, bowed to their feet with their heads, [F.5.a] and with palms
                        together in a gesture of prayerful supplication bowed forward.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-18"/>
                    <p tid="22"> Then, in the great billionfold world system the beings who were
                        born blind saw forms with their eyes, the deaf heard sounds with their ears,
                        the insane regained their senses, those with distracted thoughts became
                        one-pointed in their thoughts, the naked found clothes, the poor found
                        wealth, the hungry found food, the thirsty found drink, the sick were
                        healed, the sense faculties of those with damaged sense faculties were
                        repaired, and the physically exhausted became no longer exhausted. Those who
                        had not given up unwholesome deeds of body, speech, and mind, and
                        unwholesome livelihood, gave up their unwholesome habits. All beings
                        considered every being in the same way as they considered their mother,
                        father, brother, and sister, and as they considered their friends, close
                        relatives, and blood relatives. And they were endowed with the ten wholesome
                        paths of action, and became celibate, pure, free from the stain of
                        immorality, and free from all unwholesome conceptualization. And at that
                        time all beings, possessed of all happiness, acquired the ease a monk feels
                        when absorbed in the third concentration. And at that very time they were
                        endowed with such knowledge that they knew, “Good is charity! Good is
                        self-discipline! Good is restraint! Good it is to observe celibacy! Good is
                        nonviolence toward living creatures!” And at that time [F.5.b] the lord
                        buddhas in other buddhafields cried out cries of delight: “Ah! It is amazing
                        these beings are thus endowed with such knowledge that knows, ‘Good is
                        charity! Good is self-discipline! Good is restraint! Good it is to observe
                        celibacy! Good is nonviolence toward living creatures!’ ” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-19"/>
                    <p tid="23"> Thereupon the Lord, seated on this very lion throne, stood out
                        towering over the great billionfold world system with Sumeru, the encircling
                        mountain ranges, the abodes of the gods, Indra, Brahmā, Vaśavartin,
                        Śuddhāvāsa, and the classes of gods and asuras,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-20"> “Asuras”: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lha ma yin</foreign> renders <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dānava</foreign>.</note> shining forth, gleaming,
                        dazzling, and shedding light with his light, color, brilliance, and glory in
                        the same way as, for example, a strong sun or the disk of a full moon in a
                        clear sky.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-21"/>
                    <p tid="24"> So too the Lord stood out towering over as many world systems as
                        there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River to the east with his light,
                        color, brilliance, and glory. Similarly the Lord stood out towering over as
                        many world systems as there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River to the
                        south, west, and north, in the intermediate directions, and below and
                        above—in each of the ten directions—shining forth, gleaming, dazzling, and
                        shedding light with his light, color, brilliance, and glory in the same way
                        as, for example, Sumeru, the king of mountains, stands out towering over all
                        mountains, shining forth, gleaming, dazzling, and shedding light; or in the
                        same way as, for example, the disk of the moon towers over all the stars,
                        shining forth, gleaming, dazzling, and shedding light; or in the same way
                        as, for example, the disk of the sun [F.6.a] stands out towering over all
                        other lights, shining forth, gleaming, dazzling, and shedding light. So too
                        the Lord stands out towering over world systems in the ten directions with
                        their gods, Indras, Brahmās, Śuddhāvāsas, and the classes of gods and
                        humans, shining forth, gleaming, dazzling, and shedding light with his
                        light, color, brilliance, and glory.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-22"/>
                    <p tid="25"> Thereupon the Lord exhibited an ordinary bodily form, like that of
                        beings in the great billionfold world system. Then in the great billionfold
                        world system all the gods, from the gods of the Śuddhāvāsa class, down to
                        the Brahmā, Paranirmitavaśavartin, Nirmāṇarati, Tuṣita, Yāma, Trāyastriṃśa,
                        and Cāturmahārājik gods saw the body of the Tathāgata you can never see
                        enough. Feeling contented, pleased, delighted, joyful, and joyous, with such
                        mental happiness they took celestial flowers, celestial garlands, celestial
                        incense, celestial creams, celestial powders, and celestial perfumes;
                        celestial blue lotuses, lotuses, red lotuses, white lotuses, nalina lilies
                        and saugandhaka lilies; celestial flowers, nāgavṛkṣa flowers, and tamāla
                        leaves; and celestial robes, celestial jewelry, celestial parasols, flags,
                        and banners and approached the Lord. Those humans to be trained, and in the
                        form of recipients seated in the great billionfold world system, saw the
                        body of the Tathāgata you can never see enough, took land and water flowers
                        and approached the body of the Tathāgata you can never see enough. [F.6.b]
                        Both gods and humans then strewed near, strewed in front, and strewed
                        flowers all around<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-23"> Nakamura
                            (2014: 516) renders these “strewing [flowers] near [to Buddha], strewing
                            [flowers] in front [of Buddha] and strewing [flowers] all around
                            [Buddha].” The Tib says, literally, “strew down on, strew over, and
                            strew right over.”</note> the body of the Tathāgata these celestial
                        flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, creams, powders, robes, parasols,
                        flags, banners, and land and water flowers. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-24"/>
                    <p tid="26"> By the sustaining power of the Lord all this rain of flowers,
                        incense, perfumes, garlands, creams, powders, robes, parasols, flags,
                        banners, and land and water flowers strewed down on the Lord stayed there
                        like a second story made of flowers and so on, with the dimensions of the
                        great billionfold world system, in the sky right above the Lord’s head. And
                        from this second story tassels made of celestial flowers and silk were
                        suspended, hanging there, hanging right there, and these tassels made of
                        celestial flowers and silk made the great billionfold world system look very
                        beautiful. And the brightly shining golden color of the Lord streaming forth
                        in the ten directions pervaded and lit up as many world systems as there are
                        sand particles in the Gaṅgā River in each direction. This thought then
                        occurred to each of the gods and humans in all the Jambudvīpa world systems
                        in the great billionfold world system: “The Tathāgata is seated in front of
                        us teaching the Dharma.” Similarly, this thought occurred to the gods in the
                        Godānīyas to the west, Videhas to the east, and Kurus to the north, to the
                            Cāturmahārājika<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-25"> For
                            consistency <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal chen bzhi’i ris</foreign> is rendered
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cāturmahārājika</foreign> (“[gods] belonging to the group of the
                            four Great Kings”) even though there are a number of Skt forms (Edgerton
                            says the forms are <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cāturmahārājakāyika</foreign> and less often
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturmahārājakāyika</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cāturmahārājika</foreign> and
                            less often <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturmahārājika</foreign>) and slight differences are
                            encountered in the Tib translation. “Gods” is sometimes rendered
                            explicitly and is sometimes implicit in the Tib.</note> gods up to the
                        Akaniṣṭha gods, and similarly to all of the gods and humans in a
                        thousandfold [four-continent] world system, in a millionfold world system,
                        or in a great billionfold world system: [F.7.a] “The Tathāgata is seated in
                        front of us teaching the Dharma.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-26"/>
                    <p tid="27"> Thereupon the Lord, seated on this very lion throne, smiled once
                        again. Through the illumination from that smile the great billionfold world
                        system was lit up, and all the beings seated in the great billionfold world
                        system saw the Lord Buddha, together with his śrāvaka saṅgha, in as many
                        world systems as there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River to the east.
                        And all those beings seated in as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River to the east saw the Lord Śākyamuni, together
                        with his community of monks, in this Sahā world system.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-27"/>
                    <p tid="28"> Similarly, the beings included in this Sahā world system saw the
                        Lord Buddha, together with his śrāvaka saṅgha, in as many world systems as
                        there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River to the south, west, and north,
                        in the intermediate directions to the northeast, southeast, southwest, and
                        northwest, below and above. And all those beings seated in as many world
                        systems as there are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River as well saw this Sahā
                        world system and the Lord Śākyamuni, together with his community of
                        monks.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-28"/>
                    <p tid="29"> In the east, beyond as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River, at the very limit of these world systems,
                        there is a world system called Ratnāvatī. In it the tathāgata, worthy one,
                        perfectly complete buddha Ratnākara now dwells and maintains himself. He
                        teaches to the bodhisattvas this very perfection of wisdom. [F.7.b] Then, in
                        that world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called Samantaraśmi saw this
                        great illumination, this great shaking of the earth, and the body of the
                        Lord you can never see enough, and he approached the lord Ratnākara, the
                        tathāgata, and inquired of the tathāgata Ratnākara, “What is the cause, O
                        Lord, what is the reason for this great illumination having manifested in
                        the world, and for this great shaking of the earth, and for the presence of
                        the body of the tathāgata you can never see enough?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-29"/>
                    <p tid="30"> The lord Ratnākara replied to the bodhisattva Samantaraśmi, “There
                        is, child of a good family, beyond as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River in the western direction a world system called
                        Sahā. There the tathāgata Śākyamuni now dwells and maintains himself, also
                        teaching the Dharma to the bodhisattvas. This sort of thing is his
                        power.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-30"/>
                    <p tid="31"> Then the bodhisattva Samantaraśmi said to the tathāgata Ratnākara,
                        “I will go to that Sahā world system to see, salute, and honor that
                        tathāgata Śākyamuni, and to see those bodhisattva great beings, for the most
                        part in the form of the young, who have acquired the dhāraṇīs and detailed
                        and thorough knowledges, and have acquired mastery over all the meditative
                        stabilizations and absorptions.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-31"/>
                    <p tid="32"> The Lord replied, “Go then, child of a good family, since you feel
                        that now is the right time.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-32"/>
                    <p tid="33"> Thereupon the tathāgata Ratnākara gave the bodhisattva Samantaraśmi
                        [F.8.a] a thousand lotuses made of manifold jewels, each with a thousand
                        petals shining like gold, saying, “These lotuses, child of a good family,
                        strew over the tathāgata Śākyamuni. Be on your best behavior<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-33"> I have based this translation
                            in part on Z 272 n. 253 and have rendered <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shes bzhin du spyod cig</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">samprajānacarī bhāveḥ</foreign>) “be
                            on your best behavior” instead of “be careful” (Z) or “act with full
                            self-possession” (LSPW) because in this Tib version the bodhisattva is
                            very polite without having first been instructed by his buddha. Z has a
                            good summary of the possible meanings. </note> in that buddhafield. And
                        why? Because the bodhisattvas born in that Sahā world system are difficult
                        to approach.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-34"/>
                    <p tid="34"> Thereupon the bodhisattva Samantaraśmi received from the tathāgata
                        Ratnākara the lotuses made of manifold jewels, each with a thousand petals
                        shining like gold. Surrounded by, and at the head of, many hundred thousand
                        one hundred million billion bodhisattvas, householders and renunciates,
                        young men and women, he disappeared together with them from that buddhafield
                        and, having respected, revered, honored, and worshiped as many lords as
                        there are dwelling and maintaining themselves in the east with flowers,
                        incense, perfumes, garlands, creams, powders, robes, parasols, flags, and
                        banners, arrived there in the Sahā world through that bodhisattva’s great
                        wonder-working and that bodhisattva’s great power. He approached the
                        tathāgata Śākyamuni, went up to him, bowed to the Lord’s feet with his head,
                        and stood to one side. The bodhisattva Samantaraśmi then addressed the Lord,
                        the tathāgata Śākyamuni: “The lord Ratnākara inquires about the Lord’s
                        health, hopes that the Lord is well and free from sickness, alert and
                        buoyant, eating well, strong, and comfortable. [F.8.b] The lord Ratnākara
                        has also dispatched these lotuses for the Lord.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-35"/>
                    <p tid="35"> The lord tathāgata Śākyamuni accepted the lotuses and threw them
                        back to the lord buddhas in as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River to the east. Those lotuses spread throughout
                        those world systems, and on them were seated buddha bodies. In those
                        buddhafields they taught Dharma—this very teaching of Dharma associated with
                        the perfection of wisdom. And the beings who heard that Dharma became
                        definite to reach unsurpassed, perfect, complete awakening. Thereupon those
                        bodhisattvas, the householders and renunciates, young men and women, each
                        one by virtue of his or her own wholesome roots respected, revered, honored,
                        and worshiped the lord Śākyamuni and sat down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-36"/>
                    <p tid="36"> Then in the south, beyond as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River, at the very limit of these world systems,
                        there is a world system called Sarvaśokāpagata. In it the tathāgata, worthy
                        one, perfectly complete buddha Aśokaśrī now dwells and maintains himself.
                        Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called Vigatāśoka
                            <distinct>and so on</distinct>. <distinct>Connect to the previous, at
                            length</distinct>, <distinct>up to</distinct> and sat down on one
                        side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-37"/>
                    <p tid="37"> Then in the west there is a world system called Upaśānta. In it the
                        tathāgata, worthy one, perfectly complete buddha Ratnārcis now dwells and
                        maintains himself. Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great being,
                        called Cāritramati <distinct>and so on, at length, up to</distinct> and sat
                        down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-38"/>
                    <p tid="38"> Then in the north [F.9.a] there is a world system called Jayā. In
                        it the tathāgata, worthy one, perfectly complete buddha Jayendra now dwells
                        and maintains himself. Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great
                        being, called Jayadatta <distinct>and so on, at length, up to</distinct> and
                        sat down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-39"/>
                    <p tid="39"> Then in the intermediate northeast direction there is a world
                        system called Samādhyalaṃkṛtā. In it the tathāgata, worthy one, perfectly
                        complete buddha Samādhihastyuttaraśrī now dwells and maintains himself.
                        Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called
                        Vijayavikrāmin <distinct>and so on, at length, up to</distinct> and sat down
                        on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-40"/>
                    <p tid="40"> Then in the intermediate southeast direction there is a world
                        system called Bodhimaṇḍalālaṃkārasurucitā. In it the tathāgata, worthy one,
                        perfectly complete buddha Padmottaraśrī now dwells and maintains himself.
                        Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called Padmahasta
                            <distinct>and so on, at length, up to</distinct> and sat down on one
                        side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-41"/>
                    <p tid="41"> Then in the intermediate southwest direction there is a world
                        system called Vigatarajasaṃcayā. In it the tathāgata, worthy one, perfectly
                        complete buddha Sūryamaṇḍalaprabhāsottaraśrī now dwells and maintains
                        himself. Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called
                        Sūryapratibhāsa <distinct>and so on, at length, up to</distinct> and sat
                        down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-42"/>
                    <p tid="42"> Then in the intermediate northwest direction there is a world
                        system called Vaśībhūtā. In it the tathāgata, worthy one, perfectly [F.9.b]
                        complete buddha Ekachattra now dwells and maintains himself. Then, in that
                        world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called Ratnottama <distinct>and
                            so on, at length, up to</distinct> and sat down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-43"/>
                    <p tid="43"> Then in the direction below there is a world system called Padmā.
                        In it the tathāgata, worthy one, perfectly complete buddha Padmaśrī now
                        dwells and maintains himself. Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a
                        great being, called Padmottama <distinct>and so on, at length, up
                            to</distinct> and sat down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-44"/>
                    <p tid="44"> Then in the direction above, beyond as many world systems as there
                        are sand particles in the Gaṅgā River, at the very limit of these world
                        systems, there is a world system called Nandā. In it the tathāgata, worthy
                        one, perfectly complete buddha Nandaśrī now dwells and maintains himself.
                        Then, in that world system a bodhisattva, a great being, called Nandadatta
                        saw this great illumination, this great shaking of the earth, and the body
                        of the Lord you can never see enough, and he approached the lord Nandaśrī,
                        the tathāgata, and inquired of the tathāgata Nandaśrī, “What is the cause, O
                        Lord, what is the reason for this great illumination being manifested in the
                        world, and for this great shaking of the earth, and for the presence of the
                        body of the tathāgata you can never see enough?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-45"/>
                    <p tid="45"> The lord Nandaśrī replied to the bodhisattva Nandadatta, “There is,
                        O child of a good family, beyond as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River in the direction below a world system called
                        Sahā. There the tathāgata arhat, perfectly [F.10.a] complete buddha
                        Śākyamuni now dwells and maintains himself, also teaching the Dharma to the
                        bodhisattvas. This sort of thing is his power.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-46"/>
                    <p tid="46"> Then the bodhisattva Nandadatta said to the tathāgata Nandaśrī, “I
                        will go to that Sahā world system to see, salute, and honor that tathāgata
                        Śākyamuni, and to see those bodhisattva great beings, for the most part in
                        the form of the young, who have acquired the dhāraṇīs and detailed and
                        thorough knowledges, and have acquired mastery over all the meditative
                        stabilizations and absorptions.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-47"/>
                    <p tid="47"> The Lord replied, “Go then, child of a good family, since you feel
                        that now is the right time.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-48"/>
                    <p tid="48"> Thereupon the tathāgata Nandaśrī gave the bodhisattva Nandadatta a
                        thousand lotuses made of manifold jewels, each with a thousand petals
                        shining like gold, saying, “These lotuses, child of a good family, strew
                        over the tathāgata Śākyamuni. Be on your best behavior in that buddhafield.
                        And why? Because the bodhisattvas born in that Sahā world system are
                        difficult to approach.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-49"/>
                    <p tid="49"> Thereupon the bodhisattva Nandadatta received from the tathāgata
                        Nandaśrī the lotuses made of manifold jewels, each with a thousand petals
                        shining like gold. Surrounded by, and at the head of many hundred thousand
                        one hundred million billion bodhisattvas, householders and renunciates,
                        young men and women, he disappeared together with them from that
                        buddhafield, and, having respected, revered, honored, and worshiped as many
                        lords as there are dwelling and maintaining themselves in the direction
                        above [F.10.b] with flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, creams, powders,
                        robes, parasols, flags, and banners, arrived there in the Sahā world through
                        that bodhisattva’s great wonder-working and that bodhisattva’s great power.
                        He approached the tathāgata Śākyamuni, went up to him, bowed to the Lord’s
                        feet with his head, and stood to one side. The bodhisattva Nandadatta then
                        addressed the lord, the tathāgata Śākyamuni: “The lord Nandaśrī inquires
                        about the Lord’s health, hopes that the Lord is well and free from sickness,
                        alert and buoyant, eating well, strong, and comfortable. The lord Nandaśrī
                        has also dispatched these lotuses for the Lord.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-50"/>
                    <p tid="50"> The lord tathāgata Śākyamuni accepted the lotuses and threw them
                        back to the lords, the buddhas in as many world systems as there are sand
                        particles in the Gaṅgā River in the direction above. Those lotuses spread
                        throughout those world systems, and on them were seated buddha bodies. In
                        those buddhafields they demonstrated Dharma—this very demonstration of
                        Dharma associated with the perfection of wisdom. And the beings who heard
                        that Dharma became irreversible from unsurpassed, perfect, complete
                        awakening. Thereupon those bodhisattvas, the householders and renunciates,
                        young men and women, each one by virtue of his or her own wholesome roots
                        respected, [F.11.a] revered, honored, and worshiped the lord Śākyamuni and
                        sat down on one side.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-51"/>
                    <p tid="51"> Thereupon, at that moment, minute, and second, the great
                        billionfold world system became constituted of jewels, filled with various
                        blossoms, hung with clusters of silk streamers, made fragrant with incense
                        pots, and beautified with wish-fulfilling trees whose stem-tips bend down
                        with ornaments and fruit, and with flower trees, fruit trees, fragrance
                        trees, flower-garland trees, and powder trees, just like Padmavatī, the
                        buddhafield of the tathāgata Samantakusuma where Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta lives,
                        as well as the god Susthitamati, and others who are magnificent bodhisattva
                        great beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-52"/>
                    <trailer tid="52">This was the first chapter, Introduction, of <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Wisdom in Eighteen Thousand
                            Lines</title>. </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-chapter-2">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="53">Chapter 2: Production of the Thought</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-53"/>
                    <p tid="54">[Chapter 2 and following chapters to be entered here. Please update
                        the heading of this chapter if it has changed in the polished version]</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="55">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-54"/>
                    <p tid="56">[Colophon to be entered here]</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="57">Notes</head>

            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="58">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-029-001-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="59">Main Section</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-029-001-55">[Insert Bibliography information here]</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>