<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas sgo’i le’u/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Chapter on the Complete Approach</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samantamukhaparivarta</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa kun nas sgo’i le’u zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Exposition on the Universal Gateway”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryasamantamukhaparivartanāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">Chinese Title</title>
                
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-72">Oriane Lavolé</author>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-256">Douglas Duckworth</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-307">Sylviane Tillemans</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-51">Dr. James Duncan Gentry</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-322">Stella Bonnie</editor>
                
                <consultant role="dharmaMaster" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.0 <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons
                            CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0
                            copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or
                            personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative
                            Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-040-005"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2020-04-29</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh54" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 54</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 40 (dkon brtsegs, kha), folios 184.b–195.a</biblScope>
                    <!--vol:40, ff.184v-195r(pp.368-389)-->
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="22">
                        <volume number="40" start-page="368" end-page="389"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11585" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-04-25T08:32:45.355Z" user="admin">25/04/2020 08:32:45</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-10-18T19:47:29.352Z" user="laura">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2019-10-18T19:47:29.352Z" user="laura">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-01-28T06:10:19.874Z" user="mike">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2020-03-16T14:07:54.966Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2020-04-24T12:46:44.903Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-04-25T08:32:43.585Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>In <title xml:lang="en">The Exposition on the Universal Gateway</title>, the bodhisattva Amalagarbha arrives in this world from a distant pure land to request teachings from the buddha Śākyamuni. The Buddha proceeds to explain to all assembled bodhisattvas, monks, and lay devotees the manner in which the five aggregates are equal to absorption. He also explains how the various classes of beings and all other phenomena are absorption as well. In conclusion, he lists the names of various absorptions and the benefits one obtains upon attaining these states.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. The translation was produced by Oriane Lavolé who also wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor compared the translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text.</p>
                <p>The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Exposition on the Universal Gateway</title> takes place at Vulture Peak Mountain where a celestial bodhisattva named Amalagarbha arrives with a large retinue to request teachings from the Buddha Śākyamuni. In response, the Buddha delivers a teaching that describes how all phenomena are forms of absorption. The Buddha first points out how each of the aggregates are absorption and then he proceeds to describe how all beings and phenomena are absorption as well. The reason why phenomena are absorption is their shared empty nature. Since emptiness is the intrinsic nature of absorption and all other phenomena, they are ultimately alike in this respect. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>Following this teaching, Mañjuśrī asks the Buddha to list the names of various absorptions for the benefit of the assembled bodhisattvas. In response, Śākyamuni mentions a number of absorptions as well as the spiritual accomplishments that they bring. Mañjuśrī rejoices in this teaching and makes aspiration prayers to benefit all those who hear this teaching. Suddenly, however, the demon Māra appears and laments this situation. He begs the Buddha not to bless the teaching he has just delivered, since that would result in Māra’s realm becoming empty. The Buddha surprisingly grants Māra this request and so the demon joyfully returns with his aims fulfilled. In answer to Mañjuśrī’s astonishment at this unexpected turn of events, the Buddha delivers a short teaching on the nondual nature of all phenomena, which delights the whole congregation and reassures everyone that everything is well, nevertheless. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>To our knowledge, a Sanskrit version of this sūtra no longer exists. However, an early Sanskrit prototype of the text appears to have circulated in the southern parts of Central Asia as an independent scripture, not yet part of the Heap of Jewels collection, as early as the mid-fifth century.<note place="end">Dhammadinnā 2013, 340.</note> Khotanese references to this sūtra from that time also seem to confirm its Sanskrit title, which is otherwise not attested elsewhere.<note place="end">Dhammadinnā 2013, 340.</note> </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>The sūtra was translated twice into Chinese. The first of the Chinese translations (T.315) was produced in 287 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> by the monk Dharmarakṣa (c. 233–310 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>).<note place="end"> Sen et al., 2011. </note> The second translation (T.310-10) was produced by the renowned South Indian translator Bodhiruci (?–727) between 706 and 713 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>.<note place="end">
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> Orzech et al., 2011.</hi>
                    </note> This is the version that was included in the Chinese collection of the Heap of Jewels.<note place="end"> Da baoji jing <title xml:lang="Input Language">大寶積經</title>, T.310. This text has also been translated into English by Chang (1983, 134–148).</note>
                </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>In Tibet, the text was translated together with the other scriptures in the Heap of Jewels collection. The Tibetan colophon lists the translators as the Indian scholars Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi, and the Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé, who were active translators in the late eighth and early ninth centuries.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                        <note place="end"> This dating is also confirmed by the text’s inclusion in the Denkarma inventory of the early ninth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce.</hi> See Denkarma, 295.b.7. See also Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, 22, no. 34.</note>
                    </hi> The sūtra appears to have had limited popularity in Tibet, as it is not quoted widely in commentarial treatises. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>This English translation was prepared based on the Tibetan translation found in the Degé Kangyur, in consultation with the Stok Palace manuscript and the Comparative Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        
    </text>
</TEI>