<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba rnam par gtan la dbab pa nye bar ’khor gyis zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">འདུལ་བ་རྣམ་པར་གཏན་ལ་དབབ་པ་ཉེ་བར་འཁོར་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya­viniścayopāli­paripṛcchā</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya: Upāli’s Questions</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’dul ba rnam par gtan la dbab pa nye bar ’khor gyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa
                    chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­vinaya­viniścayopāli­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་འདུལ་བ་རྣམ་པར་གཏན་ལ་དབབ་པ་ཉེ་བར་འཁོར་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “Determining the Vinaya: Upāli’s Questions”</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="en">Conquering All Beings</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can thams cad yang dag par 'joms pa</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-34">Translated by the UCSB Buddhist Studies Translation Group<lb/>under the
                    patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-201">Jake Nagasawa</author>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-261">Philippe Turenne</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-201">Jake Nagasawa</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-204">ErdeneBaatar Erdene-Ochir</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-205">Jaakko Takkinen</author>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-252">Dion Blundell</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-74">Ryan Damron</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-206">José I. Cabezón</consultant>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.3.1 <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s
                    words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial -
                            No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for
                            commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-043-005"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard
                    logic.</note>
                <date>2021-06-03</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh68" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 68</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 115.a–131.a</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="33">
                        <volume number="43" start-page="229" end-page="261"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11604" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2023-06-04T16:30:27.461Z" user="admin">04/06/2023 16:30:27</note>

                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-11-06T13:11:59.611Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2019-11-06T13:11:59.611Z" user="andreas">2.g</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.h" date-time="2020-01-27T12:59:05.322Z" user="mike">2.h</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2020-03-24T14:18:09.067Z" user="line-tofte">2.g</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2020-07-30T10:21:53.713Z" user="line-tofte">2.f</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.1" date-time="2020-10-13T14:24:58.104Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.2" date-time="2020-10-13T14:31:08.167Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-10-13T14:31:54.369Z" user="line-tofte">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.3" date-time="2020-10-13T14:31:54.369Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2020-10-13T14:32:57.358Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-11-10T08:28:49.637Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.5" date-time="2020-11-10T08:28:49.637Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2021-01-28T15:30:16.446Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.6" date-time="2021-01-28T15:30:16.446Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.7" date-time="2021-02-26T20:26:41.862Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2021-02-26T20:27:21.31Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.8" date-time="2021-02-26T20:27:21.31Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>

                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2021-03-12T10:25:23.894Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2021-03-12T10:25:23.894Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2021-03-16T13:35:15.302Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2021-04-20T13:45:48.136Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.5" date-time="2021-05-28T12:43:24.752Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
            
    <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2021-06-03T16:21:50.715Z" user="mike">1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2021-06-03T16:21:50.715Z" user="mike">First Published Version</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.1" date-time="2021-07-01T21:35:44.116Z" user="konchog">Fixed one typo at 1.66</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.2" date-time="2021-07-02T14:58:25.205Z" user="konchog">Fixed two more typos.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.0" date-time="2021-10-25T19:35:04.278Z" user="john">1.1.0</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.1" date-time="2021-11-05T13:27:23.346Z" user="andre">Added short definitions to the 35 buddhas and bodhisattvas</note>

    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.1" date-time="2021-12-21T20:21:06.482Z" user="john">Added mention of Ten and Five Royal Sūtras, disambiguation from Upali's Questions in Toh 7/7a, edited and added Chinese titles, added titles and Tohs of Tengyur commentaries etc. cited.</note>

    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.2" date-time="2021-12-27T11:19:45.334Z" user="john">corrected typo</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.3" date-time="2022-06-24T21:12:26.282Z" user="laura">Typo in glossary (dDar chag)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.4" date-time="2022-07-10T18:25:08.22Z" user="john">Harmonization of trailer and colophon</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.5" date-time="2023-01-16T16:58:52.361Z" user="celso">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.6" date-time="2023-01-18T16:58:06.914Z" user="celso">Auto (remove-tid-from-back-list-items)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.7" date-time="2023-03-21T18:01:32.218Z" user="john">Typo fixed, line break spaces added in intro.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.8" date-time="2023-03-24T05:04:30.734Z" user="martina-cotter">edited milestone.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.2.9" date-time="2023-03-24T05:08:59.148Z" user="martina-cotter">undid previous change.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.3.1" date-time="2023-06-04T16:30:24.593Z" user="john">Changed title throughout.</note>
</notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-1"/>
                <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya: Upāli’s Questions</title> is a sūtra focused on the relationship between and
                    integration of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātimokṣa</foreign> vows of monastic discipline and the conduct of a
                    bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna tradition. The sūtra’s two main interlocutors, Śāriputra and Upāli, query the Buddha about
                    the relationship between these two levels of commitments, eliciting a teaching on the different orientations held by the followers
                    of different Buddhist vehicles and how their different views affect the application of their vows. <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> is a particularly valuable sūtra for its inclusion of a unique form of the confessional
                    “Three Sections” rite, making it one of the few extant canonical sources to describe it at length. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated, edited, and introduced by ErdeneBaatar Erdene-Ochir, Jake Nagasawa, and Jaakko Takkinen, members of the UCSB
                    Buddhist Studies Translation Group. The group wishes to thank José I. Cabezón for his support and guidance.</p>
                <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="6">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-introduction-1">
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya: Upāli’s Questions</title> (hereafter <title xml:lang="en">Determining
                            the Vinaya</title>) is a sūtra from the Heap of Jewels (Skt. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>; Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon brtsegs</title>) section of the Kangyur that explores the relationship between the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātimokṣa</foreign> vows and the conduct of a bodhisattva. The sūtra can be loosely divided
                        into two parts: a first section for which the monk Śāriputra is the main interlocutor, and which contains the pledge by
                        numerous bodhisattvas to work for the benefit of beings, followed by a general discourse by the Buddha on the conduct of a
                        bodhisattva. In the second section, the titular Upāli poses a series of questions that prompt a more in-depth discourse from
                        the Buddha on the relationship between monastic codes of conduct and the commitments of a bodhisattva, with a focus on the
                        views that guide the followers of the śrāvaka, pratyekabuddha, and bodhisattva vehicles.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-4"/>
                    <p tid="8">The sūtra opens in the north Indian city of Śrāvastī, where the Buddha resides among a vast assembly of monks and
                        bodhisattvas in Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park at Prince Jeta’s Grove. Addressing the bodhisattvas in the assembly, the Buddha asks who
                        will uphold the Dharma and bring beings to maturity in future times. A number of the bodhisattvas present in the assembly
                        voice their <term type="ignore">desire</term> to uphold various aspects of the Dharma or to help beings through specific
                        powers. At Śāriputra’s prompting, the Buddha next describes the special means that bodhisattvas utilize to bring beings to
                        spiritual maturity, and how the three poisons—desire, anger, and delusion—are to be understood in the context of bodhisattva
                        conduct. It is at this point that the Buddha teaches a special method for confessing misdeeds: the “Three Sections” rite,
                        which will be discussed below. He offers this rite of confession as a potent means for bodhisattvas to purify their faults and
                        attain samādhi. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-5"/>
                    <p tid="9">Following this, the eponymous Upāli emerges from meditative seclusion and joins the assembly to address questions to
                        the Buddha about the relationship between the prātimokṣa vows as they are observed by śrāvakas and pratyekabuddhas, and the
                        conduct of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna. Upāli is a famous figure in Buddhist literature and is regarded as foremost
                        among the Buddha’s disciples in upholding the monastic discipline detailed in the Vinaya. Such was Upāli’s mastery of the
                        Vinaya that he was selected to recite the Vinaya at the first full assembly of the saṅgha after the Buddha’s passing. As a
                        recurring figure in Pāli literature, Upāli is more generally linked to the rules of monastic conduct of non-Mahāyāna Buddhism;
                        here, however, Upāli’s questions primarily concern the observation of monastic discipline in the context of a bodhisattva’s
                        conduct according to the Mahāyāna tradition. Upāli’s close connection to the Vinaya and the code of monastic conduct thus make
                        him a particularly potent interlocutor in exploring the relationship between these two overlapping but seemingly contradictory
                        modes of Buddhist conduct.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-493">“Upāli’s Questions” (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upāli­paripṛcchā</title>)
                            as part of the title of this text should not be confused with the “Upāli’s Questions” that form part of the purely
                            Mūla­sarvāsti­vāda vinaya compendium, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayottara­grantha</title> (Toh 7 and 7A)
                        in the Discipline (Vinaya) section of the Kangyur.</note> </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-6"/>
                    <p tid="10">At Upāli’s prompting, the Buddha clarifies the relationship between these two modes of conduct. He explains that the
                        training of a śrāvaka and that of a bodhisattva are both aimed at the highest goal, but their respective practices are
                        essentially different. For bodhisattvas, the training of śrāvakas and pratyekabuddhas is limiting because they do not engage
                        with other beings, and they seek a quick exit from saṃsāra instead of returning life after life to continue helping beings.
                        Moreover, the core of the bodhisattva’s training is the mind of awakening (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhicitta</foreign>), an aspiration that guides a bodhisattva’s conduct and that, if violated, can easily be mended by
                        again turning the mind toward awakening. A follower of the Śrāvakayāna, on the other hand, is bound by vows, especially
                        serious ones, that once broken cannot be easily repaired. The relationship between these two modes of conduct is further
                        clarified by a question posed by the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī: If phenomena themselves are already “inherently tamed,” i.e., if
                        there is nothing inherent in phenomena that causes affliction within beings, then what is the purpose of the rules of monastic
                        discipline? The Buddha responds by saying that if beings already knew this, then the Tathāgata would not have to continually
                        explain the rules of monastic discipline; the rules, therefore, are provisional, and meant to help beings gradually understand
                        that all phenomena are innately disciplined.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-7"/>
                    <p tid="11">As part of its focus on the conduct of a bodhisattva, <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> includes a
                        version of the “Three Sections” rite, a confessional practice for mending breaches of a bodhisattva’s discipline. This sūtra,
                        along with the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ugra­paripṛcchā Sūtra</title> (Toh 63),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-8"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ugraparipṛcchā</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh63.html"/>, another sūtra from the Heap of Jewels 
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>) section of the Kangyur,
                            has been extensively studied and translated from Chinese and Tibetan in Nattier 2003.</note> serves as one of the
                        principal canonical sources for the rite, but the rite presented here 
                        (<ptr target="#UT22084-043-005-94"/>–<ptr target="#UT22084-043-005-111"/>) is distinctive for the set of thirty-five buddhas before
                        which bodhisattvas are directed to make their confession. That the “Three Sections” became an important practice in Indian
                        Buddhism is attested by the fact that it is referenced in Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-9"> See
                            Barnes 2012.</note> and was commented on by Nāgārjuna in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyāpatti­deśanāvṛtti</title>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4005.html"/>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-10">
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyāpatti­deśanāvṛtti</title> (“A Running Commentary on the Confession of Transgressions 
                                of Bodhisattvas”), Toh 4005 in the Degé Tengyur. Both the confession liturgy 
                                and Nāgārjuna’s commentary have been translated in Beresford 1980.</note> Nāgārjuna mentions details of the occasions and setting 
                        (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nidāna</foreign>) for the Buddha’s teaching the “Three Sections” that, he says, are not found in the 
                        Ratnakūṭa version of the text, suggesting that a separate version may have circulated in India. The
                        Indian Buddhist master Kṛṣṇa composed a liturgical text (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sādhana</foreign>), the
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Skandha­tri­sādhana</title>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4008.html"/>,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-482">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Skandha­tri­sādhana</title> (“A Sādhana of the Three Heaps”), Toh 4008 in the Degé Tengyur.</note> that explains a full procedure for the confession ritual.
                        Kṛṣṇa’s text and the rite it describes were deemed important by the Bengali master Atiśa Dīpaṅkaraśrījñāna (982–c. 1055 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>), who worked with Tibetan translators to make it available to a Tibetan audience. Another commentary was written by the tenth century 
                        Indian master Jitāri.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-483">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyāpatti­deśanā­vṛtti­bodhi­sattva­śikṣā­krama</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4008.html"/> 
                            (“A Running Commentary on the Confession of Transgressions of Bodhisattvas According to Bodhisattva Precepts”), 
                            Toh 4006 in the Degé Tengyur.</note>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-11"/>
                    <p tid="197">There are several extant Sanskrit witnesses for portions of this sūtra: a lengthy citation drawn from the sūtra’s 
                        second section is preserved in the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa Sūtra</title>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>, 
                        which was studied and reproduced by Nalinaksha Dutt in 1931,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-14"> Dutt 1931, 278–85.</note> and 
                        verses from <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> are cited by Śāntideva in his 
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> 
                        and by Candrakīrti in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-15"> For the 
                            Sanskrit text of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śīkṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>
                            see Bendall 1902, and for the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/> see La Vallée Poussin 1903. The verses from <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> 
                            recorded in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śīkṣāsamuccaya</title> have
                            been studied, edited, and translated in Lang 2001. </note> The Pāli Canon contains a text called 
                        <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Upāliparipucchāsutta</title>, which has been studied by Valentina Stache-Rosen in comparison to a Chinese version, but it
                        does not appear to be the same text translated here.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-16"> See Stache-Rosen 1984 and
                            Matsumura 1990.</note> Chinese translations of the whole or part of the text can be found in the Chinese Buddhist Canon
                        (Taishō 310, 325, and 326<!--, and 1466-->).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-484">
                            Taishō 310: in the 大寶積經 (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāratnakūṭasūtra</title>), sūtra 24, 優波離會 (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Youboli hui</title>), translated by Bodhiruci (eighth century).
                            Taishō 325: 決定毘尼經 (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Jueding pini jing</title>), translated by an unknown translator in Dunhuang in the Western Jin (third to fifth century). 
                            Taishō 326: 三十五佛名禮懺文 (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Sanshi wu fo ming li chan wen</title>), translated by Amoghavajra in the Tang (eighth century).</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-479"/>
                    <p tid="198">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> was translated into Tibetan during Tibet’s imperial period by the
                        Tibetan translator and monk Yeshé Dé, with the assistance of the Indian masters Jinamitra, Prajñāvarman, and Surendrabodhi.
                        This is evidenced not only by the colophon of the text, but also by its mention in the two extant imperial-period catalogs,
                        the Denkarma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-12">
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ldan kar ma</title>, Herrmann-Pfandt 2009, text no. 48; Toh 4364<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html"/>.</note> and Phangthangma catalogs.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-13">
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>, Kawagoe 2005, text no. 28.</note> According to the fourteenth-century 
                        Tibetan <title xml:lang="en">Chronicles of Padma</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">padma bka’
                            thang</title>), the “Three Sections” part of the text (see <ptr target="#UT22084-043-005-7"/> above) was included among
                        the “Ten Royal Sūtras” (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo bcu</title>), the recitation of which was prescribed by Padmasambhava to
                        the Tibetan king Trisong Detsen (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khri srong lde
                            bstan</foreign>, 755–97 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>) to prolong his life. It is also traditionally placed in 
                        a subset, the “Five Royal Sūtras.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-478">In the 
                            list of “Ten Royal Sūtras,” this text is designated as having the function of purification of karmic obscurations 
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub ltung bshags las sgrib dag pa’i mdo</foreign>). For the “Five Royal Sūtras,” there 
                            are several different explanations. One holds that each concisely summarize one of the five great sūtra collections 
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’bum sde lnga</foreign>). Among these, this text is said to represent the 
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra­sūtra</title> (Toh 107), 
                            corresponding to activity (out of body, speech, mind, qualities, and activity). According to another explanation, each is simply 
                            “royal” or sovereign in its category, which in this case is that of confessions 
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bshags pa</foreign>). See “bsdu sgrigs gsal bshad,” in Khomthar Jamlö 2014, vol. 1, pp. 2–4.</note> </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-481"/>
                    <p tid="199">A French translation of <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> was made by Pierre Python (1973) 
                        based on the available Sanskrit,
                        Tibetan, and Chinese versions. Garma C. C. Chang translated the Chinese version into English in <title xml:lang="en">A
                            Treasury of Mahāyāna Sūtras: Selections from the Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title> (1983). </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-17"/>
                    <p tid="13">This English translation was prepared based on the Tibetan translation in the Degé Kangyur in consultation with the
                        Pedurma comparative edition (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) and the version of the
                        translation recorded in the Stok Palace Kangyur. We also consulted the Sanskrit fragments listed above, along with Python’s
                        French translation and the Mongolian canonical translation.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="14"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="15">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="16">Determining the Vinaya: Upāli’s Questions</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-section-1">
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-18"/>
                    <p tid="17">
                        <ref cRef="B1" type="bampo"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.115.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-427"/> Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-19"/>
                    <p tid="18">Thus did I hear at one time: The Bhagavān was dwelling in Śrāvastī, at Anāthapiṇḍada’s park in Prince Jeta’s Grove,
                        together with a great monastic assembly of about five hundred monks as well as a thousand bodhisattvas. The Bhagavān looked
                        upon those bodhisattva mahāsattvas with a gaze like an elephant’s and said to them, “Sons of noble birth, for the sake of
                        upholding the holy Dharma in the future, in later times, who among you wishes to take up the unsurpassed, completely perfect
                        awakening that took the Tathāgata countless myriads of eons to accomplish? Who among you, for the sake of bringing beings to
                        maturity, wishes to nurture them by means of various methods, ways, and ideas?” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-20"/>
                    <p tid="19">Then the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya arose from his seat, adjusted his upper robe on one shoulder, knelt on his
                        right knee, bowed to the Bhagavān with his palms joined in devotion, and said, “Bhagavān, for the sake of upholding the holy
                        Dharma in the future, in later times, I wish to take up the unsurpassed, completely perfect awakening that took the Tathāgata
                        countless myriads of eons to accomplish.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-21"/>
                    <p tid="20">The bodhisattva Siṃha said, “Bhagavān, I wish to nurture beings using various methods, ways, and ideas.” <ref cRef="F.115.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-428"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="21">The bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi said, “Bhagavān, I wish to release beings from going to the lower realms.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-23"/>
                    <p tid="22">The bodhisattva Youthful Mañjuśrī said, “Bhagavān, I wish to fulfill the individual aspirations of beings.” </p>
                    <p tid="23">The bodhisattva Jñānaketu said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring untold numbers of beings to maturity.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-25"/>
                    <p tid="24">The bodhisattva Dharmaketu said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity through the gift of Dharma.”</p>
                    <p tid="25">The bodhisattva Candraketu said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by means of good qualities.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-27"/>
                    <p tid="26">The bodhisattva Sūryaketu said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by means of the easy vehicle.”</p>
                    <p tid="27">The bodhisattva Niḥśaṅka said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring the limitless realms of beings to maturity and to support
                        them.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-29"/>
                    <p tid="28">The bodhisattva Bhadrapāla said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by proclaiming the names they are to
                        attain as result.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-30"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ming ’bras bu
                                mchis pa</foreign>. This translation is conjectural and is informed by the act of bestowing names upon newly awakened
                            beings. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="29">The bodhisattva Akṣayamati said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate inexhaustible realms of beings through extensive
                        aspirations.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-32"/>
                    <p tid="30">The bodhisattva Youthful Candraprabha said, “Bhagavān, I wish to supply beings with all the requisites of happiness.”
                            <ref cRef="F.116.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-429"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="31">The bodhisattva Sunetra said, “Bhagavān, I wish to establish the foundation for the happiness and contentment of
                        beings.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-34"/>
                    <p tid="32">The bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara said, “Bhagavān, I wish to protect beings from lower realms and bad rebirths.”</p>
                    <p tid="33">The bodhisattva Mahā­sthāma­prāpta said, “Bhagavān, I wish to save beings who have not escaped from the lower
                        realms.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-36"/>
                    <p tid="34">The bodhisattva Rāśika said, “Bhagavān, I wish to teach undisciplined beings the way of discipline.”</p>
                    <p tid="35">The bodhisattva Sumanas said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings with inferior inclinations to maturity.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-38"/>
                    <p tid="36">The bodhisattva Sūrata said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings with inferior wisdom to maturity.”</p>
                    <p tid="37">The bodhisattva Tejorāśi said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings who have been born from the wombs of animals to
                        maturity.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-40"/>
                    <p tid="38">The bodhisattva Recognizer of Unafflicted Realization said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by correctly
                        teaching them the way.”</p>
                    <p tid="39">The bodhisattva Priya­darśana said, “Bhagavān, I wish to equip beings with the immeasurable requisites of happiness.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-42"/>
                    <p tid="40">The bodhisattva Excellent Faculties said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by causing them to reflect on
                        suffering.”</p>
                    <p tid="41">The bodhisattva Engaged in Inconceivable Liberation said, “Bhagavān, with merely a thought I wish to liberate beings
                        born in the world of pretas.” <ref cRef="F.116.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-430"/>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-44"/>
                    <p tid="42">The bodhisattva Sūryaprabha said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring to maturity those beings who are not yet mature.” </p>
                    <p tid="43">The bodhisattva Vimalakīrti said, “Bhagavān, I wish to fulfill every intention beings have.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-46"/>
                    <p tid="44">The bodhisattva Tejobala said, “Bhagavān, I wish to destroy the way beings take unfortunate rebirths.”</p>
                    <p tid="45">The bodhisattva Vimatiprahāṇa said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate inferior beings.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-48"/>
                    <p tid="46">The bodhisattva Niḥśaṅka­sthāna said, “Bhagavān, for the sake of gathering beings I wish to express encouragement by
                        saying ‘Wonderful!’ ”</p>
                    <p tid="47">The bodhisattva Jñānaśrī said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity according to their varying
                        predispositions.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-50"/>
                    <p tid="48">The bodhisattva Boundless Stillness said, “Bhagavān, I wish to teach beings the way of the unconditioned.”</p>
                    <p tid="49">The bodhisattva Fearless toward All Phenomena said, “Bhagavān, I wish to teach beings according to their own
                        predisposition.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-52"/>
                    <p tid="50">The bodhisattva Ratnaśrī said, “Bhagavān, I wish to display a heap of jewels to beings.”</p>
                    <p tid="51">The bodhisattva Sumati said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by showing them a beautiful form.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-54"/>
                    <p tid="52">The bodhisattva Vimalatejas said, <ref cRef="F.117.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-431"/> “Bhagavān, I wish to
                        support and bring beings to maturity through affection.” </p>
                    <p tid="53">The bodhisattva Maṇibhadra said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by causing them to remember their past
                        births.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-56"/>
                    <p tid="54">The bodhisattva Puṇyaraśmi said, “Bhagavān, I wish to guide beings by means of perfect aspiration prayers.” </p>
                    <p tid="55">The bodhisattva <term>Bhadraśrī</term> said, “Bhagavān, I wish to permanently liberate beings from suffering.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-58"/>
                    <p tid="56">The bodhisattva Ratnapāṇi said, “Bhagavān, I wish to make beings happy with jewels.”</p>
                    <p tid="57">The bodhisattva Mati said, “Bhagavān, I wish to end the poverty of poor beings.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-60"/>
                    <p tid="58">The bodhisattva Sarva­nīvaraṇa­viṣkambhin said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate beings from all the afflictions.” </p>
                    <p tid="59">The bodhisattva Vajra Light said, “Bhagavān, I wish to teach beings the exalted way.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-62"/>
                    <p tid="60">The bodhisattva Manifesting the Appearance of Good Qualities said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate beings by causing all
                        their thoughts to be joyful.”</p>
                    <p tid="61">The bodhisattva Exalted Dharma said, “Bhagavān, I wish to show the pure eye of Dharma to beings.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-64"/>
                    <p tid="62">The bodhisattva Vajragarbha said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate beings from the obscurations. <ref cRef="F.117.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-432"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="63">The bodhisattva Dharmākara said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate beings through the Dharma.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-66"/>
                    <p tid="64">The bodhisattva <term>Nothing</term> said, “Bhagavān, I wish to eliminate all the poisonous afflictions of beings.” </p>
                    <p tid="65">The bodhisattva Candrottara said, “Bhagavān, I wish to teach the perspective of the Dharma to beings.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-68"/>
                    <p tid="66">The bodhisattva Siṃhamati said, “Bhagavān, I wish to give the gift of Dharma to beings.” </p>
                    <p tid="67">The bodhisattva Luminous Youth said, “Bhagavān, I wish to liberate beings from inferior states.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-70"/>
                    <p tid="68">The bodhisattva Glorious Awakening said, “Bhagavān, I wish to block beings’ way to lower rebirths by teaching them the
                        exalted way.”</p>
                    <p tid="69">The bodhisattva Suvarṇa­prabha said, “Bhagavān, I wish to bring beings to maturity by displaying a physical body.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-72"/>
                    <p tid="70">The bodhisattva Puṇyaketu said, “Bhagavān, I wish to help those beings who help others.”</p>
                    <p tid="71">The bodhisattva Jagatīndhara said, “Bhagavān, I wish to destroy beings’ gateway into hell.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-74"/>
                    <p tid="72">The bodhisattva Nectar Holder said, “Bhagavān, I wish to save beings from saṃsāra.” </p>
                    <p tid="73">The youthful bodhisattva Jālinīprabha said, “Bhagavān, in the future, in later times, I wish to pacify beings’
                        afflictions through displays of light.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-76"/>
                    <p tid="74">After hearing such revelations from the bodhisattvas about <ref cRef="F.118.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-433"/> donning the armor that will mature beings, the venerable Śāriputra was seized with wonder
                        and amazement. He said to the Bhagavān, “Ah! Bhagavān, the great compassion possessed by these bodhisattva mahāsattvas is
                        amazing, as is their inconceivable skill in means and their donning of the great armor of stable diligence. It is amazing how
                        these bodhisattvas cannot be overcome by any being, how difficult they are to fathom, to meet with, or to subjugate, and how
                        their brilliance cannot be overcome. Furthermore, Bhagavān, when supplicants come before these bodhisattva mahāsattvas, whose
                        brilliance cannot be overcome, and beg for their heads, hands, feet, and eyes—even when they beg for everything—these
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas do not recoil or become discouraged but rather are overjoyed. This is amazing to me. Bhagavān, I also
                        think that any beings who harm bodhisattva mahāsattvas and then ask for their various inner and outer constituents will surely
                        become bodhisattva mahāsattvas who rest in inconceivable liberation.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-77"/>
                    <p tid="75">The Bhagavān replied to the venerable Śāriputra, “So it is, Śāriputra, so it is! Such is the scope of these
                        bodhisattvas’ samādhi, methods, wisdom, and gnosis. Śāriputra, the scope of these bodhisattvas is not that of śrāvakas or
                        pratyekabuddhas. Śāriputra, bodhisattva mahāsattvas, in order to meet the inclinations of beings, manifest all the emanations
                        of the buddhas, but while doing so they do not waver from their bodhisattva nature. <ref cRef="F.118.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-434"/>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-78"/>
                    <p tid="76">“Śāriputra, bodhisattva mahāsattvas will manifest the bodies of householders in order to dispel the delusions of
                        grandeur held by householders who are intoxicated with arrogance. In order to remove the manic arrogance of beings who are
                        inflated and intoxicated by mania, they display the power of a champion,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-79"> Tib.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshan po che chen po</foreign>; Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">mahānagna</foreign>. This enigmatic term seems to refer to someone with athletic strength and prowess or a seasoned
                            fighter. </note> or the exuberant power of Nārāyaṇa. They reveal the various paths to nirvāṇa for those beings who seek
                        nirvāṇa. They display the form of śrāvakas to those beings oriented to the Śrāvakayāna and use the Śrāvakayāna to bring them
                        to complete nirvāṇa. They display the form of pratyekabuddhas to beings oriented to the Pratyekabuddhayāna so that they can
                        direct them toward dependent arising. They display the forms of buddhas to those beings who seek awakening so that they may
                        attain all the qualities of a buddha.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-80"/>
                    <p tid="77">“Śāriputra, in this way, once bodhisattva mahāsattvas have matured the realm of beings using a variety of methods,
                        they set beings firmly in the qualities of buddhahood. Why? Śāriputra, beings will find no liberation apart from the
                        liberation of final nirvāṇa, the gnosis of the tathāgatas. This is why they are called <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct>. Why?
                        They are called <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct> because tathāgatas know the nature of reality just as it is. They are called
                            <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct> because they use various concepts to induce understanding in beings. <ref cRef="F.119.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-435"/> They are called <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct> because they possess all
                        virtuous qualities and have abandoned all nonvirtuous qualities. They are called <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct> because they
                        demonstrate liberation to beings who are in bondage. They are called <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct> because they reveal the
                        exalted path to beings who have embarked on an evil path. They are called <distinct>tathāgatas</distinct> because they teach
                        emptiness and arise from emptiness.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-81"/>
                    <p tid="78"> “Śāriputra, bodhisattva mahāsattvas demonstrate liberation to ordinary, deluded, childish beings by using various
                        forms of knowledge that align with their inclinations and thus bring them to an understanding of the true Dharma. And yet,
                        they never waver from their bodhisattva nature. They display various types of illusion in order cause beings to progressively
                        reach the seat of awakening.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-82"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Furthermore, Śāriputra, lay householder bodhisattva mahāsattvas should practice two types of giving: giving the
                        Dharma and giving material goods. Śāriputra, lay householder bodhisattva mahāsattvas should practice these two types of giving
                        without attachment or anger. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-83"/>
                    <p tid="80">“Śāriputra, renunciant bodhisattva mahāsattvas should engage in four types of giving:<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-84"> The Lhasa, Narthang, and Stok Palace versions of the translation read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sbyin pa chen po bzhi</foreign>, “the four types of great giving.”</note> giving pens,
                        giving ink, giving books, and giving the Dharma. Śāriputra, renunciant bodhisattva mahāsattvas should practice these four
                        types of giving. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-85"/>
                    <p tid="81">“Śāriputra, bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have accepted that phenomena are unproduced should practice three types of
                        relinquishment: <ref cRef="F.119.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-436"/> relinquishment, great relinquishment, and the
                        highest relinquishment. With respect to these, “relinquishment” means to give away the kingdom; “great relinquishment” is to
                        give away one’s wives, sons, and daughters; and the “greatest relinquishment” is to give away one’s own head, hands, feet,
                        eyes, skin, bones, and marrow. Śāriputra, a bodhisattva mahāsattva who has accepted that phenomena are unproduced should
                        practice these three types of relinquishment.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-86"/>
                    <p tid="82">Śāriputra asked, “Bhagavān, are bodhisattvas not afraid of desire? Are they not afraid of anger and delusion?”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-87"/>
                    <p tid="83">The Bhagavān replied,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-88"> The following passage, with some variants and
                            omissions, is cited by Śāntideva in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>. See Bendall’s edition (1902), 168–71. </note> “Śāriputra,
                        the faults associated with the great misdeeds of bodhisattvas are twofold: those related to anger and those related to
                        delusion. Śāriputra, these are the two faults associated with the great misdeeds of bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-89"/>
                    <p tid="84">“Śāriputra,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-90"> This paragraph is not included in the citation recorded in
                            the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>. </note> among these, desire is a minor misdeed and is given
                        up slowly. Anger is a major misdeed and is given up quickly. Delusion is a major misdeed and is given up slowly. Why is this?
                        Śāriputra, desire is the ensnaring vine of saṃsāra and thus the seed of rebirth. Anger is eliminated quickly and is the cause
                        of unfortunate rebirths. Delusion is difficult to relinquish and is the cause of falling into the eight great hells.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-91"/>
                    <p tid="85">“Regarding these, Śāriputra, a bodhisattva should openly confess the weightiest of faults to an assembly of ten.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-92"> Given the sequence that follows, the “weightiest fault” or “primary fault” (Skt.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prathamāpatti</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nyes pa
                                dang po’i lci ba</foreign>) perhaps refers to sexual intercourse on the part of a renunciant bodhisattva.</note> A
                        weighty fault of the hand—that is, grasping a woman’s hand—should be confessed to an assembly of five. <ref cRef="F.120.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-437"/> The fault of looking at a woman with ill intent should be confessed before one
                        or two people.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-93"> The Skt. passage cited in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> reads, “The heavy
                            fault of the hand should be confessed to an assembly of five. Holding a woman’s hand or looking at her—the weighty fault
                            of ill intent (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">duṣṭa­cittāpatti</foreign>)—should, Śāriputra, be confessed before
                            one or two people.”</note> A bodhisattva should confess the faults associated with the five grave acts of immediate
                        retribution, faults related to women, faults related to boys, faults related to the hand, faults related to stūpas, faults
                        related to the saṅgha, or any other weighty fault before the thirty-five bhagavān buddhas, doing so on their own throughout
                        the day and night. The confession is as follows:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-94"/>
                    <lg tid="187">
                        <l>“ ‘I (name) seek refuge in the Buddha,</l> 
                        <l>I seek refuge in the Dharma,</l> 
                        <l>I seek refuge in the Saṅgha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-470"/>
                    <lg tid="188">
                        <l>“ ‘I pay homage to the tathāgata, the arhat, the completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni!</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Vajra­garbha­pramardin.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-95"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rdo rje’i snying pos rab tu ’joms pa</foreign>.
                            In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> this name is given as Vajrapramardin. </note> </l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Ratnārcis.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Nāgeśvara­rāja.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Vīrasena.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Vīranandin.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Ratnāgni.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-96"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rin chen
                            me</foreign>. In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> this name is given as <term type="ignore">Ratnaśrī</term>.</note>
                        </l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Ratna­candra­prabha.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Amoghadarśin.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Ratnacandra.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Vimala.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-97"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dri ma med
                                pa</foreign>. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> lists two names here: Nirmala and Vimala.</note>
                        </l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Śūradatta.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to <term>Brahmā</term>.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Brahma­datta.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Varuṇa.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Varuṇadeva.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Bhadraśrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Candanaśrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Anantaujas.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Prabhāsa­śrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Aśokaśrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to <term>Nārāyaṇa</term>.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Kusumaśrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to the Tathāgata Brahma­jyotir­vikrīḍitābhijña.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to the Tathāgata Padma­jyotir­vikrīḍitābhijña.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-98"> This name does not
                            appear in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>.</note>
                            <ref cRef="F.120.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-438"/> </l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Dhanaśrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Smṛtiśrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Suparikīrtita­nāmadheya­śrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Indra­ketu­dhvaja­rāja.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Suvikrānta­śrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Suvijita­saṃgrāma.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-99"> In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> this name is
                            replaced with Vicitra­saṃkrama. The names are orthographically similar, so the difference is likely the result of a
                            variant or scribal error in the Skt. manuscript. </note> </l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Vikrānta­gāmin.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Samantāvabhāsa­vyūha­śrī.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to Ratna­padma­vikrāmin.</l> 
                        <l>I pay homage to the tathāgata, the arhat, the completely perfect Buddha Ratna­padma­supratiṣṭhita­śailendra­rāja.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-100"/>
                    <p tid="87">“ ‘To them, and to all the other tathāgata, arhat, and completely perfect buddhas who dwell, live, and endure in all realms
                        throughout the ten directions—to those blessed buddhas, I pray, please pay heed to me!</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-101"/>
                    <p tid="189">“ ‘In this and in all the other births that I have taken in saṃsāra without beginning or end, I have committed evil
                        actions, I have asked others to commit them, or have rejoiced when they were committed.</p> 
                    <p tid="190">“ ‘I have stolen the property of
                            stūpas,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-102"> John Strong notes that stūpas containing relics were venerated as
                            if they were the Buddha himself. If built near or in a monastery, the stūpa was treated as a legal resident of that
                            monastery and was considered to have personal ownership of the land it was built on; thus, destroying a stūpa was
                            tantamount to murder. See Strong 2004, 3–4.</note> the property of the saṅgha, or the property of the saṅghas of the four
                            directions,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-103"> “The saṅghas of the four directions” is not found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>
                                citation. </note> have made others steal them, or have rejoiced when they were stolen.</p> 
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-471"/>
                    <p tid="191">“ ‘I have committed the five grave
                        acts of immediate retribution, have made others commit them, or have rejoiced when they were committed.</p> 
                    <p tid="192">“ ‘I have taken the path
                        of the ten nonvirtuous actions, have made others take it, or have rejoiced in their taking it.</p> 
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-472"/>
                    <p tid="193">“ ‘Having been affected by karmic
                        obscurations, I will go to the hells,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-104"> For more on the complex conceptions of hells
                            in Buddhist cosmography, see the entry for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nāraka</foreign> in the <title xml:lang="en">Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism</title>, 575.</note> I will go to the animal realm,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-105"> Here the passage in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title> includes the
                            additional line “I will go to the realm of Yama.”</note> I will go to the preta realm, I will be born among barbarians in
                        a border region,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-106"> “Border region” refers to a place where the Dharma of the
                            Buddha is unknown. The English translation here follows the Skt. syntax <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">pratyanta­jana­padeṣu mleccheṣu</foreign>. </note> I will be born among the long-lived devas, I will have incomplete
                        faculties, I will hold false views, or I will not be able to delight in the appearance of a buddha in the world.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-107"> This is a version of the “eight freedoms” (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">aṣṭakṣaṇa</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dal ba brgyad</foreign>), the
                            requirements for proper practice of the Dharma.</note>
                        <ref cRef="F.121.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-439"/> </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-473"/>
                    <p tid="194">“ ‘All these karmic obscurations I confess in the presence of the
                        bhagavān buddhas, who are wise, who have vision, who witness, who are authoritative, and who know and see. I reveal these
                        actions; I do not conceal them, and I will henceforth show restraint. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-108"/>
                    <p tid="89">“ ‘May those bhagavān buddhas pay heed to me!</p> 
                    <p tid="195">“ ‘In this and in all the other births that I have taken in saṃsāra without
                        beginning or end, whatever gifts I have given, even if just a small bit of food to an animal, whatever roots of virtue I may
                        possess from maintaining discipline, whatever roots of virtue I may possess from chaste conduct, whatever roots of virtue I
                        may possess by bringing beings to maturity, whatever roots of virtue I may possess through the mind of awakening, and whatever
                        roots of virtue I may possess through unsurpassed gnosis, I collect, combine, and coalesce all of it and dedicate it to
                        unsurpassed, completely perfect awakening by making unsurpassable, unexcelled, and supreme dedications.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-474"/>
                    <p tid="196">“ ‘Just as the bhagavān
                        buddhas of the past have dedicated, just as the bhagavān buddhas of the future will dedicate, and just as the bhagavān buddhas
                        of the present now dedicate,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-109"> The passage cited in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> reads, “and just
                            as the bhagavān buddhas of the present from throughout the ten directions.”</note> in the same way, I also dedicate the
                        virtue. I confess all evil actions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-110"> This line is not found in the passage cited
                            in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>.</note> I rejoice in all merit. I supplicate all buddhas.
                        May my gnosis be unsurpassed. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-111"/>
                    <lg tid="90">
                        <l>“ ‘With folded hands I seek refuge </l>
                        <l>In all the conquerors, the most supreme beings</l>
                        <l>Of the present, of the past, and who have not yet come,</l>
                        <l>Who possess an ocean of qualities limitless and praiseworthy.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-112"> The citation
                                in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> includes another verse not attested in Tibetan sources. </note>
                            <ref cRef="F.121.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-440"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-113"/>
                    <p tid="91">“Śāriputra, in the same way, a bodhisattva should follow all tathāgatas in contemplating the thirty-five bhagavān
                        buddhas and the rest, and thereby purify all their evil actions. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-114"/>
                    <p tid="92">“Similarly, for the sole purpose of liberating beings, those very bhagavān buddhas reveal themselves directly to those
                        who purify all evil actions. They likewise teach confused, foolish beings using a variety of words in order to bring them to
                            maturity,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-115"> At this point the passage cited in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> skips ahead to a
                            later section of the sūtra. </note> all without wavering from the dharmadhātu. They make perfect aspirations for the sake
                        of liberating beings, liberating each according to their own predispositions. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-116"/>
                    <p tid="93">“Śāriputra, bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the samādhi of <distinct>great compassion</distinct> appear
                        in the form of hell beings, animals, beings in the world of Yama, and asuras for the sake of bringing beings to maturity.
                        Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the samādhi of <distinct>great array</distinct> appear in the form of
                        householders for the sake of bringing beings to maturity. Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the
                            <distinct>supreme</distinct> samādhi appear in the form of cakravartins for the sake of bringing beings to maturity.
                        Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the samādhi of <distinct>intense brilliance</distinct> appear in the forms of
                        Indra and Brahmā for the sake of bringing beings to maturity. Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the
                            <distinct>single-pointed</distinct> samādhi appear in the form of śrāvakas for the sake of bringing beings to maturity.
                            <ref cRef="F.122.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-441"/> Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the samādhi
                        of <distinct>nondual purity</distinct> appear in the form of pratyekabuddhas for the sake of bringing beings to maturity.
                        Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the samādhi of <distinct>peace</distinct> appear in the form of completely
                        perfect buddhas for the sake of bringing beings to maturity. Bodhisattva mahāsattvas who have entered into the samādhi
                            <distinct>mastery of all phenomena</distinct> appear in forms aligned with various predispositions for the sake of
                        bringing beings to maturity.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-117"/>
                    <p tid="94">“Śāriputra, in that way, for the sake of bringing beings to maturity, holy beings sometimes appear in the form of
                        Indra, sometimes in the form of Brahmā, and sometimes in the form of a cakravartin, all without wavering from the dharmadhātu.
                        How so? Bodhisattvas, for the sake of bringing beings to maturity, appear to beings of different predispositions in a variety
                        of recognizable forms, but the bodhisattvas objectify neither themselves nor beings as they appear in various forms to those
                        beings. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-118"/>
                    <p tid="95">“Śāriputra, what do you think? Can a cat withstand the roar of a lion, the king of beasts?”</p>
                    <p tid="96">Śāriputra replied, “Bhagavān, it cannot withstand it.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-120"/>
                    <p tid="97">The Bhagavān said, “Śāriputra, what do you think? Can a donkey bear the load of a great rutting elephant?”</p>
                    <p tid="98">Śāriputra replied, “Bhagavān, it cannot bear it.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-122"/>
                    <p tid="99">The Bhagavān said, <ref cRef="F.122.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-442"/> “Śāriputra, what do you think? Can
                        poor people endure the lordly magnificence of Indra and Brahmā?”</p>
                    <p tid="100">Śāriputra replied, “Bhagavān, they cannot endure it.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-124"/>
                    <p tid="101">The Bhagavān said, “Śāriputra, what do you think? Can a fledgling vulture withstand the attack of a garuḍa, the king
                        of birds?” </p>
                    <p tid="102">Śāriputra replied, “Bhagavān, it cannot withstand it.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-126"/>
                    <p tid="103">“Similarly Śāriputra,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-127"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> cites this
                            passage, with some variation from what appears in the Tib. translation.</note> no ordinary being or follower of the
                        Śrāvakayāna or Pratyekabuddhayāna is able to purify the faults of bodhisattvas that have arisen from the power of their
                        courageous mind and roots of virtue or from their knowledge, nor can they purify pernicious faults, which are purified by
                        entering the samādhi of <distinct>seeing the buddhas</distinct>. Bodhisattvas memorize and recite the names of these bhagavān
                        buddhas, and by reciting the Dharma discourse of the Three Sections<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-128"> This rite
                            of the Three Sections is further explained in the introduction to this translation. </note> three times during the day and
                        three times at night, they renounce their pernicious faults and obtain samādhi.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-129"> The passage from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> reads, “A bodhisattva escapes pernicious faults—a condition
                            that anyone belonging to the Śrāvakayāna or Pratyekabuddhayāna is unable to purify—by recalling and reciting the names and
                            epithets of those bhagavān buddhas day and night and by employing the Dharma discourse of Three Sections. [They then]
                            attain samādhi.”</note>
                        <ref cRef="B2" type="bampo"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-130"/>
                    <p tid="104">On the same occasion, the venerable Upāli emerged from meditative seclusion and came to where the Bhagavān was
                            staying.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-131"> The abridged citation of this sūtra found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/> begins here. The Sanskrit of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title> was edited and published in Dutt 1931. </note> Upon arriving, he bowed his head
                        at the feet of the Bhagavān, circumambulated him three times, and sat to one side. The venerable Upāli then said to the
                        Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, when I was in solitary meditative seclusion, this thought arose in my mind: <ref cRef="F.123.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-443"/> the Bhagavān has taught the followers of the Śrāvakayāna and the
                        Pratyekabuddhayāna that the prātimokṣa vows are the pure training and superior ethical discipline. The Bhagavān has also
                        taught that followers of the Bodhisattva­yāna do not abandon their training even for the sake of their lives.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-132"> This translation follows the reading consistent across Tibetan versions of the text. The
                            attested Skt., however, reads, “But the Bhagavān has taught followers of the Bodhisattva­yāna that the training is also
                            [forsaken] when [the current] life is forsaken.”</note> How then would a bhagavān, one who has either passed into
                        parinirvāṇa or still remains, explain the prātimokṣa vows of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna? How would the prātimokṣa vows
                        of the followers of the Pratyekabuddhayāna be explained? How would the prātimokṣa vows of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna
                        be explained? The Bhagavān has said that I am supreme among those who uphold the Vinaya. I will certainly listen closely to
                        the Bhagavān’s expertise in the Vinaya and, having mastered it precisely, will gain fearlessness and teach it perfectly and in
                        detail to the assemblies. Therefore, I thought to ask the Bhagavān to teach me perfectly and in detail.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-133"> The Skt. witness preserves a slightly different reading: “Grant me understanding of this,
                            Bhagavān. Demonstrate expertise in the Vinaya. Bhagavān, listening closely in the Bhagavān’s presence, learning what [I
                            was taught] directly, I will have attained fearlessness and will illuminate [the topic] in detail among the assemblies.”
                            Here we disagree with Dutt’s conjecture of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upāyakauśalya</foreign>, and instead
                            read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vinayakauśalya</foreign>, “expertise in the Vinaya,” as supported by the
                            Tibetan. </note>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-134"/>
                    <p tid="105">“Bhagavān, while I was alone in private meditative seclusion, I thought, ‘I should go before the Tathāgata and
                        request a detailed explanation of the Vinaya.’ Since this thought came to mind, Bhagavān, I ask the Tathāgata to offer a
                        clear, thorough, and detailed explanation of the Vinaya to this great assembly of monks and bodhisattvas.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-135"/>
                    <p tid="106">The Bhagavān responded to the venerable Upāli, “Upāli, you should say that the training of the followers of the
                        Śrāvakayāna is pure in terms of its distinctive application and distinctive orientation. <ref cRef="F.123.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-444"/> You should also say that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna is pure in
                        terms of its distinctive application and distinctive orientation. Why? Upāli, it is because the followers of the Śrāvakayāna
                        have a distinctive application and orientation, while bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna have another distinctive
                        application and orientation.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-136"/>
                    <p tid="107">“Upāli, the pure ethical discipline of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna is impure ethical discipline for bodhisattvas
                        who follow the Mahāyāna; for the latter it is highly corrupt ethical discipline. The pure ethical discipline of bodhisattvas
                        who follow the Mahāyāna is impure ethical discipline for the followers of the Śrāvakayāna; for the latter it is highly corrupt
                        ethical discipline. Why? Upāli, it is because the followers of the Śrāvakayāna do not even have the fleeting desire to take
                        rebirth in the world. This is pure ethical discipline for the followers of the Śrāvakayāna but is impure, highly corrupt
                        ethical discipline for bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna. Upāli, why is it that pure ethical discipline of bodhisattvas who
                        follow the Mahāyāna is impure, highly corrupt ethical discipline for the followers of the Śrāvakayāna? Upāli, it is because
                        bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna take rebirth in saṃsāra for countless eons without aversion or weariness. This is pure
                        ethical discipline for bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna <ref cRef="F.124.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-445"/>
                        but is impure, highly corrupt ethical discipline for the followers of the Śrāvakayāna. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-137"/>
                    <p tid="108">“Upāli, you should therefore say that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna guards and that the
                        training of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna does not guard. You should say that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the
                        Mahāyāna serves as a remedy and that the training of those who follow the Śrāvakayāna does not serve as a remedy. You should
                        say that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna is pursued over a long duration and that the training of the
                        followers of the Śrāvakayāna proceeds in stages. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-138"/>
                    <p tid="109">“Upāli, why is it that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna guards, while the training of the
                        followers of the Śrāvakayāna does not guard? Upāli, bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna should work with the minds of other
                        beings and other people,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-139"> In the section of this sūtra found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>, this line reads “take up the benefit (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hita</foreign>) of other beings and other people.” It would thus seem that the Sanskrit
                            witness translated by the Tibetans reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">cittam anuvartitavyam</foreign>, where
                            the extant Sanskrit witness reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">hitam anuvartitavyam</foreign>. </note> while
                        the followers of the Śrāvakayāna do not need to. Upāli, that is why the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna
                        guards, while the training of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna does not guard. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-140"/>
                    <p tid="110">“Upāli, why is it that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna serves as a remedy, while the training of
                        the followers of the Śrāvakayāna does not serve as a remedy? Upāli,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-141"> In addition
                            to being cited in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>, the Skt. of the following paragraph is also cited in the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>. See Bendall’s edition, 178. The translation that follows
                            here is deeply informed by the attested Skt. terminology and syntax from both these sources, which are in general
                            agreement. </note> if a bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna commits a fault in the morning and does not part from the
                        omniscient mind at midday, <ref cRef="F.124.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-446"/> then the complement of ethical
                        discipline of the bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna is not at all inhibited. If the bodhisattva commits a fault at midday
                        and has not parted from, but rather maintains, the omniscient mind in the afternoon, then the complement of ethical discipline
                        of the bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna is not at all inhibited. If the bodhisattva commits a fault in the afternoon and
                        has not parted from, but rather maintains, the omniscient mind in the first watch of the night, then the complement of ethical
                        discipline of the bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna is not at all inhibited. If the bodhisattva commits a fault in the
                        first watch of the night and has not parted from, but rather maintains, the omniscient mind in the middle watch of the night,
                        then the complement of ethical discipline of the bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna is not at all inhibited. If the
                        bodhisattva commits a fault in the middle watch of the night and has not parted from, but rather maintains, the omniscient
                        mind in the last watch of the night, then the complement of ethical discipline of the bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna is
                        not at all inhibited. Therefore, Upāli, the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna serves as a remedy. Bodhisattvas
                        should neither give rise to excess remorse for nor feel overly dejected about their faults. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-142"/>
                    <p tid="111">“Upāli, you should understand that when the followers of the Śrāvakayāna commit a fault repeatedly, the complement of
                        ethical discipline of those followers of the Śrāvakayāna deteriorates,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-143">
                            Śāntideva’s citation ends here.</note> degenerates, and is exhausted.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-144">
                            “Degenerates and is exhausted” is not found in the two Skt. witnesses. </note> Why? Because followers of the Śrāvakayāna,
                        for the sake of eliminating all afflictions, act as if their head and clothes were on fire. <ref cRef="F.125.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-447"/> In this way, the training of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna—who fervently desire
                        parinirvāṇa—does not serve as a remedy. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-145"/>
                    <p tid="112">“Upāli, how is it that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna is pursued over a long duration, while
                        the training of the Śrāvakayāna proceeds in stages? Upāli, you should understand that even if bodhisattvas who follow the
                        Mahāyāna revel in, relish, and enjoy the five sense pleasures for as many eons as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges
                        but do not give up the mind of awakening, then the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna will not be inhibited at
                            all.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-146"> As incorporated into the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>,
                            this line reads, “Upāli, bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna revel in, relish, and enjoy the five sense pleasures for as
                            many eons as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges but do not give up the mind of awakening. This, Upāli, is to be
                            understood as the training of a bodhisattva who follows in the Mahāyāna” (Dutt 1931, 282). </note> Why? Because, Upāli,
                        there are times and instances in which bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna have so fully assimilated bodhicitta that they are
                        not even affected by the afflictions in their dreams. Upāli, bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna do not eliminate the
                        afflictions in a single lifetime; the afflictions of bodhisattvas whose roots of virtue have matured are exhausted gradually.
                        Followers of the Śrāvakayāna, whose roots of virtue have not matured<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-147"> The
                            Narthang and Lhasa versions of the Tib. translation, as well as the Skt. of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>,<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>
                            read “followers of the Śrāvakayāna whose roots of virtue have matured.”</note> and who act as if their head and clothes
                        were on fire, will not take rebirth in saṃsāra for even an instant. Therefore, Upāli, the training of bodhisattvas who follow
                        the Mahāyāna is to be pursued over a long duration, and the training of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna proceeds in stages.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-148"/>
                    <p tid="113">“Therefore, Upāli, you should say that the training of bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna guards, serves as a remedy,
                        and is pursued over a long duration. <ref cRef="F.125.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-448"/> You should say that the
                        training of the followers of the Śrāvakayāna does not guard, does not serve as a remedy, and proceeds in stages. Why? Upāli,
                        unsurpassed, completely perfect awakening requires significant requisites; it is not easy for bodhisattvas who follow the
                        Mahāyāna to take rebirth and transmigrate for limitless eons if they are singularly discontented with saṃsāra.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-149"/>
                    <p tid="114"> “Upāli, the tathāgata, arhat, completely perfect buddhas recognize that there is a purpose in not teaching
                        bodhisattvas engaged in the Mahāyāna about discontentment alone, or in teaching them about dispassion alone or only about
                        revulsion. They also teach on being joyful and delighted,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-150"> At this point the
                            passage in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/> includes the line, “teach on experiencing dependent
                            origination.”</note> on what is profound and what is not defiled, about subtleties, analysis,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-151"> “Analysis” is not found in the passage from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>.</note> and about being without regret and obsession. They teach about what is unobstructed, about what is unobscured,
                        and about emptiness. Hearing these teachings, bodhisattvas are overjoyed, do not feel discontent for saṃsāra, and perfect
                        nonattachment, the unsurpassed, completely perfect state of awakening.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-152"> This
                            line, as cited in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>, reads, “Having heard these teachings, [bodhisattvas] are
                            overjoyed, fulfilled, and do not feel discontent. They perfect the requisites for awakening” (Dutt 1931, 283). </note>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-153"/>
                    <p tid="115">Then the venerable Upāli asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, among the things considered to be errors, some are associated
                        with desire, some are associated with anger, and some are associated with delusion. That being so, Bhagavān, which of those
                        are the weightiest errors for bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna—those associated with desire, those associated with anger,
                        or those associated with delusion?” <ref cRef="F.126.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-449"/>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-154"/>
                    <p tid="116">The Bhagavān replied to the venerable Upāli,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-155"> Śāntideva cites an
                            abridged version of the following passage in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>. See Bendall (1902), 164–65.</note> “Upāli, suppose that, on
                        the one hand, a bodhisattva who follows the Mahāyāna commits faults associated with desire for as many eons as there are
                        grains of sand in the river Ganges; and suppose that, on the other hand, the same bodhisattva commits a single fault related
                        to anger. If we consider each of these cases in the context of the Bodhisattva­yāna, then the fault related to anger is much
                        weightier than the faults related to desire. Why? Upāli, anger forsakes beings, whereas desire brings beings together. Upāli,
                        bodhisattvas are not deceived by and do not fear afflictions that gather beings together; but bodhisattvas are deceived by and
                        fear the afflictions that forsake beings.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-156"/>
                    <p tid="117">“Moreover, Upāli, the Tathāgata has taught that desire is a minor misdeed that is given up slowly, anger is a major
                        misdeed that is given up quickly, and delusion is a major misdeed that is given up slowly. Among those, Upāli, minor misdeeds
                        that are given up slowly are not considered afflictions for bodhisattvas. Major misdeeds that are given up quickly should be
                        viewed as afflictions for bodhisattvas; indeed, they should not desire them, even in their dreams. Therefore, Upāli, you
                        should say that the faults of bodhisattvas that are associated with desire are not faults, because for bodhisattvas there is
                        no deception or fault in them. <ref cRef="F.126.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-450"/> You should say that faults
                        associated with anger are faults, because for bodhisattvas there is deception and fault in them.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-157"> This line is not found in the passage from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>.</note> Upāli, those bodhisattvas who are not skilled in means are frightened by the faults associated with desire but
                        are not frightened by the faults associated with anger. Bodhisattvas who are skilled in means are frightened by the faults
                        associated with anger but are not frightened by the faults associated with desire.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-158"> Śāntideva’s citation ends here. </note>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-159"/>
                    <p tid="118">Then Youthful Mañjuśrī, who was in the assembly, said to the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, what is discipline when all
                        phenomena are thoroughly tamed?” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-160"/>
                    <p tid="119">The Bhagavān replied to Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, if foolish beings knew that all phenomena are thoroughly tamed,
                        then the Tathāgata would not have to formulate the Vinaya over and over. Because beings do not know this, the Tathāgata
                        gradually formulated the Vinaya so that they may understand that all phenomena are thoroughly tamed.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-161"> The citation of this sūtra preserved in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/> ends
                            here. </note>
                    </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-162"/>
                    <p tid="120">Then the venerable Upāli said to the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, Youthful Mañjuśrī has not offered any kind of explanation
                        on the instructions for determining the Vinaya. Bhagavān, for that reason, please have Youthful Mañjuśrī teach some of the
                        important points.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-163"/>
                    <p tid="121">The Bhagavān said to Youthful Mañjuśrī, <ref cRef="F.127.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-451"/> “Mañjuśrī,
                        because the monk Upāli wishes to hear about mastering the Vinaya, give a teaching beginning with the topic of the
                            <distinct>thoroughly tamed</distinct>.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-164"/>
                    <p tid="122">Then Youthful Mañjuśrī said to the venerable Upāli, “Honorable Upāli, all phenomena are thoroughly tamed—it is for
                        the sake of disciplining one’s own mind that the topic of the <distinct>thoroughly tamed</distinct> is taught. No phenomenon
                        is defiled; it is because the self cannot be apprehended that the discipline of remorse is taught. No phenomenon is mistaken;
                        it is because they are inherently pure that the topic of the <distinct>thoroughly tamed</distinct> is taught. All phenomena
                        are an ultimate gateway to suchness; it is because training should be free of deceit that pure training is taught. All
                        phenomena are nonconceptual, cannot be accepted, and cannot be rejected; it is because they are inconceivable that the state
                        of nonattachment is taught. All phenomena are free of attachment and do not persist; it is because they do not persist for
                        long that the purity of all beings is taught. All phenomena are found within the limits of space; it is because they lack
                        materiality that the lack of inherent existence has been taught. No phenomenon can be differentiated; it is because the limits
                        of past, future, and present are not apprehended that the sameness of the three times is taught. All phenomena lack
                        designations; it is because the mind is oriented to equanimity that the elimination of doubt is taught. </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-165"/>
                    <p tid="123">“Honorable Upāli, that is the thoroughly tamed dharmadhātu realized by bhagavān buddhas. Noble sons and daughters who
                        do not have faith in the true nature of phenomena are far removed from the training of the Tathāgata.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-166"/>
                    <p tid="124">Then the venerable Upāli said to the Bhagavān, <ref cRef="F.127.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-452"/>
                        “Bhagavān, the teaching that Youthful Mañjuśrī has given emerges from the inconceivable itself.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-167"/>
                    <p tid="125">The Bhagavān replied to the venerable Upāli, “Upāli, the Dharma teaching of Youthful Mañjuśrī is aligned with
                        liberation; there is no liberation that is not rooted in inconceivability. For that reason Youthful Mañjuśrī teaches the
                        Dharma for the sake of removing the arrogance of those arrogant ones who believe that they are free of all concepts but are
                        caught up in thought.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-168"/>
                    <p tid="126">Then the venerable Upāli asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, what thoughts do monks have that illustrate this arrogance?” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-169"/>
                    <p tid="127">The Bhagavān then replied to the venerable Upāli, “Upāli, if a monk thinks he has eliminated desire, then he acts
                        with arrogance. If he thinks he has eliminated anger and delusion, then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘The qualities
                        of desire are one thing, and the qualities of a buddha are another,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘The qualities
                        of anger are one thing and the qualities of a buddha are another,’ or ‘the qualities of delusion are one thing and the
                        qualities of the Buddha are another,’ he acts with arrogance. If he thinks he is happy, he acts with arrogance. If he thinks
                        of his deeds, he acts with arrogance. If he thinks he is liberated, he acts with arrogance. If he thinks of emptiness, he acts
                        with arrogance. If he thinks of signlessness, he acts with arrogance. If he thinks of wishlessness, he acts with arrogance.
                            <ref cRef="F.128.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-453"/> If he thinks of preconceived notions, he acts with
                        arrogance. If he thinks of nonorigination, he acts with arrogance. If he thinks of immateriality, he acts with arrogance. If
                        he thinks that phenomena exist, he acts with arrogance. If he thinks that all phenomena are impermanent, he acts with
                        arrogance. If he thinks, ‘What is there to do if all phenomena are empty?’ then he acts with arrogance. This is the arrogance
                        of a follower of the Śrāvakayāna.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-170"/>
                    <p tid="128">“What is the arrogance of a follower of the Bodhisattva­yāna? If he thinks, ‘I have generated the attitude that
                        aspires to the gnosis of the buddhas, which is superior to everything else,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘I
                        should practice the six perfections,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks that the perfection of wisdom refers to
                        renunciation, then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘This is profound, and that is not profound,’ then he acts with
                        arrogance. If he thinks, ‘This leads to purity, and that does not lead to purity,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks,
                        ‘These are the qualities of buddhas, these are the qualities of pratyekabuddhas, and these are the qualities of śrāvakas,’
                        then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘This is logical, and that is not logical,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he
                        thinks, ‘This is defiled, and that is not defiled,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘This is the path, and that is
                        not the path,’ then he acts with arrogance. <ref cRef="F.128.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-454"/> If he thinks, ‘I
                        will quickly and fully attain unsurpassed, completely perfect awakening,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘Since
                        all phenomena are inconceivable, I will not contemplate them,’ then he acts with arrogance. If he thinks, ‘Since unsurpassed,
                        completely perfect awakening is inconceivable, there is nothing to be contemplated,’ then he is engaged in significant
                        objectification. This is the arrogance of a follower of the Bodhisattva­yāna.” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-171"/>
                    <p tid="129">Then the venerable Upāli asked the Bhagavān, “How does a monk avoid arrogance?” </p>
                    <p tid="130">The Bhagavān replied to the venerable Upāli, “Upāli, a monk avoids arrogance if he is not attached to the causal
                        conditions for omniscient gnosis, to the inconceivable.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-173"/>
                    <p tid="131">Then, to explain the inconceivable in detail, the Bhagavān spoke in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="132">
                        <l>“Always happy are those people </l>
                        <l>Who understand that phenomena are inconceivable. </l>
                        <l>They have no concept of Dharma and non-Dharma;</l>
                        <l>Everything is differentiated by mental elaboration.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-175"> This verse is cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 21 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 429 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-176"/>
                    <lg tid="133">
                        <l>“Since everything is inconceivable and everything is unreal,</l>
                        <l>Gnosis should discern between the existent and non-existent.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-177"> Here we
                                understand the Tib. term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par shig</foreign> to be a translation of the
                                Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vibhāvayi</foreign> and have translated it into English accordingly.
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>But fools who have fallen under the power of mind</l>
                        <l>Suffer for billions of existences.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-178"> This verse is cited by Candrakīrti in
                                chapter 21 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 429 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-179"/>
                    <lg tid="134">
                        <l>“The Buddha is inconceivable and nonexistent;</l>
                        <l>Monks who do not consider him supreme are incorrect in their thinking.</l>
                        <l>The Buddha is a product of their conceptualization,</l>
                        <l>But even this conceptualization is unreal. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-180"/>
                    <lg tid="135">
                        <l>“Fools who think that phenomena are empty</l>
                        <l>Have taken a wrong path. <ref cRef="F.129.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-455"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Phenomena that are declared empty with words</l>
                        <l>Are themselves wordless but expressed in words.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-181"> This verse is cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 21 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 429 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-182"/>
                    <lg tid="136">
                        <l>“The mind that thinks phenomena are peaceful and pacified</l>
                        <l>Is itself unborn and unreal.</l>
                        <l>All conceptual elaborations are postulations of the mind.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, know that phenomena are inconceivable.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-183"> This verse is cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 21 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 430 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239. In this version, the fourth line reads, “Know that phenomena are subtle and inconceivable.”</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-184"/>
                    <lg tid="137">
                        <l>“All of these phenomena are unthinkable, unimaginable;</l>
                        <l>To the extent they are unthought, so are they empty.</l>
                        <l>A person who wants to think about emptiness</l>
                        <l>Finds it all the more inconceivable. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-185"/>
                    <lg tid="138">
                        <l>“When all conditions are right, the eye sees.</l>
                        <l>But forms that the eye normally sees</l>
                        <l>Cannot be seen at night or when conditions are not right.</l>
                        <l>Thus the presence or absence of conditions are concepts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-186"> This verse is cited
                                by Candrakīrti in chapter 3 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 121 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-187"/>
                    <lg tid="139">
                        <l>“In dependence on light, the eye sees </l>
                        <l>Various forms both pleasing and unpleasant.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-188"> For this line the Skt. reads,
                                “[The eye] distinguishes various pleasing forms.”</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Since it sees depending on the right conditions, </l>
                        <l>The eye in fact never sees.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-189"> This verse is cited by Candrakīrti in chapter 3
                                of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 121 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-190"/>
                    <lg tid="140">
                        <l>“Pleasant sounds that are heard</l>
                        <l>Never actually enter the ear. </l>
                        <l>Their entry is not observable;</l>
                        <l>Sound occurs through the force of concepts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-191"> This verse is cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 3 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 122 and Lang (2001), 237,
                                239.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-192"/>
                    <lg tid="141">
                        <l>“All these phenomena have been explained </l>
                        <l>Using words to label and account for them.</l>
                        <l>Although phenomena are neither present nor absent, </l>
                        <l>That is not how it appears to fools. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-193"/>
                    <lg tid="142">
                        <l>“Although I have praised generosity to the world, </l>
                        <l>The phenomenon of avarice is not to be found. </l>
                        <l>Similarly, the Conqueror’s qualities are inconceivable; </l>
                        <l>They are also not found and not seen. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-194"/>
                    <lg tid="143">
                        <l>“Although I have taught pure ethical discipline,</l>
                        <l>Ethical infractions are like a hand in space.</l>
                        <l>All bad ethical discipline is like space,</l>
                        <l>And so too is proper ethical discipline.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-195"/>
                    <lg tid="144">
                        <l>“Although I have explained the excellence of patience,</l>
                        <l>Its essence can never be seen. </l>
                        <l>Even though there is no phenomenon to be upset by,</l>
                        <l>The Conqueror has explained patience. <ref cRef="F.129.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-456"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-196"/>
                    <lg tid="145">
                        <l>“I have praised supreme wakefulness,</l>
                        <l>For the purpose of remaining vigilant day and night.</l>
                        <l>Although one may exert oneself for hundreds of eons, </l>
                        <l>Nothing increases and nothing diminishes.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-197"/>
                    <lg tid="146">
                        <l>“Beings have been taught the excellence of meditation, liberation, and samādhi,</l>
                        <l>As well as their points of entry. </l>
                        <l>Although there is no end to the doctrines they contain,</l>
                        <l>I have taught them after determining their sections. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-198"/>
                    <lg tid="147">
                        <l>“Stating that phenomena must be understood through wisdom,</l>
                        <l>I have taught on wisdom, insight, and the intellect.</l>
                        <l>And yet, nature and its lack can never be understood,</l>
                        <l>But it is still necessary to teach them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-199"/>
                    <lg tid="148">
                        <l>“I have taught the world that asceticism is bad,</l>
                        <l>Saying, ‘Take delight in cultivating isolation and contentment!’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-200"> The Stok
                                Palace and Phukdrak versions of the translation read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos shes</foreign>
                                (“knowledge of the Dharma”) for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chog shes</foreign> (“contentment”). This is a
                                compelling variant, as many versions of the translation, including the Degé, Stok Palace, and Phukdrak versions, read
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos shes</foreign> in line three of this verse. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Anything that cannot be attained through contentment<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-201"> In this case, we follow
                                the Kangxi reading of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chog shes</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos shes</foreign>. The Narthang and Lhasa read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mchog
                                    shes</foreign>. Also in this line the Stok Palace and Phukdrak versions read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi mthong</foreign> (“not see”) in place of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi ’thob</foreign>
                                (“not attain).”</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is not to be found in this Dharma.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-202"> This Tibetan translation of this verse
                                varies substantially across the versions found in the diverse Kangyur collections. For this reason, this translation
                                can only be a conjecture. We have elected to consistently read the variant <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chog
                                    shes</foreign> (“contentment”), but this verse could just as viably read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos shes</foreign> (“knowledge of the Dharma”) in place of one or both instances of “contentment.” </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-203"/>
                    <lg tid="149">
                        <l>“I have taught about the frightening hells</l>
                        <l>That terrify many thousands of beings.</l>
                        <l>And yet, there is no one who, upon death,</l>
                        <l>Takes a terrifying rebirth.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-204"> This and the next three verses are cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 1 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 53–54 and Lang (2001),
                                237–39.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-205"/>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l>“There is no one who inflicts harm</l>
                        <l>With a sword, a spear, or a blade. </l>
                        <l>It is through the power of concepts that in those lower realms</l>
                        <l>Nonexistent weapons are seen to fall upon the body. </l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-206"/>
                    <lg tid="151">
                        <l>“There is no one who has made </l>
                        <l>The various delightful, blossoming flowers</l>
                        <l>And pleasant, radiant golden palaces;</l>
                        <l>They manifest through the power of concepts. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-207"/>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“The world is fabricated by concepts;</l>
                        <l>Fools discriminate by clinging to ideas.</l>
                        <l>Clinging and non-clinging do not exist;</l>
                        <l>Fabrications are like illusions and mirages. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-208"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“Although I have taught exalted, supreme conduct,</l>
                        <l>Saying, ‘Generate the mind of awakening for the benefit of beings!’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-209"> Reading
                                the variant, imperative form <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skyed</foreign> attested in the Yongle and Kangxi
                                versions of the translation. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>There is no awakening to be observed;</l>
                        <l>That which is desired simply does not exist. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-210"/>
                    <lg tid="154">
                        <l>“I have taught that the mind is luminous and pure by nature, </l>
                        <l>That it is dustless, free of dust, and stainless. </l>
                        <l>Fools conceptualize that which is nonexistent, </l>
                        <l>And so they develop desire, anger, and delusion. <ref cRef="F.130.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-457"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-211"/>
                    <lg tid="155">
                        <l>“When the sublime Dharma of meditative equanimity is attained,</l>
                        <l>Desire, anger, and delusion do not exist. </l>
                        <l>Phenomena, which are free of desire and liberated,</l>
                        <l>Do not serve as the basis of anything, and nirvāṇa is attained. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-212"/>
                    <lg tid="156">
                        <l>“Those who understand these space-like phenomena </l>
                        <l>Can go to hundreds of realms unhindered. </l>
                        <l>Since their mind is free of desire, </l>
                        <l>They must cultivate the path without obstruction.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-213"/>
                    <lg tid="157">
                        <l>“Although one has practiced for hundreds of eons</l>
                        <l>And liberated countless beings,</l>
                        <l>There never were beings;</l>
                        <l>They neither decrease nor proliferate endlessly. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-214"/>
                    <lg tid="158">
                        <l>“A magician can conjure</l>
                        <l>Hundreds of beings into the world</l>
                        <l>And then kill all those emanations</l>
                        <l>Without any illusions being killed. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-215"/>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“Similarly, all beings have an illusory nature, </l>
                        <l>And their extent is wholly unknown.</l>
                        <l>Those who invested themselves in this infinite multitude</l>
                        <l>Are insensitive to the world. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-216"/>
                    <lg tid="160">
                        <l>“Those who know that phenomena lack inherent nature</l>
                        <l>Are heroes who found nirvāṇa in the world.</l>
                        <l>Although they enjoy sense pleasures, they are unattached;</l>
                        <l>They forsake attachments and discipline beings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-217"> This verse is cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 23 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 474 and Lang (2001),
                                238–39.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-218"/>
                    <lg tid="161">
                        <l>“Although there are neither beings nor living things here,</l>
                        <l>The lords of men work for the welfare of beings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-219"> Where the Tib. reads
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi’i dbang po</foreign> (“lords of men”) the extant Sanskrit reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jinendra</foreign> (“lords of conquerors”).</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>They benefit beings, even though beings do not exist.</l>
                        <l>For them, this is an arduous task.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-220"> This verse is cited by Candrakīrti in
                                chapter 14 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. The Sanskrit manuscript edited by La Vallée Poussin
                                (1903, 257) was illegible in places but has been restored by Lang (2001, 238–39).</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-221"/>
                    <lg tid="162">
                        <l>“If one shows a closed hand to a child</l>
                        <l>And says ‘Here is a laḍḍu,’ </l>
                        <l>The child will cry </l>
                        <l>Upon seeing an empty hand. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-222"/>
                    <lg tid="163">
                        <l>“Likewise, the inconceivable buddhas, </l>
                        <l>Who know and are proficient in the ways of beings, </l>
                        <l>Realize that all phenomena are deceptive </l>
                        <l>But teach the world about material things. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-223"/>
                    <lg tid="164">
                        <l>“In this delightful instruction,</l>
                        <l>The compassionate one also taught,</l>
                        <l>‘Abandon the trappings of a householder and renounce.</l>
                        <l>Then the best results will come.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-224"> This and the next two verses are cited by
                                Candrakīrti in chapter 20 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>. See La Vallée Poussin (1903), 408–9 and Lang (2001),
                                238–39.</note>
                            <ref cRef="F.130.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-458"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-225"/>
                    <lg tid="165">
                        <l>“Having abandoned the trappings of a householder and renounced,</l>
                        <l>One will attain every result. </l>
                        <l>Yet if one considers the nature of phenomena,</l>
                        <l>There is no attainment and no results at all. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-226"/>
                    <lg tid="166">
                        <l>“However, those who attain results and attainments<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-227"> The citation from the
                                    <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/> reads “those who do not attain” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">alabhanta</foreign>). </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Feel great astonishment and say,</l>
                        <l>‘Ah! The best of men,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-228"> Here the Tib. reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi mchog</foreign> (“best of men”) where the extant Skt. reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">narasiṃha</foreign> (“lion among men”).</note> the compassionate Conqueror,</l>
                        <l>Has explained his reasoning well.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-229"/>
                    <lg tid="167">
                        <l>“In this way these peaceful phenomena</l>
                        <l>Have been taught using thousands of terms and phrases. </l>
                        <l>They are referred to as <distinct>sense faculties</distinct>, <distinct>meditative concentration</distinct>,
                                <distinct>liberation</distinct>, </l>
                        <l>
                            <distinct>Powers</distinct>, <distinct>factors of awakening</distinct>, and <distinct>peace</distinct>. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-230"/>
                    <lg tid="168">
                        <l>“Sense faculties have never developed, and there are no powers;</l>
                        <l>No factor of awakening or peace has ever been generated. </l>
                        <l>Though these phenomena are neither material nor immaterial, </l>
                        <l>They have been explained in the world through the force of knowledge.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-231"/>
                    <lg tid="169">
                        <l>“Of the attainments that I have explained to beings, </l>
                        <l>All completely lack characteristics. </l>
                        <l>Those who think that they have reached attainment</l>
                        <l>Are arrogant about an attainment they have never actually had. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-232"/>
                    <lg tid="170">
                        <l>“Since there is nothing substantial in the entire world,</l>
                        <l>There is also no attainment whatsoever.</l>
                        <l>One who understands attainment and nonattainment as I have taught it to beings</l>
                        <l>Is one who has reached attainment. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-233"/>
                    <lg tid="171">
                        <l>“This attainment of the result is superior to all others.</l>
                        <l>I have taught that such beings do not actually exist, </l>
                        <l>That beings are not found at all;</l>
                        <l>If beings do not exist, who is it that attains? </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-234"/>
                    <lg tid="172">
                        <l>“Sprouts do not grow in a field </l>
                        <l>Where seeds have not been planted.</l>
                        <l>Likewise, if beings are nowhere to be found,</l>
                        <l>Where is attainment in the absence of beings?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-235"/>
                    <lg tid="173">
                        <l>“All these beings have reached nirvāṇa,</l>
                        <l>But its roots are nowhere to be found. </l>
                        <l>To those who believe in this way of Dharma, </l>
                        <l>I taught nirvāṇa without remainder.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-236"/>
                    <lg tid="174">
                        <l>“Many hundreds of buddhas have passed beyond,</l>
                        <l>And none have tamed any beings. <ref cRef="F.131.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-459"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>If any beings were to appear here,</l>
                        <l>They would never pass into nirvāṇa.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-237"/>
                    <lg tid="175">
                        <l>“Therefore, this path has no defilement, </l>
                        <l>And there is no attachment in it at all. </l>
                        <l>The minds of those who believe in this reality</l>
                        <l>Will have no attachment to mundane existence.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-238"/>
                    <p tid="176">When the Bhagavān finished speaking these verses that teach accomplishment, two hundred arrogant monks, freed from
                        clinging, were liberated from the defilements. Sixty thousand bodhisattvas accepted that phenomena are unproduced.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-239"/>
                    <p tid="177">Then the venerable Upāli said to the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, what is the name of this Dharma discourse? How should it be
                        preserved?” </p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-240"/>
                    <p tid="178">The Bhagavān said, “Upāli, since you asked, this Dharma discourse should be preserved under the name <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya</title> or <title xml:lang="en">Conquering All Beings</title>.”</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-241"/>
                    <p tid="179">After the Bhagavān spoke, the venerable Upāli, Youthful Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattvas, the monks, everyone assembled
                        there, and the gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the Bhagavān’s teaching.</p>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-242"/>
                    <trailer tid="180">This concludes <title xml:lang="en">Determining the Vinaya: Upāli’s
                        Questions</title>, the twenty-fourth of the one hundred thousand sections of the Dharma discourse known as The Noble Great Heap of Jewels.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="181">Colophon</head>
                    <tei:milestone xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-243"/>
                    <p tid="182">Translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra, Prajñāvarman, and Surendrabodhi, with
                        the chief Tibetan editor and translator, Bandé Yeshé Dé, and others. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="183">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="184">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="185">Tibetan Canonical Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-244">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba rnam par gtan la dbab pa nye bar ’khor gyis zhus pa</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya­viniścayopāli­paripṛcchā</title>). Toh 68, Degé Kangyur vol. 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca),
                        folios 115.a–131.a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-245">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba rnam par gtan la dbab pa nye bar ’khor gyis zhus pa</title>.
                        bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe
                        sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i
                        bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 43, pp. 324–69.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-461">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba rnam par gtan la dbab pa nye bar ’khor gyis zhus pa</title>.
                        Stok Palace Kangyur vol. 39 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 218.b–242.b.</bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-460">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">drag shul can gyis zhus pa’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ugra­pari­pṛcchā­sūtra</title>).
                        Toh 63, Degé Kangyur vol. 42 (dkon brtsegs, nga), folios 257.b–288.a.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh63.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-248">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi ltung ba bshags pa’i ’grel pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyāpatti­deśanāvṛtti</title>). Toh 4005, Degé Tengyur vol. 116 (mdo ’grel, ji), folios
                        178.a–187.b</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-462">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang sems sor thar chos bzhi sgrub pa’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­prātimokṣa­catuṣka­nirhāra­sūtra</title>). Toh 248, Degé Kangyur vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), folios 46.b–59.a.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh248.html"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-463"> Candrakīrti. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu ma rtsa ba’i ’grel pa tshig gsal ba</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūlamadhyamakavṛttiprasannapadā</title>). Toh 3860, Degé Tengyur vol. 102 (dbu ma, ’a), folios
                            1.b–200.a.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-254">Kṛṣṇa. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po gsum pa’i sgrub thabs</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Skandha­tri­sādhana</title>). Toh 4008, Degé Tengyur vol. 116 (mdo ’grel, ji), folios 198.b–199.b.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4008.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-466"> Nāgārjuna. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi ltung ba bshags pa’i ’grel pa byang chub
                            sems dpa’i bslab pa’i rim pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyāpatti­deśanā­vṛtti­bodhisattva­śikṣā­krama</title>).
                        Toh 4006, Degé Tengyur vol. 116 (mdo tshogs, ’grel pa), folios 187.b–194.a. English translation in Beresford (1980). <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4006.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-465"> Śāntideva. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa kun las btus pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣā­samuccaya</title>). Toh 3940, Degé Tengyur vol. 111 (dbu ma, khi), folios 3.a–194.b.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-464">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan dkar gyi chos kyi ’gyur ro cog gi dkar
                            chag</title> [Denkarma]. Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-467">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye brag tu rtogs par
                            byed pa chen po</title>). Toh 4346, Degé Tengyur vol. 204 (sna tshogs, co), folios 1.b–131.a.</bibl>
                </div>

                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-listBibl-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="186">Other Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-246">Barnes, Nancy J. “Rituals, Religious Communities, and Buddhist Sutras in India and China.”
                            <title xml:lang="en">Sino-Platonic Papers</title> 222 (2012): 212–25. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-265">Bendall, Cecil M. A., ed. <title xml:lang="en">Çikshasamuccaya: A Compendium of Buddhist
                            Teachings Compiled by Çāntideva Chiefly from Earlier Mahāyāna-Sūtras</title>. St. Petersburg: Imperial Academy of
                        Sciences, 1902.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-468">Beresford, Brian C., trans. <title xml:lang="en">The Confession of Downfalls</title>.
                        Dharamsala: Library of Tibetan Works &amp; Archives, 1980. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-247">Buswell, Robert E., Jr., and Donald S. Lopez Jr. <title xml:lang="en">The Princeton Dictionary
                            of Buddhism</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-256">Chandra, Lokesh, ed. “Qutuγ-tu nomuγadqaqu-yi teyin böged maγadqui Ubali-yin öčigsen neretü
                        yeke kölgen sudur.” In <title xml:lang="en">Mongolian Kanjur</title>, vol. 52 (Erdeni dabqurliγ), 282–324, folios 141.b–162.b.
                        Śata-piṭaka Series: Indo-Asian Literature, vol. 152. New Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-249">Chang, Garma C. C., ed. <title xml:lang="en">A Treasury of Mahāyāna Sūtras: Selections from the
                            Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title>. Translated by The Buddhist Association of the United States. University Park: The
                        Pennsylvania State University Press, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-250">Dutt, Nalinaksha, ed. “Bodhisattva Prātimokṣa Sūtra.” <title xml:lang="en">The Indian
                            Historical Quarterly</title> 7, no. 2 (1931): 259–86. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-251">Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and
                            Dictionary</title>. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-252">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins
                            Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften,
                        2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-253">Kawagoe, Eishin, ed. <title xml:lang="ja">川越 英真</title>. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dKar chag
                            ’Phang thang ma</title>. Sendai: Tōhoku indo chibetto kenkyūkai <foreign xml:lang="ja" type="term">東北インド・チベット研究会</foreign>
                        (Tohoku Society for Indo-Tibetan Studies), 2005. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-480">Khomthar Jamlö (khoM thar ’jam los), editor for si khron pod yig
                        dpe rnying bsdu sgrig khang. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo bcu’i rtsa ’grel phyogs
                            bsgrigs</title> [<title xml:lang="en">The Ten Sūtras of the King, collected texts and
                                commentaries</title>]. 10 vols. Sichuan: si khron mi rigs dpe skrun khang [Sichuan
                        Minorities Publishing House], 2014. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-255">Lang, Karen C. “Poetic License in the Buddhist Sanskrit Verses of the Upāliparipṛcchā.” <title xml:lang="en">Indo-Iranian Journal</title> 44, no. 3 (2001): 231–40. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-257">La Vallée Poussin, Louis de, ed. <title xml:lang="fr">Mūlamadhyamakakārikās de
                            Nāgārjuna</title>. St. Petersburg: Imperial Academy of Sciences, 1903.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-258">Matsumura, Hisashi. “Miscellaneous Notes on the Upāliparipṛcchā and Related Texts.” <title xml:lang="en">Acta Orientalia</title> 51 (1990): 61–109.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-260">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men: The Bodhisattva Path According to the
                            Inquiry of Ugra</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ugraparipṛcchā</title>). Honolulu: University of Hawai‘i Press,
                        2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-261">Nanjio, Bunyiu. <title xml:lang="en">A Catalogue of the Chinese Translation of the Buddhist
                            Tripiṭaka, the Sacred Canon of the Buddhists in China and Japan</title>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1883. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-262">Negi, J. S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan–Sanskrit Dictionary </title>(<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bod skad dang legs sbyar gyi tshig mdzod chen mo</title>). Sarnath: Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies,
                        1993–2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-263">Python, Pierre. <title xml:lang="fr">Vinaya-viniścaya-upāli-paripṛcchā: Enquête d’Upāli pour
                            une Exégèse de la Discipline</title>. Paris: Adrien-Maisonneuve, 1973. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-264">Sakaki, Ryōzaburō. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>. 2 vols. Kyōto: Shingonshū
                        Kyōto Daigaku, 1926.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-266">Stache-Rosen, Valentina. <title xml:lang="de">Upāliparipṛcchāsūtra: ein Text zur buddhistischen
                            Ordensdisziplin</title>. Göttingen: Vandenhoek &amp; Ruprecht, 1984. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-005-267">Strong, John. <title xml:lang="en">Relics of the Buddha</title>. Princeton: Princeton
                        University Press, 2004.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-268">
                            <term>acceptance that phenomena are unproduced</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva’s realization that all phenomena are unproduced and empty. This attainment is
                                variously said to occur on either the first or eighth bodhisattva level.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">accepted that phenomena are unproduced</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-269">
                            <term> seat of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhimaṇḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The place where every buddha in this world system will attain buddhahood. It is identified with
                                the spot beneath the Bodhi tree in the Bodhgaya. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-270">
                            <term>those who uphold the Vinaya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba ’dzin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུལ་བ་འཛིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vinayadhāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Those who are expert in monastic discipline.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-271">
                            <term>affliction</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kleśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mental factors that disturb the mind and incite unwholesome deeds of body, speech, and
                                mind.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-272">
                            <term>arhat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">A “worthy one,” who has destroyed the afflictions (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśa</foreign>) and all causes for future rebirth, and who thus will reach awakening at death.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-273">
                            <term>asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                            <!--<term type="definition">One of the six classes of sentient beings. The asuras are engendered and dominated by envy,
                                ambition, and hostility and are metaphorically described as being incessantly embroiled in disputes with the gods
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">deva</foreign>). They are frequently portrayed in brahmanical mythology as
                                having a disruptive effect on cosmological and social harmony.</term>-->
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-005-274" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="definition">A common epithet for a buddha, often rendered in English as “Blessed One.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-275">
                            <term>bodhisattva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “awakening being”; a being on the path to awakening who has generated <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhicitta</foreign> for the benefit of all beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-276">
                            <term>bodhisattva mahāsattva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’ sems dpa’ chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattva­mahā­sattva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Generally refers to bodhisattvas who have reached at least the seventh of the ten bodhisattva levels (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhūmis</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-277">
                            <term>Bodhisattva­yāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’i theg pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཐེག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­yāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The path of the bodhisattvas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-278">
                            <term>cakravartin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor los sgyur ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravartin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A term for an idealized, utopic vision of kingship in South Asian cultures. A cakravartin reigns
                                over vast regions of the universe in accordance with principles of righteous law (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">
                                    <term type="ignore">dharma</term>
                                </foreign>). Such a king is called a cakravartin because he possesses
                                a wheel or discus (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cakra</foreign>) that rolls across different realms and
                                brings them all under his power.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-279">
                            <term>Conqueror</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jina</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-280">
                            <term>desire</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod chags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་ཆགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six root afflictions (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mūlakleśa</foreign>),
                                often listed as one of the three poisons (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">triviṣa</foreign>) along with
                                anger (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dveṣa</foreign>) and delusion (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">moha</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-281">
                            <term>deva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
                            <!--<term type="definition">Cognate with the English term “divine,” the devas are most generically a class of divine,
                                celestial beings who populate the narratives of Indian mythology. Devas make regular appearances in Buddhist
                                literature at the head of the assemblies of celestial and supernatural beings who attend the teachings, interact with
                                the Buddha, bodhisattvas and other spiritual figures, and celebrate the delivery of their sermons. In Buddhist
                                cosmology, the devas are subdivided into numerous classes based on the specific <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">devalokas</foreign>, the “heavens” in which they reside. Traditionally there are between twenty-six and
                                twenty-eight devalokas, divided between the <term type="ignore">desire</term> realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāmadhātu</foreign>),
                                material realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">rūpadhātu</foreign>), and immaterial realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arūpyadhātu</foreign>). The state of deva is reached either through meritorious acts
                                or the cultivation of subtle meditative states, and is therefore considered a higher mode of rebirth in comparison
                                to rebirth among hell beings, pretas, and animals. Nonetheless, all the devalokas are within the three realms of
                                saṃsāra and therefore transitory. Thus, while the devas occupy the highest strata within the scheme of the five or six
                                “destinies” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gati</foreign>), the realms within saṃsāra where beings take
                                rebirth, their state is still one determined by the fetters (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saṃyojana</foreign>) that bind one to the perpetual cycle of rebirth. </term>AR: replaced by standard definition-->
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-282">
                            <term>Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Teachings of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-283">
                            <term>dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The nature of phenomena; the dimension or space (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhātu</foreign>) in which phenomena (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>) appear.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-284">
                            <term>doors of liberation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par thar pa’i sgo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པའི་སྒོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimokṣamukha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A set of three points associated with the nature of reality that when contemplated and integrated
                                lead to liberation. The three are emptiness, signlessness, and wishlessness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-285">
                            <term>emptiness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་པ་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūnyatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A term used to describe how phenomena are devoid of any nature of their own. One of the three
                                doors of liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-286">
                            <term>eon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bskal pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྐལ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-287">
                            <term>ethical discipline</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīla</term>
                            <term type="definition"> The second of the six perfections (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāramitā</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-288">
                            <term>eye of Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi mig </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་མིག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmacakṣus</term>
                            <term type="definition">The capacity of awakened beings to comprehend the inherent truth of impermanence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-005-289" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>grave acts of immediate retribution</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams ma mchis pa lnga’i las</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མ་མཆིས་པ་ལྔའི་ལས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ānantarya­karman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams med</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མེད།</term>
                            <term type="definition">The five heinous deeds or acts that bring immediate retribution: (1) killing one’s father, (2) killing one’s mother, (3) killing an arhat, (4) drawing blood from the body of a tathāgata with malicious intent, and (5) causing schism in the saṅgha. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-290">
                            <term>five sense pleasures</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dod pa’i yon tan lnga po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དོད་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་ལྔ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcakāmaguṇāḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Pleasures corresponding to each of the five senses: vision, hearing, smell, taste, and
                                touch.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">sense pleasures</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-291">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of generally benevolent nonhuman beings who inhabit the sky and are most renowned as
                                celestial musicians.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-292">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of being described as an eagle-type bird with a gigantic wingspan. They were traditionally
                                enemies of the nāgas. In the Vedas, they were thought to have brought nectar from the heavens to earth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-293">
                            <term>giving</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dāna</term>
                            <term type="definition"> The first of the six perfections (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāramitā</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-294">
                            <term>gnosis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Pure knowledge free of conceptual impediments.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-295">
                            <term>inner and outer constituents</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang dang phyi’i dngos po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནང་དང་ཕྱིའི་དངོས་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Various inner bodily parts and outer material things that may be requested from
                                bodhisattvas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-296">
                            <term>karmic obscuration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi sgrib pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལས་ཀྱི་སྒྲིབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karmāvaraṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The persistent physical, mental, or emotional obstacles to spiritual progress.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-297">
                            <term>laḍḍu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">la du </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལ་དུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">laḍḍu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A popular South Asian sweet.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-298">
                            <term>Mahāyāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāyāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-299">
                            <term>meditative concentration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསམ་གཏན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition"> The fifth of the six perfections (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāramitā</foreign>). </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-300">
                            <term>meditative seclusion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang du yang dag ’jog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṁlāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-301">
                            <term>mind of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The intention to reach unsurpassed, completely perfect awakening (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anuttara­samyak­saṃbodhi</foreign>) in order to liberate all beings from suffering.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-302">
                            <term>nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meaning “extinguished” in Sanskrit and “beyond suffering” in Tibetan translation, this is a term
                                for the state of awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-303">
                            <term>nirvāṇa without remainder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhag med mya ngan ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷག་མེད་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupadhiśeṣa­nirvāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirupadhiśeṣa­nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mode of nirvāṇa in which all physical and mental attributes have been relinquished. This mode
                                occurs after death, as some physical and mental attributes remain when an awakened being is still alive.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-304">
                            <term>obscuration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrib pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲིབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āvaraṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nivaraṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The obscurations to liberation and omniscience. They are generally categorized as two types:
                                affective obscurations (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśāvaraṇa</foreign>), the arising of afflictive
                                emotions, and cognitive obscurations (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jñeyāvaraṇa</foreign>), those caused by
                                misapprehension and incorrect understanding about the nature of reality. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-305">
                            <term>parinirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su myan ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོངས་སུ་མྱན་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parinirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The final passage into nirvāṇa upon the death of a buddha or an arhat.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-306">
                            <term>path of the ten nonvirtuous actions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dge ba bcu’i las kyi lam </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśā­kuśala­karma­patha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Physical, verbal, and mental activities that lead to unsalutary rebirths.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-307">
                            <term>phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</term>
                            <term type="alternative">phenomenon</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-308">
                            <term>prātimokṣa vows</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so sor thar pa’i sdom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་སོར་ཐར་པའི་སྡོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātimokṣa­saṃvara</term>
                            <term type="definition"> The regulations and rules that constitute Buddhist discipline. The number and scope of the vows
                                differs depending on one’s status (lay, novice monastic, or full monastic) and whether one is a monk or a nun. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-309">
                            <term>pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who has attained liberation entirely through their own contemplation as a result of
                                progress in previous lives but, unlike a buddha, does not have the accumulated merit and motivation to teach others.
                                Like <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</foreign>, this term is also used to denote Buddhists who do not follow the Mahāyāna.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-310">
                            <term>Pratyekabuddhayāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas kyi theg pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyeka­buddha­yāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The path of the pratyekabuddhas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-311">
                            <term>preta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡི་དགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally “the departed” and analogous to the ancestral spirits of the Vedic tradition, the
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛs</foreign>, who starve without the offerings of descendants. In
                                Buddhism they are said to suffer intensely, particularly from hunger and thirst, and their realm is one of the three
                                or four unfortunate realms of rebirth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-313">
                            <term>roots of virtue</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i rtsa ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kuśalamūla</term>
                            <term type="definition">Cumulative meritorious deeds performed by an individual throughout past lives. The most common
                                threefold list of roots of virtue include non-greed (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">alobha</foreign>),
                                non-hatred (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adveṣa</foreign>), and non-delusion (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">amoha</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-314">
                            <term>samādhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A state of deep meditative absorption. There are numerous samādhis that can be entered into and
                                sustained by realized beings. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-315">
                            <term>saṃsāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The cycle of rebirth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-316">
                            <term>saṅgha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ’dun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་འདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṅgha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The “community” of ordained Buddhist monks and nuns.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-317">
                            <term>signlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan ma med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་མ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">animitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The absence of the conceptual identification of perceptions. One of the three doors of
                                liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-318">
                            <term>six perfections</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rol du phyin pa drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕ་རོལ་དུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaṭpāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The six perfections are giving (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dāna</foreign>),
                                ethical discipline (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śīla</foreign>), patience or acceptance (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>), effort (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vīrya</foreign>), meditative concentration (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhyāna</foreign>), and
                                wisdom (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñā</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-319">
                            <term>skill in means</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs la mkhas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐབས་ལ་མཁས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāyakauśalya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The extraordinary skills of the buddhas and advanced bodhisattvas.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">skilled in means</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-320">
                            <term>śrāvaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Based on the verb “to hear,” the Sanskrit term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śrāvaka</foreign> is used in reference to followers of the non-Mahāyāna traditions of Buddhism, in contrast to
                                the bodhisattvas who follow the Mahāyāna path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-321">
                            <term>Śrāvakayāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos kyi theg pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvakayāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The path of the śrāvakas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-322">
                            <term>stūpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">stūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A reliquary, often in the shape of a hemispherical mound that contains relics or possessions of
                                the Buddha or a saint. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-005-323" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Thus-Gone One”; epithet of the Buddha and a general term for buddhas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-324">
                            <term>unsurpassed, completely perfect awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa’i byang chub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anuttara­samyak­saṃbodhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The awakening of a buddha, which is superior to all other forms of awakening. According to the
                                Mahāyāna, in <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anuttara­samyak­saṃbodhi</foreign>, both of the two kinds of
                                obscuration, the afflictive obscuration (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśāvaraṇa</foreign>) and the
                                obscurations to omniscience (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jñeyāvaraṇa</foreign>), have been completely
                                overcome.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-325">
                            <term>Vinaya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vinaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Discipline”; one of the Three Baskets (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Tripiṭaka</foreign>), the Vinaya is the body of literature on monastic discipline and training.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-326">
                            <term>wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The sixth of the six perfections (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāramitā</foreign>);
                                the precise discernment of all things.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-327">
                            <term>wishlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨོན་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apraṇihita</term>
                            <term type="definition">The absence of any conceptual goal that one is focused upon achieving. One of the three doors of
                                liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-328">
                            <term>Fearless toward All Phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos thams cad la bag tsha ba med par gnas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བག་ཚ་བ་མེད་པར་གནས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-329">
                            <term>Akṣayamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros mi zad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་མི་ཟད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣayamati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-330">
                            <term>Amoghadarśin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthong ba don yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐོང་བ་དོན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Amoghadarśin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-331">
                            <term>Anantaujas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi brjid mtha’ yas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་བརྗིད་མཐའ་ཡས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Anantaujas</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-332">
                            <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term type="definition">A wealthy merchant from the city of Śrāvastī who was a great patron of the Buddha Śākyamuni and
                                the saṅgha. He is better known in the West by the alternative form Anāthapiṇḍika.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-333">
                            <term>Aśokaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan med pa’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་མེད་པའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Aśokaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-334">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-335">
                            <term>Bhadrapāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang skyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟང་སྐྱོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrapāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-336">
                            <term>Bhadraśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal bzang</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Bhadraśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-476">
                            <term>Bhadraśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Bhadraśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-338">
                            <term>Boundless Stillness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnas pa dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནས་པ་དཔག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-339" mode="marked">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-475">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high-ranking deity presiding over a divine world where other beings consider him the creator; he is also considered to be the Lord of the Sahā world (our universe). Though not considered a creator god in Buddhism, Brahmā occupies an important place as one of two deities (the other being Indra/Śakra) that are said to have first exhorted Śākyamuni to teach the Dharma. The particular heavens found in the form realm over which Brahmā rules are often some of the most sought-after realms of higher rebirth in Buddhist literature. Since there are multiple universes and world systems, there are also multiple Brahmās presiding over them.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-340">
                            <term>Brahma­datta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pas byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པས་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Brahma­datta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-341">
                            <term>Brahma­jyotir­vikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa’i ’od zer rnam par rol pas mngon par mkhyen pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་འོད་ཟེར་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པས་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Brahma­jyotir­vikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-342">
                            <term>Candanaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsan dan dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཙན་དན་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Candanaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-343">
                            <term>Candraketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བའི་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Candraketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-344">
                            <term>Candrottara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla mchog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་མཆོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Candrottara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-345">
                            <term>Dhanaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhanaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-346">
                            <term>Dharmākara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’byung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་འབྱུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Dharmākara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-347">
                            <term>Dharmaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Dharmaketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-348">
                            <term>Engaged in Inconceivable Liberation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par thar pa bsam gyis mi khyab pa la yang dag par zhugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-349">
                            <term>Exalted Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos mngon par ’phags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་མངོན་པར་འཕགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-350">
                            <term>Excellent Faculties</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-351">
                            <term>Glorious Awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-352">
                            <term>Indra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indra is the Vedic king of the gods of the atmosphere or sky. Indra is included in the
                                Buddhist pantheon as a guardian of the Dharma and the king of the deva realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-353">
                            <term>Indra­ketu­dhvaja­rāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po tog gi rgyal mtshan gyi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ་ཏོག་གི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Indra­ketu­dhvaja­rāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-354">
                            <term>Jagatīndhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’gro ba ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འགྲོ་བ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Jagatīndhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-355">
                            <term>Jñānaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānaketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-356">
                            <term>Jñānaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-357">
                            <term>Kusumaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Kusumaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-358">
                            <term>Luminous Youth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzhon nu ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཞོན་ནུ་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-359">
                            <term>Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu chen thob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐུ་ཆེན་ཐོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-360">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of the next buddha, “The Benevolent One,” who now abides in Tuṣita heaven as a
                                bodhisattva, awaiting the proper time to take his final rebirth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-361">
                            <term>Maṇibhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor bu bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་བུ་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Maṇibhadra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-362">
                            <term>Manifesting the Appearance of Good Qualities</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yon tan gzugs ston </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོན་ཏན་གཟུགས་སྟོན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-363">
                            <term>Mati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-364">
                            <term>Nāgeśvara­rāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu dbang gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ་དབང་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Nāgeśvara­rāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-365">
                            <term>Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sred med kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲེད་མེད་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Child of No Craving”; a name of the god Viṣṇu.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-477">
                            <term>Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sred med kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲེད་མེད་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-366">
                            <term>Nectar Holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud rtsi ’chang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད་རྩི་འཆང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-367">
                            <term>Niḥśaṅka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bag tsha ba med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བག་ཚ་བ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Niḥśaṅka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-368">
                            <term>Niḥśaṅka­sthāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bag tsha ba med par gnas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བག་ཚ་བ་མེད་པར་གནས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Niḥśaṅka­sthāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-369">
                            <term>Nothing</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ci yang min </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཅི་ཡང་མིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-370">
                            <term>Padma­jyotir­vikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad ma’i ’od zer rnam par rol pas mngon par mkhyen pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མའི་འོད་ཟེར་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པས་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Padma­jyotir­vikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-371">
                            <term>Prabhāsa­śrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prabhāsa­śrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-372">
                            <term>Priya­darśana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthong dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐོང་དགའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Priya­darśana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-373">
                            <term>Puṇyaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསོད་ནམས་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Puṇyaketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-374">
                            <term>Puṇyaraśmi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams ’od zer </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསོད་ནམས་འོད་ཟེར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Puṇyaraśmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-375">
                            <term>Rāśika </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshogs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚོགས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāśika </term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-376">
                            <term>Ratnacandra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratnacandra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-377">
                            <term>Ratna­candra­prabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen zla ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཟླ་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratna­candra­prabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-378">
                            <term>Ratnāgni</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen me </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་མེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratnāgni</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-379">
                            <term>Ratna­padma­supratiṣṭhita­śailendra­rāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin po che’i pad ma la rab tu bzhugs pa ri dbang gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་པད་མ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བཞུགས་པ་རི་དབང་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratna­padma­supratiṣṭhita­śailendra­rāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-380">
                            <term>Ratna­padma­vikrāmin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen pad mas rnam par gnon pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་པད་མས་རྣམ་པར་གནོན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratna­padma­vikramin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-381">
                            <term>Ratnapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag na rin po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལག་ན་རིན་པོ་ཆེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratnapāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-382">
                            <term>Ratnārcis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’od ’phro </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འོད་འཕྲོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratnārcis</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-383">
                            <term>Ratnaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Ratnaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-384">
                            <term>Recognizer of Unafflicted Realization</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs pa med pa rtogs par khong du chud pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ་རྟོགས་པར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-385">
                            <term>Śākyamuni</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni</term>
                            <term type="definition">A common epithet of the historical Buddha, Siddhārtha Gautama, meaning “the sage (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">muni</foreign>) of the Śākya clan.” Here mentioned as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-386">
                            <term>Samantāvabhāsa­vyūha­śrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas snang ba bkod pa’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ནས་སྣང་བ་བཀོད་པའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Samantāvabhāsa­vyūha­śrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-387">
                            <term>Śāriputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ri’i bu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the chief disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-388">
                            <term>Sarva­nīvaraṇa­viṣkambhin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrib pa thams cad rnam par sel ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲིབ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་སེལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sarva­nīvaraṇa­viṣkambhin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-389">
                            <term>Siṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-390">
                            <term>Siṃhamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེ་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Siṃhamati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-391">
                            <term>Smṛtiśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Smṛtiśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-392">
                            <term>Sumanas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid bzangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་བཟངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sumanas</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-393">
                            <term>Sumati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sumati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-394">
                            <term>Sunetra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིག་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sunetra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-395">
                            <term>Suparikīrtita­nāmadheya­śrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan dpal shin tu yongs bsgrags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་དཔལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡོངས་བསྒྲགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Suparikīrtita­nāmadheya­śrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-396">
                            <term>Śūradatta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpas byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔས་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Śūradatta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-397">
                            <term>Sūrata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">des pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sūrata</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-398">
                            <term>Sūryaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi ma’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་མའི་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sūryaketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-399">
                            <term>Sūryaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Sūryaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-400">
                            <term>Suvarṇa­prabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསེར་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Suvarṇaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-401">
                            <term>Suvijita­saṃgrāma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">g.yul las shin tu rnam par rgyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཡུལ་ལས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Suvijita­saṃgrāma</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-402">
                            <term>Suvikrānta­śrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu rnam par gnon pa’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གནོན་པའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Suvikrānta­śrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-403">
                            <term>Tejobala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi brjid stobs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་བརྗིད་སྟོབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tejobala</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-404">
                            <term>Tejorāśi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi brjid phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་བརྗིད་ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Tejorāśi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-405">
                            <term>Upāli</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar ’khor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བར་འཁོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upāli</term>
                            <term type="definition">An arhat who was foremost among the Buddha’s disciples in his knowledge of the monastic code of
                                discipline (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vinaya</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-406">
                            <term>Vajra Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེའི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-407">
                            <term>Vajragarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje’i snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-408">
                            <term>Vajra­garbha­pramardin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje’i snying pos rab tu ’joms pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྙིང་པོས་རབ་ཏུ་འཇོམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Vajra­garbha­pramardin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-409">
                            <term>Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag na rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-410">
                            <term>Varuṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Varuṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-411">
                            <term>Varuṇadeva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu lha’i lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་ལྷའི་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Varuṇadeva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-412">
                            <term>Vikrānta­gāmin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par gnon pas gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་གནོན་པས་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Vikrānta­gāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-413">
                            <term>Vimala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri ma med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Vimala</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-414">
                            <term>Vimalakīrti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri ma med par grags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མ་མེད་པར་གྲགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalakīrti</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-415">
                            <term>Vimalatejas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med gzi brjid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མེད་གཟི་བརྗིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Vimalatejas</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-416">
                            <term>Vimatiprahāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid gnyis spong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་གཉིས་སྤོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimatiprahāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-417">
                            <term>Vīranandin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal dgyes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་དགྱེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Vīranandin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-418">
                            <term>Vīrasena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo’i sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོའི་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Vīrasena</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tathāgata mentioned here as one of the thirty-five buddhas of confession.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-419">
                            <term>Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Lord of Death, who judges the dead and rules over the hells.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-420">
                            <term>Youthful Candraprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ’od gzhon nur gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་འོད་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-421">
                            <term>Jālinīprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dra ba can gyi ’od</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Jālinīprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-422">
                            <term>Youthful Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nur gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A common epithet for the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-423">
                            <term>Prince Jeta’s Grove</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jetavana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The grove of Prince Jeta in Śrāvastī; the Buddha taught many of his discourses there, especially
                                during the rainy season retreat.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-424">
                            <term>river Ganges</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang gA’i klung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṅgānadī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The major river in North India and, according to Buddhist cosmology, one of the four sacred rivers
                                that flow through the southernmost continent of Jambudvīpa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-425">
                            <term>Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Capital city of Kośala and one of the major cities in India at the time of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-005-426">
                            <term>world of Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje’i ’jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yamaloka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The world of Yama, the Lord of Death.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-005-469" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>Three Sections</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po gsum pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ་གསུམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tri­skandhaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A confessional practice for mending breaches of a bodhisattva’s discipline.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>