<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<tei:TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surataparipṛcchāsūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">des pas zhus pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">དེས་པས་ཞུས་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “Surata’s Questions”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryasurataparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་དེས་པས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa des pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">《善順所問經》（大正藏：《大寶積經善順菩薩會第二十七》）</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-34">Translated by the UCSB Translation Group 2<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-203">Jed Forman</author>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-74">Ryan Damron</editor>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-51">James Duncan Gentry</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-203">Jed Forman</consultant>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-204">ErdeneBaatar Erdene-Ochir</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-202">Michael Ium</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-206">José I. Cabezón</consultant>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-289">Nathaniel Rich</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.6 <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into
                    modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <tei:p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial -
                            No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for
                            commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</tei:p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-043-008"/>
                <date>2021-10-13</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh71" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 71</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 181.a–193.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bandé Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="26">
                        <volume number="43" start-page="361" end-page="386"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11610" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2022-07-10T18:28:21.91Z" user="admin">10/07/2022 18:28:21</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2020-03-11T09:16:15.209Z" user="line-tofte">2.g</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2020-11-30T10:33:16.883Z" user="line-tofte">2.f</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2020-11-30T10:33:16.883Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2021-02-18T09:06:08.229Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2021-02-18T09:06:08.229Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2021-02-18T09:06:45.121Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2021-03-29T08:24:51.383Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.5" date-time="2021-03-29T08:24:51.383Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.6" date-time="2021-03-29T08:35:46.067Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.7" date-time="2021-09-03T12:21:08.986Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2021-09-09T06:55:50.983Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.8" date-time="2021-09-09T06:55:50.983Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.9" date-time="2021-09-10T09:27:04.775Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2021-09-10T09:28:08.837Z" user="line-tofte">2.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.10" date-time="2021-09-10T09:28:08.837Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.11" date-time="2021-09-16T13:04:06.053Z" user="andre">Auto
                    (update-titles)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2021-09-23T05:30:56.548Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.12" date-time="2021-09-23T05:30:56.548Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.13" date-time="2021-10-07T08:47:46.372Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2021-10-13T04:37:17.236Z" user="mike">1</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2021-10-13T04:37:17.236Z" user="mike">first published
                    version</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.1" date-time="2021-11-16T14:52:28.951Z" user="andre">Corrected Skt to:
                    anāthapiṇḍadasya ārāmaḥ</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.2" date-time="2022-01-13T19:47:54.069Z" user="celso">Added long english
                    title</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.3" date-time="2022-02-28T12:20:17.437Z" user="laura">Corrections to i.9 from reader and John</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.5" date-time="2022-06-27T10:06:48.1Z" user="admin">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.6" date-time="2022-07-10T18:28:18.083Z" user="john">Harmonization of trailer and colophon</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-1"/>
                <tei:p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title> follows Surata, a seemingly poor vagabond endowed with a wealth of
                    ethical virtue. The juxtaposition of Surata’s poverty with the abundance of his moral merits forms a central theme of the sūtra.
                    After being tested by the god Śakra, Surata finds a precious gem that he decides to give to the poorest person in the city. The
                    narrative’s irony ensues when Surata decides that King Prasenajit should receive the gem, since his ethical depravity vitiates his
                    material wealth. The shock of Surata’s decision occasions a valuable lesson on true wealth lying in moral integrity, to which the
                    Buddha himself attests upon his arrival midway through the sūtra. The sūtra concludes with King Prasenajit’s recognition of the
                    error of his ways and the Buddha’s prophecy of Surata’s coming awakening.</tei:p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-2"/>
                <tei:p tid="4">Translated, edited, and introduced by ErdeneBaatar Erdene-Ochir, Jed Forman, and Michael Ium, members of the UCSB
                    Buddhist Studies Translation Group 2. The translation team would like to acknowledge their indebtedness to Professor José Cabezón
                    for his ongoing support. We would also like to thank all of our teachers. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Sarvamaṅgalam</foreign>!</tei:p>
                <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-3"/>
                <tei:p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
                    Buddha.</tei:p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="6">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-introduction-1">
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-4"/>
                    <tei:p tid="8">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title>, the twenty-seventh sūtra in the <title xml:lang="en">
                            <term>Heap of
                                Jewels</term>
                        </title> section of the Kangyur, displays many of the common tropes of Mahāyāna literature, including the
                        Buddha’s unimaginably vast retinue, his performance of miracles, such as lights emanating from his body, and the conversion of
                        a previously stubborn interlocutor. Also typical of Mahāyāna sūtras, the main protagonist is the eponymous figure of the
                        sūtra, in lieu of the Buddha. <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title> thus mainly focuses on the story of Surata in a
                        narrative that can be conceptualized in six movements. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-5"/>
                    <tei:p tid="9">First, Surata, identified simply as a “poor city-dweller,” is tested by the god Śakra in Śrāvastī, the city where
                        the Buddha himself happens to be residing. With his divine eye, Śakra perceives Surata to be of impeccable moral character and
                        so decides to determine the limits of his resolve. Śakra magically creates several scenarios to tempt Surata to succumb to a
                        desire for power, wealth, and sexual gratification. But being inveterately moral and without desire, Surata resists each
                        temptation, and responds to them in eloquent verses that highlight the dangers of succumbing to each of them. At this point,
                        Śakra becomes deeply impressed with Surata.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-7"/>
                    <tei:p tid="10">In the second movement, Surata chances upon a precious gem. As a good bodhisattva, he resolves to give the jewel
                        to the poorest person in the city of Śrāvastī, the capital of Kośala. Announcing this publicly, the townsfolk predictably make
                        their case for why they are the poorest and therefore the most deserving of the gem. They are also predictably irritated when
                        Surata declares he has decided to give the gem to the king of Kośala, the famed King Prasenajit. Having gained the crowd’s
                        attention through his audacity, Surata gives a soliloquy on how true wealth lies not in possessions, but in virtue. Surata
                        therefore displays characteristic Mahāyāna skillful means, leveraging the townsfolk’s infatuation with the gem to impart a
                        moral lesson.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-8"/>
                    <tei:p tid="11">With the crowd in tow, Surata delivers the gem to King Prasenajit. It is a backhanded gesture since Surata offers
                        it with the explanation that the king is the poorest person in Śrāvastī. Insulted, the king asks Surata to explain how he
                        could possibly be the poorest. Surata proceeds to describe how the king’s political maneuverings and plundering have made him
                        bereft of moral virtue. His possessions mean nothing without the merit of good deeds, for without this, one is karmically
                        doomed to a miserable future. The king is both moved and angered by Surata’s exposition, and so remains unconvinced, asking if
                        there is anyone who can bear witness to Surata’s testament. This ushers in the fourth movement of the story. Surata says that
                        the Buddha will bear such witness. King Prasenajit therefore requests Surata to invite the Buddha, but Surata counters that
                        there is no need, for, being omniscient, the Buddha will arrive simply through Surata’s mental aspiration. The Buddha suddenly
                        bursts forth from the ground, accompanied by a dizzying number of holy beings. The Buddha attests to Surata’s summation of the
                        king’s wealth, and so Prasenajit is convinced. Surata suggests that the Buddha give a sermon, since it would be a shame for
                        him to come without doing so. After delivering his sermon, the Buddha and his retinue continue their upward trajectory by
                        flying into the sky. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-9"/>
                    <tei:p tid="12">In the fifth movement, Surata delivers a sermon of his own, describing the various meanings of
                            <distinct>retinue</distinct>. At the conclusion, the king again feels moved to contrition, offering bolts of cloth to the
                        rag-clad Surata. When Surata rejects the offer, the king requests Surata to at least walk upon the cloth. This is a great show
                        of respect because the feet are considered the most impure part of a person’s body. Thus to request someone to touch an object
                        with their feet suggests that even the lowest part of that person’s body confers immense blessing. Surata then requests that
                        the king give this cloth to the poor townsfolk, demonstrating that Surata did not trade their welfare solely to create an
                        opportunity to teach the Dharma; in lieu of the gem, he was still able to offer them something of value in the end.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-10"/>
                    <tei:p tid="13">The sixth and final movement of the story reads somewhat like an epilogue. Sometime later, King Prasenajit, his
                        family, and his royal attendants accompany Surata to visit the Buddha. Śakra emanates a grand throne for the Buddha and his
                        retinue with the requisite fanfare. Some of the other gods question why Surata, out of place in his ragged garments, is in
                        attendance. Śakra’s earlier respect for Surata resurfaces when he comes to Surata’s defense by admonishing the other gods for
                        their failure to realize how special Surata is. As Śakra foreshadows, the Buddha concludes the sūtra by predicting Surata’s
                        awakening, to the grand jubilation of all.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-11"/>
                    <tei:p tid="14">Surata is a common personal name in Buddhist literature, but no other text appears to mention a renunciate
                        bodhisattva who might be identifiable as the Surata of this text. In contrast, the prominent role in this narrative of
                        Prasenajit, king of Kośala, a well-known figure in Buddhist literature, is noteworthy. It is believed that Prasenajit was born
                        in the same year as Siddhārtha, the future Buddha, and it is possible, given the close geographical and political ties between
                        Kośala and the Śākya kingdom, that Prasenajit and the Śākya prince Siddhārtha moved in the same royal circles and knew each
                        other from an early age. Prasenajit is generally depicted as a dedicated, lifelong patron of the Buddha with an exemplary
                        degree of devotion to him. This devotion is clearly demonstrated in Prasenajit’s most famous deed: his fashioning of a
                        sandalwood image of Śākyamuni—perhaps the earliest record of any image of the Buddha—to soothe his longing and devotion when
                        the Buddha was away from Śrāvastī. Prasenajit is also a frequent interlocuter in Buddhist sūtras, presenting the questions to
                        Śākyamuni that elicit his sermons. For his role in Buddhist sūtras and his acts of patronage and devotion, Prasenajit is often
                        held up as the model of Buddhist kingship. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-12"/>
                    <tei:p tid="15">This general depiction of Prasenajit in Buddhist literature makes his role in <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s
                            Questions</title> a curious one. Here he is described as a rapacious and maniacal tyrant who steals the wealth of his
                        people and inflicts needless suffering upon them. It is only through Surata’s challenge and the Buddha’s subsequent
                        chastisement that Prasenajit realizes his faults as a king and awakens his devotion to the Buddha and his community. That this
                        narrative stands somewhat at odds with Prasenajit’s general status in Buddhist literature may simply demonstrate the
                        malleability of common Buddhist narratives for the sake of expediency in articulating the ethical or doctrinal message of a
                        given scriptural discourse. Possibly, too, in describing what seems to be his first meeting with the Buddha following the
                        latter’s awakening, the text could be read as indicating that Prasenajit’s views on how best to wield royal power had, prior
                        to that first encounter with Surata’s challenge as a prelude, been fiercer and more autocratic than is suggested in other
                        accounts of his subsequent doings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-13"> A further hint that leaves room for such
                            speculation is the traditional narrative according to which the Buddha was not invited to Śrāvastī either by King
                            Prasenajit or by any other member of the ruling family, but instead by the wealthy merchant Anāthapiṇḍada, who then had to
                            pay Prasenajit’s son Prince Jeta a huge sum of money for land on which to build a vihāra to accommodate the Buddha and his
                            followers. This was in stark contrast to the insistent invitations, welcome, patronage, and provision of resources
                            extended to the Buddha by Bimbisara, king of Magadha. </note> If this is an account of Prasenajit’s first meeting with the
                        Buddha, however, it should be noted that it is a quite different one from the classic account related in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅghabhedavastu</title> (Toh 1 chapter 17<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh1-17.html"/>),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-14"> Degé Kangyur
                            vol. 4 (’dul ba, nga) F.89.b et seq. See Miller et al., <title xml:lang="en">The Chapter on Schisms in the
                                Saṅgha</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh1-17.html"/>, 84000: Translating the
                            Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</note> in its standalone derivative the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhiniṣkramanasūtra</title> (Toh 301<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh301.html"/>), and in
                        the Pali <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dahara-sutta</title> (SN 3.1). This unique perspective on the figure of Prasenajit thus
                        counts among the numerous ways <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title> makes a significant contribution to our
                        understanding of Buddhist literature.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-15"/>
                    <tei:p tid="16">In addition to the Tibetan translation found in various Kangyurs, three Chinese translations of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surataparipṛcchā</title> are presently available. Of the two earlier versions, the first, translated by
                        Bai Yan in the mid-third century<!--Cao Wei (220–265 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>)-->, is titled <title xml:lang="zh">佛說須賴經</title> (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Fo shuo xulai jing</title>, Taishō 328), and
                        the second, translated by Zhi Shilun in 373 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>, has the title <title xml:lang="zh">須賴經</title>
                        (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Xu lai jing</title>, Taishō 329). The attributions and dates of these two early translations, given here from the standard catalogs, remain disputed by scholars. A later version was translated in the sixth century by
                        Bodhiruci under the title <title xml:lang="zh">善順菩薩會</title> (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Shanshun pusa hui</title>), which is
                        one title (number 27) among the 49 texts included under Taishō 310, the Ratnakūṭa. The latter translation by Bodhiruci served
                        as the basis for the English translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surataparipṛcchā</title> published by Garma C. C.
                        Chang and his team in 1983. There are marked differences between Bodhiruci’s translation and the Tibetan versions used in the
                        translation of this sūtra that follows here, which are closer to the two earlier versions. These differences are reflected in
                        Chang’s English translation. The final, sixth movement is not found in the Chinese version, and the order of events varies. In
                        the sequence from the Tibetan translation reported above, the narrative continues after the Buddha has given his sermon on the
                        meanings of <distinct>retinue</distinct>; the Chinese version of the sūtra, however, concludes at this point. The contents of
                        the Buddha’s sermon in the fourth movement also vary widely between the two versions: in the Chinese, the Buddha discusses the
                        thirty-two practices that good Mahāyāna adherents must follow, while in the Tibetan, the Buddha expounds six different sets of
                        four, each tetrad communicating seemingly disconnected aspects of Buddhist practice. Other differences are minor but
                        noteworthy: in the Tibetan version, for instance, Surata chances upon a precious gem, and in the Chinese, he finds a golden
                        bell. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-16"/>
                    <tei:p tid="17">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title> is only mentioned by name in one work of the Tengyur, an anthology
                        titled <title xml:lang="en">Compendium of Sūtras on the Steps of Meditation</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāvanā­krama­sūtra­samuccaya</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsgom pa’i rim pa mdo kun las btus pa</title>). The work
                        cites two interesting parts of the sūtra, both of which are in verse. The first reads:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-17"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="18">
                            <l>When the seeds are bitter,</l>
                            <l>They will bear bitter fruit.</l>
                            <l>When the seeds are sweet,</l>
                            <l>They will bear sweet fruit.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-18"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="19">
                            <l>Applying this example,</l>
                            <l>A wise person understands</l>
                            <l>The bitterness of the ripening of sins</l>
                            <l>And the sweetness of the fruits of white deeds. [F.130.b]</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-19"/>
                    <tei:p tid="20">This verse is given in the midst of several other citations describing the importance of keeping one’s ethics in
                        order to escape the suffering of saṃsāra. The second selection is cited as an example of how to go to refuge to the Three
                        Jewels—the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-20"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="21">
                            <l>You delight in eliminating desire, hatred, and delusion;</l>
                            <l>Your mind is peaceful and impartial, yet compassionate;</l>
                            <l>You speak truthfully and know the ultimate;</l>
                            <l>Thus, I pay homage to you, who liberates all three realms! [F.137.b]</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-21"/>
                    <tei:p tid="22">The context of these passages becomes clear in the sūtra translated below. However, the decision to isolate these
                        passages and place them in a mélange of other such passages from other sūtras suggests they may have been recognized as
                        standalone aphorisms that were well-known in the compiler’s contemporary Buddhist community and worthy of record.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-22"/>
                    <tei:p tid="23">There is no surviving Sanskrit witness to <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title>. It was translated into
                        Tibetan by a group of translators, including the famous translator Bandé Yeshé Dé, no later than the early ninth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. The text is recorded in both the Denkarma and the Phangthangma—both early catalogs of Tibetan
                        translations. The translation below relies primarily on the Degé (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</title>) edition of the
                        text, but other editions included in the Comparative Edition of the Kangyur (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ ’gyur dpe bsdur
                            ma</title>) as well as the Stok Palace (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang</title>) edition of the Kangyur were
                        consulted, particularly when the Degé seemed to contain errors or nonintuitive readings. Chang’s English translation of the
                        Chinese version of this text—which, as described above, is markedly different from the Tibetan—was also consulted for
                        comparison.</tei:p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="24"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="25">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="26">Surata’s Questions</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-section-1">
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-25"/>
                    <tei:p tid="30">
                        <ref cRef="F.181.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-295"/> Homage to all the buddhas and
                        bodhisattvas!</tei:p>
                    <lb/>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-26"/>
                    <tei:p tid="31">Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling in Śrāvastī, in Prince Jeta’s Grove at Anāthapiṇḍada’s
                        Park, together with a great monastic assembly of one thousand two hundred and fifty monks and with thirty-two thousand
                        bodhisattvas. He was venerated, revered, honored, and worshiped by the fourfold community, as well as by the king, ministers,
                        townsfolk, and citizens.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-27"/>
                    <tei:p tid="32">At that time in Śrāvastī there lived a poor city-dweller named Surata. He had unshakable faith in the Buddha,
                        unshakable faith in the Dharma, and unshakable faith in the Saṅgha. He held to the five basic precepts and adhered to the ten
                        virtuous actions. Being kind, he was equanimous toward all sentient beings. Being compassionate, he was indefatigable. Being
                        joyful, he reveled in and longed for the bliss of Dharma. Being impartial, he was unmoved by happiness or suffering. He was
                        dedicated to the pursuit of unsurpassable, perfect awakening, and was perfected through previous practice. Through skillful
                        means, he brought sentient beings to full maturity, despite being considered poor.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-28"/>
                    <tei:p tid="33">Śakra, lord of the gods, beheld the poor city-dweller Surata with his divine eye, whose clarity surpasses any
                        human’s. Śakra perceived that he had few desires, that he was content, that he had ethical discipline and was morally upright,
                        that his mind was unperturbed, that he always wore a smile, that he did not judge others for their mistakes, <ref cRef="F.181.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-296"/> that he cared for the mental welfare of all sentient beings,
                        that he was not covetous, that he acted mindfully, that he was content, easily fulfilled, and easily sated, that he had good
                        intentions, that he was not deceitful, that he was not conceited, that he was eloquent, that he was respectful, that he
                        continually observed the eight precepts, that he carried a bowl made of leaves in his hands, that he slept on a grass mat,
                        that he wore tattered garments, that he would not take things he chanced upon, that he would share his food no matter its
                        quality, that he had regard for the Tathāgata at all times, that he wanted to hear the Dharma, that he was inspired by various
                        parables, and that when sentient beings saw him, they were happy.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-29"/>
                    <tei:p tid="34">Seeing this, Śakra, lord of the gods, thought to himself, “Let me examine whether this poor city-dweller’s moral
                        resolve is firm.” He then emanated a crowd of people who abused and rebuked the poor city-dweller Surata with offensive words.
                        Surata patiently tolerated their threats, even as they brandished clumps of earth, sticks, and blades; he was neither
                        irritated, nor gave rise to malicious thoughts.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-30"/>
                    <tei:p tid="35">Śakra, lord of the gods, then emanated another crowd in front of Surata. With kind words, they said to him, “We
                        would like to help you. If you wish, we will exterminate all the enemies who threaten you.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-31"/>
                    <tei:p tid="36">“Friends, don’t say such things!” replied Surata. “Even if those people were to cut my body into a hundred pieces,
                        I still would not think badly of them. Friends, in the various worlds, there are two types of beings, the virtuous and the
                        nonvirtuous. The virtuous ones have happy rebirths, and the nonvirtuous ones have miserable rebirths. Therefore, since I don’t
                        even want to get angry with them, how could I harm them physically?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-32"/>
                    <tei:p tid="37">Surata then spoke these verses:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-33"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>“When the seeds are bitter,</l>
                        <l>They will bear bitter fruit. <ref cRef="F.182.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-297"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>When the seeds are sweet,</l>
                        <l>They will bear sweet fruit.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-34"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>“Applying this analogy,</l>
                        <l>A wise person understands</l>
                        <l>The bitterness of the ripening of sins</l>
                        <l>And the sweetness of the fruits of white deeds.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-35"> That is, virtuous
                                deeds.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-36"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>“You should never commit the three kinds of sins</l>
                        <l>With your body, speech, or mind!</l>
                        <l>And when others commit them,</l>
                        <l>The wise should not rejoice!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-37"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>“You should always perform the three white deeds</l>
                        <l>With your body, speech, and mind!</l>
                        <l>And when others perform virtues, </l>
                        <l>You should rejoice in them!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-38"/>
                    <tei:p tid="42">Then, on another occasion, Śakra, lord of the gods, showed Surata a heap of jewels and gold and said, “Surata, use
                        these to make donations and make merit! Get some clothes and jewelry! Why should you be poor and wretched?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-39"/>
                    <tei:p tid="43">“Friends,”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-40"> “Friends” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">grogs
                                po dag</foreign>) is clearly in the plural in the Tibetan, but it is unclear whom Surata is addressing.</note> said
                        Surata, “because I performed evil deeds in the past toward sentient beings with my body, speech, and mind, I am now considered
                        poor. Therefore, I don’t want to take what is not given to me.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-41"/>
                    <tei:p tid="44">“Surata, now is the time to be living happily!” Śakra insisted. “Why are you thinking of the world
                        beyond?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-42"/>
                    <tei:p tid="45">“Friend,” replied Surata, “living for the sake of this life is the way of childish beings. The wise live for the
                        sake of their next life. Those who are possessed by desire, possessed by hatred, possessed by delusion, and possessed by lust
                        take what is not given to them, whereas the wise are not covetous. Those who live for the sake of hoarding take what is not
                        given to them, whereas the wise do not hoard. Those who hold concepts of ‘mine’ and who are possessive take what is not given
                        to them, whereas the wise do not hold concepts of ‘mine’ and are not possessive. Those who focus on their bodies and vitality
                        take what is not given to them, whereas the wise do not focus on their bodies and vitality. <ref cRef="F.182.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-298"/> Those who are not satisfied and not contented take what is not given to them, whereas the
                        wise know satisfaction and contentment. Those who live impurely take what is not given to them, whereas the wise live purely.
                        Those who do not have insight into karma take what is not given to them, whereas the wise have insight into karma. Those who
                        live for the sake of harming others take what is not given to them, whereas the wise live for the sake of not harming others.
                        Those who do not have loving attitudes take what is not given to them, whereas the wise have loving attitudes. Those whose
                        minds are polluted by the four wrong views take what is not given to them, whereas the minds of the wise are not wrong.
                        Moreover, may the poor heed these verses!</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-43"/>
                    <lg tid="46">
                        <l>“The learned have explained</l>
                        <l>That those with tens of billions of treasures</l>
                        <l>But who refuse to give</l>
                        <l>Are poor in this world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-44"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>“The insightful have explained</l>
                        <l>That those without even porridge to eat</l>
                        <l>But who continue to give</l>
                        <l>Are wealthy in this world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-45"/>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>“Noble ones are without sin, </l>
                        <l>And thus are always beautiful.</l>
                        <l>Childish beings commit sins</l>
                        <l>And so are ugly, even adorned with ornaments.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-46"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>“What the wise revile with ease</l>
                        <l>The childish praise instead.</l>
                        <l>The childish praise sin;</l>
                        <l>Sin is what the wise condemn.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-47"/>
                    <tei:p tid="50">Then, on another occasion, Śakra, lord of the gods, emanated another person who brought a pile of gold to Surata
                        and said, “Hey Surata, I’ve brought this gold for you. I’m in the midst of a dispute with someone and only you can act as my
                        witness. You need to be my witness!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-48"/>
                    <tei:p tid="51">Surata replied, “Give it up, my friend! Don’t say that! I don’t want to lie. My friend, lying would deceive not
                        only myself and others, but the noble ones as well. Lying ruins one’s reputation. Lying makes one untrustworthy and
                        unpleasant. <ref cRef="F.183.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-299"/> Lying makes one despicable. Lying torments one’s
                        mind. My friend, lying gives one bad breath. Lying makes one’s body feeble. Lying makes one despised by the gods. My friend,
                        lying steals away one’s roots of virtue. Lying dulls one’s memory. Lying blocks one’s path to fortunate rebirths. My friend,
                        noble ones do not engage in lying.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-49"> This translation follows the reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtson par mi bya ba</foreign> attested in the Yongle, Kangxi, Narthang, and Lhasa
                            versions of the text. The Degé reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btson par mi bya ba</foreign>. </note> Lying
                        makes one’s speech distasteful among truthful people. Lying is criticized by the wise. Lying is the root of all sins. Lying
                        severs the fulfillment of one’s religious observances at the root. Lying is the root of all miserable rebirths.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-50"/>
                    <tei:p tid="52">The poor city-dweller Surata then spoke these verses:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-51"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>“From the mouths of liars</l>
                        <l>Emerges foul breath.</l>
                        <l>Lying eliminates all of one’s prior white deeds,</l>
                        <l>Akin to destroying a monastery.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-52"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“Deluded people dishearten themselves</l>
                        <l>As well as deities and noble beings.</l>
                        <l>A person who tells lies</l>
                        <l>Will always be suspect.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-53"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“Telling a lie</l>
                        <l>Is the root of all sins.</l>
                        <l>It severs the root of ascetic practices,</l>
                        <l>And is said to be the path to miserable rebirths.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-54"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“Even if you were to offer me gold</l>
                        <l>Enough to fill Jambudvīpa,</l>
                        <l>To protect the Dharma,</l>
                        <l>I would never tell a lie.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-55"/>
                    <tei:p tid="57">Unable to get Surata to lie, the person emanated by Śakra went away.</tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="58">Then Śakra, lord of the gods, said to the goddess Sunlight and the asura Śacī,</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-57"/>
                    <tei:p tid="59">“You two go test whether this practitioner of religious observances and austerities indulges in sensual
                        gratification or if he truly doesn’t strive for pleasure!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-58"/>
                    <tei:p tid="60">At daybreak, the asura Śacī and the goddess Sunlight went to where Surata was staying and spoke to him sweetly,
                        “Wake up, Surata! <ref cRef="F.183.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-300"/> We’re here to serve you. Surata, behold our
                        perfect bodies! Behold the curves, luster, and shapeliness of our bodies. Behold our bodies, anointed with unguents and
                        adorned with ornaments, garments, and accessories! Behold how we exude the bloom of youth! Surata, behold our well-formed,
                        perfect bodies, the kind that will please you.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-59"/>
                    <tei:p tid="61">Seeing them, Surata said, “You two serve those in hell, the realms of animals, and Yama’s realm, but not those in
                        the god or human realms. I see your bodies as illusory and dream-like. I see your bodies as being like foam, bubbles, and
                        mirages. I see your bodies, anointed with sandalwood ointment, as covered in soggy flesh. I see your ornaments and garments as
                        illusions that deceive the eyes. I see your youthfulness as impermanent and subject to change. Since I see all that to be
                        meritless, I feel no attraction to you. You two serve those whose minds are like monkeys and those whose minds are like
                        women’s, but you can’t serve those whose minds are protected by mindfulness. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-60"/>
                    <tei:p tid="62">“Sisters, those who rely on desire are ugly. Those who rely on desire smell foul. Those who rely on desire are
                        rotten. Those who rely on desire suffer greatly. Those who rely on desire are barred from all happiness. Those who rely on
                        desire will frequent the hells, animal realms, and Yama’s realm. Those who rely on desire will remain in miserable rebirths.
                        Those who rely on desire will resort to fighting, disputing, and quarreling. Those who rely on desire will have to live in
                        disharmony and become trapped. Those who rely on desire develop misconceptions. <ref cRef="F.184.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-301"/> Those who rely on desire will maintain their propensities for continued existence.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-61"> The Stok Palace version has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sred
                                pa</foreign> here, which could be read as “attachment” or “craving.” The Degé reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid pa</foreign>. </note> Those who rely on desire are very deluded, completely deluded, and thoroughly
                        deluded. Those who rely on desire are fully oppressed, very oppressed, and extremely oppressed. Those who rely on desire are
                        thoroughly tormented, very tormented, and entirely tormented. Those who rely on desire pursue nonvirtue and degrade their
                        virtue. Those who rely on desire plant the roots of nonvirtue. Those who rely on desire are completely trapped in an
                        impenetrable fog of nonvirtue. Those who rely on desire are intimate with rākṣasīs, with those who have ugly bodies, and with
                        piśācīs. Those who rely on desire will have relations with cattle, donkeys, dogs, pigs, camels, elephants, horses, sheep, and
                        foxes. Those who rely on desire will rely on degenerate people. Those who rely on desire will rely on people who entirely
                        forsake discipline, study, and acts of generosity. Those who rely on desire forsake religious observances and ascetic
                        practices. Those who rely on desire are completely careless. Those who rely on desire greatly increase their mental
                        afflictions. Those who rely on desire create many obstacles.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-62"/>
                    <tei:p tid="63">The poor city-dweller Surata then spoke these verses:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-63"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“Desire tarnishes the impermanent as permanent;</l>
                        <l>Desire completely destroys happiness with suffering;</l>
                        <l>Desire makes miserable realms your home.</l>
                        <l>Those with deluded minds always rely on desire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-64"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>“Due to desire, the quarrelsome become unhappy and evil.</l>
                        <l>They are trapped in contentiousness and disharmony;</l>
                        <l>They are a fertile ground for misconceptions;</l>
                        <l>Their craving increases and happiness vanishes.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-65"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“Due to desire, they become very deluded, extremely deluded, and thoroughly deluded;</l>
                        <l>They are constantly oppressed and experience harm;</l>
                        <l>They are thoroughly tormented, very tormented, and entirely tormented; <ref cRef="F.184.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-302"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And they engage in evil and squander their virtue.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-66"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“Desire is the root of all nonvirtue.</l>
                        <l>Relying on desire is like an impenetrable fog;</l>
                        <l>Relying on desire, one will be intimate</l>
                        <l>With piśācīs, rākṣasīs, and ugly women.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-67"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>“Due to desire, one even has relations</l>
                        <l>With cattle, donkeys, horses,</l>
                        <l>Pigs, dogs, foxes, camels, elephants, and sheep.</l>
                        <l>Thus, holy beings abandon desire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-68"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“Desire ruins discipline, study, and acts of generosity</l>
                        <l>As well as ascetic practice and religious observance;</l>
                        <l>Due to desire, one is always careless, and faults increase.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, those who wish for liberation always reject women.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-69"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l>“Even if the world were filled</l>
                        <l>With radiant beauties like you,</l>
                        <l>Being stable in good qualities, my focused mind</l>
                        <l>Would never be swayed toward desire.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-70"/>
                    <tei:p tid="71">The asura Śacī and the goddess Sunlight then went back to Śakra, lord of the gods, and spoke this verse:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-71"/>
                    <lg tid="72">
                        <l>“Surata perceives unfailingly</l>
                        <l>The true deficiencies of women.</l>
                        <l>The more he rejects sense objects,</l>
                        <l>The less he has any desire for them.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-72"/>
                    <tei:p tid="73">Thereupon Śakra, lord of the gods, came to the poor city-dweller Surata and spoke this verse:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-73"/>
                    <lg tid="74">
                        <l>“O righteous Surata, what is it you desire?</l>
                        <l>Keeper of religious observances, tell me truthfully!</l>
                        <l>Do you want to become Sūrya, Candra, or Indra,</l>
                        <l>Or Brahmā, or a divine king?”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-74"/>
                    <tei:p tid="75">Surata responded:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-75"/>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>“What wise person would want to become any of those mighty great beings,</l>
                        <l>Whether it is Sūrya, Candra, or even Śakra,</l>
                        <l>Brahmā, a divine king, or anyone else,</l>
                        <l>Seeing that their frolicking is impermanent and unstable?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-76"/>
                    <lg tid="77">
                        <l>“I am resolved, in thought and deed,</l>
                        <l>To obtain that which is birthless, ageless, deathless,</l>
                        <l>And beyond judgments of beauty and ugliness—</l>
                        <l>That is called ‘becoming a buddha who liberates beings.’ ”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-77"/>
                    <tei:p tid="78">Śakra said: </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-78"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>“I rejoice in your beneficent words; <ref cRef="F.185.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-303"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>May you completely accomplish your wishes!</l>
                        <l>Having swiftly subjugated the entire horde of māras,</l>
                        <l>May you attain awakening like the conqueror Śākyasiṃha!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-79"/>
                    <tei:p tid="80">On another occasion, the poor city-dweller Surata found a priceless and precious gem. He thought to himself,
                        “Assuredly, I should give this precious gem, the finest in Jambudvīpa, to the poorest person in Śrāvastī.” He went to the city
                        and announced, “I will give this gem to the poorest among you.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-80"/>
                    <tei:p tid="81">A crowd of neglected poor people gathered there and called out, “We are poor, so give it to us!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="82">“You are not poor!” countered Surata. “But there is someone else in Śrāvastī who is exceedingly poor, so I will
                        give it to that person.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-82"/>
                    <tei:p tid="83">The crowd asked, “Who?” </tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="84">“It is King Prasenajit,” replied Surata.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-84"/>
                    <tei:p tid="85">“Don’t say that!” the crowd retorted. “King Prasenajit is rich and wealthy with vast resources, whereas we are
                        poor and neglected.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-85"/>
                    <tei:p tid="86">Surata responded:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-86"/>
                    <lg tid="87">
                        <l>“What is the use of so much wealth?</l>
                        <l>Like nāgas unsatisfied with what’s in the ocean,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-87"> The ocean is said to be the
                                source of precious jewels. So even though the nāgas who live there have extensive access to riches, they still are not
                                satisfied.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Those for whom nothing is ever enough</l>
                        <l>Are unrestrained and thus truly poor.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-88"/>
                    <lg tid="88">
                        <l>“Those deluded ones,</l>
                        <l>Whose desires intensify</l>
                        <l>And whose minds are tormented,</l>
                        <l>Are poor in both this life and the next.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-89"/>
                    <tei:p tid="89">Then the poor city-dweller Surata, carrying the precious gem and accompanied by the crowd, went to where King
                        Prasenajit was administering his royal duties.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-90"/>
                    <tei:p tid="90">At that time, as a penalty for some minor infractions, King Prasenajit had seized the possessions of some five
                        hundred eminent merchants and householders who were from good families.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-91"/>
                    <tei:p tid="91">The poor city-dweller Surata offered the king the precious gem and said, “Great king, I’ve found this priceless
                        and precious gem whose worth matches that of all Jambudvīpa, <ref cRef="F.185.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-304"/>
                        and I thought that I would give it to the poorest person in Śrāvastī. I think you are the poorest among everyone here.
                        Therefore, O King, please accept it!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-92"/>
                    <tei:p tid="92">Thereupon King Prasenajit became nervous and embarrassed, and he asked the poor city-dweller Surata, “Surata, how
                        am I even poorer than you?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="93">Surata replied, “O Your Majesty, it is true. You are poorer than me.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-94"/>
                    <tei:p tid="94">“In what way am I poor?” asked the king.</tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="95">Surata then spoke these verses:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-96"/>
                    <lg tid="96">
                        <l>“When someone has increasingly intense desires, is not contented with his own possessions,</l>
                        <l>Disturbs the kingdom by causing harm, forsakes even himself,</l>
                        <l>Fails to protect the people in his kingdom, and holds in high esteem those of meager quality,</l>
                        <l>Then those intent on the Dharma will think him poor.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-97"/>
                    <lg tid="97">
                        <l>“When someone practices loving kindness, is not harsh to sentient beings,</l>
                        <l>Is always content with the bare necessities, has no desire,</l>
                        <l>Is constantly compassionate when he sees the destitute, and does not despise them,</l>
                        <l>Then he is rich, wealthy, and immensely affluent, enjoys the treasures of faith, and so forth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-98"/>
                    <lg tid="98">
                        <l>“Know that when someone possesses immense power over the people here, but does not protect the Dharma;</l>
                        <l>When he knows that lowly people are tormented by suffering, yet punishes them further;</l>
                        <l>When he delights in focusing on what’s in front of him with his mistresses, but has no regard for the world beyond,</l>
                        <l>Then he does not protect the Dharma—he is abjectly poor and the lowest of people!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-99"/>
                    <lg tid="99">
                        <l>“Those whose minds are stainless due to their faith, who remain unshakably ethical,</l>
                        <l>Who always know shame and propriety, who uphold learning and enjoy giving,</l>
                        <l>Who have perfected wisdom, are intelligent, and have concern for all beings</l>
                        <l>Never fall into poverty and are worthy of veneration by those intent upon the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-100"/>
                    <lg tid="100">
                        <l>“Those <ref cRef="F.186.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-305"/> who are attached to wealth, enjoy pleasures, and are
                            miserly,</l>
                        <l>Who take their own body and life to heart, but never bother with what is essential—</l>
                        <l>Those whose minds are crazed and frantic, like a rampaging elephant,</l>
                        <l>And who are unmindful—Your Majesty, all of them fall into poverty.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-101"/>
                    <lg tid="101">
                        <l>“Those who have great devotion to the stainless Three Jewels,</l>
                        <l>Who are always skillful at using what’s essential from their body, life, and wealth—</l>
                        <l>Those who are not covetous, malicious, foolish, or prideful,</l>
                        <l>And those who are adorned with the Dharma—Your Majesty, all of them are wealthy and holy beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-102"/>
                    <lg tid="102">
                        <l>“Your Majesty, a wildfire is never satisfied with just burning the dry bark in a forest.</l>
                        <l>Your Majesty, the ocean is never satisfied with just the water it receives from rivers.</l>
                        <l>Likewise, the sun and moon are never satisfied with their progressions in the sky.</l>
                        <l>Due to craving, a king is never content with his wealth, and so is brought to ruin.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-103"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>“Once grass has been incinerated by fire, it will not burn again.</l>
                        <l>Similarly, the wise are never content with their wisdom and so do not blaze with afflictions.</l>
                        <l>Since, like a water drop, a kingdom is unstable and prone to destruction,</l>
                        <l>Who would seek out such a kingdom that is a wellspring of harm and smothers virtue?”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-104"/>
                    <tei:p tid="104">King Prasenajit became agitated and demanded of the poor city-dweller Surata, “Surata, who could attest, on your
                        behalf, that I am poor and you are rich?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-105"/>
                    <tei:p tid="105">“Your Majesty,” replied Surata, “haven’t you heard that the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha is
                        dwelling here in Śrāvastī?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="106">“I’ve heard this, but have yet to see him,” said the king.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-107"/>
                    <tei:p tid="107">“Your Majesty, he has become the eye for all beings, including the gods!” said Surata. “He has become the
                        authority. He could attest on my behalf.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:p tid="108">“Go invite the Tathāgata and I will hear what he has to say,” said the king.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-109"/>
                    <tei:p tid="109">Surata replied:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-110"/>
                    <lg tid="110">
                        <l>“One need not send this humble servant,</l>
                        <l>Nor any other envoy for the Teacher, <ref cRef="F.186.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-306"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>For when I think of him,</l>
                        <l>He will know and come hither.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-111"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>“In this world and beyond,</l>
                        <l>There is nothing unknown to him.</l>
                        <l>Knowing my thoughts,</l>
                        <l>The Guide will come hither.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-112"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>“Because of his compassion toward sentient beings,</l>
                        <l>He does not fall prey to conceit.</l>
                        <l>Because he is ever attentive to sentient beings,</l>
                        <l>He will come hither, even from afar.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-113"/>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>“O great king, in your great kindness,</l>
                        <l>Please now do what I ask!</l>
                        <l>Please seek a statement of truth </l>
                        <l>From the Teacher who is coming here!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-114"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“Please prepare</l>
                        <l>Flowers, incense, flower garlands,</l>
                        <l>Victory banners, parasols, ointments, and cymbals—</l>
                        <l>The Guide is coming.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-115"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>Surata, with hands joined together,</l>
                        <l>Uncovered one shoulder, </l>
                        <l>Knelt down on the ground,</l>
                        <l>And said these words:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-116"/>
                    <lg tid="116">
                        <l>“If you are truly omniscient,</l>
                        <l>Then you should know what I am thinking.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, O Sage, please come before me</l>
                        <l>By the truth of my words!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-117"/>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>As soon as these words were spoken,</l>
                        <l>The earth shook violently.</l>
                        <l>The ground burst open,</l>
                        <l>And the Tathāgata emerged.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-118"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>He was surrounded by five hundred śrāvakas,</l>
                        <l>Who possessed miraculous powers,</l>
                        <l>And was escorted </l>
                        <l>By twelve hundred bodhisattvas,</l>
                        <l>As well as protectors, gods, nāgas,</l>
                        <l>And the gods Śakra and Brahmā.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-119"/>
                    <lg tid="119">
                        <l>When they saw these miracles,</l>
                        <l>The people were astonished.</l>
                        <l>The king, together with his ministers and army,</l>
                        <l>Prostrated at the Teacher’s feet.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-120"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>Then thousands of other living beings</l>
                        <l>Also made offerings to the Teacher.</l>
                        <l>Making offerings to the perfect Buddha,</l>
                        <l>They mentally prostrated as well, for the sake of awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-121"/>
                    <tei:p tid="121">Thereupon the poor city-dweller Surata paid homage by touching his head to the Bhagavān’s feet and
                        circumambulated him seven times. Then he said, “Bhagavān, while wandering about Śrāvastī, <ref cRef="F.187.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-307"/> I found a priceless, precious gem. I decided to give it to the poorest person in Śrāvastī.
                        I determined that King Prasenajit is the poorest, because no matter how much he plunders, he is never satisfied; he seeks
                        riches again and again, yet it is never enough. He is never satisfied with the possessions of others; he harms those already
                        suffering and quickly uproots the happiness of others. He leads the poor to ruin and subjugates the wealthy. He has gone
                        completely mad! Having determined that he is completely bound by the wealth of his kingdom and by his cravings, I offered him
                        the gem but he didn’t accept it. He asked, ‘Who could attest, on your behalf, that I am poor and you are rich?’ Therefore, O
                        Bhagavān—who is impartial to all sentient beings, who never turns away from them, and who is without obstinacy, impurity, and
                        enmity—Bhagavān, please tell us clearly if what I have said is true!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-122"/>
                    <tei:p tid="122">The Bhagavān then said, “Great king, you think yourself rich based on the resources of your kingdom that you have
                        acquired in this life, such as gold, jewels, pearls, lapis lazuli, conch shells, crystals, corals, gold powder, silver,
                        horses, elephants, chariots, infantry, cavalry, storehouses, and treasuries. Great king, Surata thinks himself rich based on
                        his generosity, discipline, self-restraint, forbearance, gentleness,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-123"> Though
                            this is describing a quality of Surata, “gentleness” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">des pa</foreign>) here
                            happens to be the same word for his name.</note> ethical discipline, religious observances, ascetic practices,
                        conscientiousness, virtuous practices, frugality, kindness, compassion, joy, equanimity, <ref cRef="F.187.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-308"/> devotion to the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha, faith, ethical discipline, learning, acts of
                        generosity, wisdom, sense of shame, modesty, stability, and vows. Great king, suppose that all the people under your authority
                        became wealthy like you. Even added together, the mound of their collective merit could not match one hundredth the merit that
                        Surata accumulates by walking seven steps with his discipline, learning, religious observance, ascetic practices, and
                        conscientiousness alone. It is incomparable.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-124"/>
                    <tei:p tid="123">“Bhagavān,” said Prasenajit, “finding people like him, with such vast qualities, living in our land is a great
                        discovery!” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-125"/>
                    <tei:p tid="124">The Bhagavān replied, “Great king, there are many people with these vast qualities in your land.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-126"/>
                    <tei:p tid="125">King Prasenajit then spoke these verses to Surata:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-127"/>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>“With your words, you have certainly eliminated my pride;</l>
                        <l>Therefore, Surata, you are my second teacher!</l>
                        <l>Let me give you my entire kingdom and my armies.</l>
                        <l>Make me your disciple and teach me!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-128"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>“I have been deceived by my pride for a long time,</l>
                        <l>And have been surrounded and coddled by wicked companions.</l>
                        <l>Since I have heard this Dharma from you, Surata,</l>
                        <l>I will restrain myself and behave in accordance with the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-129"/>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“For the sake of wealth I have punished </l>
                        <l>These five hundred householders.</l>
                        <l>From now on I will no longer do this;</l>
                        <l>Let me leave them alone and make them comfortable.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-130"/>
                    <lg tid="129">
                        <l>“Let these five hundred who are now free</l>
                        <l>Also develop deep respect for Surata.</l>
                        <l>May they never fatigue, and without distraction,</l>
                        <l>May they aspire for happiness and the state of omniscience!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-131"/>
                    <lg tid="130">
                        <l>“Surata, you spoke well when you said,</l>
                        <l>‘I am not poor. You are poor.’</l>
                        <l>Whoever now calls Surata ‘poor’ <ref cRef="F.188.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-309"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Breaks the king’s command.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-132"/>
                    <tei:p tid="131">Surata, a child of the lineage, then made a request of the Bhagavān: “Bhagavān, it is not enough for the great
                        assembly of people gathered here merely to see you. Therefore, Bhagavān, please offer them whatever teachings will make their
                        encounter with the Tathāgata meaningful!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-133"/>
                    <tei:p tid="132">The Bhagavān replied, “Surata, if a child of the lineage possesses these four dharmas, he or she will clearly see
                        the Tathāgata. What are the four? Conviction, faith, regret, and reverence are the four. Whoever possesses these four will
                        clearly see the Tathāgata.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-134"/>
                    <tei:p tid="133">“There is another set of four: generating the intention for unsurpassable, perfect awakening while gazing at the
                        form body of the Tathāgata and wishing, ‘May I become like him’; generating the special and pure intention because the
                        Tathāgata is trustworthy;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-135"> The phrase here, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lhag pa’i bsam pa yongs su dag pa</foreign>, seems to suggest <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lhag
                                bsam rnam dag</foreign>, a technical term describing a stage preceding the development of full bodhicitta where one
                            takes on the personal responsibility to eliminate the suffering of all sentient beings.</note> generating the intention to
                        teach the Dharma to all sentient beings until they are completely liberated; and generating the intention to uphold the
                        supreme Dharma so that the continuity of the lineage of the Three Jewels is maintained. Whoever possesses these four will
                        clearly see the Tathāgata.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-136"/>
                    <tei:p tid="134">“There is still another set of four: seeing form as <term>detached</term>; seeing sensations, perceptions,
                        formations, and consciousnesses as <term>detached</term>; seeing the four elements as space-like; and seeing the sense spheres
                        to be like empty cities. Whoever possesses these four will clearly see the
                        Tathāgata.<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-138"> The word “detached” is a translation of
                            the Tib. term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dben pa</foreign> and the Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">viveka</foreign>. It is traditionally categorized as being
                            of three types: (1) detachment or seclusion of the body (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāyaviveka</foreign>), which refers to remaining in solitude free from
                            desirous or disturbing objects; (2) detachment or seclusion of the mind (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cittaviveka</foreign>), which is mental detachment from
                            desirous or disturbing objects; and, (3) detachment or seclusion from the “substrate”
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upadhiviveka</foreign>), which indicates
                            detachment from all things that perpetuate rebirth, including the five aggregates, the
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśas</foreign>, karma, etc. This last category
                            is what is being referenced here.</note>-->
                    </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-139"/>
                    <tei:p tid="135">“There is still another set of four: the purity of the self because there is no self; the purity of a sentient
                        being because there is no sentient being; the purity of a living being because there is no living being; and the purity of a
                        person because there is no person. Whoever possesses these four will clearly see the Tathāgata. <ref cRef="F.188.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-310"/>
                    </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-140"/>
                    <tei:p tid="136">“There is still another set of four: the divine eye that is uncontrived;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-141"> Here we follow the Kangxi, Narthang, Lhasa, Stok Palace, and Yongle versions in reading
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon par byed pa med pa</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anabhisaṃskāra</foreign>), where the Degé reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon par byed pa</foreign>
                            (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">abhisaṃskāra</foreign>). </note> the wisdom eye that is all-pervasive; the
                        dharma eye that discriminates; and the buddha eye that is fully aware.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-142"> These
                            are four of the “five eyes” (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyan lnga</foreign>; Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pañcacakṣuḥ</foreign>) or five types of extraordinary vision possessed by a buddha. The
                            five are the flesh eye, divine eye, wisdom eye, dharma eye, and buddha eye. The flesh eye is omitted in this list.</note>
                        Whoever possesses these four will clearly see the Tathāgata.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-143"/>
                    <tei:p tid="137">“There is still another set of four: because all phenomena are not objective, the component of ethics is pure;
                        because all phenomena are equal, the component of concentration is pure; because transcendent gnosis is internalized, the
                        component of wisdom is pure; because the liberation of that gnosis is seen, the component of the gnosis seeing liberation is
                            pure.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-144"> These are the “five uncontaminated components” (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zag med phung po lnga</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pañcānāsravaskandha</foreign>): the component of ethics, the component of concentration, the component of wisdom, the
                            component of liberation, and the component of gnosis seeing liberation. </note> Surata, child of the lineage, whoever
                        possesses these four will clearly see the Tathāgata.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-145"/>
                    <tei:p tid="138">Then, having brought joy to that great assembly of people with this sermon, the Bhagavān flew into the sky like
                        the king of geese, accompanied by his retinue.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-146"/>
                    <tei:p tid="139">King Prasenajit of Kośala said to the child of the lineage, Surata, “Surata, when you go to see the Tathāgata,
                        please let me know! I will come with you to see the Tathāgata.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-147"/>
                    <tei:p tid="140">“Great king, I will do so,” replied Surata. “I will take you and your retinue—your wives, heirs, ministers, and
                        the rest—to see the Tathāgata. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-148"/>
                    <tei:p tid="141">“Great king, bodhisattvas do not act for their own benefit alone; instead, they are resplendent when surrounded
                        by a grand retinue.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-149"/>
                    <tei:p tid="142">“Surata, what is the retinue of a bodhisattva?” asked the king.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-150"/>
                    <tei:p tid="143">Surata replied, “All sentient beings are the retinue of a bodhisattva for the sake of training and maturing them.
                        Great king, bodhicitta, which motivates others toward awakening so that they do not desire other vehicles, is also the retinue
                        of a bodhisattva. Great king, <ref cRef="F.189.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-311"/> the special intention to
                        discipline crooked beings is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, inexorable resoluteness is also the retinue of a
                        bodhisattva. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-151"/>
                    <tei:p tid="144">“Great king, the generosity that matures miserly beings is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, the
                        ethical discipline that matures unethical beings is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, the tolerance that matures
                        beings with harmful intentions is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, the diligence that matures lazy beings is
                        also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, the concentration that matures distracted beings is also the retinue of a
                        bodhisattva. Great king, the wisdom that matures unwise beings is also the retinue of a bodhisattva.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-152"/>
                    <tei:p tid="145">“Great king, the kindness that is equanimous toward all sentient beings is also the retinue of a bodhisattva.
                        Great king, the compassion that does not wane with the vicissitudes of cyclic existence is also the retinue of a bodhisattva.
                        Great king, the joy that delights in and seeks the bliss of the Dharma is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, the
                        equanimity that is free of attachment and aversion is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-153"/>
                    <tei:p tid="146">“Great king, the four means of gathering disciples that bring all beings to maturity are also the retinue of a
                        bodhisattva. Great king, accumulating all the various roots of virtue that purify buddhafields is also the retinue of a
                        bodhisattva. Great king, the emptiness, signlessness, and wishlessness that completely overcome all demonic machinations are
                        also the retinue of a bodhisattva. <ref cRef="F.189.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-312"/>
                    </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-154"/>
                    <tei:p tid="147">“Great king, the truthfulness and gentleness that make one’s words respectable are the retinue of a bodhisattva.
                        Great king, the refusal to blame and disparage others that perfects one’s eloquence is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-155"/>
                    <tei:p tid="148">“Great king, accumulating the tools necessary to preserve one’s learning is also the retinue of a bodhisattva.
                        Great king, reverence for one’s masters and preceptors for the sake of learning is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great
                        king, the learning that allows one to fully grasp the supreme Dharma is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great king, a full
                        grasp of the supreme Dharma that causes one to master the teachings of all tathāgatas is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-156"/>
                    <tei:p tid="149">“Great king, dwelling in a forest, which perfects all of one’s roots of virtue, is also the retinue of a
                        bodhisattva. Great king, a pure livelihood that inspires the faithless to faith is also the retinue of a bodhisattva. Great
                        king, the conscientiousness that causes one to achieve the factors conducive to awakening is also the retinue of a
                        bodhisattva.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-157"/>
                    <tei:p tid="150">King Prasenajit then rejoiced; he felt great joy. Filled with such boundless joy, he offered Surata one thousand
                        pairs of finely woven upper and lower garments, worthy of a king, as religious robes. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-158"/>
                    <tei:p tid="151">“Great king,” said Surata, “you seek to venerate and make offerings to me! Although the king may want to give all
                        that to me, I don’t want clothes that would make me hold conceptions of ‘mine’ or make me possessive. I already have rags sewn
                        together from a hundred patches of tattered cotton. Great king, during the hot season, when I leave these rags hanging on a
                        branch for one, two, ten, or a hundred days, no one steals them, <ref cRef="F.190.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-313"/> and no one becomes covetous. I just leave them there without worrying about them, and there they remain. Great king, I
                        don’t want any clothes that would make me hold conceptions of ‘mine’ or make me possessive. Great king, bodhisattvas only
                        possess those clothes for which they have no desire and which will not give rise to desire in others.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-159"/>
                    <tei:p tid="152">The king replied, “Surata, if you won’t accept these pairs of finely woven upper and lower garments, please, out
                        of sympathy for me, at least tread on them with your feet!” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-160"/>
                    <tei:p tid="153">Saying, “Your Majesty, I’ll do as you wish,” Surata trod on them with his feet and returned to the king.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-161"/>
                    <tei:p tid="154">“Surata, what should I do with these pairs of finely woven upper and lower garments that have been beneath your
                            feet?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-162"> The <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dman ma</foreign> in the
                            phrase here, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rkang pa’i dman mar gyur pa</foreign>, can denote “old” or “left
                            over.” In colloquial English, we might call the cloth “used clothing.”</note> asked the king.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-163"/>
                    <tei:p tid="155">“Great king,” replied Surata, “give them away to the poor and naked.” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-164"/>
                    <tei:p tid="156">The king said, “Yes, I will do as you say,” and entrusted the matter to his attendants, who carried out his
                        order.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-165"/>
                    <tei:p tid="157">Those poor people, who received and put on those pairs of finely woven upper and lower garments, were immediately
                        moved to repay Surata’s kindness. Then, due to the blessing of the Buddha and the power of Surata’s aspiration, they heard
                        these verses from the sky:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-166"/>
                    <lg tid="158">
                        <l>“Although you may want to offer</l>
                        <l>Flowers, incense, perfumes,</l>
                        <l>Food, drink, and jewelry as repayment,</l>
                        <l>These will not suffice, for Surata is delighted by bodhicitta.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-167"/>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“Surata has no desire for food and clothes,</l>
                        <l>Nor for personal gain, nor veneration, nor fame.</l>
                        <l>Surata desires the qualities that arise from bodhicitta;</l>
                        <l>It is bodhicitta that pleases Surata.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-168"/>
                    <tei:p tid="160">Sometime later, Surata, a child of the lineage, and King Prasenajit with his retinue of queens, ministers, and
                        entourage, as well as the men, women, boys, and girls of Śrāvastī and hundreds of other creatures, went to see the
                        Bhagavān.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-169"/>
                    <tei:p tid="161">Between Śrāvastī and Prince Jeta’s Grove, Śakra, lord of the gods, emanated a large, well-decorated pavilion that
                        was vast, towering, and beautiful to behold; it was a beautifully adorned palace that resembled Vaijayanta, his palace in the
                        Heaven of the Thirty-Three. <ref cRef="F.190.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-314"/> At the center of the palace he
                        emanated a wish-fulfilling tree, in front of which he emanated a well-proportioned lion throne fit for the Bhagavān, one that
                        was beautiful to behold and covered with hundreds of thousands of divine, finely woven cotton cloths. Finally, he emanated
                        sixty thousand seats for bodhisattvas.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-170"/>
                    <tei:p tid="162">Twelve thousand goddesses, such as the asura Śacī, came bringing flowers, incense, perfumes, flower garlands,
                        ointments, and divine sandalwood powders, while playing cymbals and drums. Since they were Surata’s attendants, they
                        ornamented the Bhagavān’s lion throne. Knowing that this great assembly of people was coming, the Bhagavān emerged from the
                        monastery and sat down on the prepared seat, surrounded by bodhisattvas and śrāvakas.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-171"/>
                    <tei:p tid="163">Then, the gandharva Pañcaśikha said to the goddess Sunlight, “Kind lady, come here! As an act of service to
                        Surata, please worship the Tathāgata with string instruments and melodious songs!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-172"/>
                    <tei:p tid="164">The goddess Sunlight together with some five hundred goddesses then sang these verses of praise accompanied by
                        string instruments:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-173"/>
                    <lg tid="165">
                        <l>“For the past hundred eons, you have practiced asceticism;</l>
                        <l>You have delighted in the ways of gathering disciples, discipline, and generosity;</l>
                        <l>Your body, speech, and mind are completely pure—</l>
                        <l>Thus, I pay homage to you, the foremost in the three realms!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-174"/>
                    <lg tid="166">
                        <l>“You are without callousness, and delight in forbearance and kindness;</l>
                        <l>Your diligence is firm, and your powers perfected;</l>
                        <l>You delight in the dawning of concentration, intelligence, and ethics—</l>
                        <l>Thus, I pay homage to you, who dispels the blemishes of the three stains! </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-175"/>
                    <lg tid="167">
                        <l>“You delight in eliminating desire, hatred, and delusion;</l>
                        <l>Your mind is peaceful and impartial, yet compassionate;</l>
                        <l>You speak truthfully and know the ultimate—</l>
                        <l>Thus, I pay homage to you, who liberates all three realms! <ref cRef="F.191.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-315"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-176"/>
                    <lg tid="168">
                        <l>“You eliminate doubts in those who see you;</l>
                        <l>You eliminate all faults in those who see you;</l>
                        <l>You bring great delight to those who see you—</l>
                        <l>Thus, I go for refuge to you, the Conqueror, with all my heart!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-177"/>
                    <lg tid="169">
                        <l>“Even sublime goddesses who are extremely lustful,</l>
                        <l>Upon seeing you, delight in the Dharma.</l>
                        <l>Delighted, they will attain expansive mindfulness. </l>
                        <l>Delighted, they will be free from delighting in lust for beauty.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-178"/>
                    <lg tid="170">
                        <l>“You have the supreme, luminous qualities of being perfectly adorned</l>
                        <l>With the ornaments of the thirty-two supreme marks.</l>
                        <l>You are a holy man, whose speech is pure and supreme;</l>
                        <l>I pay homage to you, whose radiance is unparalleled!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-179"/>
                    <lg tid="171">
                        <l>“Your beautiful palms are like the gold of the noble Jambu River. </l>
                        <l>The Sage’s chest is like a lion’s, and your posture like an elephant’s.</l>
                        <l>Your eyebrows and nose are elegant; your teeth are even, beautiful, and have no gaps—</l>
                        <l>I bow to you, the great Śākyamuni, who is like the śrīgarbha jewel!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-180"/>
                    <lg tid="172">
                        <l>“By the limitless capacities of the merit</l>
                        <l>Acquired from praising the delightful Sugata,</l>
                        <l>A conqueror replete with hundreds of good qualities,</l>
                        <l>May the whole world come to buddhahood together!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-181"/>
                    <tei:p tid="173">Surata, a child of the lineage, then approached the Bhagavān along with the great crowd of people. Surata bowed
                        his head to the Bhagavān’s feet and sat to one side. King Prasenajit said to Surata, a child of the lineage, “Please sit
                        here!” and personally offered him a well-prepared seat, which Surata accepted. King Prasenajit and his retinue also bowed
                        their heads to the Bhagavān’s feet and took their seats. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-182"/>
                    <tei:p tid="174">Thereupon, some of the gods<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-183"> The Stok Palace, Lhasa, Kangxi,
                            Narthang, and Yongle Kangyurs omit “gods” and instead have “children of the lineage” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs kyi bu gang bdag gis</foreign>).</note> who were unfamiliar with Surata, a child of the lineage,
                        wondered to themselves, “Why has this shabbily dressed poor man received such abundant honors?” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-184"/>
                    <tei:p tid="175">Śakra, lord of the gods, told those gods, <ref cRef="F.191.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-316"/>
                        “Friends, don’t belittle him! I have seen for myself the great qualities possessed by this child of the lineage. Friends, just
                        sit down for now! You will see the display of qualities this child of the lineage possesses.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-185"/>
                    <tei:p tid="176">Realizing what those gods were thinking, Surata, a child of the lineage, made a request to the Bhagavān:
                        “Bhagavān, please teach us the means that bodhisattvas display to bring sentient beings to maturity and the means they display
                        to bring them to gnosis!”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-186"/>
                    <tei:p tid="177">The Bhagavān then emitted light rays from his body. When the light rays reached Surata, his body became over a
                        hundred thousand times more beautiful than the perfect body of Śakra, the lord of the gods. Those gods were thunderstruck and
                        rained flowers upon Surata.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-187"/>
                    <tei:p tid="178">Then the Bhagavān replied to Surata, a child of the lineage, “Surata, whenever bodhisattvas have adamantine
                        power, they feign to be lowly for the sake of bringing sentient beings to maturity. And even when they have little power, they
                        feign to be supreme, also for the sake of bringing sentient beings to maturity. This is their display. Immersed in gnosis,
                        they feign ignorance, and even when feigning ignorance, their knowledge is keen. This is their display. With their physical
                        and moral conduct, they inspire faith in those without gnosis. Showing all types of conduct, they reveal miracles to those
                        with gnosis. This is their display. By constantly mastering their minds, they are revered by Brahmā despite manifesting as
                        poor and destitute, and when maintaining their supreme display, they are still revered by ordinary beings. This is their
                        display. For the sake of attracting sentient beings, they teach the poor and destitute. For the sake of inspiring sentient
                        beings to renounce the world, they appear as renunciants, despite possessing vast wealth. This is their display.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-188"/>
                    <tei:p tid="179">Thereupon, venerable Ānanda asked the Bhagavān, <ref cRef="F.192.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-317"/>
                        “Bhagavān, what good deeds has Surata, a child of the lineage, done for the sake of awakening?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-189"/>
                    <tei:p tid="180">The Bhagavān answered, “Ānanda! Surata, a child of the lineage, has venerated millions of buddhas. He has been
                        perfected through previous practice. He has attained the three forbearances. He has attained eloquence. He is artful with his
                        extraordinary powers. He is skilled in bringing sentient beings to maturity. By being poor and destitute, he disciplines
                        sentient beings.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-190"/>
                    <tei:p tid="181">“Bhagavān,” asked Ānanda, “how many sentient beings has this poor and destitute man disciplined?” </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-191"/>
                    <tei:p tid="182">The Bhagavān replied, “Ānanda, he has brought many hundreds of thousands of gods to the maturity of unsurpassable
                        and perfect awakening. He has done the same for an equal number of human beings.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-192"/>
                    <tei:p tid="183">“Bhagavān,” asked Ānanda, “how will he become an unsurpassable, perfect, and completely awakened buddha? How will
                        his buddhafield be arrayed? What will his name be?”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-193"/>
                    <tei:p tid="184">The Bhagavān replied to venerable Ānanda with these verses:</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-194"/>
                    <lg tid="185">
                        <l>“Listen, Ānanda, and I will explain to you</l>
                        <l>The nature of his efforts to benefit beings, his consistency in religious observances,</l>
                        <l>How his great renown is held in the hearts of many,</l>
                        <l>And the way his conduct is steadfast in the qualities of awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-195"/>
                    <lg tid="186">
                        <l>“Whatever good deeds Surata has done,</l>
                        <l>Whether it is his veneration of the conquerors through supreme offerings,</l>
                        <l>Or striving to protect the holy Dharma,</l>
                        <l>They are too numerous to be listed now.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-196"/>
                    <lg tid="187">
                        <l>“He is well trained in all the perfections;</l>
                        <l>He has been artful with his extraordinary powers in past lives;</l>
                        <l>He has perfected the divine states of mind;</l>
                        <l>He is well trained in skillful activity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-197"/>
                    <lg tid="188">
                        <l>“Now, he sees well the faults of composite phenomena;</l>
                        <l>Even the complete awakening of the buddhas is evident to him.</l>
                        <l>He is well trained in those skills</l>
                        <l>That bring all sorts of different beings to liberation. <ref cRef="F.192.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-318"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-198"/>
                    <lg tid="189">
                        <l>“He is fearless and endowed with intelligence, realization, and mindfulness,</l>
                        <l>As well as eloquence and dhāraṇīs.</l>
                        <l>He has escaped Māra’s hook and the mire of mental afflictions,</l>
                        <l>And he is firmly set in the purview of the buddhas, the ultimate goal.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-199"/>
                    <lg tid="190">
                        <l>“He is not tainted by worldly affairs;</l>
                        <l>Like a stone, he is unmoved by lust and the like.</l>
                        <l>He neither gets close to nor distant from anyone;</l>
                        <l>Just like space, he is free of both bondage and liberation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-200"/>
                    <lg tid="191">
                        <l>“He is steadfastly compassionate and indefatigable; </l>
                        <l>He is self-restrained and kind to those who are bewildered.</l>
                        <l>Considering all sentient beings as dear as himself,</l>
                        <l>He does not perceive others’ faults and thus is never quarrelsome.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-201"/>
                    <lg tid="192">
                        <l>“He steadfastly practices exactly as he was taught;</l>
                        <l>He conducts himself exactly in accord with the teachings.</l>
                        <l>By following the Dharma, he is well trained in the essence of dharmas.</l>
                        <l>He yearns for emptiness and is free of dualism.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-202"/>
                    <lg tid="193">
                        <l>“He has attained the three forbearances and transcends the purview of ordinary beings;</l>
                        <l>He is steadfast in the way and pure qualities of the buddhas.</l>
                        <l>In whatever world he roams,</l>
                        <l>He liberates numerous beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-203"/>
                    <lg tid="194">
                        <l>“Wherever this child of the buddhas resides,</l>
                        <l>There is never an absence of tathāgatas.</l>
                        <l>Thus, the entire world, including the gods,</l>
                        <l>Pays respect to him in the manner of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-204"/>
                    <lg tid="195">
                        <l>“After I pass into nirvāṇa during the age of degeneration,</l>
                        <l>Surata will perform a buddha’s deeds.</l>
                        <l>Then, he will return to Abhirati, Akṣobhya’s realm,</l>
                        <l>Where he previously resided.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-205"/>
                    <lg tid="196">
                        <l>“Imperturbable,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-206"> “Imperturbable” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtan po</foreign>) here may be a play on the meaning of Akṣobhya’s name, which is “immovable.” </note> he will
                            benefit living creatures,</l>
                        <l>And seek out the treasures of that buddhafield.</l>
                        <l>For the sake of bringing sentient beings to the maturity of awakening,</l>
                        <l>He will perform good deeds for three countless eons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-207"/>
                    <lg tid="197">
                        <l>“After that, he will become a guardian, a conqueror,</l>
                        <l>Whose name will be Lord King of the World.</l>
                        <l>His world will be equal to</l>
                        <l>The buddhafield of the Tathāgata Akṣobhya.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-208"/>
                    <lg tid="198">
                        <l>“That world will be called Elegantly Emanated, <ref cRef="F.193.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-319"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And will be endowed with all good qualities.</l>
                        <l>His lifespan will be ten thousand years,</l>
                        <l>And his saṅgha members beyond reckoning.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-209"/>
                    <lg tid="199">
                        <l>“He will have few saṅgha members within the Śrāvaka Vehicle,</l>
                        <l>While most will strive for awakening.</l>
                        <l>All will possess the power of gnosis and miraculous powers,</l>
                        <l>And they will be endowed with the liberations and be fearless.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-211"/>
                    <lg tid="200">
                        <l>“That world will resound with the continual reverberation</l>
                        <l>Of nothing but their eloquent elucidations of the Dharma.</l>
                        <l>There will be no māras, nor attachment to saṃsāra;</l>
                        <l>They will all be knowledgeable and completely pure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-212"/>
                    <lg tid="201">
                        <l>“After that sugata passes into complete nirvāṇa,</l>
                        <l>His sublime Dharma will be practiced</l>
                        <l>For eighty-four years,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-213"> This seems a paltry number of years for Surata’s
                                future Dharma teachings to persist. However, this is the literal number suggested by the Tibetan, “<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lo ni brgyad cu dag las bzhi lhag</foreign>.” It may be a shorthand of 84,000, which is a
                                significant number in Buddhist texts.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>During which time his Dharma tradition will have no disharmony.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-214"/>
                    <lg tid="202">
                        <l>“Those who are brought to maturity by Surata</l>
                        <l>Will pursue unsurpassable awakening.</l>
                        <l>The sentient beings who are born in that buddhafield</l>
                        <l>Will become free from all faults.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-215"/>
                    <tei:p tid="203">As soon as the Bhagavān had made this prophecy about Surata, a child of the lineage, the trichiliocosm shook in
                        six ways as divine flowers, powders, garments, and ornaments rained down. The entire retinue offered their garments to Surata,
                        a child of the lineage. Many hundreds of merchants, householders, and brahmins were went forth as renunciants.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-216"/>
                    <tei:p tid="204">Thereupon Surata said to the Bhagavān, “Please permit me to go forth in the tradition of the Dharma and Vinaya
                        that you have taught so well.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-217"/>
                    <tei:p tid="205">The Bhagavān then raised his hand and blessed Surata, a child of the lineage, upon his head. The moment the
                        Bhagavān touched his head, Surata, a child of the lineage, transformed into a monk wearing saffron robes.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-218"/>
                    <tei:p tid="206">Then the Bhagavān said to venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, there are five degenerations: the degeneration of time, the
                        degeneration of sentient beings, the degeneration of place, the degeneration of lifespan, and the degeneration of mental
                        afflictions. <ref cRef="F.193.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-320"/> In the time of these degenerations, and following
                        my perfect awakening, no one should be disciplined in ways other than how Surata has been disciplined. </tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-219"/>
                    <tei:p tid="207">“Ānanda, I don’t tame sentient beings of the Sahā world system with the Vinaya of the buddhas. Ānanda, I tame
                        sentient beings with fears and warnings of becoming poor and destitute, or of taking lower rebirths. Ānanda, if in this world
                        system I taught and gave instructions about the Dharma from a Buddha’s point of view, not one sentient being would be tamed
                        and no Dharma would be realized. Therefore Ānanda, just as Surata and I tame sentient beings, so should you. Ānanda, there
                        will be many sentient beings who will gain faith and realization; by hearing this Dharma discourse they will find faith and
                        practice accordingly.”</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-220"/>
                    <tei:p tid="208">When the Bhagavān finished speaking, venerable Ānanda, the bodhisattva Surata, the other bodhisattvas, the monks,
                        Śakra, lord of the gods, King Prasenajit, and the gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas of the world rejoiced and praised what
                        the Bhagavān had said.</tei:p>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-221"/>
                    <trailer tid="209">This concludes <title xml:lang="en">Surata’s Questions</title>, the twenty-seventh of the one hundred 
                        thousand sections of of the Dharma discourse known as The Noble Great Heap of Jewels.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="210">Colophon</head>
                    <tei:milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-222"/>
                    <tei:p tid="211">Translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi, the Tibetan chief-editor 
                        and translator Bandé Yeshé Dé, and others.</tei:p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="212">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="214">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="215">Primary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-226">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">des pas zhus pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surataparipṛcchā</title>). Toh 71, Degé Kangyur vol. 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios
                        181.a–193.b.</bibl> 
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-227">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">des pas zhus pa</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition
                            of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation
                            Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center), 108 volumes. Beijing: Krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                            Publishing House). 2006–9, vol. 43, pp. 511–43.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-228">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">des pas zhus pa</title>. Stok Palace Kangyur vol. 39
                        (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 314.b–334.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-224">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsgom pa’i rim pa mdo kun las btus pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāvanā­krama­sūtra­samuccaya</title>). Toh 3933, Degé Tengyur vol. 110 (dbu ma, ki), folios
                        125.b–148.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-225">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan [/ lhan] dkar gyi chos ’gyur ro
                            cog gi dkar chag</title>). Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-229">Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>). Beijing: mi rigs dpe
                        skrun khang, 2003.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-listBibl-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="216">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-230">Chang, Garma C. C., ed. “Bodhisattva Surata’s Discourse.” In <title xml:lang="en">A Treasury of
                            Mahāyāna Sūtras: Selections from the Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title>, 243–55. University Park: Pennsylvania State University
                        Press, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-231">Nattier, Jan. “Indian Antecedents of Huayan Thought: New Light from Chinese Sources.” In <title xml:lang="en">Reflecting Mirrors: Perspectives on Huayan Buddhism</title>, edited by Imre Hamar, 109–38. Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-232">Negi, J. S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Sanskrit Dictionary</title>. 16 vol. Sarnath,
                        Varanasi: Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-008-233">Pekar Sangpo (pad dkar bzang po). “Le’u nyer bdun pa ’phags pa des pas zhus pa’i mdo.” In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde spyi’i rnam bzhag</title> [<title xml:lang="en">Presentation of the sūtras in the
                            Kangyur</title>], edited by mi nyag mgon po, 85–87. Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang, 2006.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified"></term>
                            <term type="definition"></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-326">
                            <term>three realms</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">khams gsum pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས་གསུམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">tridhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">(1) The desire realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāmadhātu</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod khams</foreign>), (2) the form realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs khams</foreign>), and (3) the formless realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arūpyadhātu</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs med khams</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-325">
                            <term>asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">lha ma yin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">asura</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of divine beings who are engaged in a mythic war with the gods (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">deva</foreign>) for possession of the nectar of immortality. In Buddhist cosmology,
                                they inhabit a realm below those of the gods, from which they observe the gods with intense jealousy.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-008-324" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bcom ldan ’das</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Buddhist literature, an epithet applied to buddhas, most often to Śākyamuni. The Sanskrit term
                                generically means “possessing fortune,” but in specifically Buddhist contexts this term implies that a buddha is in
                                possession of six auspicious qualities (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhaga</foreign>) associated with
                                complete awakening. The Tibetan term—where <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bcom</foreign> is said to refer to
                                “subduing” the four māras, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ldan</foreign> to “possessing” the great qualities
                                of buddhahood, and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">’das</foreign> to “going beyond” saṃsāra and
                                nirvāṇa—possibly reflects the commentarial tradition where the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagavat</foreign> is interpreted, in addition, as “one who destroys the four māras.” This is achieved either by
                                reading <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagavat</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagnavat</foreign> (“one who broke”), or by tracing the word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhaga</foreign> to the root <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">√bhañj</foreign>, “to break.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-323">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">de bzhin gshegs pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">A frequently used synonym for buddha. According to different explanations, it can be read as
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathā-gata</foreign>, literally meaning “one who has thus gone,” or as
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathā-agata</foreign>, “one who has thus come.” <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Gata</foreign>, though literally meaning “gone,” is a past passive participle used to describe a state
                                or condition of existence. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Tatha</foreign>­(<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tā</foreign>), often rendered as “suchness” or “thusness,” is the quality or condition of things as
                                they really are, which cannot be conveyed in conceptual, dualistic terms. Therefore, this epithet is interpreted in
                                different ways, but in general it implies one who has departed in the wake of the buddhas of the past, or one who has
                                manifested the supreme enlightenment dependent on the reality that does not abide in the two extremes of existence and
                                quiescence. </term>
                            <term type="definition">Here also used as a specific epithet of the Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-322" mode="marked">
                            <term>detachment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dben pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">viveka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Detachment is traditionally categorized as being of three types: (1) detachment or seclusion of
                                the body (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāyaviveka</foreign>), which refers to remaining in solitude free
                                from desirous or disturbing objects; (2) detachment or seclusion of the mind (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cittaviveka</foreign>), which is mental detachment from desirous or disturbing objects; and, (3) detachment or
                                seclusion from the “substrate” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upadhiviveka</foreign>), which indicates
                                detachment from all things that perpetuate rebirth, including the five aggregates, the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśas</foreign>, karma, etc. This last category is what is being referenced here.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">detached</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-321">
                            <term>sense sphere</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">skye mched</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The sense spheres are a collective list of the six sense objects (forms, sounds, odors, tastes,
                                textures, mental phenomena) with their respective senses (eye, ear, nose, tongue, tactile sense, and mind) totaling
                                twelve and indicating their interdependence. In this sūtra, they are equated to an “empty city.” This most likely
                                denotes the fact that there is no self independent of the interaction of these or perceiver independent of the process
                                of perception.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-235">
                            <term>bodhicitta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">bodhicitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally “the mind of awakening,” but more technically, one’s particular aspiration to become
                                fully awakened for the specific purpose of liberating all sentient beings. This is the necessary and sufficient
                                condition to be a bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-236">
                            <term>dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">gzungs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">As incantations or spells, dhāraṇīs are mnemonic formulas possessed by advanced bodhisattvas that
                                contain a quintessence of their attainments. The same term in Sanskrit and Tibetan also refers to a highly developed
                                power present in bodhisattvas that is a process of memory and recall of detailed teachings. This is best translated
                                “retention” in certain contexts.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-238">
                            <term>five basic precepts</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bslab pa’i gzhi lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསླབ་པའི་གཞི་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">pañcaśikṣāpada</term>
                            <term type="definition">Abstaining from killing, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, and intoxication.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-239">
                            <term>five degenerations</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">snyigs ma lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྙིགས་མ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">pañcakaṣāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">In this text, the five degenerations are: (1) the degeneration of time, (2) the degeneration of
                                sentient beings, (3) the degeneration of place, (4) the degeneration of lifespan, and (5) the degeneration of mental
                                afflictions. This differs from other presentations of this list in which the degeneration of views replaces the
                                degeneration of place.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-240">
                            <term>four means of gathering disciples</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bsdu ba’i dngos po bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྡུ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">catuḥ­saṅgraha­vastu</term>
                            <term type="definition">Generosity, kind talk, meaningful actions, and practicing what one preaches.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-241">
                            <term>four wrong views</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">phyin ci log bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">caturviparyāsa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Viewing what is impermanent to be permanent, viewing what brings suffering to be pleasurable,
                                viewing what is tainted to be pure, and viewing what is non-self to be self.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-242">
                            <term>fourfold community</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’khor bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">catuḥpariṣad</term>
                            <term type="definition">Monks, nuns, and male and female lay practitioners. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-243">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of nonhuman being often rendered as “celestial musicians” who fly through space and serve
                                as musicians for the gods.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">gandharvī </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="text" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-244" mode="marked">
                            <term>Heap of Jewels</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dkon mchog brtsegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Ratnakūṭa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A collection of texts comprising a section of the Kangyur as well as of the Chinese Buddhist
                                canon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-245">
                            <term>liberations</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rnam par thar pa rnams</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པ་རྣམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">vimokṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Though not explicit in this text, this may be a reference to eight stages to liberation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭavimokṣa</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par thar pa brgyad</foreign>), a series
                                of increasingly subtle states of meditative realization or attainment. There are several presentations of these found
                                in the canonical literature. One of the most common is as follows: (1) One observes form while the mind dwells at the
                                level of the form realm. (2) One observes forms externally while discerning formlessness internally. (3) One dwells in
                                the direct experience of the body’s pleasant aspect. (4) One dwells in the realization of the sphere of infinite space
                                by transcending all conceptions of matter, resistance, and diversity. (5) Transcending the sphere of infinite space,
                                one dwells in the realization of the sphere of infinite consciousness. (6) Transcending the sphere of infinite
                                consciousness, one dwells in the realization of the sphere of nothingness. (7) Transcending the sphere of nothingness,
                                one dwells in the realization of the sphere of neither perception nor nonperception. (8) Transcending the sphere of
                                neither perception and nonperception, one dwells in the realization of the cessation of conception and feeling.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-246">
                            <term>māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of beings related to the demon Māra or a term for the demon Māra himself. Māra and the
                                māras are portrayed as the primary adversaries and tempters of people who vow to take up the religious life, and māras
                                can be understood as a class of demonic beings responsible for perpetuating the illusion that keeps beings bound to
                                the world and worldly attachments and the mental states those beings elicit.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">Māras </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>

                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-247">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of nonhuman beings who live in subterranean aquatic environments and who are known to
                                hoard wealth and esoteric teachings. They are associated with snakes and serpents.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-248">
                            <term>perfected through previous practice </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sngon gyi tshul phun sum tshogs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྔོན་གྱི་ཚུལ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">pūrvayogasampanna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-249">
                            <term>piśācī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sha za ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ཟ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">piśācī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A female member of a class of nonhuman beings traditionally associated with the wild, remote
                                places of the earth. They are considered particularly violent and are known to devour flesh. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-008-250" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>four dharmas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">chos bzhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="alternative">four dharmas</term>
                            <term type="definition">In this sūtra, these are taught as conviction, faith, regret, and reverence—whoever possesses these four will clearly see the Tathāgata.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-251">
                            <term>propensities for continued existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">srid pa’i bag la nyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིད་པའི་བག་ལ་ཉལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Various unwholesome mental states that lead to continued suffering and existence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-008-252" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>rākṣasī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">srin mo</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">rākṣasī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A female member of a class of Indic spirit deities generally considered malevolent and
                                demonic.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-008-253" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>śrāvaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">nyan thos</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A “listener” or direct disciple of the Buddha. Often used to denote the non-Mahāyāna monastic
                                community.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-254">
                            <term>Śrāvaka Vehicle </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">nyan thos theg pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས་ཐེག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">śrāvakayāna </term>
                            <term type="definition">The vehicle comprising the teaching of the śrāvakas, the disciples or “Hearers” who heard the
                                teachings from the Buddha. According to Mahāyāna sources, this is one of the two constitutents (along with the
                                Pratyekabuddhayāna) of the so-called “Lesser Vehicle” (Hīnayāna). </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-255">
                            <term>divine states of mind</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">tshangs pa’i gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">brahmavihāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four qualities that are said to result in rebirth in the paradise of Brahmā: limitless love,
                                compassion, rejoicing, and equanimity.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-256">
                            <term>eight precepts</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">gso sbyong gi yan lag brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསོ་སྦྱོང་གི་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">aṣṭāṅgapoṣadha</term>
                            <term type="definition">These are the eight <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upavasatha</foreign> vows, similar to the
                                commitments of a monk, but maintained only for one day. On such days one pledges: (1) not to kill, (2) not to steal,
                                (3) not to engage in sexual intercourse, (4) not to lie, (5) not to partake of any intoxicants, (6) not to sing or
                                dance, (7) not to eat after noon, and (8) not to use high seats or luxurious beds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-257">
                            <term>śrīgarbha jewel</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dpal gyi snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">śrīgarbha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A kind of gem, reddish in color. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-258">
                            <term>ten virtuous actions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dge ba bcu’i las kyi lam </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">daśakuśalakarmapatha</term>
                            <term type="definition">These are the opposite of the ten sins, i.e., refraining from engaging in activities related to
                                the ten sins and doing the opposite. There are three physical virtues: saving lives, giving, and sexual propriety.
                                There are four verbal virtues: truthfulness, reconciling discussions, gentle speech, and religious speech. There are
                                three mental virtues: loving attitude, generous attitude, and right views. The whole doctrine is collectively called
                                the “tenfold path of good action” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśa­kuśala­karma­patha</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-259">
                            <term>three forbearances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bzod pa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟོད་པ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">trikṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">The three types of forbearance needed on the spiritual path: (1) forbearance with regard to harms,
                                (2) forbearance with regard to undertaking hardships, and (3) forbearance with regard to having confidence in the
                                Dharma.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-260">
                            <term>three stains</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dri ma gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">trimala</term>
                            <term type="definition">The same as the three poisons: desire, hatred, and delusion.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-261">
                            <term>thirty-two supreme marks</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mtshan mchog sum cu rtsa gnyis </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་མཆོག་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">dvātriṃśanmahāpuruṣalakṣaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">These are thirty-two physical characteristics of a “great person.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-262">
                            <term>virtuous practices</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sbyangs pa’i yon tan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱངས་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">dhūtaguṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">An optional set of thirteen practices that monastics can adopt in order to cultivate greater
                                detachment. They consist of (1) wearing patched robes made from discarded cloth rather than from cloth donated by
                                laypeople; (2) wearing only three robes; (3) going for alms; (4) not omitting any house while on the alms round,
                                rather than begging only at those houses known to provide good food; (5) eating only what can be eaten in one sitting;
                                (6) eating only food received in the alms bowl, rather than more elaborate meals presented to the Saṅgha; (7) refusing
                                more food after indicating one has eaten enough; (8) dwelling in the forest; (9) dwelling at the root of a tree; (10)
                                dwelling in the open air, using only a tent made from one’s robes as shelter; (11) dwelling in a charnel ground; (12)
                                being satisfied with whatever dwelling one has; and (13) sleeping in a sitting position without ever lying
                                down.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-263">
                            <term>Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mi ’khrugs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཁྲུགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Sanskrit, “Immovable,” the name of a tathāgata. In Surata’s next life, he returns to Abhirati,
                                the realm of Akṣobhya. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-264">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha’s cousin and longtime attendant. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-265">
                            <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term type="definition">Anāthapiṇḍada was a wealthy merchant in the town of Śrāvastī, who became a patron of the Buddha
                                Śākyamuni. He bought the land from Prince Jeta to serve as the Buddha’s first monastery. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-266">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high-ranking deity, presiding over a divine world where other beings consider him the creator;
                                he is also considered to be the “Lord of the Sahā World” (our universe).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-267">
                            <term>Candra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Candra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The god of the moon; the moon personified.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-268">
                            <term>Indra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Indra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A Vedic god who eventually emerged as one of the most important in the Vedic pantheon. Indra
                                retains his role as the “Lord of the Gods” in Buddhist literature, where he is often referred to by the name
                                Śakra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-269">
                            <term>Jeta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rgyal byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Jeta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Prince who sold a piece of land in Śrāvastī to the householder Anāthapiṇḍada, who built a
                                monastery there and offered it to the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-270">
                            <term>Lord King of the World</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’jig rten rgyal po dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་རྒྱལ་པོ་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The name Surata is known by after he becomes enlightened. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-271">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The demon who assailed Śākyamuni prior to his awakening; any demonic force; the personification of
                                conceptual and emotional obstacles.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-272">
                            <term>Pañcaśikha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">gtsug phud lnga pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཙུག་ཕུད་ལྔ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Pañcaśikha </term>
                            <term type="definition">A certain young gandharva allied with the god Śakra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-273">
                            <term>Prasenajit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">gsal rgyal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསལ་རྒྱལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Prasenajit</term>
                            <term type="definition">King of the country of Kośala, he reigned in the city of Śrāvastī. In this sūtra, Surata humbles
                                him and then becomes one of his teachers. See also <ptr target="#UT22084-043-008-11"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-275">
                            <term>Śacī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bde sogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་སོགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Śacī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A goddess typically understood to be the wife of Indra/Śakra. In this text, it refers to a female
                                asura who attempts to seduce Surata and later becomes one of his attendants.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-276">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Another name for Indra, a Vedic god who eventually emerged as one of the most important in the
                                Vedic pantheon. Indra retains his role as the “Lord of the Gods” in Buddhist literature, where he is often referred to
                                by the name Śakra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-277">
                            <term>Śākyamuni</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">shAkya thub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Śākyamuni</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of the historical Buddha, Siddhartha Gautama. He was a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">muni</foreign> (“sage”) from the Śākya clan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-278">
                            <term>Śākyasiṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">shAkya seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Śākyasiṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Sanskrit, “Lion of the Śākyas,” an epithet for the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-279">
                            <term>Sunlight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">nyi ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A goddess who attempts to seduce Surata and later becomes one of his attendants. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-280">
                            <term>Surata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">des pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Surata</term>
                            <term type="definition">A poor city-dweller in Śrāvastī and protagonist of the text. Poor in resources, he is endowed with
                                the proverbial wealth of virtue. See also <ptr target="#UT22084-043-008-11"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-281">
                            <term>Sūrya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">nyi ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Sūrya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The god of the sun; the sun personified.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-282">
                            <term>Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">gshin rje</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of death in Indian mythology who judges the dead and rules over the hells and the realm
                                of the hungry ghosts.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-283">
                            <term>Abhirati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mngon par dga’ ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Abhirati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lit. “Intense Delight.” The universe, or buddhafield, of the Tathāgata Akṣobhya. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-284">
                            <term>Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga’ ra ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Anāthapiṇḍadasya ārāmaḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">This was an important early site for the Buddha’s growing community. Anāthapiṇḍada, a wealthy
                                patron of the Buddha, purchased the park, located outside Śrāvasti, at great cost, purportedly covering the ground
                                with gold, and donated it to the saṅgha. It was there that the Buddha spent several rainy seasons and gave discourses
                                that were later recorded as sūtras. It was also the site for one of the first Buddhist monasteries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-285">
                            <term>Elegantly Emanated</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">legs par sprul pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེགས་པར་སྤྲུལ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The name of Surata’s buddhafield after he becomes awakened.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-287">
                            <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">trāyastriṃśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The paradise of Indra on the summit of Sumeru where there are thirty-three leading deities, hence
                                the name “Heaven of the Thirty-Three.” The second (counting from the lowest) of the six paradises in the desire
                                realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-288">
                            <term>Jambu River</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’dzam bu chu bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ་ཆུ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Jambunadī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine river whose gold is believed to be especially fine.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-289">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’dzam bu gling</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’dzam gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of the southern continent in Buddhist cosmology, which can signify either the known human
                                world, or more specifically the Indian subcontinent, literally “the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jambu</foreign>
                                island/continent.” Jambu is the name used for a range of plum-like fruits from trees belonging to the genus <foreign xml:lang="la">Szygium</foreign>, particularly <foreign xml:lang="la">Szygium jambos</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">Szygium cumini</foreign>, and has commonly been rendered “rose apple” although “black plum” may be a
                                less misleading term. Among various explanations given for the continent being so named, one (in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title>) is that a jambu tree grows in its northern mountains beside Lake
                                Anavatapta, mythically considered the source of the four great rivers of India, and that the continent is therefore
                                named from the tree or the fruit. Jambudvīpa has the vajrāsana at its center and is the only continent upon which
                                buddhas attain awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-290">
                            <term>Kośala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ko sa la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀོ་ས་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Kośala</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient kingdom, northwest of Magadha, abutting Kāśi, whose capital was Śrāvastī. During the
                                Buddha’s time it was ruled by Prasenajit. It presently corresponds to an area within Uttar Pradesh.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-291">
                            <term>Prince Jeta’s Grove</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Jetavana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A grove owned by Prince Jeta in Śrāvastī, the capital of the kingdom of Kośala. It was bought by
                                Anāthapiṇḍada and became the monastery that the Buddha spent most rainy seasons in and is therefore the setting for
                                many sūtras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-292">
                            <term>Sahā world system</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’jig rten gyi khams mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Sahālokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">This universe of ours, or the trichiliocosm (but sometimes referring to just this world system of
                                four continents), presided over by Brahmā. The term is variously interpreted as meaning the world of suffering, of
                                endurance, of fearlessness, or of concomitance (of karmic cause and effect).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-008-293">
                            <term>Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Capital city of the kingdom of Kośala, ruled by one of the Buddha’s royal patrons, King
                                Prasenajit, where the Buddha often dwelt in the Jetavana grove, the site of many Mahāyāna sūtras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-043-008-294" type="place" mode="match">
                            <term>Vaijayanta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rnam par rgyal ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" status="verified">Vaijayanta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The palace of Śakra in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</tei:TEI>