<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang gA’i mchog gis zhus pa</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">གང་གཱའི་མཆོག་གིས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of Gaṅgottarā</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṅgottara­pari­pṛcchā</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gang gA’i mchog gis zhus pa zhes bya ba
          theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་གང་གཱའི་མཆོག་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Questions of
          Gaṅgottarā”</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­gaṅgottara­pari­pṛcchānāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
        <author xml:id="UT22084-043-012-1" role="translatorMain">Translated by the 84000 Translation
          Team<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
          Buddha</author>
        <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-2">Sophie McGrath</author>
        <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-3">David Fiordalis</editor>
        <editor role="copyEditor" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-24">Dawn Collins</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-34">Rory Lindsay</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-45">Martina Cotter</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
          initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them
          available to everyone. </publisher>
        <availability status="2">
          <licence>
            <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
            <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND
              (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or
              printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage
              or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno xml:id="UT22084-043-012"/>
        <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that
          these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
        <date>2023-11-28</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl key="toh75" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 75</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 222.a–225.b</biblScope>
          <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="8">
            <volume number="43" start-page="443" end-page="450"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11615" work="W22084"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <notesStmt/>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change who="#admin" when="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" type="text-version" status="v 0.0.1" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-4">
          <desc>Automated version increment</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-03-22T14:05:04.88Z" type="translation-status" status="" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-5">
          <desc/>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-03-22T14:05:04.88Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-6">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-03-22T14:08:35.938Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-7">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-04-17T07:13:43.571Z" type="translation-status" status="3" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-8">
          <desc>3</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-04-17T07:13:43.571Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-9">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-04-17T07:14:27.892Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.5" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-10">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-05-30T15:07:12.57Z" type="translation-status" status="2.h" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-11">
          <desc>2.h</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-05-30T15:07:12.57Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.6" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-12">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-13T14:12:40.643Z" type="translation-status" status="2.g" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-13">
          <desc>2.g</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-13T14:12:40.643Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.7" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-14">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-13T14:13:15.914Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.8" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-15">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-07-17T08:22:51.941Z" type="translation-status" status="2.f" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-16">
          <desc>2.f</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-07-17T08:22:51.941Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.9" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-17">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.10" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-18">
          <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-09-08T09:53:14.583Z" type="translation-status" status="2.e" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-19">
          <desc>2.e</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-09-08T09:53:14.583Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.11" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-20">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-09-08T09:53:42.941Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.12" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-25">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-10-10T08:51:28.974Z" type="translation-status" status="2.d" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-26">
          <desc>2.d</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-10-10T08:51:28.974Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.13" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-27">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-10-16T08:38:24.328Z" type="translation-status" status="2.c" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-28">
          <desc>2.c</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-10-16T08:38:24.328Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.14" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-29">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-11-13T11:13:07.069Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.15" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-35">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-11-15T08:38:05.119Z" type="translation-status" status="2.b" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-36">
          <desc>2.b</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-11-15T08:38:05.119Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.16" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-37">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-11-28T11:54:43.45Z" type="translation-status" status="2.a" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-38">
          <desc>2.a</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-11-28T11:54:43.45Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.17" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-39">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-11-28T11:55:20.02Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.18" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-46">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-12-05T12:51:41.279Z" type="translation-status" status="2" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-213">
                    <desc>2</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-12-05T12:51:41.279Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-214">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!--Note the "Contents" outline from the Word DOCX has not been included in the script. If the 
                    Outline to the text is quite complex, it is recommended that you paste the outlined contents from the DOCX here as a comment for
                    markup's reference. The actual table of contents will be generated in the Reading Room by the parser.-->
    <front>
      <div type="summary">
        <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-47"/>
        <p tid="2">In <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Gaṅgottarā</title>, a laywoman named
          Gaṅgottarā leaves her home in the city of Śrāvastī and visits the Buddha Śākyamuni in
          Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park. The Buddha asks her from where she has come, sparking a dialogue on
          the true nature of things. Among other things, they discuss the fact that, from the
          perspective of ultimate truth, all things, including Gaṅgottarā herself, are like magical
          creations, and thus no one comes or goes or pursues nirvāṇa. After their dialogue, the
          Buddha smiles. When Ānanda asks him why, he explains that a thousand tathāgatas of the
          past have already taught this discourse at this same location to a thousand different
          laywomen, all named Gaṅgottarā; and that through it they have all achieved nirvāṇa. The
          sūtra concludes with a brief explanation of the reasons why the present laywoman named
          Gaṅgottarā received this teaching and how it should be remembered in the future.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgment">
        <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-48"/>
        <p tid="4">The initial draft was completed by Sophie McGrath and reviewed by Laura Goetz,
          who offered various suggestions. The translation was then revised and edited by David
          Fiordalis, who also expanded the introduction and the notes.</p>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-49"/>
        <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
          Translating the Words of the Buddha. Dawn Collins copyedited the text. Martina Cotter was
          in charge of the digital publication process.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction">
        <head type="introduction" tid="8">Introduction</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-introduction-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-52"/>
          <p tid="10">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Gaṅgottarā</title> is a short but
            sophisticated dialogue that opens with a laywoman named Gaṅgottarā leaving her home in
            the city of Śrāvastī and going to visit the Buddha Śākyamuni, who is dwelling nearby in
            Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park. When she arrives, the Buddha asks her, “from where have you come?”
            and this question sparks a dialogue between them on the true nature of things. They
            discuss the fact that all things, including Gaṅgottarā herself, are like magical
            creations, and thus, from the perspective of ultimate truth, no one comes or goes or
            pursues nirvāṇa. They also discuss the implications of this idea for the ontological
            status of concepts found in basic Buddhist teaching, such as the five aggregates,
            dependent arising, rebirth in hells and heavens, even nirvāṇa itself. They then discuss
            some of the related implications for ethical themes, such as good and bad deeds, virtue,
            purity and impurity, and the correct practice of the path.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-53"/>
          <p tid="11">The sūtra is thus noteworthy not only for its teachings, but also for the fact
            that it features a woman as one of its main characters, and a laywoman at that—a
            laywoman who has the intellectual aptitude and fortitude to engage in a challenging
            philosophical discussion with the Buddha.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-54">
              Schuster 1981, p. 39, makes a similar point, and also provides a brief synopsis of the
              Chinese translation of this sūtra.</note> Peter Skilling, who has also published a
            translation of this sūtra into English, compares it with the scene in <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching of Vimalakīrti</title> wherein the goddess who lives in
            Vimalakīrti’s house engages Śāriputra in a sophisticated dialogue that is in some ways
            comparable to the one in this sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-55">
              Skilling 2021, pp. 345–46. This episode can be found at milestone <ptr target="#UT22084-060-005-249">6.12</ptr>-<ptr target="#UT22084-060-005-278">43</ptr>
              of the 84000 translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching of
              Vimalakīrti</title>.</note> At one point in that sūtra, however, the goddess magically
            transforms Śāriputra into a goddess to demonstrate her point that all things are like
            magical illusions. There is no such marvelous demonstration in this sūtra, unless we
            count the episode at the end wherein the gods produce divine flowers and sandalwood
            powders with which to worship the Buddha. However, that action does not seem intended to
            emphasize the idea that all things are like magical illusions. Additionally, the
            dialogue in the present sūtra is between the Buddha and a human woman, and the gender
            roles are the reverse of those found in <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching of
              Vimalakīrti</title>, with the Buddha Śākyamuni in the teacher role and the laywoman
            Gaṅgottarā as the student.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-56"/>
          <p tid="12">After Gaṅgottarā’s discussion with the Buddha has concluded, he smiles. When
            Ānanda asks him why, the Buddha states that a thousand tathāgatas of the past have
            already given this same teaching at this same location in the past to a thousand
            different laywomen, all named Gaṅgottarā, and that all of these women practiced the path
            and achieved parinirvāṇa. Skilling points out the remarkable nature of this statement,
            which has the effect of emphasizing not only that many laywomen have received profound
            teachings from the Buddha but also that they have achieved nirvāṇa, the goal of the
            path.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-57"/>
          <p tid="13">Although the nirvāṇa that these women achieve is not the “unsurpassable and
            perfect awakening” of a buddha, but rather the “remainderless nirvāṇa” of a “worthy one”
              (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arhat</foreign>), there is no explicit claim
            made in the sūtra that this is somehow a lesser accomplishment. That it will be
            Gaṅgottarā’s future achievement is also suggested by the description of the light rays
            that issue from the Buddha’s smile, which the canonical version depicts as returning to
            disappear into the Buddha’s mouth. In other common descriptions of the Buddha’s smile,
            this indicates that the Buddha is giving a prediction of someone’s future awakening as a
            disciple (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śrāvaka</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-58"> For more on the Buddha’s smile, see Fiordalis
              2021.</note> In this way, the sūtra also combines two of the circumstances in which
            the Buddha smiles: he describes something that has happened in the same location in the
            past, and he gives a prediction of someone’s future awakening.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-59"/>
          <p tid="14">The strength and achievements of the laywoman Gaṅgottarā are also explicitly
            emphasized in the sūtra in another way. After the Buddha has smiled and given a brief
            explanation of how the sūtra should be remembered in the future, the narrator mentions a
            number of monks and nuns as being present in the audience, along with various gods and
            divine beings. These gods express wonder at the laywoman Gaṅgottarā of the narrative
            present and they praise her for her ability to converse with the Buddha without becoming
            weary. They explain this by saying that she has practiced virtue and the holy life for a
            long time and served many buddhas in the past, and that this is why she has now received
            this teaching. The sūtra concludes with the Buddha confirming what the gods have said
            and everyone rejoicing at the Buddha’s words.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-60"/>
          <p tid="15">There are no known extant Sanskrit witnesses to this sūtra, but translations
            of it, ostensibly made from Sanskrit manuscripts, are preserved in the Tibetan Kangyur
            and the Chinese Tripiṭaka. In both the Tibetan and Chinese canons, the sūtra is
            classified as part of the collection of sūtras known as <title xml:lang="en">The Great
              Heap of Jewels</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāratnakūṭa</title>). The Chinese
            translation has been attributed to Bodhiruci, who was active in the early eighth century
            and who may have been responsible for compiling the Ratnakūṭa collection as we know it
              today.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-61"> For more information, see the
                entry on <ref target="https://dazangthings.nz/cbc/text/1364/">Taishō 310</ref> in the Chinese Buddhist Canonical Attributions database, and the entry on <ref target="http://www.acmuller.net/descriptive_catalogue/files/k0022-31.html">K 22(31)</ref> in Lewis R.
              Lancaster’s Descriptive Catalogue of the Korean Buddhist Canon. See also
              Schuster 1981, p. 26, and Silk 2019, p. 230.</note> A translation of the Chinese is
            also available in English.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-62"> Chang 1991, pp.
              37–40.</note> The colophon to the canonical Tibetan translation states that the sūtra
            was translated by Dānaśīla and Jinamitra, along with Yeshé Dé, all of whom flourished in
            the late eighth or early ninth century. Its relatively early date of translation into
            Tibetan is also supported by its inclusion in the Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhan kar ma</title>), the catalog of Tibetan translations compiled in the ninth
              century.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-63"> Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, p.
              32.</note> It is not mentioned in the Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phang
              thang ma</title>).</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-64"/>
          <p tid="16">While no citations or references to this sūtra have as yet been discovered in
            other canonical works of Buddhist literature, as Skilling has also noted, another
            complete Tibetan translation of this sūtra can be found among the Dunhuang
            manuscripts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-65">This manuscript is classified as Pelliot Tibétain 89 and is available <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b8302856k?rk=21459;2">here</ref> on Gallica, the digital library of the Bibliothèque National de France.</note> A
            comparison reveals that the Tibetan translation in this Dunhuang manuscript would seem
            to be quite closely related to the Chinese translation by Bodhiruci. In fact, Jonathan
            Silk has even argued that it was made directly from the Chinese translation.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-66"> See Silk 2014, which contains several
              examples to support his argumen; also see Silk 2019.</note> The precise relationship
            between all three translations requires more detailed analysis, but for the purposes of
            further comparison and the reader’s edification, we have included translations and
            transcriptions of many passages from the Dunhuang manuscript in the notes to our present
            translation from the Kangyur. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-67"/>
          <p tid="17">For the main text of the canonical Tibetan, we have based our translation on
            the edition in the Degé Kangyur in consultation with the Pedurma Comparative Edition
              (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and the edition in the Stok Palace
            Kangyur (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang</title>).</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="translation">
        <head type="translation"> The Translation </head>
        <head type="titleHon" tid="18">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
        <head type="titleMain" tid="19">“The Questions of Gaṅgottarā”</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-section-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-70"/>
          <p tid="23">
                        <ref cRef="F.222.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-205"/> Homage to all
            buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
          <lb/>
          <p tid="26">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Prince Jeta’s
            Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park, near Śrāvastī. At that time a laywoman named Gaṅgottarā was
            living in the great city of Śrāvastī.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-74"> The
              Dunhuang manuscript says it a bit more simply: “At that time, there was a laywoman
              named Gaṅgottarā in the city of Śrāvastī…” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de’i tshe grong khyer mnyan yod na | dge bsnyen ma gang ga’i mchog ces bya ba zhig
                yod de |</foreign> …).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-75"/>
          <p tid="27">One day, the laywoman Gaṅgottarā left Śrāvastī and went to Prince Jeta’s
            Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-76"> Degé:
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de nas dge bsnyen ma gang gA’i mchog mnyan
                yod nas byung nas rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga’ ra
                ba ga la ba der song ste</foreign>… Again, the Dunhuang manuscript reads a bit more
              simply, “She came out from her dwelling and went to see the Blessed One” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de gnas nas phyir byung ste | bcom ldang ’das ga la
                ba der song ste |</foreign> …). Similarly, the English translation of the Chinese in
              Chang 1991, 37, has, “Gaṅgottarā came from her dwelling in Śrāvastī to see the
              Buddha.”</note> When she arrived, she bowed down before the Blessed One with her head
            at his feet and, then she sat to one side.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-77"/>
          <p tid="28">Once she had sat down, the Blessed One asked the laywoman Gaṅgottarā a
            question, even though he already knew the answer:<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-78"> Degé has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bcom
                ldan ’das kyis mkhyen bzhin du</foreign>… (literally “the Blessed One, though he
              already knew…”). The Dunhuang manuscript also has the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mkhyen bzhin du</foreign>, “though he already knew,”
              but this part of the line is absent in the Chinese version.</note> “From where have
            you just come, Gaṅgottarā?”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-79"/>
          <p tid="29">“Blessed One,” Gaṅgottarā replied, “if someone were to ask a magically created
            being, ‘From where have you just come?’ what would be the answer?” <ref cRef="F.222.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-206"/>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-80"/>
          <p tid="30">“Gaṅgottarā,” responded the Blessed One, “a magically created being neither
            stands nor sits. It does not lie down. It does not come or go. It does not die. It is
            not born. So, how could one declare that it has come from some place?”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-81"/>
          <p tid="31">“Blessed One,” asked Gaṅgottarā, “are all things like magical creations?”</p>
          <p tid="32">“It is so, Gaṅgottarā.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-83"> Degé:
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bka’ stsal pa | gang gA’i mchog de bzhin
                no</foreign>. By contrast, the Dunhuang manuscript reads, “The Blessed One said, ‘It
              is so, it is so. It is just as you have said…” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bcom ldan ’das kyis bka’ stsal pa’ | de de bzhin no | de de bshin de |
                khyod kyis ci skyad smras pa bshin no |</foreign>…). Chang 1991 has “The Blessed One
              said, ‘Yes, indeed. What you say is true.’ ” (37).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-84"/>
          <p tid="33">“Blessed One,” she responded, “if all things are like magical creations, why
            do you ask, ‘Laywoman Gaṅgottarā, from where have you just come?’ ”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-85"/>
          <p tid="34">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One answered, “since magically created beings<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-86"> Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sprul pa ni</foreign>; Dunhuang: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sprul pa’i
                skyes bu gang yin ba de ni</foreign>, “a being that is magically created.”</note> do
            not go to the lower realms, and they do not go to higher realms, and they do not go to
            parinirvāṇa, do you, too, Gaṅgottarā, not go to the lower realms, or go to the higher
            realms, or go to parinirvāṇa?”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-87"/>
          <p tid="35">“Blessed One,” Gaṅgottarā replied, “if I truly saw the laywoman Gaṅgottarā as
            being different in nature from a magical creation, then it would not be appropriate for
            me to compare myself to a magically created being by saying, ‘The laywoman Gaṅgottarā
            does not go to the lower realms, does not go to the higher realms, and does not go to
            parinirvāṇa.’ Nevertheless, Blessed One, I do not see myself as being different in
            nature from a magical creation.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-88"> The
              Dunhuang manuscript reads differently: “If I saw my body as different from a magical
              illusion or a magically created being, then I would go to a good place of rebirth or a
              bad place of rebirth or realize complete nirvāṇa, but since I see no difference
              between my body and a magical illusion or a magically created being…” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdag gi lus sgyu ma dang | sprul pa dang tha dad par
                mthong na ni | dge ’gro dang | ngan ’gror mchi zhing mya ngan las ’das pa yang mngon
                du bgyid pa zhig na | bdag gi lus sgyu ma dang | sprul pa dang | tha myi dad par
                mthong bas</foreign>…).</note> Since I do not see myself in that way, Blessed One,
            how can I declare in this way that the laywoman Gaṅgottarā goes to the lower realms,
            goes to the higher realms, or goes to parinirvāṇa?</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-89"/>
          <p tid="36">“Even with this being the case, Blessed One, it is in accordance with the
            presence of mental straying, mental conceit, mental agitation, and vain imagining that
            one thinks the thoughts, ‘I go to the lower realms,’ ‘I go to the higher realms,’ and
              <ref cRef="F.223.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-207"/> ‘I go to
              parinirvāṇa.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-90"> This sentence is not in
              the Dunhuang manuscript or in the Chinese as reflected in Chang 1991.</note> Blessed
            One, the state of nirvāṇa<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-91"> Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mya ngan las ’das pa’i dbyings</foreign>; the
              Dunhuang manuscript has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mya ngan las ’das pa’i
                ngo bo nyid</foreign>, “the true nature of nirvāṇa.” On this passage, see also Silk
              2014.</note> is such that it never goes to the lower realms, it never goes to the
            higher realms, and it never goes to parinirvāṇa. The laywoman Gaṅgottarā has a similar
            state, Blessed One.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-92"> The Dunhuang
              manuscript reads, “I see that my own body also has the same nature” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdag gi lus kyang de bzhin du mthong lags
                so</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <p tid="37">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One responded, “have you not set out for
              parinirvāṇa?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-94"> Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gang gA’i mchog khyod ci yongs su mya ngan las ’das
                pa la yang dag par ma zhugs sam</foreign>. The Dunhuang manuscript here reads: “Are
              you not inclined toward the state of nirvāṇa?” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ci khyod mya ngan las ’das pa’i dbyings la gzhol bar myi byed
                dam</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-95"/>
          <p tid="38">“Blessed One,” Gaṅgottarā replied, “if someone were to ask what is not born,
            ‘Have you not set out for parinirvāṇa?’ what would be the answer?”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-96"/>
          <p tid="39">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One said, “since the phrase ‘what is not born’ is a
            designation for nirvāṇa, what would be the answer?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-97"> The Dunhuang manusript reads differently: “The true
              nature of that which is not born is nirvāṇa” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kye ba myed pa gang yin ba de nyid ni mya ngan las ’das pa yin no</foreign>). Once
              again, the Dunhuang manuscript is similar to the Chinese as reflected in Chang 1991,
              38.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-98"/>
          <p tid="40">“Blessed One,” Gaṅgottarā replied, “are all things the same as nirvāṇa?”</p>
          <p tid="41">“It is so, Gaṅgottarā,” he said. “All things are the same as nirvāṇa.”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-100"/>
          <p tid="42">“If all things are the same as nirvāṇa, then why, Blessed One, do you ask,
            ‘Gaṅgottarā, have you not set out for parinirvāṇa?’ Blessed One, if someone were to ask
            a magically created being, ‘Have you not set out for parinirvāṇa?’ what would be the
              answer?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-101"> The Dunhuang manuscript reads
              differently here: “Furthermore, Blessed One, it would be as if one magically created
              being were to ask another magically created being, ‘Are you not inclined toward the
              state of nirvāṇa?’ In that case, what would be the answer?” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gzhan yang bcom ldan ’das ’di lta ste | dper na sprul
                ba’i skyes bu zhig gis sprul pa’i skyes bu la ci khyod mya ngan las ’das pa’i
                dbyings la gzhol bar myi byed dam zhes de skad rmas par gyur na | des ci skad lan
                ’debs par gyur lags |</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-102"/>
          <p tid="43">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One responded, “this question does not have an
            objective basis.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-103"> The Dunhuang manuscript
              agrees here with the canonical Tibetan translation. Chang 1991 reads “A magically
              produced being has no mental attachments” (38), but the Chinese 此所問者無有攀緣 (“this
              question does not have an objective basis”) clearly matches the Tibetan, so we would
              disagree with Chang’s reading. For the Chinese version of this text, see <foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Henghe shang youpoyi hui</foreign>
              <foreign xml:lang="zh">恒河上優婆夷會</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṅgottara­pari­pṛcchā</foreign>), Taishō 310(31) (<ref target="https://ntireader.org/taisho/t0310_098.html">CBETA</ref>; <ref target="https://21dzk.l.u-tokyo.ac.jp/SAT2018/T0310.html">SAT</ref>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-104"/>
          <p tid="44">Gaṅgottarā inquired, “Do the words that the Blessed One has spoken have some
            connection to an objective basis?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-105"> The
              Dunhuang manuscript reads differently here: “Has this question been asked because
              there is some objective basis on the part of the Tathāgata?” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ci de bzhin gshegs pa la dmyigs pa mnga’ ba’i slad du
                bka’s rmas pa’ ’di rmas lags sam</foreign>). Chang 1991 has, “Does the Tathāgata’s
              very question stem from some mental attachment” (38). </note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-106"/>
          <p tid="45">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One answered, “even though this question does not
            have an objective basis, nevertheless, asking it will be of great benefit to the noble
            sons and noble daughters who are gathered here in this assembly.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-107"> The Dunhuang manuscript appears to read both similarly
              and differently from both the canonical Tibetan and the Chinese translation here:
              “Even though there is no objective basis to what I have said, nevertheless this
              question has been asked in order to bring to maturity those noble sons and noble
              daughters who are gathered in this assembly” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ngas smras pa la dmyigs pa yod pa ma yin mod kyi | ’on kyang ’khor ’di na yod pa’i
                rigs kyi bu dang | rigs kyi bu mo dag yongs su smyin par bya ba’i phyir | ’dri ba
                ’di dris pa yin no</foreign>). Chang 1991 reads, “I raised the question because
              there are in this assembly good men and good women who can be brought to maturity. I
              am free of mental attachment” (38).</note> Why is this? When the Tathāgata had not
            awakened directly and completely even to what is called the true nature of things,
            Gaṅgottarā, how much less would there be a thing arising from it that remains in
              parinirvāṇa?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-108"> Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gang gA’i mchog de bzhin gshegs pas ni chos nyid ces
                bya ba yang mngon par rdzogs par sangs ma rgyas na gang</foreign> (Degé, Stok, etc.;
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yang</foreign> Phugdrag) <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de las byung ba’i chos yongs su mya ngan las ’das pa
                la gnas pa lta ga la yod</foreign>. The translation above assumes <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de las byung ba’i chos</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yongs su mya ngan las ’das pa</foreign> are not in
              apposition. However, it is also possible to interpret them as being in apposition,
              with <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gang</foreign> thereby modifying the
              latter, in which case the translation could run as follows: “If the Tathāgata had not
              completely awakened even to what is called the true nature of things, Gaṅgottarā, how
              could he remain in the parinirvāṇa that is the thing (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>) that arises from it?” Skilling 2021, pp. 348–49,
              translates this sentence somewhat differently: “If the Tathāgata had not fully
              awakened to the true nature, Gaṅgottarā, then in his final nirvāṇa there would be a
              remainder of the dharmas arising from it.” The passage could perhaps be rendered in
              other ways, too. The Dunhuang manuscript also reads quite differently here, even while
              some of the component terms and phrases seem to be present, such as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lta yod par ga la ’gyur</foreign>: “For the Tathāgata
              even the names of such things do not have an objective basis, much less the existence
              of the things and of those who are inclined toward nirvāṇa” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de bzhin gshegs pa ni chos de dag gi mying yang
                dmyigs par myi ’gyur na | chos rnams dang | mya ngan las ’da’s pa la gzhol ba de dag
                lta yod par ga la ’gyur</foreign>). Chang 1991 translates the Chinese here as
              follows: “Because the Tathāgata knows that even the names of things are
              inapprehensible, let alone the things themselves or those who seek nirvāṇa”
              (38).</note>
            <ref cRef="F.223.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-208"/>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-109"/>
          <p tid="46">“If the Tathāgata had not awakened directly and completely even to what is
            called the true nature of things, and even less would there be a thing arising from it,”
            she replied, “how did the Blessed One properly plant roots of virtue in order to achieve
              awakening?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-110"> The first part of this
              sentence, in which Gaṅgottarā simply restates the preceding sentence, is not found in
              the Dunhuang manuscript or in the Chinese as reflected in Chang 1991. In the Dunhuang
              manuscript, Gaṅgottarā says only, “If that is so, why then does one produce an
              accumulation of the roots of virtue for the sake of awakening?” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gal te de ltar na | ci ltar byang chub kyi ched du
                dge ba’i rta ba’i stsogs par bgyid lags</foreign>). </note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-111"/>
          <p tid="47">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One responded, “a root of virtue is not something
            that has an objective basis. During the time when the Bodhisattva was planting the roots
            of virtue, he never let go of inconceivability. During the time when he was not planting
            them, he also did not let go of inconceivability.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-112"> The Dunhuang manuscript says, “Bodhisattvas do not have
              any objective basis and neither do the roots of virtue, because they have no thought
              at the time even that something is accumulated and similarly also at the time that
              something is not accumulated” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">byang cub sems
                dpa’ rnams dang | dge ba’i rtsa ba de dag kyang dmyigs su myed de | bstsags pa nyid
                kyi tshe sems myed pa’i phyir | bstsags pa ma yin ba’i tshe yang de bzhin
                no</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-113"/>
          <p tid="48">“With respect to the inconceivable,” Gaṅgottarā asked, “Blessed One, why is
            the inconceivable called the inconceivable?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-114"> The Dunhuang manuscript says, “What meaning is indicated
              by saying that there is no thought?” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sems ma
                mchis pa zhes bka’ stsal pa des don gang zhig ston par mdzad
            lags</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-115"/>
          <p tid="49">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One answered, “this teaching is not to be attained
            by the mind; it cannot be attained by the mind.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-116"> The Dunhuang manuscript says here, “This teaching can
              neither be understood by thinking, nor can it be attained by thinking” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">chos ’di ni bsam ba dag gis shes par ’gyur ba yang ma
                yin la | bsam ba dag gis ’thob par ’gyur ba yang ma yin no</foreign>).</note> Why is
            this? According to this teaching, when not even the mind itself has an objective basis,
            how much less so would the things that arise from the mind?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-117"> Though it is rendered a bit differently from the
              canonical Tibetan translation, the Dunhuang manuscript has a similar sense here:
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’di la sems kyang dmyigs par myi ’gyur na |
                sems las byung ba’i chos lta smos kyang ci dgos te</foreign>. </note> The mind’s
            lack of an objective basis, Gaṅgottarā, is what is called the continuous stream of the
              inconceivable.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-118"> The Dunhuang manuscript
              says here, “In this way, the mind’s very lack of an objective basis is what is taught
              as the state of the inconceivable” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’di ltar
                sems dmyigs su myed pa gang yin pa de nyid la bsams gyis myi khyab pa’i gnas shes
                bstan ste</foreign>).</note> That which is the continuous stream of the
            inconceivable is not attained. It is not fully realized. It is not known. It is not
            something to be experienced directly. It is not something to be attained. It is not
            afflicted. It is not purified. Why is this? It is because, Gaṅgottarā, the Tathāgata
            knows with certainty that all things are like space. All things, Gaṅgottarā, are
            unobstructed, just like space.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-119"> The last
              few sentences of the canonical Tibetan translation are conveyed in the Dunhuang
              manuscript with much the same meaning: “The state of the inconceivable is neither
              attained nor fully realized; it is neither afflicted nor purified. Why is this? It is
              because, as the Tathāgata always teaches, all things, being the same as space, are
              unobstructed” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bsam kyis myi khyab pa’i gnas
                de dag la ni thob pa yang myed | mgnon par rtogs pa yang myed de | kun nas nyon
                mongs pa yang ma yin | rnam par byang ba yang ma yin no | de ci’i phyir zhes na | de
                bzhin gshegs pas rtag du chos thams cad ni nam mkha’ dang mtshungs te | togs pa myed
                pa’i phyir ro zhes gsungs pas so</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-120"/>
          <p tid="50">“Blessed One,” Gaṅgottarā asked, “if all things are unobstructed, just like
            space, then why does the Blessed One use verbal expressions like ‘form,’ ‘feeling,’
            ‘conception,’ ‘formation,’ and ‘consciousness,’ as well as verbal expressions like ‘the
            aggregates,’ ‘the elements,’ and ‘the sense spheres’; ‘dependent arising’; ‘the
            intoxicated’ and ‘what is free of intoxication’; ‘the afflicted’ and ‘the purified’; and
            ‘saṃsāra’ and ‘nirvāṇa’?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-121"> The above
              paragraph is rendered in very much the same way in the Dunhuang manuscript, though it
              specifies “the twelvefold chain of dependent arising” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rten cing ’brel bar ’byung ba bcu gnyis</foreign>), rather than simply
              “dependent arising,” and it does not include the phrase “the aggregates.”</note>
            <ref cRef="F.224.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-209"/>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-122"/>
          <p tid="51">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One replied, “just as one uses the expression ‘self’
            even though the self has no objective basis at all, in precisely the same way,
            Gaṅgottarā, I use the expression ‘form,’ even though form has no objective basis at all.
            In the same way, too, I use the expressions ‘feeling,’ ‘conception,’ ‘formation,’ and
            ‘consciousness,’ even though consciousness has no objective basis at all. I also use the
            expressions ‘the aggregates,’ ‘the elements,’ and ‘the sense spheres’; ‘dependent
            arising’; ‘the intoxicated’ and ‘what is free of intoxication’; ‘the afflicted’ and ‘the
            purified’; and ‘saṃsāra’ and ‘nirvāṇa,’ even though nirvāṇa has no objective basis at
              all.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-123"> After the sentence, “…I use the
              expression ‘form,’ but form has no objective basis at all,” the Dunhuang manuscript
              says simply, “and the same is true with [the other expressions] up to nirvāṇa”
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mya ngan las ’da’s pa zhes bya ba’i bar du
                yang de bzhin no</foreign>).</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-124"/>
          <p tid="52">“Gaṅgottarā, just as a mirage does not produce water and has no objective
            basis at all, in precisely the same way, Gaṅgottarā, I use the expression ‘form,’ even
            though form has no objective basis at all. In the same way, too, I use the expressions
            ‘feeling,’ ‘conception,’ ‘formation,’ and ‘consciousness,’ even though consciousness has
            no objective basis at all. I also use the expressions ‘the aggregates,’ ‘the elements,’
            ‘the sense spheres’; ‘dependent arising’; ‘the intoxicated’ and ‘what is free of
            intoxication’; ‘the afflicted’ and ‘the purified’; and ‘saṃsāra’ and ‘nirvāṇa,’ even
            though ultimately not one of these things exists or has any objective basis.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-125"> In the Dunhuang manuscript, this whole
              paragraph is rendered more simply: “Furthermore, just as water has no basis in a
              mirage (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">smyug </foreign>[sic] <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgyu la chu myi dmyigs pa</foreign>), in the same way
              I use the expressions from ‘forms’ up to ‘nirvāṇā,’ even though it is the same [with
              them].”</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-126"/>
          <p tid="53">“One who practices the holy life without holding onto the Dharma as the final
            word, Gaṅgottarā, dwells in the practice of the holy life according to the well-stated
            Dharma and Discipline.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-127"> The Dunhuang
              manuscript reads differently here: “Gaṅgottarā, those who are established in the
              practice of the holy life in accordance with my teachings, and regard all things in
              the right way as having no objective basis, are the first ones who should be called
              those who are established in the practice of the holy life in the right way” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gang ga’i mchog gang gis nga’i bstan pa las tshangs
                par spyod pa mngon bar bsgrub pa de dag thams cad dmyigs su myed par yang dag par
                rjes su mthong na | gdod yang dag par tshangs par spyod pa mngon bar bsgrub pa zhes
                bya’o</foreign>). </note>
            <ref cRef="F.224.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-210"/> There are some who have
            self-conceit, Gaṅgottarā, who practice the holy life while thinking that their abiding
            by it has an objective basis, and I say that their practice of the holy life is not
            completely purified.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-128"> The Dunhuang
              manuscript reads a bit differently here: “It should not be said that those with
              self-conceit, who declare that an objective basis exists, dwell in the practice of the
              holy life in the right way” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mngon ba’i nga
                rgyal can dmyigs pa yod par ston pas na | yang dag par tshangs par spyod pa la gnas
                pa zhes myi bya ste</foreign>). This may help to make more sense of the terse phrase
              in the canonical translation,<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote"> gnas dmigs
                nas</foreign>, rendered in the main translation as “while thinking that their
              abiding by it has an objective basis.”</note> When they hear a profound teaching such
            as this one on cutting off the continuous stream, those who do not practice the holy
            life with complete purity become terrified, and they do not become free from birth, old
            age, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering, distress, and conflict; they
            receive their share of suffering, I say.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-129">
              The Dunhuang manuscript continues, “When they hear such a profound teaching as this
              one, those with self-conceit feel extremely frightened and become filled with a great
              doubt (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">the tsom</foreign> [sic] <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">chen po</foreign>). As a result, I declare, they do
              not become free from birth, old age, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering,
              and distress.”</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-130"/>
          <p tid="54">“Whether now or after I have passed away,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-131"> The Dunhuang manuscript reads, “After my parinirvāṇa…”
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">nga yongs su mya ngan las ’da’s pa’i ’ong
                du</foreign>). </note> Gaṅgottarā, there will be those who teach this kind of
            profound teaching on cutting off the continuous stream,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-132"> The Dunhuang manuscript says, “this kind of profound
              teaching on cutting off the continuous stream of saṃsāra” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’khor ba rgyun gcod pa</foreign>).</note> and ignorant people will come
            to conceive the idea that they have the intent to kill them. Due to their
            misunderstanding, these ignorant people thus come to generate a homicidal hatred and go
            to the lower realms.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-133"> The Dunhuang
              manuscript says, “some fools, due to the force of abiding by their wicked beliefs,
              will hate these individuals who teach the Dharma, and they will thereby conceive the
              intent to do them harm. As a result of these causes and conditions, they will fall
              into the hells” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">blun po kha cig lda ba ngan
                pa la gnas pa’i dbang gyis chos ’chad pa’i gang zag dag la zhe sdang gis gnod sems
                skyed pas na | rgu dang rkyen des sems can dmyal ba rnams su ltung bar ’gyur
                ro</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-134"/>
          <p tid="55">“ ‘Cutting off the continuous stream, cutting off the continuous stream,’ ”
            Gaṅgottarā replied. “Blessed One, what is it that you call cutting off the continuous
              stream?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-135"> The Dunhuang manuscript says,
              “When the Blessed One speaks of the teaching on cutting off the continuous stream of
              saṃsāra, what does it mean to say ‘cutting off the continuous stream of saṃsāra’?”
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bcom ldan ’das kyis ci skad du ’khor ba
                rgyun god pa’i chos shes gang gsungs pa de don gang gi slad du ’khor ba rgyun gcod
                pa zhes bgyi lags</foreign>).</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-136"/>
          <p tid="56">“Gaṅgottarā,” the Blessed One answered, “this teaching does not cut off the
            continuous stream; it is not the disintegration of it; it is not the destruction of it.
            For this reason, it should be called <emph>cutting off the continuous stream</emph>. It
            should also be called <emph>the ultimate endpoint</emph>. It should be called <emph>the
              continuous stream of the inconceivable</emph>.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-137"> The Dunhuang manuscipt says, “In this regard, that which
              should be spoken of as cutting off the continuous stream of saṃsāra is as follows:
              since that which is the ultimate endpoint and something (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>) of the state of the inconceivable cannot be destroyed or
              disintegrated, for this reason, I have declared it to be the teaching (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>) of cutting off the continuous stream
              of saṃsāra” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de la ’khor ba rgyun gcod pa zhes
                bya ba ni ’di lta ste | yang dag pa’i mtha’ dang | bsam gyis myi khyap pa’i dbyings
                kyi chos gang yin ba de ni dbyug cing gzhig du myed pas | de’i phyir ’khor ba’i
                rgyun gcod pa’i chos shes bstan to</foreign>). In both the Dunhuang manuscript and
              the canonical Tibetan, the Buddha’s explanation here would seem to rely on the dual
              sense of the meaning of the word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>) as both a
              phenomenon and the teaching.</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-138"/>
          <p tid="57">Then, at that moment, the Blessed One displayed a smile. Various multicolored
            rays of light issued from the Blessed One’s mouth in such a way that blue, yellow, red,
            white, rose madder, crystalline, and silvery rays of light spread throughout endless,
            limitless world systems, reaching as far as the Brahmā realm, and then they returned and
            disappeared into the Blessed One’s mouth.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-139">
              The Dunhuang manuscript reads similarly, except that fewer colors of light are
              mentioned and the names of them are slightly different: blue, golden yellow (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gser po</foreign>), red, rose madder, and water
              crystalline (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chu shal</foreign>). Also,
              significantly, the rays of light are said to disappear “on the top of the Tathāgata’s
              head” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de bzhin gshegs pa’i dbu’i gtsug
                du</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-140"/>
          <p tid="58">At that point, the venerable Ānanda draped his upper robe over one shoulder,
            knelt on his right knee, and then, joining his palms together in a gesture of respect
            toward the Blessed One, he paid homage to the Blessed One <ref cRef="F.225.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-211"/> and said this: “Blessed One, the
            tathāgatas do not display their smile without a reason. What is the cause? What is the
            condition? Why have you displayed your smile?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-141"> The Dunhuang manuscript says, “Then, when he had seen
              such a thing (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dngos po de lta bu dag mthong
                nas</foreign>), venerable Ānanda had the thought, ‘the tathāgata, the worthy one,
              the fully awakened buddha does not display a smile without cause or condition,’ and so
              he placed his robe over one shoulder, knelt down on his right knee, joined his palms
              together in a gesture of respect toward the Blessed One, and said this: ‘What is the
              cause, what is the condition, that the Blessed One has displayed a smile?’”</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-142"/>
          <p tid="59">“Ānanda,” the Blessed One replied, “I have direct knowledge of the fact<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-143"> Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ngas mngon par shes te</foreign>; the Dunhuang manuscript says, “I
              remember directly…” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ngas mngon bar dran
                te</foreign>). </note> that, in this very place, one thousand tathāgatas have taught
            this formulation of the Dharma, always starting with a single laywoman whose name was
            always Gaṅgottarā. All those laywomen went forth and achieved parinirvāṇa—that is, the
            state of parinirvāṇa without any remaining aggregates.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-144"> The Dunhuang manuscript says, “In a time in the past
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sngon ’dass</foreign> [sic] <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">pa’i dus</foreign>), in this place a thousand
              tathāgatas taught a teaching of this kind. At the head of each of the assemblies [to
              which it was taught] there was a laywoman named Gaṅgottarā. After hearing this
              teaching, all those laywomen and those in the assemblies went forth and achieved
              parinirvāṇa—that is, the nirvāṇa without any remainder (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lhag ma myed pa’i mya ngan las ’da’s pa</foreign>).”</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-145"/>
          <p tid="60">The venerable Ānanda then asked the Blessed One, “What is the name of this
            formulation of the Dharma, Blessed One? How should it be remembered?”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-146"/>
          <p tid="61">“Ānanda,” the Blessed One replied, “you may call this formulation of the
            Dharma <title xml:lang="en">Stainless</title>. Remember it as the one you may call
              <title xml:lang="en">Stainless</title>.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-147"> In the Dunhuang manuscript, the Buddha calls it “<distinct>Stainless
                Purity</distinct>” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dri ma myed pa’i rnam
                par dag pa</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-148"/>
          <p tid="62">When this Dharma discourse was taught, the minds of seven hundred monks and
            four hundred nuns were freed from the intoxicants and did not grasp any more. Then the
            gods of the desire realm and the gods of the form realm magically created divine flowers
            and sandalwood powder and strewed them over the Blessed One while saying, “It is
            marvelous that such a laywoman lives in the city of Śrāvastī! Not only does she converse
            with the Tathāgata but also her body does not become weary from it. In the very same
            way, this laywoman Gaṅgottarā has served victors of the past, generated roots of virtue,
            practiced virtue for a long time, practiced the holy life for a long time, and venerated
            many buddhas!”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-149"> An almost identical
              paragraph appears in the Dunhuang manuscript.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-150"/>
          <p tid="63">“So it is, divine ones,” the Blessed One said. “For a long time, she has
            served victors of the past, generated roots of virtue, <ref cRef="F.225.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-212"/> and practiced the holy life.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-151"> This sentence does not appear in the Dunhuang
              manuscript.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-152"/>
          <p tid="64">After the Blessed One had spoken these words, the laywoman Gaṅgottarā was
            delighted, and so was the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas, and they
            rejoiced at what the Blessed One had said.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-153"/>
          <trailer tid="65">Thus concludes “<title xml:lang="en">The Chapter of the Questions of
              Gaṅgottarā</title>,” the thirty-first of the one hundred thousand chapters of the
            formulation of the Dharma known as “<title xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Heap of
              Jewels</title>.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-154"> The Dunhuang
              manuscript also has a colophon that says it is part of the one hundred thousand
              chapters of <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Heap of Jewels</title>, and gives its
              title as “<title xml:lang="en">The Meeting with the Laywoman Gaṅgottarā</title>”
                (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen ma gang ga’i mchog gi ’dus pa</title>).
            </note>
                    </trailer>
        </div>
        <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-colophon">
          <head type="colophon" tid="66">Colophon</head>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-155"/>
          <p tid="67">Translated, edited, corrected according to revised terminology, and finalized
            by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Dānaśīla, along with the chief editor and
            translator Bandé Yeshé Dé and others.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes">
        <head type="notes" tid="68">Notes</head>
      </div>
      <div type="listBibl">
        <head type="listBibl" tid="70">Bibliography</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-listBibl-1">
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-156">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gang gA’i mchog gis
              zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo </title>(<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­gaṅgottara­pari­pṛcchānāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 75, Degé Kangyur vol. 43
            (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 222.a–225.b.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-157">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gang gA’i mchog gis
              zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
            [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
            bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
            Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China
            Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 43, pp. 638–49.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-158">
                        <ref target="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Pelliot%20tibétain%2089;img=1">Pelliot tibétain 89</ref>. Bibliothèque nationale de France, Paris. Accessed through
              <title xml:lang="en">The International Dunhuang Project: The Silk Road
            Online</title>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-159">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gang ga’i mchog gis
              zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Stok Palace Kangyur vol. 39 (dkon
            brtsegs, ca), folios 373.b–378.b.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-160">Chang, Garma C. C., ed. <title xml:lang="en">A Treasury
              of Mahāyāna Sūtras: Selections from the Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title>. 1983. Reprint,
            Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1991.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-161">Fiordalis, David V. “Buddhas and Body Language: The
            Literary Trope of the Buddha’s Smile.” In <title xml:lang="en">The Language of the
              Sūtras: Essays in Honor of Luis Gómez</title>, edited by Natalie Gummer, 59–103.
            Berkeley: Mangalam Press, 2021.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-162">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die
              lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen
              Texte</title>. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften,
            2008.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-163">Schuster, Nancy. “Changing the Female Body: Wise Women
            and the Bodhisattva Career in Some <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāratna­kūṭa­sūtras</foreign>.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International
              Association of Buddhist Studies</title> 4, no. 1 (1981): 24–69.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-164">Skilling, Peter. <title xml:lang="en">Questioning the
              Buddha: A Selection of Twenty-Five Sutras</title>. Boston: Wisdom Publications,
            2021.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-165">Silk, Jonathan A. “Out of the East: Tibetan Scripture
            Translations from Chinese.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Tibetology</title> 9
            (Beijing, 2014): 29–36.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-012-166">Silk, Jonathan A. “Chinese Sūtras in Tibetan
            Translation: A Preliminary Survey.” <title xml:lang="en">Annual Report of the
              International Research Institute for Advanced Buddhology </title>22 (Tokyo, 2019):
            227–46.</bibl>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="glossary" status="excluded">
        <list type="glossary">
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-168">
              <term type="translationMain">magically created being</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sprul pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྤྲུལ་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">nirmita</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A noun derived from the verb <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mā</foreign> (“to create”) and connected to the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">māyā</foreign> (“magical illusion”). </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-169">
              <term type="translationMain">magical creation</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sprul pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྤྲུལ་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">nirmita</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A noun derived from the verb <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mā</foreign>, (“to create”) and connected to the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">māyā</foreign> (“magical illusion”).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-170">
              <term type="translationMain">lower realms</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ngan song </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ངན་སོང་།</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-171">
              <term type="translationMain">higher realms</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mtho ris </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མཐོ་རིས།</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-172">
              <term type="translationMain">state of nirvāṇa</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mya ngan las ’das pa’i dbyings </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་དབྱིངས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">nirvāṇadhātu</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>Seemingly conceived of as either the state or nature of
                  being or that of a being. One of a number of applications of the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhātu</foreign>, which can have the sense of an
                  element or constituent part of the world and of the person. It can also be used in
                  the sense of “the true state of things” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmadhātu</foreign>) and “the sphere of the worlds” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">lokadhātu</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-173">
              <term type="translationMain">parinirvāṇa</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">yongs su mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">parinirvāṇa</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-174">
              <term type="translationMain">designation</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">tshig bla dags </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཚིག་བླ་དགས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">adhivacana</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A word that is used to refer to something else, a name, or
                  a term. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-175">
              <term type="translationMain">the ultimate endpoint</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">yang dag pa’i mtha’ </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">bhūtakoṭi</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-176">
              <term type="translationMain">form</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gzugs </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གཟུགས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">rūpa</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-177">
              <term type="translationMain">feeling</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">tshor ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཚོར་བ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">vedanā</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-178">
              <term type="translationMain">conception</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’du shes </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འདུ་ཤེས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">saṃjñā</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-179">
              <term type="translationMain">formation</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’du byed </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">saṃskāra</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-180">
              <term type="translationMain">consciousness</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rnam par shes pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">vijñāna</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-181">
              <term type="translationMain">aggregate</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">phung po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཕུང་པོ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">skandha</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-182">
              <term type="translationMain">element</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">khams </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཁམས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">dhātu</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-183">
              <term type="translationMain">sense sphere</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">skye mched </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">āyatana</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-184">
              <term type="translationMain">dependent arising</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rten cing ’brel bar ’byung ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྟེན་ཅིང་འབྲེལ་བར་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">pratītyasamut­pāda</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-185">
              <term type="translationMain">the intoxicated</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">zag pa dang bcas</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཟག་པ་དང་བཅས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">sāsrava</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>One who is still under the influence of the “intoxicants”
                    (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āsrava</foreign>), of which there are
                  sometimes said to be four: “lust” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāma</foreign>), “becoming” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhava</foreign>), “ignorance” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avidyā</foreign>), and “views” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dṛṣṭi</foreign>)</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-186">
              <term type="translationMain">what is free of intoxication</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">zag pa med pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཟག་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">anāsrava</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>One who is no longer under the influence of the
                  “intoxicants” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āsrava</foreign>), of which
                  there are sometimes said to be four: “lust” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāma</foreign>), “becoming” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhava</foreign>), “ignorance” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avidyā</foreign>), and “views” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dṛṣṭi</foreign>)</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-187">
              <term type="translationMain">objective basis </term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dmigs pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དམིགས་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">ālambana</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">ālambate</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Tibetan can translate both a noun (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālambana</foreign>) and a related verb (in which case the
                third person singular is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālambate</foreign>, “[one]
                perceives or conceives [something] as having an objective basis”). This term is
                  tied to the general idea that an act of sense perception or mental conception
                  takes an object of some kind that forms the basis or support for its continuing
                  perception or conception.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-188">
              <term type="translationMain">nature of things</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">chos nyid </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཆོས་ཉིད།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">dharmatā</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-189">
              <term type="translationMain">the afflicted</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">kun nas nyon mongs pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-190">
              <term type="translationMain">the holy life</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">tshangs par spyod pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">brahmacārya</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-191">
              <term type="translationMain">monk</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge slong </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">bhikṣu</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-192">
              <term type="translationMain">nun</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge slong ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་སློང་མ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">bhikṣunī</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-193">
              <term type="translationMain">victor</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rgyal ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">jina</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>An epithet for the Buddha.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-194">
              <term type="translationMain">blessed one</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bcom ldan ’das </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">bhagavat</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-196">
              <term type="translationMain">Gaṅgottarā</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gang gA’i mchog </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གང་གཱའི་མཆོག</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="reconstructedPhonetic">gaṅgottarā</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The laywoman who features prominently in this sūtra, as
                  well as the name of one thousand laywoman of the past who attained nirvāṇa,
                  according to the Buddha in this sūtra.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-197">
              <term type="translationMain">Ānanda</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">kun dga’ ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀུན་དགའ་བ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">ānanda</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-198">
              <term type="translationMain">Jinamitra</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dzi na mi tra</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="reconstructedPhonetic">jinamitra</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-199">
              <term type="translationMain">Dānaśīla</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dA na shI la</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དཱ་ན་ཤཱི་ལ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="reconstructedPhonetic">dānaśīla</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-200">
              <term type="translationMain">Bandé Yeshé Dé</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ye shes sde</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-202">
              <term type="translationMain">Śrāvastī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mnyan yod </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">śrāvastī</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-203">
              <term type="translationMain">Prince Jeta’s Grove </term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">jetavana</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-043-012-204">
              <term type="translationMain">Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga’ ra ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">anātha­piṇḍadārāma</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>