<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s Questions</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha­pari­pṛcchā</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ges zhus pa</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “Siṃha’s
          Questions”</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­siṃha­pari­pṛcchānāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa seng ges zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa
          chen po’i mdo</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སེང་གེས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">佛説太子刷護經</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="bo">གྱལ་བུ་སེང་གེས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">大寶積經, 阿闍世王子會</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gyal bu seng ges zhus pa</title>
        <author role="translatorMain" ref="eft:team-39">Translated by the Kīrtimukha Translation
          Group<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
          Buddha</author>
        <author role="translatorEng" ref="eft:person-95">Celso Wilkinson</author>
        <author role="translatorEng" ref="eft:person-92">Laura Goetz</author>
        <author role="translatorEng" ref="eft:person-96">L. S. Summer</author>
        <consultant role="advisor" ref="eft:person-97">William Giddings</consultant>
        <consultant role="projectManager" ref="eft:person-95">Celso Wilkinson</consultant>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="eft:person-51">James Duncan Gentry</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="eft:person-250">Rory Lindsay</editor>
        <editor role="associateEditor" ref="eft:person-362">Xiaolong Diao</editor>
        <editor role="copyEditor" ref="eft:person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="eft:person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="eft:person-274">Adam Krug</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="eft:person-391">Sameer Dhingra</editor>
        <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="eft:person-74">Ryan Damron</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="eft:person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.4 <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

      <publicationStmt status="2">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
          initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them
          available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
          <licence>
            <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
            <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND
              (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or
              printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage
              or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-044-001"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that
          these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2022-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl key="toh81" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 81</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 27.a–29.b</biblScope>
          <author role="translatorTib">Dānaśīla</author>
          <author role="translatorTib">Munivarman</author>
          <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
          <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="6">
            <volume number="44" start-page="53" end-page="58"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11623" work="W22084"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2022-09-15T14:52:02.901Z" user="admin">15/09/2022 14:52:02</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-11-04T09:32:27.59Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2019-11-04T09:32:27.59Z" user="andreas">2.e</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2020-01-27T13:10:23.67Z" user="mike">2.f</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.1" date-time="2021-06-15T11:58:44.452Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2021-07-05T15:11:19.175Z" user="line-tofte">2.e</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.2" date-time="2021-07-05T15:11:19.175Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
          (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.3" date-time="2021-07-06T09:17:42.579Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2021-07-12T14:00:53.829Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2021-07-12T14:00:53.829Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
          (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2021-07-19T06:25:53.337Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.5" date-time="2021-07-19T06:25:53.337Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
          (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.6" date-time="2021-11-22T15:52:17.975Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2022-02-24T10:12:23.876Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.7" date-time="2022-02-24T10:12:23.876Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
          (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.8" date-time="2022-02-24T10:12:54.169Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2022-02-28T08:59:27.905Z" user="line-tofte">2.a</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.9" date-time="2022-02-28T08:59:27.905Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
          (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.10" date-time="2022-02-28T08:59:55.774Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2022-04-12T11:51:03.044Z" user="line-tofte">2</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2022-04-12T11:51:03.044Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2022-04-12T11:51:34.263Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
          <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2022-09-15T14:51:54.832Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
      </notesStmt>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!--Note the "Contents" outline from the Word DOCX has not been included in the script. If the 
                    Outline to the text is quite complex, it is recommended that you paste the outlined contents from the DOCX here as a comment for
                    markup's reference. The actual table of contents will be generated in the Reading Room by the parser.
    Summary
    Acknowledgments
    Introduction 
    The Translation: Siṃha’s Questions
    Colophon
    Abbreviations 
    Bibliography

    -->
    <front>
      <div type="summary">
        <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-1"/>
        <p tid="2">At the opening of this sūtra, King Ajātaśatru’s son Siṃha and his five hundred
          attendants approach the Buddha, who is residing at Vulture Peak Mountain. After paying
          homage and offering golden parasols, Siṃha asks the Buddha a series of questions about the
          conduct of bodhisattvas. The Buddha answers each of Siṃha’s questions with a series of
          verses describing the various karmic causes that result in the qualities and attributes of
          bodhisattvas. Afterward, when Siṃha and his attendants promise to train in this teaching,
          the Buddha smiles, causing the three-thousandfold world system to quake. When the
          bodhisattva Ajita asks the Buddha why he smiled, the Buddha explains that Siṃha and all of
          his companions will become buddhas and establish buddhafields similar to that of
          Amitābha.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgment">
        <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-2"/>
        <p tid="4">This sūtra was translated by the Kīrtimukha Translation Group in Boulder,
          Colorado. Celso Wilkinson, Laura Goetz, and L. S. Summer translated the text from the
          Tibetan and Sanskrit. Thank you to William Giddings for serving as consultant for
          inquiries related to the Chinese versions of the text. Also, thank you to Tsultrim Delek
          for answering some of our questions regarding the Tibetan.</p>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-3"/>
        <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
          Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction">
        <head type="introduction" tid="8">Introduction</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-introduction-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-6"/>
          <p tid="10">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s Questions</title> is listed as the thirty-seventh
            chapter of the Ratnakūṭa (Heap of Jewels) section of the Kangyur and was translated into
            Tibetan from an unknown Sanskrit source in the early ninth century by the Indian
            scholars Dānaśīla and Munivarman and the Tibetan translator and chief editor Yeshé Dé.
            It is listed in both ninth-century imperial catalogs, the Denkarma and
              Phangthangma.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-7"> In both catalogs it is
              listed as being sixty ślokas in length, although the Phangthangma notably does not
              list it under the Ratnakūṭa collection but instead includes it among a general list of
              short sūtras less than one <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bampo</foreign> in
              length.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-8"/>
          <p tid="11">There are three versions of the text found in the Chinese Tripiṭaka. The
            translator of Taishō 344, the first and likely earliest version of the sūtra, is
              unknown.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-9"> Vinītā 2010, vol. I,2, p.
              456.</note> Taishō 343 was translated by Dharmarakṣa (<foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">zhu
              fa hu</foreign>
            <foreign xml:lang="zh">竺法護</foreign>) during the Jing Dynasty, around 200–300 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. The text was again revised in China by the Indian
            translator Bodhiruci (<foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">pu ti liu zhi</foreign>
            <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩提流志</foreign>) sometime between 706 and 713, when he undertook a
            project to translate the Ratnakūṭa collection as a whole (Taishō 310) into Chinese. At
            that time, <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s Questions</title> was included among fifteen
            sūtras that Bodhiruci chose to retranslate while accepting into his collection the
            Chinese of twenty-two other sūtras that had been translated previously.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-10"> Pederson 1980, p. 60.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-11"/>
          <p tid="12">Any Sanskrit original was thought to be lost until recently, when a Sanskrit
            manuscript of <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s Questions</title>, along with nineteen other
            sūtras, was found in the Potala Palace in Lhasa. Bhikṣuṇī Vinītā published a critical
            edition of this collection in the series <title xml:lang="en">Sanskrit Texts from the
              Autonomous Region</title> (2010) along with an emended edition of the Sanskrit,
            parallel editions of the Tibetan and Chinese, an English translation based on the
            Sanskrit, and reference to other Tibetan and Chinese recensions in the notes.
            Unfortunately, due to the manuscript’s inaccessibility and the collection missing a
            final colophon, its origin and date are currently unknown.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-12"> Currently the manuscript is kept in the Potala Palace in
              Lhasa. Vinītā’s critical edition is based on a copy of the manuscript kept in the
              China Tibetology Research Center. For further details on the state of this manuscript
              see Vinītā 2010, vol. I,1, pp. xv–xvii.</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-13"/>
          <p tid="13">The sūtra is not particularly well known, but verses of it are quoted in a few
            Indian commentaries, including Śāntideva’s training anthology, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>. It is also quoted in some Tibetan
            commentaries, usually in the context of using the Buddha’s words to verify that a
            certain virtuous practice is the concordant cause for developing a particular positive
            result or quality.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-14"> Our research has
              revealed two Sakya texts that quote a text called <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ges
                zhus pa</title> (<title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s Questions</title>), saying that it
              decries the negative effects of <term type="ignore">giving</term> someone alcohol: “If
              one gives alcohol to another, one will be born five hundred times with crippled limbs”
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gzhan la chang sbyin na skye ba lnga brgyar
                lag rdum du skye</foreign>). See Könchok Lhündrup and Sangyé Phuntsok, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa skya’i chos ’byung gces bsdus</title> volume 4, p. 55; the same
              quote is found in Künga Sangpo, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bzang po’i bka’
                ’bum</title>, volume 4, folio 314.a (p. 627). However, this passage is not found in
              any version of the text known to us. In fact, the sūtra seems to only discuss virtuous
              causes for positive qualities and does not discuss the inverse negative
            ones.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-15"/>
          <p tid="14">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s Questions</title> presents the practices of
            bodhisattvas through a question-and-answer dialogue between the Buddha and Prince Siṃha,
            the son of King Ajātaśatru of Magadha. At the beginning of the sūtra, Siṃha and five
            hundred of his attendants approach the Buddha and supplicate him, each offering a golden
            parasol. Feeling confident, Siṃha asks the Buddha a series of questions about the
            conduct of bodhisattvas concerning how one attains the various sublime qualities and
            attributes possessed by bodhisattvas and by the Buddha himself. The Buddha then directly
            answers each question, listing the practice or virtuous conduct that acts as the
            concordant cause for acquiring each particular quality. The dialogue thereby becomes an
            elementary teaching on virtuous causes and results, encompassing a broad range of
            attainments and how they are accomplished through the proper virtuous activity. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-16"/>
          <p tid="15">The dialogue between Siṃha and the Buddha seems to keep a wide audience in
            mind, discussing matters that could potentially appeal to a layperson’s worldly
            interests, such as acquiring wealth, beauty, power, and loyal servants. However, the
            primary focus of Siṃha’s series of questions remains how to correctly follow the
            practices of bodhisattvas and attain the final goal of becoming a buddha. Even when his
            questions are concerned with how to attain wealth and power, they can be understood to
            be relevant to a bodhisattva’s career (to attract followers, etc.), and we can surmise
            that Siṃha’s interest in them is for the benefit of others.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-17"/>
          <p tid="16">At the conclusion of the sūtra, Siṃha and his attendants promise to follow
            this teaching. The Buddha is pleased and gives them an extraordinary prophecy: Siṃha and
            all five hundred attendants will become buddhas and will, three hundred eons after the
            emanation of Maitreya, in an eon called Great Illumination, establish buddhafields “like
            that of Amitābha.”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-18"/>
          <p tid="17">Prince Siṃha himself is an elusive figure within Buddhist literature. While
            his father, King Ajātaśatru, is quite famous in the sūtras, any mention of this
            particular Siṃha seems to be unique to this sūtra. King Ajātaśatru’s other son and
            eventual successor, Udayabhadra, is much better known in the histories and literature,
            but from our research there does not seem to be any connection between these two
            princes, nor mention of Siṃha, outside of this sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-19"> Our research included a thorough survey of Sanskrit,
              Pali, and Tibetan resources for any mention of Siṃha. There is a Licchavi general
              named Sīha (the Pali equivalent of Siṃha), who questions the Buddha about generosity,
              found in the Anguttara Nikāya of the Pali canon (A.iii.38f; iv.79f), but he is
              unrelated to the Prince Siṃha of this sūtra. Further research on Siṃha’s identity
              might consider untranslated Chinese sources, which falls outside the scope of this
              project.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-20"/>
          <p tid="18">Our translation is based primarily on the Tibetan found in the Degé Kangyur,
            with reference to all the recensions found in the Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and Stok Palace Kangyurs. Any significant
            differences in meaning between these versions have been documented in the notes. We also
            consulted fragments of the text found in the collection from Dunhuang, but these did not
            show any notable differences.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-21"> The first of
              the two fragments, IOL Tib J 201, is not currently available. The second fragment, IOL
              Tib J 202, did not show any significant difference from the passages found in the
              Kangyur witnesses. </note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-22"/>
          <p tid="19">The Sanskrit manuscript from the Potala was closely consulted, as were the
            Sanskrit verses quoted in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>. The
            Sanskrit witnesses have been favored in some instances where they present a clearer
            reading than the Tibetan, particularly when these differences were verified by the
            Chinese translations. In this regard, Vinītā’s critical edition was an invaluable
            source, as we consulted it for the Sanskrit as well as for its comparative editions of
            the Tibetan and Chinese. In cases where we have referred to the Chinese, we have given
            preference to Bodhiruci’s translation, as it was a revision made with knowledge of the
            previous Chinese versions, and it also corresponds most closely with the Sanskrit
            manuscript. Any significant differences in meaning found in the Sanskrit and Chinese
            have been documented in the notes.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="translation">
        <head type="translation" tid="20"> The Translation </head>
        <head type="titleHon" tid="21">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
        <head type="titleMain" tid="22">Siṃha’s Questions</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-section-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-26"/>
          <p tid="26">
                        <ref cRef="F.27.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-289"/> Homage to all
            buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
          <lb/>
          <p tid="27">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Rājagṛha at
            Vulture Peak Mountain, together with a great saṅgha of 1,250 monks and a great saṅgha of
              bodhisattvas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-28"> The opening in the
              Sanskrit manuscript is somewhat unclear, as the traditional opening itself immediately
              enters into verse, and the description of the Buddha’s retinue is omitted. Vinītā
              suggests it is likely that this opening became corrupted through the processes of
              versification. See Vinītā 2010, vol. I,2, p. 456. Vinītā’s conjectural reconstruction
              for this opening is as follows: “Thus have I heard. At one time the Blessed One left
              Rājagṛha, / the victor, the unparalleled one, would roam about at the Vulture’s Peak”
                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">evaṃ mayā śrutam ekasmin samaye bhagavān
                rājagṛhāt samuddhitaḥ | vyavahared gṛdhrakūṭe jino hy apratipudgalaḥ ||</foreign>).
              “And together with a great saṅgha of bodhisattvas” is missing in Taishō 310.</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-29"/>
          <lg tid="28">
            <l><!--module starts-->Knowing all and seeing all,<!--module ends--></l>
            <l>The Victorious One is a peerless being.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-30">
                These two lines are included in the first verse of the Potala Sanskrit manuscript,
                where Vinītā has conjecturally reconstructed the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">jino hy apratipudgalaḥ</foreign> (“the victor, the unparalleled
                one”). Because of this, verses 1–4 of the Tibetan are out of line with the Sanskrit
                but realign with verse 5 in both editions due to the omission in the Sanskrit of the
                second half of verse 4 (see <ptr target="#UT22084-044-001-39"/>). These two lines
                are absent in Taishō 310.</note>
            </l>
            <l>The son<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-31"> Taishō 310 reads “the beloved
                son” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">所愛之子</foreign>).</note> of King
              Ajātaśatru</l>
            <l>Was known as Siṃha.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-32"> It is curious that
                the anonymously translated Chinese version (Taishō 344) names the prince <foreign xml:lang="zh">和休</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">he xiu</foreign>). Old
                Chinese phonology (Karlgren 1957) give this as <foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">g’ăb
                  χia̯b</foreign> or similar, whereas Tang dynasty reconstructions (Stimson 1976)
                would suggest <foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">*huɑ*xiou</foreign>, which approximates the
                Indic <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siṃha</foreign> only if the sequence of syllables
                is reversed. Assuming the possibility that <foreign xml:lang="zh">和休</foreign> is
                metathesis, <foreign xml:lang="zh">休和</foreign> may denote an attempt to transcribe
                the Prakrit form <foreign xml:lang="Pra-Ltn">sīha</foreign> (Woolner 1912, p. 213),
                which also means “Lion.”</note> {1}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-33"/>
          <lg tid="29">
            <l>Accompanied and attended</l>
            <l>By five hundred wealthy noblemen,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-34"> The
                N, H, and S editions of the Kangyur differ from D and the Sanskrit, as they all have
                “noblewomen,” or literally “daughters of merchants” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshong dpon bu mo</foreign>); however, all the Kangyur editions later
                on in verse 47 refer to Siṃha’s attendants as “these brahmin boys” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bram ze’i khye’u</foreign>). Usually, the term
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khye’u</foreign> refers to boys, so we have
                translated it accordingly. Taishō 310 reads “five hundred friends” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">與其同友五百人俱。</foreign>).</note>
              <ref cRef="F.27.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-290"/>
                        </l>
            <l>He departed from Rājagṛha</l>
            <l>With great royal grandeur.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-35"> This line is
                absent in Taishō 310.</note> {2}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-36"/>
          <lg tid="30">
            <l>Carrying golden parasols,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-37"> Taishō 310
                has “various types of parasols” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">種種幢幡寶蓋</foreign>) rather than “golden parasols.”</note>
                        </l>
            <l>They went before the perfect Buddha. </l>
            <l>Bowing their heads to the feet of the Buddha,</l>
            <l>They offered the five hundred parasols. {3}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-38"/>
          <lg tid="31">
            <l>Offering these to the Great Sage, </l>
            <l>All of them set out for awakening. </l>
            <l>By the power of the perfect Buddha, </l>
            <l>They became fearless.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-39"> These last two
                lines in verse 4 are not found in the Sanskrit or any of the Chinese.</note> {4}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-40"/>
          <lg tid="32">
            <l>Siṃha joined his palms in reverence</l>
            <l>And asked the perfect Buddha,</l>
            <l>“Will the Guide<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-41"> Taishō 310 has
                “Tathāgata” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">如來</foreign>).</note> please explain
              to me </l>
            <l>The conduct of bodhisattvas? {5}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-42"/>
          <lg tid="33">
            <l>“How does one become beautiful?</l>
            <l>How does one take miraculous birth?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-43">
                Taishō 310 reads “How can one be lotus-born?” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">蓮花中化生</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>How does one remember previous births?</l>
            <l>Great Sage, please give your <term type="ignore">instruction</term>.” {6}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-44"/>
          <lg tid="34">
            <l>Knowing their pure intentions with his wisdom,</l>
            <l>The Buddha gave his <term type="ignore">instruction</term>:<!--<note place="end"
                xml:id="UT22084-044-001-45"> For these two lines the Sanskrit has <foreign
                  xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">teṣām adhyāśayaṃ jñātvā buddho jñānena
                  cābravit</foreign>. While Vinītā interprets the Sanskrit in the same way we have
                interpreted the Tibetan, Silk asserts that “The <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"
                  type="term">jñānena</foreign> in pāda b cannot be taken with pāda a, despite the
                Tibetan rendering” and suggests that the translation from the Sanskrit should rather
                be “Having perceived their disposition, through this perception the Buddha
                said . . .” Silk (2013), p. 77.</note>-->
                        </l>
            <l>“I will give a teaching on what you have asked:</l>
            <l>The conduct of bodhisattvas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-46"> This verse
                is rendered in prose in Taishō 310 as “At that time, the Tathāgata, who had reached
                the shore of perfection in all conduct, replied to the question and spoke the
                following verses” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">爾時如來了達諸行究竟彼岸,
                  隨問而答即說頌曰</foreign>).</note> {7}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-47"/>
          <lg tid="35">
            <l>“One becomes beautiful through patience.</l>
            <l>One takes miraculous birth by pure conduct.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-48"> Taishō 310 reads that the cause for miraculous birth is
                generosity (Ch. <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">施</foreign>, correlating to Skt.
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dāna</foreign>). The line in Taishō 310
                reads, “One becomes lotus-born through giving” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">施蓮花化生</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>One recalls past lives by giving the Dharma.</l>
            <l>Youth, know it to be thus!”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-49"> Śikṣ places
                the last two lines of verse 8 after verse 16, which also refers to the giving of
                Dharma.</note> {8}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-50"/>
          <lg tid="36">
            <l>“How does one manifest</l>
            <l>The thirty-two marks, the eighty excellent signs,</l>
            <l>And a body radiant like gold<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-51"> This third
                line of the verse is absent in Taishō 310.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>That delights beings upon seeing?” {9}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-52"/>
          <lg tid="37">
            <l>“The marks manifest through complete generosity.</l>
            <l>Likewise, the excellent signs come to be through love.</l>
            <l>The golden radiance of the victorious ones</l>
            <l>Manifests by having an attitude of equality toward all beings.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-53"> The last two lines of this verse read differently in
                Taishō 310: “Through having an attitude of equality toward all beings, one has the
                form that delights beings upon seeing” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">等心於眾生，觀者無厭足</foreign>).</note> {10}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-54"/>
          <lg tid="38">
            <l>“How is retention attained?</l>
            <l>How does absorption arise?</l>
            <l>How do statements become acceptable?</l>
            <l>Great Sage, please give your teaching!”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-55">
                This fourth line of this verse is absent in Taishō 310.</note> {11}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-56"/>
          <lg tid="39">
            <l>“Retention is attained through receptivity to the Dharma.</l>
            <l>Absorption arises by training the mind.</l>
            <l>Statements become acceptable</l>
            <l>When one abandons senseless talk.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-57"> The
                fourth line of this verse in Taishō 310 reads, “when one respects all beings”
                  (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">敬重於眾生</foreign>).</note> {12}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-58"/>
          <lg tid="40">
            <l>“How does one become mindful?</l>
            <l>O Sage,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-59"> Omitted in the Sanskrit, which
                gives “O Great Sage” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahāmune</foreign>) in
                the fourth line.</note> how does one become intelligent?</l>
            <l>How does one come to act according to the Dharma?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-60"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos spyod
                  ’gyur</foreign>; Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gatimān</foreign> (“imbued with practices”). </note>
              <ref cRef="F.28.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-291"/>
                        </l>
            <l>O Holy Being,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-61"> The Sanskrit has “O Great
                Sage” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahāmune</foreign>).</note> how does
              one become wise?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-62"> The last two lines of
                Taishō 310 read, “[How can they achieve] practicing as taught in Dharma; [How can
                they be] solid [. . .] and indestructible?” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">如法而修行，堅固不可壞</foreign>). Vinītā 2010, vol. I,2, p. 471, note c.</note> {13}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-63"/>
          <lg tid="41">
            <l>“One comes to possess mindfulness by being undeceiving.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-64"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">g.yo med
                  pa</foreign> (“undeceiving”) can also be read as “unwavering”; however, the
                Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">aśaṭhaḥ</foreign> (“not being
                false”) and the Chinese <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">不諂</foreign> (“not
                flattering”) support the former connotation used here. The Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">g.yo ba med pa</foreign> (=<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">aśaṭhaḥ</foreign>) is attested in Negi 1993, p.
                6088.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>One becomes intelligent by contemplating meaning.</l>
            <l>One comes to act according to the Dharma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-65"> See <ptr target="#UT22084-044-001-60"/>.</note> by having reverence.</l>
            <l>One becomes wise by knowing the characteristics of phenomena.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-66"> The Sanskrit manuscript reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">paṇḍito dharmarakṣayā</foreign> (“One becomes wise
                by safeguarding the Dharma”). Taishō 310 reads, “by protecting Dharma his mind
                becomes solid” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">尊重所修行，護法心堅固</foreign>). Vinītā
                2010, vol. I,2, p. 473, note a.</note> {14}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-67"/>
          <lg tid="42">
            <l>“By what action is a bodhisattva<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-68">
                Reading the Sanskrit. In the Tibetan the subject is omitted.</note> born</l>
            <l>In the presence of the guardians of the world?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-69"> We are here following the Sanskrit manuscript and
                Chinese by placing this epithet for buddhas in the plural, since the Tibetan is
                ambiguous as to whether it is singular or plural. Although here in Siṃha’s question
                this might seem a bit odd, due to the cosmology that is referenced later on in the
                sūtra, it makes sense for Siṃha to speak about meeting with <emph>many</emph>
                buddhas throughout the multi-lifetime career of a bodhisattva. </note>
                        </l>
            <l>How do they come to ask questions</l>
            <l>Directly<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-70"> D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon sum du</foreign>; Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">viśāradaḥ</foreign> (“with confidence”).</note> before the guardians
              of the world?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-71"> The last two lines of
                this verse read differently in Taishō 310: “As [we] come to ask for the subtle
                truth, may the Tathāgata tell [us about it]” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">能請微妙義, 唯願如來說</foreign>).</note> {15}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-72"/>
          <lg tid="43">
            <l>“The one who never obstructs</l>
            <l>The giving of Dharma</l>
            <l>Will with great swiftness<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-73"> This third
                line in Taishō 310 reads, “By doing that, he will always be able to . . .” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">因此故恆得</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Come to meet the guardians of the world.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-74"> Taishō 310 reads “tathāgatas” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">諸如來</foreign>) rather than “guardians of the world.”</note> {16}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-75"/>
          <lg tid="44">
            <l>“How does one relinquish rebirth in inopportune states?</l>
            <l>How does one go forth to favorable states?</l>
            <l>How does one become heedful</l>
            <l>Wherever one takes birth throughout all of one’s lives?” {17}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-76"/>
          <lg tid="45">
            <l>“Inopportune births are relinquished through faith.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-77"> Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">śrāddho ’kṣaṇaṃ varjayati</foreign>. Śikṣ quotes as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">śrāddhayā kṣaṇaṃ akṣaṇaṃ varjayati</foreign> (“Opportune and
                inopportune births are relinquished through faith”).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>One goes forth to favorable states through moral discipline.</l>
            <l>One becomes always heedful</l>
            <l>By becoming familiar with emptiness.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-78">
                Here the Sanskrit applies the adverb “always” to “becoming familiar,” which are both
                in the same pāda in the Sanskrit manuscript: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">śūnyatāṃ bhāvayen nityam</foreign>.</note> {18}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-79"/>
          <lg tid="46">
            <l>“O Sage,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-80"> Omitted in the Sanskrit and
                Taishō 310.</note> how do bodhisattvas<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-81">
                The Sanskrit has the singular <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhisattvaḥ</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Purify their karma? </l>
            <l>How do they dodge the snares of Māra?</l>
            <l>How do they avoid becoming bereft of Dharma?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-82"> The last two lines of this verse in Taishō 310 read
                “How can he be loved by all in every lifespan?” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">而於世世中，為眾之所愛</foreign>). Vinītā 2010, vol. I,2, p. 477, note c. </note> {19}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-83"/>
          <lg tid="47">
            <l>“Karma is purified through firm resolution.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-84"> Here we are following the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhimokṣa</foreign> (“firm resolution”), which is
                confirmed by Taishō 310, <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">勝解</foreign>. The
                Tibetan has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par grol ba</foreign>
                (“complete liberation”), which in this case would suggest the Sanskrit
                back-translation <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vimokṣa</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Māra is subdued through perseverance.</l>
            <l>They avoid becoming bereft of the Dharma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-85"> Taishō 310 reads “he will be loved wherever he is born” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">如說而修行，所生令眾愛</foreign>). Vinītā (2010), vol. I,2, 473, note
              e.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>By acting according to their words.” {20}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-86"/>
          <lg tid="48">
            <l>“How does one’s voice become like the pleasing song </l>
            <l>Of the kalaviṅka bird and like the voice of Brahmā?</l>
            <l>O Sage,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-87"> “O Sage” is absent in Taishō
                310.</note> how does one please beings</l>
            <l>With their diverse inclinations?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-88"> The
                last two lines of this verse in Taishō 310 read, “How does one make beings / feel
                delighted upon seeing them?” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">云何令世間，見者皆歡喜</foreign>).</note> {21} </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-89"/>
          <lg tid="49">
            <l>“The voice of Brahmā is obtained by speaking truthfully.</l>
            <l>The voice becomes pleasing by abandoning harsh words.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-90"> This line in Taishō 310 reads, “The voice becomes like
                the song of the kalaviṅka bird through speaking gentle words” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">迦陵由軟語</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>One pleases beings<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-91"> For this line,
                Taishō 310 has “One makes those who see them feel delighted” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">見者皆歡喜</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>By relinquishing senseless talk and slander.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-92"> Here the Tibetan term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra ma</foreign> (“slander”) is not found in the Sanskrit manuscript
                (which would have read as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">piśuna</foreign> or
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">paiśunya</foreign>), though it is found in
                Taishō 310. See also Silk’s analysis of this section, where he offers a very
                different reading of the unemended manuscript: “Who separates the united pleases one
                of multiple inclinations.” Silk 2013, p. 78. </note> {22}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-93"/>
          <lg tid="50">
            <l>“How does one come to have a long life?</l>
            <l>How does one come to have fewer illnesses?</l>
            <l>How, O Supreme Guide,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-94"> The Sanskrit has
                “O Great Sage” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahāmune</foreign>).</note>
            </l>
            <l>Does a retinue<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-95"> Following the Sanskrit,
                which gives the singular <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">aparivāra</foreign>.
                The Tibetan has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">g.yog ’khor rnams</foreign>
                (“attendants”).</note> come to be undivided?” {23}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-96"/>
          <lg tid="51">
            <l>“One comes to have a long life by not killing.</l>
            <l>One will have fewer illnesses by causing no harm.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-97"> Rather than “by causing no harm,” Taishō 310 has “by
                reducing the sorrow of others” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">除他憂</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>A retinue comes to be undivided</l>
            <l>When one reconciles disputes.” {24} </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-98"/>
          <lg tid="52">
            <l>“How does one obtain wealth?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-99"> Here term
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">don</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arthāḥ</foreign>) is
                translated as “wealth.” </note>
              <ref cRef="F.28.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-292"/>
                        </l>
            <l>How do possessions cease to diminish?</l>
            <l>How does one become distinguished</l>
            <l>Wherever one is born?” {25}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-100"/>
          <lg tid="53">
            <l>“Wealth is obtained through nonattachment.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-101"> D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chags pa med
                  pas</foreign>; Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">alobhena</foreign>. Taishō 310 has “being without jealousy” (Ch. <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">不嫉</foreign>) to be the cause of obtaining wealth,
                although it may be implied that this is jealousy for other’s wealth, which would
                correlate to <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">alobha</foreign> in the
                Sanskrit. The Tibetan has “being without jealousy” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phrag dog med pas</foreign>) as the cause for the third quality in the
                Buddha’s reply, for being “distinguished wherever one is born.”</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Possessions increase by being without stinginess.</l>
            <l>One will be distinguished wherever one is born</l>
            <l>By being without jealousy.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-102"> For the
                last two lines of this verse the Sanskrit reads, “Without envy, one is
                distinguished. Being humble, one always becomes the best” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">anīrṣayā maheśatvaṃ nirmānāgragataḥ
                  sadā ||</foreign>). Taishō 310 is closer to the Sanskrit reading here: “Be humble
                to accomplish honor, / And one will possess might, power, and ease” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">謙下成尊貴，有威德自在</foreign>).</note> {26}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-103"/>
          <lg tid="54">
            <l>“How does one obtain divine sight?</l>
            <l>How does one obtain divine hearing?</l>
            <l>And how, O Guide, does one know</l>
            <l>The dying, transmigration, and rebirth of beings?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-104"> Verses 27 through 30 constitute the six
                superknowledges (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṣaḍabhijñā</foreign>),
                although for the third among these, which is represented in the last two lines of
                this verse, the Sanskrit reads differently: “How, O Guide, does one come to know /
                The arising thoughts of beings?” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">cittotpattiṃ ca sattvānāṃ jānīte kena nāyaka</foreign>). Taishō 310’s parallel
                verse supports the Sanskrit, although the two sets of questions appear in separate
                locations in the text and in the opposite order. The two older Chinese translations
                support the Tibetan, representing the third superknowledge as knowing the death and
                transmigration of beings, rather than their thoughts. </note> {27}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-105"/>
          <lg tid="55">
            <l>“Divine sight is obtained by giving lamps.</l>
            <l>The ear is purified<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-106"> Rather than “the
                ear is purified,” Taishō 310 reads “divine hearing is obtained” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">(成天耳</foreign>).</note> by giving music.</l>
            <l>The dying, transmigration, and rebirth of beings are known through wisdom.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-107"> Here the Sanskrit reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">cittotpattijñatā jñānād</foreign> (“The arising
                thoughts of beings are known through wisdom”). Taishō 310 says this is acquired
                through “avoiding the two extremes” ( <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">捨離於二邊</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Thus do these accomplishments arise.” {28}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-108"/>
          <lg tid="56">
            <l>“O Guide, how do the defilements of bodhisattvas<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-109"> This translation follows the reading in the Sanskrit
                witness, which gives the plural <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhisattvānāṃ</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Come to be exhausted?</l>
            <l>How do they recollect previous lives?</l>
            <l>How do they obtain miraculous powers?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-110">
                In Taishō 310 the order of these lines is different: miraculous powers come first,
                followed by previous lives and then defilements.</note> {29}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-111"/>
          <lg tid="57">
            <l>“The miraculous powers are obtained by offering vehicles.</l>
            <l>The recollections are gained by cultivating<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-112"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsgom
                  pa</foreign>. While Vinītā gives the emended Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">abhyāsād</foreign> (“constancy”), Silk prefers the unemended
                manuscript reading of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anāśād</foreign>
                (“nondestruction”). Silk 2013, p. 78.</note> mindfulness.</l>
            <l>They reach the cessation of defilements</l>
            <l>By fully abandoning the two extremes.” {30}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-113"/>
          <lg tid="58">
            <l>“How is the buddhafield perfected?</l>
            <l>How is its saṅgha perfected?</l>
            <l>How does its light shine perfectly</l>
            <l>Such that the ten directions are illuminated?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-114"> The third and fourth lines of this verse read
                differently in Taishō 310: “How does one obtain perfect light that follows the body?
                The ocean of merits is to be explained” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">獲隨體圓光，功德海當说</foreign>).</note> {31}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-115"> Verses 31 and 32 here appear later in the Sanskrit manuscript as Siṃha’s last
                question in the series, right after verse 40. The sequence of verses here follows
                the Tibetan translation.</note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-116"/>
          <lg tid="59">
            <l>“The buddhafield is perfected through aspiration.</l>
            <l>The saṅgha is perfected by magnetizing disciples.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-117"> For this line, Taishō 310 has “The saṅgha is perfected
                through the power of patience” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">忍力眾成就</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>The ten directions are illuminated brightly</l>
            <l>By offering jeweled canopies.” {32}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-118"/>
          <lg tid="60">
            <l>“By what quality<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-119"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>; Sanskrit and Śikṣ have <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karman</foreign> (“deed”).</note> does one attain </l>
            <l>The embodiment<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-120"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsdu ba</foreign>; Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saṃgraha</foreign>. Vinītā interprets this to mean
                one “attracts” all qualities. Vinītā 2010, vol. I,2, p. 489.</note> of all
              qualities, </l>
            <l>So that a bodhisattva<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-121"> The Sanskrit
                omits “bodhisattva.”</note> will be dear to beings</l>
            <l>Wherever they are born?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-122"> This verse is
                somewhat different in the Potala Sanskrit manuscript: “Through what act / Are all
                the dharmas included? / O Leader, how does one become / Dear to all beings?”
                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">saṃgrahaḥ sarvadharmāṇāṃ karmaṇā kena jāyate |
                  priyaś ca sarvasattvānāṃ kathaṃ bhavati nāyaka ||</foreign>). Note that the Sanskrit gives two questions here, while in
                the Tibetan there is only one. This verse is cited in Śikṣ; while the first two
                lines are identical to the Potala Sanskrit manuscript, the second two lines support
                the Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">priyaś ca bhoti sattvānāṃ yatra
                  yatropapadyate</foreign>. </note> {33}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-123"/>
          <lg tid="61">
            <l>“By surrendering the mind to the purpose of awakening</l>
            <l>In order to liberate all beings,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-124">
                Taishō 310 reads differently: “By having sufficient great aspiration / And by not
                retreating from the mind of awakening” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">勝志樂具足，不退菩提心</foreign>). “In order to liberate all beings” is absent.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>They attain the embodiment of all qualities</l>
            <l>And will thus be held dear.” {34}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-125"/>
          <lg tid="62">
            <l>“In what instruction should one train,</l>
            <l>And how should one cultivate the mind,</l>
            <l>To become an omniscient teacher</l>
            <l>Like you, Great Sage?” {35}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-126"> There is
                no parallel for verses 35 and 36 in any of the Chinese translations.</note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-127"/>
          <lg tid="63">
            <l>“If one trains in being impartial</l>
            <l>To all beings without exception,</l>
            <l>And if the mind is cultivated in that impartiality,</l>
            <l>One will become an all-surpassing victorious one.” {36}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-128"/>
          <lg tid="64">
            <l>“Throughout all one’s lives, </l>
            <l>How will the mind of awakening</l>
            <l>Never be abandoned even in a dream, <ref cRef="F.29.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-293"/>
                        </l>
            <l>Let alone while awake?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-129"> This last line
                of the verse is absent in Taishō 310.</note> {37}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-130"> The following two verses, 37 and 38, are found quoted
                in Śīkṣ. The content is quite similar to the Sanskrit manuscript. However, Siṃha’s
                question has been changed to a statement by exchanging the interrogative (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kena</foreign>) for a demonstrative pronoun
                  (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tena</foreign>). </note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-131"/>
          <lg tid="65">
            <l>“In whatever region one dwells,</l>
            <l>Whether a village or a city, </l>
            <l>By correctly guiding others toward awakening, </l>
            <l>The mind of awakening is not abandoned.” {38}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-132"/>
          <lg tid="66">
            <l>“Wherever one is born,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-133"> The first line
                of this verse is absent in Taishō 310.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>How can one acquire great strength</l>
            <l>And always be elevated with power</l>
            <l>So that even ten million māras can do no harm?”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-134"> Given the omission of the first line in Taishō 310 of
                this verse, the fourth line differs as well: “Hopefully the Honored One will explain
                it” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">唯願人尊說</foreign>).</note> {39}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-135"/>
          <lg tid="67">
            <l>“In this life, if one offers the five essences<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-136"> There is a parallel of this phrase found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>, where the Buddha describes thirty-seven
                ways that a wise person offers gifts: “He gives a gift of the five essences, which
                results in his having great strength in all his lives to come.” Rotman 2017, p.
                265.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>And gives courage to those who are afraid,</l>
            <l>Then wherever one is born<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-137"> This line is
                absent in Taishō 310.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>One will also have great strength,</l>
            <l>Always be elevated with power,</l>
            <l>And be unharmed even by ten million māras.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-138"> This final line of the verse is absent in Taishō
                310.</note> {40}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-139"> This verse is
                extended by half a verse’s length in both the Tibetan and Sanskrit.</note>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-140"/>
          <lg tid="68">
            <l>Having heard this teaching </l>
            <l>On the conduct of bodhisattvas<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-141">Reading
                the Sanskrit, which gives the plural <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bodhisattvānāṃ</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Directly from the Guardian of the World,</l>
            <l>Siṃha<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-142"> Sanskrit has <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nṛpātmaja</foreign> (“son of the king”), rather than
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">siṃha</foreign>.</note> was overjoyed.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-143"> The last three lines of this verse are
                absent in Taishō 310.</note> {41}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-144">
                From here onward, Taishō 310 is in prose rather than verse.</note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-145"/>
          <lg tid="69">
            <l>He and his companions</l>
            <l>Spoke the following words:<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-146">Sanskrit
                adds <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prāñjalir</foreign> (“with hands folded
                in respect”).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>“We will train</l>
            <l>In this teaching on conduct.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-147"> The N
                and H editions of the Kangyur have “steadfast conduct” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyod pa brtan pa</foreign>). The Sanskrit adds “O Sage” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mune</foreign>).</note> {42}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-148"/>
          <lg tid="70">
            <l>Then the Buddha smiled,</l>
            <l>And the trichiliocosm quaked.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-149"> For the
                last two lines of verse 43, the Sanskrit reads “The Buddha revealed a smile
                illuminating numerous fields” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">smitaṃ
                  prāviṣkarod buddho ’nekakṣetrāvabhāsakam </foreign>|). Taishō 310 matches the
                Sanskrit.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Ajita then asked the Buddha</l>
            <l>The following question:</l>
            <l>“Why did you smile?</l>
            <l>Great Sage,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-150"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thub chen</foreign>; Sanskrit has “Lord” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vibho</foreign>).</note> please explain this!”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-151"> In Taishō 310, “please explain this” is
                followed by “to rid us of doubts” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">斷除疑惑</foreign>).</note> {43}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-152"> This
                verse is expanded by the two lines of verse in the Tibetan. It is of regular meter
                length in the Sanskrit.</note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-153"/>
          <lg tid="71">
            <l>And so to Ajita </l>
            <l>The Buddha replied,</l>
            <l>“Ajita, please listen to the reason </l>
            <l>That I smiled.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-154"> “Please listen to the
                reason / That I smiled” is absent in Taishō 310.</note> {44}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-155"/>
          <lg tid="72">
            <l>“Previously,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-156"> “Previously” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">purā</foreign>) is taken from the Sanskrit. Taishō
                310 also reflects this with <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">於往昔</foreign>.</note>
              these boys<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-157"> In the Chinese version, the
                subject is “the prince and his five hundred friends” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">此王子等五百同友</foreign>).</note> assembled before</l>
            <l>Eight hundred million buddhas and a quadrillion more.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-158"> Here the Sanskrit reads this number as eighty <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">koṭis</foreign> and twelve <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niyutas</foreign>. Taishō 310 has ten <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niyutas</foreign> and eighty <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">koṭis</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">十那由他八十億</foreign>).</note>
            </l>
            <l>For the purpose of awakening,</l>
            <l>They made offerings to those guides of humans.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-159"> “They made offerings to the guides of humans” is
                absent in Taishō 310.</note> {45}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-160"/>
          <lg tid="73">
            <l>“Since the time of<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-161"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshun chad du</foreign>; Sanskrit has <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">upāharya</foreign>, “after having offered . . .”
                (according to Vinītā’s emendation, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upahāya</foreign> is found in the Sanskrit manuscript). Vinītā 2010, p. 498, n.
                4.</note> Dīpaṅkara—</l>
            <l>The perfect buddha,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-162"> Sanskrit has
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahārṣiṃ</foreign> (“great sage”). </note>
              supreme among people<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-163"> The phrase
                “supreme among people” is absent in the Chinese.</note>—</l>
            <l>I have been ripening</l>
            <l>These brahmin boys.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-164"> For the last two
                pādas of this verse the Sanskrit reads, “I have ripened them when they showed
                promise of accomplishment” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">paripācitā mayā
                  caite yadā siddhipradāyakāḥ ||</foreign>). Taishō 310 also includes “When I came
                before the Buddha Dīpaṅkara as a young brahmin I brought them to ripen” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">而我往在然燈佛時。作婆羅門子成熟於彼</foreign>). This addition, implying
                that the Buddha was there with the five hundred brahmin boys, relates to the
                narrative of the brahmin Megha, a previous incarnation of the Buddha Śākyamuni who
                made an offering to the Buddha Dīpaṅkara and received from him the prophecy that he
                would someday attain buddhahood as Śākyamuni. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvastu</title> recounts this narrative while also mentioning five hundred
                brahmins who were fellow students of Megha, although it does not mention them going
                before Dīpaṅkara. See Conze 1973, pp. 20–24. </note> {46}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-165"/>
          <lg tid="74">
            <l>“When the splendid<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-166"> This reading
                follows D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdzes pa</foreign>, which comes
                close to reflecting the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">suśobhana</foreign>; K has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdzes
                  po</foreign>; K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, H, N, and S have “great” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chen po</foreign>). </note> eon called</l>
            <l>Great Illumination<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-167"> The name of this
                eon varies significantly among the Chinese versions: Taishō 310 has <foreign xml:lang="zh">安樂光嚴</foreign> (“Adorned with Radiant Peace and Happiness,” Skt.
              *<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Sukhaprabhāśubha</foreign>), although
                  <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">光嚴</foreign> may just be a description of the
                eon as being “splendid” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śobha</foreign>), in
                which case the proper name would just be <foreign xml:lang="zh">安樂</foreign> “Peace
                and Happiness”; Taishō 343 has <foreign xml:lang="zh">摩訶波羅會</foreign>, which is
                possibly a transliteration for “Mahābala”; and Taishō 344 has <foreign xml:lang="zh">摩訶波羅蜜</foreign>, a transliteration for “Mahāpāramitā.”</note> arises,</l>
            <l>In that single eon</l>
            <l>They will all become guides.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-168"> The
                Sanskrit has “the most excellent among humans” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvipadottamāḥ</foreign>). “In that single eon / They will all become
                guides” is absent in the Chinese.</note> {47}<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-169"> The Sanskrit places here what is verse 49 in the
                Tibetan, thus reading the verses in the alternate order: 49, 47, 48; and then
                syncing up again with the Tibetan at verse 50.</note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-170"/>
          <lg tid="75">
            <l>“They will become guides for the world </l>
            <l>Named Jñānaketudhvaja,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-171"> The Chinese
                affirms that this implies they will all have the same name. This name predicted for
                the five hundred varies significantly among the Chinese versions: Taishō 310 has
                  <foreign xml:lang="zh">智慧幢相</foreign> (“Wisdom Banner,” Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Jñānadhvaja</foreign>); Taishō 343 has an unclear
                transliteration, <foreign xml:lang="zh">若那伎頭陀耶</foreign>; and Taishō 344 has
                  <foreign xml:lang="zh">若那頸頭陀那</foreign>, possibly as transliteration for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Jñānagadhutana</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>And their array will be</l>
            <l>Just like that of Amitābha. {48}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-172"/>
          <lg tid="76">
            <l>“From the time of Maitreya</l>
            <l>Through three hundred full eons, <ref cRef="F.29.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-294"/>
                        </l>
            <l>They will always</l>
            <l>Meet with buddhas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-173"> In Taishō 310 this
                passage reads differently: “All of them will always be miraculously born in the
                presence of Maitreya and other blessed ones in the future and sincerely make
                offerings to them. And thus, they will serve one billion blessed ones for three
                hundred eons” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">彼諸人於未來世彌勒佛等諸世尊前，恆受化生親承供養，如是奉事十億如來滿三百劫</foreign>). Taishō 310 then includes an
                additional unique passage here: “The lattermost of these buddhas will be named
                Boundless Wisdom, well trained in all dharmas. At that time, the Buddha Boundless
                Wisdom will know the hearts of all those people as desiring happiness, and so,
                appropriately for each, he will grant an account of their achievements of
                unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">其最後佛號無邊智善學諸法。時無邊智佛。知彼諸人心之欲樂。各隨所應。為授阿耨 多羅三藐三菩提記</foreign>). This is the only
                mention of the Buddha Boundless Wisdom (<foreign xml:lang="zh">無邊智</foreign>) in the
                Taishō Tripiṭaka. Boundless Wisdom is predicted to be the last buddha of the far
                distant future that Siṃha and his five hundred companions will meet during their
                long careers as bodhisattvas. For this verse the Sanskrit reads, “Now and in the
                future, after honoring sixty <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">koṭis</foreign>
                of great sages, they will become guides [i.e., buddhas]” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">adhunānāgate ’py ete  ṣaṣṭi koṭī maharṣiṇām | maitreyādīn samabhyarcya
                  bhaviṣyanti vināyakāḥ ||</foreign>). The Tibetan gives a translation for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vināyaka</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par dren pa</foreign>) in verse 47, where the Sanskrit gives
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvipadottama</foreign>. See <ptr target="#UT22084-044-001-168"/>. </note> {49}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-174"/>
          <lg tid="77">
            <l>“Moreover, whoever hears but the name </l>
            <l>Under which they attain awakening</l>
            <l>Shall, without exception, become incomparable</l>
            <l>And omniscient beings in the world.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-175">
                For this verse the Sanskrit reads, “Moreover, whoever shall hear but the name of
                those bodhisattvas / Will have no doubts in awakening or fear of the path toward it”
                  (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">ye caiṣāṃ bodhisattvānāṃ nāmaṃ śroṣyanti
                  kevalam | na teṣāṃ saṃśayo bodher nāpi tadgatito bhayam ||</foreign>). These lines
                are absent in Taishō 310.</note> {50}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-176"/>
          <lg tid="78">
            <l>“Whoever, on hearing this prophecy,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-177">
                The Tibetan and Sanskrit here (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lung
                  bstan</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vyākaraṇa</foreign>) could
                arguably refer to either the prophecy or the teaching given previous to it. Taishō
                310 describes the term as an “explanation” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">所説</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Becomes inspired </l>
            <l>Will have merit unparalleled</l>
            <l>Throughout these three worlds. {51}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-178"/>
          <lg tid="79">
            <l>“Consider someone who for six thousand eons</l>
            <l>Filled up all the buddhafields<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-179"> Here
                the Sanskrit describes filling one thousand buddhafields for one hundred <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">koṭi</foreign> eons. </note>
                        </l>
            <l>With jewels and offered them </l>
            <l>For the purpose of awakening.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-180"> “For the
                purpose of awakening” is absent in the Chinese.</note> {52}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-181"/>
          <lg tid="80">
            <l>“The tally of that person’s merit</l>
            <l>Could never match or compare to</l>
            <l>Hearing this Dharma presentation<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-182"> The
              Sanskrit has “hearing this true Dharma one will/shall (optative) have confidence in it” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">saṃśrutya saddharmaṃ śraddadhyād</foreign>). Taishō
                310 has “the roots of virtue that are born by hearing this Dharma presentation”
                  (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">聞是經典所生善根</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>And setting out for the sake of awakening.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-183"> “And setting out for the sake of awakening” is absent
                in Taishō 310.</note> {53}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-184"/>
          <lg tid="81">
            <l>When this Dharma had been expounded,</l>
            <l>By the power of the Protector of the World,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-185"> For these first two lines the Sanskrit has “Eighty
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">koṭis</foreign> of beings advanced toward
                the highest awakening” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">koṭiyāśīti sattvānām
                  agrabodhau pratasthire</foreign>). Taishō 310 matches the Sanskrit.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>The gods brought down a rain of flowers,</l>
            <l>And the trichiliocosm quaked. {54}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-186"/>
          <lg tid="82">
            <l>Siṃha, along with his companions,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-187"> The
                Sanskrit has “most excellent youths” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śreṣṭhisutaiḥ</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Obtained the five superknowledges and,</l>
            <l>Having made offerings for one week,</l>
            <l>Took ordination in the teaching.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-188"> The
                Sanskrit omits “in the teaching.”</note> {55}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-189"/>
          <lg tid="83">
            <l>All of them obtained absorption</l>
            <l>And inexhaustible<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-190"> The Sanskrit omits
                “inexhaustible.”</note> retention.</l>
            <l>Wishing to accomplish<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-191"> Reading the
                Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">sattvārthaṃ
                  sampupūrṣanto</foreign>. See Vinītā 2010, vol. I,2, p. 509, note c. </note> the
              welfare of beings,</l>
            <l>They brought them to<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-192"> Sanskrit has
                “through the exhibition of the Dharma of the buddhas” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">buddha­dharma­nidarśanāt</foreign>).</note> the Dharma of the
                buddhas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-193"> There is no parallel for
                this last verse in the Chinese. Taishō 310 includes a unique concluding passage here
                that describes the rejoicing assembly and affirms that the Buddha had eliminated any
                of Siṃha’s doubts: “At that time the bodhisattvas, all the gods, and all those who
                were inspired toward the great awakening rejoiced as they saw the prince and his
                companions demonstrate their superpowers in accordance with the wishes of all. They
                said, ‘The doubts of Prince Siṃha are all expelled by the Tathāgata, the Dharma
                King. Thus is the inconceivability of the Blessed One. His true Dharma, his pure
                faith, and their fruits are inconceivable. There is no limit or end to the
                Tathāgata’s merits; there is no Dharma that he has not attained. He causes those who
                are not awakened to become awakened; his capability pervades all realms, as he has
                attained the complete Dharma of the three times. After hearing such a collection of
                merits that results in pleasure and peace, who among the wise would not have their
                faith and satisfaction arise and be inspired toward awakening?’ ” (<foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">爾時諸菩薩摩訶薩及諸天人， 所有趣向大菩提者， 見彼王子與諸同友隨眾所樂示現神變， 皆大歡喜. 咸作是言： 「
                  師子王子所問疑惑， 如來法王悉為除斷。 如是世尊不可思議， 如來正法及能信受， 乃至果報不可思議。 如來功德無量無邊， 於一切法靡不明達。 為世導師度未度者，
                  普能遍於十方世界， 悉已了知三世諸法。 誰有智者得聞如是</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">生安樂處功德之聚， 而不發起猛利信樂, 趣求菩提？ 」</foreign>).</note> {56}</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-194"/>
          <p tid="84">When this Dharma presentation was taught, eight hundred million beings set out
            for supreme awakening.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-195"> The beginning of
              this paragraph is omitted in the Sanskrit. There, the line “eight hundred million
              beings set out for supreme awakening” is found in verse 54 (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">koṭiyāśīti sattvānām agrabodhau pratasthire</foreign>).</note> When the
            Blessed One had spoken, Siṃha, along with his companions and the world with its gods,
            humans, asuras, and gandharvas, rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-196"> The Sanskrit continues in verse up to this
              point. Verse 57 in the Sanskrit corresponds to this paragraph, which is much briefer
              in the Sanskrit, as much of the audience is omitted: “Thus the Blessed One having
              spoken, Prince Siṃha was pleased. The entire world with its gods was delighted by the
              words of the Sage” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">idaṃ hy avocad bhagavāṃs
                tuṣṭaḥ siṃho nṛpātmajaḥ | sarve sadevalokā hi abhyanandan muner
              vacaḥ ||</foreign>).</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-197"/>
          <trailer tid="85">This concludes the thirty-seventh chapter, “<title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s
              Questions,”</title> from the eleven hundred chapters of the Dharma presentation of
              <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Heap of Jewels</title>. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-colophon">
          <head type="colophon" tid="86">Colophon</head>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-198"/>
          <p tid="87">The Indian preceptors Dānaśīla and Munivarman and the chief editor-translator
            Bandé Yeshé Dé translated, edited, and finalized this according to the new lexical
            register.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes">
        <head type="notes" tid="88">Notes</head>
        <list type="abbreviations">
          <head type="abbreviations" tid="89">Abbreviations</head>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-295">
            <abbr>D</abbr>
            <expan>Degé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-200">
            <abbr>H</abbr>
            <expan>Lhasa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhol</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-201">
                        <abbr>K</abbr>
                        <expan>Kangxi (Peking late 17th century)
              Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-202">
                        <abbr>K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
            </abbr>
                        <expan>Yongle (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">g.yung lo</foreign>)
            Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-203">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snar thang</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-204">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-205">
                        <abbr>Taishō 310</abbr>
                        <expan>8th century Chinese
              translation by Bodhiruci (<foreign xml:lang="zh">菩提流志</foreign>), Taishō 310
              (37)</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-206">
                        <abbr>Taishō 343</abbr>
                        <expan>3rd century Chinese
              translation by Dharmarakṣa (<foreign xml:lang="zh">竺法護</foreign>)</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-207">
                        <abbr>Sanskrit</abbr>
                        <expan>Sanskrit manuscript found
              in the Potala Palace (see introduction and bibliography)</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-208">
                        <abbr>Śikṣ</abbr>
                        <expan>Sanskrit text of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title> by Śāntideva</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-044-001-209">
                        <abbr>Taishō 344</abbr>
                        <expan>An early Chinese
              translation by unknown translators</expan>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="listBibl">
        <head type="listBibl" tid="90">Bibliography</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-listBibl-1">
          <head type="section" tid="91">Tibetan Primary Source Texts</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-210">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ges zhus pa</title>
              (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha­paripṛcchā</title>). Toh 81, Degé Kangyur vol. 44
            (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 27.a–29.b.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-211">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ges zhus pa</title>. bka’
            ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib
            ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of
            the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe
            skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 44, pp. 72–81.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-212">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ges zhus pa</title>. Stok
            Palace Kangyur vol. 40 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 71.a–74.b. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-213">
                        <ref target="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20Tib%20J%20201;img=1">IOL Tib
              J 201</ref>. British Library, London. Accessed through The International Dunhuang
            Project: The Silk Road Online.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-214">
                        <ref target="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20Tib%20J%20202;img=1">IOL Tib
              J 202</ref>. British Library, London. Accessed through The International Dunhuang
            Project: The Silk Road Online.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-215">Śāntideva. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa kun las
              btus pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>). Toh 3940, Degé
            Tengyur vol. 213 (dbu ma, khi), folios 3.a–194.b. </bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-listBibl-2">
          <head type="section" tid="92">Other Tibetan Sources</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-216">Könchok Lhündrup (dkon mchog lhun grub) and Sangyé
            Phuntsok (sangs rgyas phun tshogs). “dam pa’i chos kyi byung tshul bstan pa’i rgya
            mtshor ’jug pa’i gru chen dang de’i rtsom ’phro kha skong legs bshad nor bu’i bang
            mdzod.” In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa skya’i chos ’byung gces bsdus</title>, 4:1–253.
            Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
            2009. <ref target="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W1PD90704">BDRC W1PD90704</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-217">Künga Sangpo (kun dga’ bzang po). “spring yig slob ma
            la phan pa.” In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngor chen kun dga’ bzang po’i bka’ ’bum</title>
              (<title xml:lang="en">The Complete Works of Ngor-chen Kun-dga’-bzang-po</title>),
            4:619–60 (folios 310.a–330.b). Dehradun: Sakya Center, 199?. <ref target="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W11577">BDRC W11577</ref>. </bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-listBibl-3">
          <head type="section" tid="93">Sanskrit and Chinese Primary Source Texts</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-218">“Siṃhaparipṛcchāmahāyānasūtra.” In <title xml:lang="en">A Unique Collection of Twenty Sūtras in a Sanskrit Manuscript from the
            Potala</title>. Sanskrit Texts from the Tibetan Autonomous Region 7/1, vol. I,2, pp.
            453–520. A critical edition of the Sanskrit, Chinese, and Tibetan with an English
            translation edited and translated by Bhikṣunī Vinītā. Beijing: China Tibetology
            Publishing House Austrian Academy of Sciences Press, 2010. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-219">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha­pari­pṛcchā­mahāyāna­sūtra</title> (<title xml:lang="zh">大寶積經, 阿闍世王子會</title>,
            “Ratnakūṭa-sūtra, the Meeting with the Son of King Ajātaśatru”). <ref target="https://cbetaonline.dila.edu.tw/en/T0310_001">Taishō 310</ref>. Accessed May
            31, 2018. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-220">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha­pari­pṛcchānāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title> (<title xml:lang="zh">佛説太子刷護經</title>).
              <ref target="https://cbetaonline.dila.edu.tw/en/T0343_001">Taishō 343</ref>. Accessed
            May 31, 2018.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-221">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha­pari­pṛcchānāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title> (<title xml:lang="zh">佛説太子和休經</title>).
              <ref target="https://cbetaonline.dila.edu.tw/en/T0344_001">Taishō 344</ref>. Accessed
            May 31, 2018.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-222">Śāntideva.<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
              Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>. In <title xml:lang="en">Śikṣāsamuccaya of Śāntideva</title>,
            edited by P. L. Vaidya. Buddhist Sanskrit Texts 11. Darbhanga: Mithila Institute of
            Post-Graduate Studies and Research in Sanskrit Learning, 1960. English translation in
            Goodman, Charles. <title xml:lang="en">The Training Anthology of Śāntideva: A
              Translation of the Śikṣā-samuccaya</title>. New York: Oxford University Press,
            2016.</bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-listBibl-4">
          <head type="section" tid="94">Secondary Literature</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-223">Chakravarti, Uma. <title xml:lang="en">Social
              Dimensions of Early Buddhism</title>. Delhi: Munshiram Manoharlal Publishers,
            1996.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-224">Conze, Edward. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist
              Scriptures</title>. Middlesex: Penguin Books, 1959.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-225">Dungkar Losang Trinlé (dung dkar blo bzang phrin las).
              <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dung dkar bod rig pa’i tshig mdzod chen mo</title> (Dungkar’s
            complete Tibetological dictionary). Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang
            (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2002.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-226">Karlgren, B. <title xml:lang="la">Grammata Serica
              Recensa</title>. Stockholm: Museum of Far Eastern Antiques, 1957.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-227">Negi, J. S., ed. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit
              Dictionary</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bod skad dang legs sbyar gyi tshig mdzod
              chen mo</title>). 16 volumes. Sarnath: Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies,
            1993.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-228">Pedersen, K. Priscilla. “Notes on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> Collection.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the
              International Association of Buddhist Studies</title> 3, no. 2 (1980): 60–66. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-229">Rotman, Andy, trans. <title xml:lang="en">Divine
              Stories: Divyavadana, Part 2</title>. Classics of Indian Buddhism. Boston: Wisdom
            Publications, 2017.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-230">Silk, Jonathan A. “Review Article: Buddhist Sūtras in
            Sanskrit from the Potala.” <title xml:lang="en">Indo-Iranian Journal</title> 56 (2013):
            61–87.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-231">Stimson, H. M. <title xml:lang="en">T’ang Poetic
              Vocabulary</title>. New Haven: Far Eastern Publications, 1976.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-232">Vinītā, Bhikṣunī, ed. and trans. <title xml:lang="en">A
              unique collection of twenty Sūtras in a Sanskrit manuscript from the Potala</title>.
            Sanskrit Texts from the Tibetan Autonomous Region 7/1, vol. I,2, Beijing: China
            Tibetology Publishing House; Vienna: Austrian Academy of Sciences Press, 2010.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-001-233">Woolner, A. C. <title xml:lang="en">Introduction to
              Prakrit</title>. Calcutta: University of the Panjab, Lahore, 1917.</bibl>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="glossary" status="excluded">
        <list type="glossary">
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-235" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>absorption</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ting nge ’dzin</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
              <term type="definition">A state of mental absorption or one-pointed concentration.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-236" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>attitude of equality</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sems mnyam pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སེམས་མཉམ་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samacitta</term>

              <term type="definition">A state of mind that regards all being equally and is without
                hostility or malice towards any being.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-237" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>buddhafield</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sangs rgyas zhing</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཞིང་།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhakṣetra</term>

              <term type="definition">A pure realm manifested by a buddha in which beings may follow
                the path to awakening without fear of falling into lower realms. In many sources it
                is said to be brought to manifestation through a buddha or bodhisattva’s merit and
                aspiration.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-238" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>characteristics of phenomena</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">chos kyi mtshan nyid</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་མཚན་ཉིད།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmalakṣaṇa</term>

              <term type="definition">The defining characteristics (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">lakṣaṇa</foreign>) of phenomena (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>). The term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">lakṣaṇa</foreign> is used in a variety of contexts to indicates the primary
                characteristic or defining feature of any particular phenomena; for instance the
                  <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">lakṣaṇa</foreign> of fire is that it is hot
                and burning.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-239" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>moral discipline</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">tshul khrims</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīla</term>
              <term type="definition">Morally virtuous or disciplined conduct and the abandonment of
                morally undisciplined conduct of body, speech, and mind. In a general sense, moral
                discipline is the cause for rebirth in higher, more favorable states, but it is also
                foundational to Buddhist practice as one of the three trainings (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">triśikṣā</foreign>) and one of the six perfections
                of a bodhisattva.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-240" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>divine hearing</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">lha’i rna ba</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་རྣ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">divyaśrotra</term>

              <term type="definition">Clairaudience, i.e., the sublime ability to understand all
                languages and listen to them whether they are nearby or far away. This is the second
                of the six (or sometimes five) superknowledges (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṣaḍabhijñā</foreign>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-241" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>divine sight</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">lha’i mig</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་མིག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">divyacakṣus</term>

              <term type="definition">Clairvoyance, i.e., the ability to see all forms whether they
                are near or far, subtle or gross; also the ability to see the births and deaths of
                sentient beings. This is the first of the six (or sometimes five) superknowledges
                  (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṣaḍabhijñā</foreign>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-242" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>eighty excellent signs</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dpe byad bzang po brgyad cu</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དཔེ་བྱད་བཟང་པོ་བརྒྱད་ཅུ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aśītyanuvyañjana</term>

              <term type="definition">The eighty minor or secondary signs possessed by a “great
                being” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahāpuruṣa</foreign>), which all
                buddhas are said to have.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-243" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>favorable states</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bzang ’gro</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བཟང་འགྲོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sadgati</term>

              <term type="definition">The higher states of rebirth including those of gods, asuras,
                and human beings.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-244" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>firm resolution</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mos pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མོས་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhimokṣa</term>
              <term type="definition">In a general sense, the mental inclination or focus toward a
                virtuous object. The term is also classified as a mental factor (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">caitta</foreign>), being categorized variably
                according to different Buddhist schools but generally indicating the mental ability
                to focus on one object without straying to another. The term is also commonly
                translated as “determination,” “interest,” or “zeal.”</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-245" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>five essences</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">snying po lnga</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སྙིང་པོ་ལྔ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcasāra</term>

              <term type="definition">The identity of the five essences is uncertain; they are only
                a few mentions of the term in Kangyur, none of which identify what they are.
                According to most Tibetan dictionaries, such as the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dung
                  dkar tshig mdzod chen mo</title>, they are honey (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sbrang rtsi</foreign>), raw sugar (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bu ram</foreign>), salt (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshwa</foreign>), ghee (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhun
                mar</foreign>), and sesame oil (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">til
                  mar</foreign>). Rotman notes that Ayurveda sources also list the five essences as
                “milk, sugar, honey, ghee, and long pepper (<foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">Piper
                  longum</foreign>).” See Rotman (2017), p. 543, n. 571.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-246" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>five superknowledges</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mngon par shes pa lnga</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcābhijñā</term>

              <term type="definition">See the six superknowledges. The five <term type="ignore">superknowledges</term> follow the same set excluding the knowledge of how to
                extinguish the defilements (discussed fourth in <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s
                  Questions</title>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-247" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>giving</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sbyin pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dāna</term>
              <term type="definition">The practice of giving or making offerings to others. One of
                the six perfections of a bodhisattva.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-248" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>Great Illumination</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">snang ba che</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སྣང་བ་ཆེ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāprabhāsa</term>
              <term type="definition">The name of the eon in the future in which Siṃha and his
                attendants are prophesied to become buddhas by the Buddha Śākyamuni. This name
                varies significantly in the Chinese versions of <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s
                  Questions</title> (see <ptr target="#UT22084-044-001-167"/>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-249" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>guardians of the world</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’jig rten mgon</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">lokanātha</term>
              <term type="definition">An epithet commonly referring to buddhas or high-level
                bodhisattvas.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-250" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>inopportune states</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mi khom pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མི་ཁོམ་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akṣaṇa</term>
              <term type="definition">The Sanskrit literally means “without leisure”; this
                refers to being born in a state in which one will not have the opportunity to meet
                with a buddha or their teachings. Eight situations are typically listed: (1) being
                born in a hell realm, (2) as an animal, (3) as a hungry ghost, (4) as a long-life
                god, (5) in a borderland or non-Buddhist country, (6) having wrong views, (7) as
                someone with impaired faculties who is unable to understand the teachings, or (8) in
                a time or place where no buddha has come.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-251" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>jealousy</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">phrag dog</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྲག་དོག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">īrṣyā</term>
              <term type="definition">The mental state of jealousy, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">īrṣyā</foreign> is sometimes translated as “envy.” It is classified as
                one of the twenty subsidiary afflictions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upakleśa</foreign>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-252" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>kalaviṅka bird</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ka la ping ka</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཀ་ལ་པིང་ཀ</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalaviṅka</term>
              <term type="definition">A mythical Indian bird renowned for its beautiful call. Some
                dictionaries equate it with the Indian cuckoo (or other Indian songbirds), while
                other sources will attribute mythical qualities to it.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-253" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>love</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">byams pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maitrī</term>
              <term type="definition">One of the four immeasurables of the Mahāyāna, known in early
                Buddhism as “pure abodes” (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">brahmavihāra</foreign>), which comprise (1) love, sometimes translated as “loving
                kindness,” (2) compassion, (3) empathetic joy, and (4) impartiality. Immeasurable
                love arises from the wish for all living beings to have happiness and the causes of
                happiness.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-254" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>mindfulness</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dran pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛti</term>
              <term type="definition">One of the most important trainings for the Buddhist
                practitioner, it is traditionally taught within the teachings on the four
                applications of mindfulness.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-255" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>miraculous birth</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rdzus te skye ba</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུས་ཏེ་སྐྱེ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upapāduka</term>
              <term type="definition">Regarded as the most superior of the four modes of birth, the
                three other modes being birth from an egg, birth from a womb, or birth from warmth
                and moisture. Those who take a miraculous birth are spontaneously born fully mature
                at the time of their birth.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-256" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>patience</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bzod pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བཟོད་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣānti</term>
              <term type="definition">On a mundane level, patience is said to be the cause for
                becoming beautiful in future lives, but it is also foundational to Buddhist practice
                and one of the six perfections of a bodhisattva. As such it can be classified into
                three modes: the capacity to tolerate abuse from sentient beings, to tolerate the
                hardships of the path to buddhahood, and to tolerate the profound nature of ultimate
                reality.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-296" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>receptivity</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bzod pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བཟོད་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣānti</term>
              <term type="definition">See Patience.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-257" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>perseverance</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">brtson ’grus</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་འགྲུས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</term>
              <term type="definition">A state of mind characterized by having joyful persistence
                when engaging in virtuous activity. One of the six perfections of a
                bodhisattva.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-258" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>instruction</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bslab pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བསླབ་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śikṣita</term>
              <term type="definition">A general term for practice of the Dharma. Sometimes
                translated as “training.”</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-259" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>pure intention</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">lhag bsam</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷག་བསམ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhyāśaya</term>
              <term type="definition">A strong sense of determination, often associated with
                altruism.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-260" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>retention</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">gzungs</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
              <term type="definition">From the Sanskrit root <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">√dhṛ</foreign>, (“to retain” or “to hold”), a dhāraṇī is a verbal formula that
                holds the words and meaning of a larger text or doctrine. In its simplest function
                it serves as a mnemonic device for remembering a certain teaching, but in certain
                contexts the dhāraṇī may carry a magical connotation, and in this sense it is a
                precursor to the mantra.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-261" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>saṅgha</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dge ’dun</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་འདུན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṅgha</term>
              <term type="definition">The community of followers of the Buddha’s teachings,
                particularly the monastics.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-298">
              <term>senseless talk</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">kyal ba</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཀྱལ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pralāpa</term>
              <term type="definition">Seventh of the ten nonvirtuous (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">akuśala</foreign>) actions, the third of the three related to speech
                (the first two being slander and harsh speech).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-263">
              <term>slander</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">phra ma</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྲ་མ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paiśunya</term>
              <term type="definition">Fifth of the ten nonvirtuous (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">akuśala</foreign>) actions, the first of the three related to speech
                (the latter two being harsh speech and senseless talk).</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-264">
              <term>six superknowledges</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mngon shes drug</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་ཤེས་དྲུག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaḍabhijñā</term>
              <term type="definition">The six superknowledges in <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s
                  Question</title> are discussed in verses 27–30 in the following order: (1) divine
                sight, a form of clairvoyance; (2) divine hearing, a form of clairaudience; (3)
                knowing the dying, transmigration, and rebirth of sentient beings; (4) knowing how
                to extinguish the defilements; (5) the recollection of former lives; and (6) knowing
                how to perform miraculous transformations. In Buddhist literature, the six are not
                always given in this order, and sometimes the superknowledges are listed as five,
                excluding knowing how to extinguish the defilements.</term>
              <term type="alternative">superknowledge</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-265" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>wealthy noblemen</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">tshong dpon bu</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཚོང་དཔོན་བུ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śreṣṭiputra</term>
              <term type="definition">The term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śreṣṭhin</foreign> and its Pāli equivalent <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">seṭṭi</foreign> have undergone a particular development in Buddhism. The Tibetan
                translation “merchant” or “owner of merchandise” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshong dpon</foreign>) reflects that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śreṣṭhin</foreign> later came to be associated with traders,
                merchants, and also moneylenders. However, in Sanskrit the term literally means
                “distinguished,” and an older survey of the term shows that it implies a kind of
                nobleman of influential social standing who has both access to wealth and a close
                association with the king. For a more detailed history on the development of this
                term, see Chakravarti (1996), chapter 3, particularly pp. 73–79.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-266">
              <term>stinginess</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ser sna</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སེར་སྣ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">matsara</term>
              <term type="definition">The mental state of stinginess, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">matsara</foreign> is sometimes translated as “miserliness” or
                “avarice.” It is classified as one of the twenty subsidiary afflictions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upakleśa</foreign>).</term>

            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-267">
              <term>voice of Brahmā</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">tshangs pa’i dbyangs</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་དབྱངས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmasvara</term>
              <term type="definition">A voice that has the qualities of the voice of the god Brahmā.
                This is one of the thirty-two marks of a buddha.</term>

            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-268">
              <term>thirty-two marks</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">sum cu rtsa gnyis mtshan</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་མཚན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvātriṃśallakṣaṇa</term>
              <term type="definition">The thirty-two marks manifested by a “great being” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahāpuruṣa</foreign>). As “great beings,” all
                buddhas are said to display them.</term>

            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-269" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>great sage</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">thub pa chen po</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāmuni</term>
              <term type="definition">An epithet of a buddha.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-270" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>guide</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’dren pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འདྲེན་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāyaka</term>
              <term type="definition">An epithet of a buddha.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-271" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>blessed one</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bcom ldan ’das</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
              <term type="definition">In Buddhist literature, an epithet applied to buddhas, most
                often to Śākyamuni. The Sanskrit term generically means “possessing fortune,” but in
                specifically Buddhist contexts implies that a buddha is in possession of six
                auspicious qualities (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhaga</foreign>)
                associated with complete awakening. The Tibetan term‍—where <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bcom</foreign> is said to refer to “subduing” the
                four māras, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ldan</foreign> to “possessing”
                the great qualities of buddhahood, and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’das</foreign> to “going beyond” saṃsāra and nirvāṇa‍—possibly reflects the
                commentarial tradition where the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagavat</foreign> is interpreted, in addition, as “one who destroys the four
                māras.” This is achieved either by reading <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagavat</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagnavat</foreign>
                (“one who broke”) or by tracing the word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhaga</foreign> to the root √<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhañj</foreign> (“to break”).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-272" type="term" mode="match">
              <term>two extremes</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mtha’ gnyis</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་གཉིས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">antadvaya</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāśvatocchedāntadvaya</term>
              <term type="definition">The two views of (1) eternalism (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nityānta</foreign>), the belief in a permanent, causeless creator
                and/or the belief in an independent, permanent, singular self; and (2) nihilism
                  (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ucchedānta</foreign>), the belief that
                things ultimately do not exist and/or the denial of the law of cause and effect or
                of past and future lives.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-274" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Ajātaśatru</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ma skyes dgra</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མ་སྐྱེས་དགྲ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ajātaśatru</term>

              <term type="definition">King Ajātaśatru of Magadha succeeded his father, Bimbisāra,
                after imprisoning him and causing his death. Despite this evil act, King Ajātaśatru
                was later repentant and, in the end, is viewed favorably in Buddhist
                literature.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-275" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Ajita</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ma pham pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མ་ཕམ་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ajita</term>
              <term type="definition">Another name for Maitreya, the future buddha.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-276" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Amitābha</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">’od dpag med</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔག་མེད།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
              <term type="definition">One of the most important buddhas in the Mahāyāna and
                Vajrayāna pantheon, Amitābha is the buddha presiding over the western pure land of
                Sukhāvatī.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-277" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Dānaśīla</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">dA na shI la</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དཱ་ན་ཤཱི་ལ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānaśīla</term>
              <term type="definition">An Indian preceptor from Kashmir who was resident in Tibet
                during the late eighth and early ninth centuries. He was a frequent collaborator of
                Yeshé Dé.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-278" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Dīpaṅkara</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mar me mdzad pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མར་མེ་མཛད་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṅkara</term>
              <term type="definition">Dīpaṅkara is a buddha of the past said to have lived one
                hundred thousand years before Śākyamuni. In depictions of the buddhas of the three
                times, he represents the buddha of the past, while Śākyamuni represents the present,
                and Maitreya represents the future.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-279" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Jñānaketudhvaja</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ye shes tog gi rgyal mtshan</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་ཏོག་གི་རྒྱལ་མཚན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñāna­ketudhvaja</term>
              <term type="definition">The name that Siṃha and his five hundred attendants will take
                when they become buddhas in the future, according to the Buddha’s prophecy. This
                name varies significantly in the Chinese versions of <title xml:lang="en">Siṃha’s
                  Questions</title> (see verse 48 and <ptr target="#UT22084-044-001-171"/>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-280" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Maitreya</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">byams pa</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
              <term type="definition">The bodhisattva who became Śākyamuni’s regent and is
                prophesied to be the next buddha, the fifth buddha in the Fortunate Eon. In early
                Buddhism he appears as the human disciple Maitreya Tiṣya, sent to pay his respects
                by his teacher. The Buddha gives him the gift of a robe and prophesies he will be
                the next Buddha, while his companion Ajita will be the next cakravartin. As a
                bodhisattva in the Mahāyāna, he has both these names.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-281" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Māra</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bdud</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
              <term type="definition">The principal deity in Paranirmitavaśavartin, the highest
                heaven in the desire realm. He is best known for his role in trying to prevent the
                Buddha’s awakening. The name Māra is also used as a generic name for the deities in
                his abode, and also as an impersonal term for destructive forces that keep beings
                imprisoned in saṃsāra.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-282" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Munivarman</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mu ni bar ma</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་ནི་བར་མ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Munivarman</term>
              <term type="definition">An Indian preceptor who was resident in Tibet during the late
                eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-283">
              <term>Siṃha</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">seng ge</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེ</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha</term>
              <term type="definition">Prince Siṃha, son of King Ajātaśatru.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-284" type="person" mode="match">
              <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">ye shes sde</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
              <term type="definition">A famous Tibetan translator and monk of the eighth to the
                ninth century, he translated into Tibetan and revised, in collaboration with various
                Indian scholars, more than two hundred and fifty texts of the Kangyur and
                Tengyur.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss xml:id="UT22084-044-001-287" type="place" mode="match">
              <term>Rājagṛha</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rgyal po’i khab</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
              <term type="definition">The ancient capital of Magadha prior to its relocation to
                Pāṭaliputra during the Mauryan dynasty, Rājagṛha is one of the most important cities
                and geographic locations in Buddhist literature, which tells us that the Buddha and
                his saṅgha spent a considerable amount of time in residence in and around Rājagṛha,
                enjoying the patronage of King Bimbisāra and then his son King Ajātaśatru of
                Magadha. Rājagṛha is also remembered as the location where the first Buddhist
                monastic council was held after the Buddha Śākyamuni passed into parinirvāṇa.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-001-288">
              <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">bya rgod kyi phung po’i ri</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhrakūṭa</term>
              <term type="definition">A mountain situated in the vicinity of Rājagṛha, it was the
                location where the Prajñāpāramitā sūtras were taught. It continues to be a sacred
                pilgrimage site for Buddhists to this day.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>