<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spobs pa’i blo gros kyis zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratibhānamatiparipṛcchā</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of Pratibhānamati</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spobs pa’i blo gros kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryapratibhānamatiparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྤོབས་པའི་བློ་གྲོས་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྤོབས་པའི་བློ་གྲོས་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation
                    Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
                    Buddha</author>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-262">David Higgins</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>
                <consultant role="dharmaMaster" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-334">Tulku Tenzin Rigsang</consultant>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-75">Timothy Hinkle</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-74">Ryan Damron</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</author>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay, Dr.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.14 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to
                    translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use,
                            but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-057-010"/>
                <date>2020-09-17</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh151" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 151</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 57 (mdo sde, pa), folios 331.b–344.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Prajñāvarman</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="26">
                        <volume number="57" start-page="662" end-page="687"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11743" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2023-01-18T16:59:43.652Z" user="celso">18/01/2023 16:59:43</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2019-05-13T14:58:41.819Z" user="laura">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-01-28T06:14:23.025Z" user="mike">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2020-03-16T14:27:55.257Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2020-04-29T10:31:30.135Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-04-29T13:06:35.506Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
            
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2020-05-08T21:13:27.16Z" user="mike">v 0.0.1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2020-05-08T21:13:27.16Z" user="mike">2</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2020-08-28T14:12:29.309Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2020-09-17T05:40:54.474Z" user="mike">1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2020-09-17T05:40:54.474Z" user="mike">first published version</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.0" date-time="2020-09-17T07:18:08.537Z" user="john">A few stylistic edits including shortened summary.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.1" date-time="2020-09-17T07:35:02.873Z" user="john">1.1.1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.2" date-time="2020-09-21T18:53:37.373Z" user="laura">Corrected typo in glossary: མིའ་ཨམ་ཅི།</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.3" date-time="2020-10-26T10:43:08.936Z" user="mike">fixed glossary entries for different types of beings</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.4" date-time="2020-11-07T01:21:08.264Z" user="laura">Corrected typo in glossary</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.5" date-time="2020-11-18T18:28:27.777Z" user="laura">Edited a typo</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.6" date-time="2020-11-23T13:57:44.998Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.0.0)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.7" date-time="2020-12-11T14:06:50.919Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.1.5)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.8" date-time="2021-01-04T22:03:33.068Z" user="laura">Updated colophon to Bandé</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.9" date-time="2021-02-12T18:55:30.714Z" user="celso">"scholar" to "preceptor" in colophon</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.10" date-time="2021-04-22T14:58:23.343Z" user="celso">added @xml:lang to a chinese string</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.11" date-time="2021-06-26T04:19:24.911Z" user="celso">kiṃnara to kinnara</note>    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.12" date-time="2022-06-27T10:06:48.1Z" user="admin">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.13" date-time="2023-01-16T16:58:52.361Z" user="celso">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.14" date-time="2023-01-18T16:58:06.914Z" user="celso">Auto (remove-tid-from-back-list-items)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-1"/>
                <p tid="2">The subject matter of this sūtra is indicated by the alternative title suggested by the
                    Buddha himself in its conclusion: <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching That Clarifies Karma</title>. In the
                        opening section, the merchant Pratibhānamati, concerned about the
                    state of society and what will become of the saṅgha in times to come, requests the Buddha
                    Śākyamuni for a teaching that offers moral guidance to future beings. With the Buddha’s
                    encouragement, he asks what actions lead to rebirth in ten different human and
                    non-human states. The Buddha answers with descriptions of the actions associated with each of these 
                    states and the effects they will bring. Pratibhānamati then invites the Buddha
                    to his home in Śrāvastī. Two beggars arrive there, and on account of their opposing
                    aspirations and conduct in the presence of the Buddha and retinue, one soon becomes
                    a king while the other is killed in an accident. The sūtra concludes as the Buddha, 
                    invited to the newly anointed king’s land, explains the karmic reasons for his
                    unexpected fortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chokyi Nyima
                    Rinpoche. The translation was produced by Timothy Hinkle, who also wrote the introduction. Ryan
                    Damron and Andreas Doctor checked the translation against the Tibetan and edited the
                    text. Tulku Tenzin Rigsang also assisted in resolving several difficult passages.</p>
                <p tid="6">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the
                    Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="7">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-introduction-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-3"/>
                <p tid="8">In this sūtra the Buddha Śākyamuni gives a teaching on the workings of karma, the
                    relationships between actions and their effects. The setting for the teaching is the Jeta Grove near
                    the city of Śrāvastī, which the benefactor Anāthapiṇḍada donated to the Buddha at great expense.
                    Prompted by questions posed by the merchant Pratibhānamati, who is concerned that monastics may
                    indulge in hypocritical behavior in the future during degenerate times, the Buddha elucidates the
                    actions that cause rebirth in ten possible states of existence: as a god, a human, a hell being, an
                    animal, a hungry spirit, a high-caste human, a slave, a fortunate human, an unfortunate human, or a
                    human on the Buddhist path. Additionally, he describes the physical, verbal, and mental traits
                    associated with each of those rebirths. These illustrate the doctrine, shared by most Indian
                    religions, that beings’ good or bad deeds determine their future modes of birth and existence. In
                    this way, the sūtra provides a moral framework geared toward the whole of society established on the
                    basis of karma theory.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-4"/>
                <p tid="9">Following the discourse, Pratibhānamati invites the Buddha to his home for the midday meal.
                    As a final illustration of the law of karma, we are introduced to two beggars who seat themselves
                    among the saṅgha when the midday meal is being served. One of them does not observe the proper etiquette
                    of ensuring honored guests are served first and thus is not served anything to eat or drink.
                    Enraged, he leaves, harboring a very negative judgment of the assembly and perversely vowing
                    revenge. As a result, he soon suffers an unfortunate death followed by millions of eons in hell. The
                    other beggar, however, observes proper etiquette and is served abundant food and drink. He
                    entertains a virtuous aspiration to serve the Buddha and his assembly for an entire week. The effect
                    of this noble wish is that he soon becomes the king of a neighboring land whose ruler has perished
                    without an appropriate heir. He is astounded at his sudden reversal of fortune and seeks to
                    understand its source. Through the blessings of the Buddha he realizes how his past actions
                    determined his current fortune. He therefore invites the Buddha and the saṅgha and serves them just
                    as he had aspired to do. The Buddha delivers a teaching that propels the king to the state of a
                    stream enterer. The sūtra concludes with the audience praising the Buddha and rejoicing in his
                    teaching. Through its descriptions and examples of the workings of karma, the sūtra underscores the
                    importance and benefits of upholding core Buddhist virtues of kindness, gratitude, generosity,
                    honesty, and respect, while warning of the grave consequences awaiting those who do the
                    opposite.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-5"/>
                <p tid="10">To our knowledge there is no extant Sanskrit version of this sūtra. It was, however,
                    translated into Chinese (Taishō 544) by Fa Chang <foreign xml:lang="zh">法場</foreign> during the early sixth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. Although it appears that the sūtra did exercise some influence in China,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-6"> See Robson 2009: 30–31. The Chinese
                        translation was not referenced for this translation.</note> it does not seem to have had
                    a particularly significant impact in Tibet. The colophon to the Tibetan translation
                    states that it was produced by the Indian preceptor Prajñāvarman and the Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé.
                    The text is also recorded in the Denkarma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-7"> Denkarma, folio 298.b.6. See also Herrmann-Pfandt (2008), p. 89,
                            no. 164.</note> and Phangthangma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-8">Phangthangma, p. 14.</note> inventories of Tibetan
                    imperial translations, so we can establish that it was first translated from Sanskrit into Tibetan
                    no later than the early ninth century, as the Denkarma is dated to 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. The primary Tibetan text used for the present translation was the Degé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</foreign>) edition, but the other editions included in the Comparative
                    Kangyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) were also consulted.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="11"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="12">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="13">The Questions of Pratibhānamati</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-section-1">
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-144"/>
                <p tid="16">
                        <ref cRef="F.331.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-188"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-12"/>
                <p tid="17">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was residing in Jeta Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s
                    park at Śrāvastī. He was there together with a great saṅgha of 1,250 monks as well as 10,000
                    bodhisattvas. Surrounded and revered by an immense retinue, the Blessed One taught the Dharma.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-13"/>
                <p tid="18">At that time, the merchant Pratibhānamati left the city of Śrāvastī, surrounded and
                    venerated <ref cRef="F.332.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-189"/> by a group of five hundred merchant’s sons, each of whom was also accompanied by
                    an entourage of five hundred servants. As they arrived at Jeta Grove in Anāthapiṇḍada’s park where
                    the Blessed One was residing, Pratibhānamati bowed his head at the Blessed One’s feet,
                    circumambulated him three times, and sat down together with his entourage. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-14"/>
                <p tid="19">At this point, through the power of the Buddha, the merchant Pratibhānamati stood up, draped
                    his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee. With palms together he bowed toward the
                    Blessed One and said, “Blessed One, you are the supreme teacher, the most eminent in the three
                    realms, the exalted ground for the merit of awakening, the one who liberates all beings, and the one
                    who brings about the attainment of unbounded skill in all-pervasive methods. Thus, Blessed One, in
                    times to come, during the degenerate age when the five polluting degenerations manifest, the three poisons
                    will burn and blaze forth. Then, among those beings who inflict misery on one another there will be
                    people with evil intentions. At that time, there will be no leader, nor anyone of this kind, and
                    kings and high ministers will be overcome by craving for objects, leading them to quarrel and wage
                    war against each other. When they wage war against each other, their armies of soldiers as well as
                    the remaining civilian population will be ravaged so that not even their names will remain. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-15"/>
                <p tid="20">“Through the power of the Buddha’s merit, many among the four types of the Buddha’s
                    disciples will enter the teachings and take on the guise of monks. Yet even these people will only
                    outwardly be cloaked in saffron robes, while inwardly they will be angry, disrespectful,
                    disharmonious, and slanderous toward one another. They will advertise the faults of others and
                    downplay their positive qualities. They will be overcome by pride, <ref cRef="F.332.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-190"/> conceit, and
                    haughtiness, and will cling to the belief in <distinct>me</distinct> and <distinct>mine</distinct>.
                    When they pass on, they will be born into the lower realms, and they will not find even a moment of
                    fortune. In their future lives they will again encounter many eons of the terrible experiences of
                    suffering and of harshness, heat, and displeasure.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-16"/>
                <p tid="21">“On account of that, Blessed One, what are the teachings that will ripen them, turn them
                    back from the paths leading to the lower realms, and enable them to attain the celestial palace due
                    to their merit?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-17"/>
                <p tid="22">The Blessed One answered Pratibhānamati, “Pratibhānamati, with this lion’s roar, you have
                    asked the Thus-Gone One a question. This sort of request for the Dharma of the Thus-Gone One stirs
                    delight in all beings. Excellent, excellent! Pratibhānamati, what attainment would make beings truly
                    splendorous, cause them to abandon the dark side, make them join the good side, and accomplish all
                    aims? You should ask about such a teaching. Having done so, you must then listen without doubt and I
                    shall explain.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-18"/>
                <p tid="23">Pratibhānamati then inquired of the Blessed One, “Blessed One, through what deeds is one
                    reborn among the class of gods? Through what actions is one reborn among the class of humans?
                    Through what actions is one reborn among hell beings? Through what actions is one reborn among the
                    animals? Through what actions is one reborn among the hungry spirits? Through what actions is one
                    reborn among the high castes? Through what actions is one reborn in servitude? Blessed One, through
                    what actions does one become a fortunate being among humans—someone who has servants, pleasant
                    breath, a nice complexion, <ref cRef="F.333.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-191"/> who is a joy to behold, who faces no harm, who is contented in
                    body and mind, and praised by many people? Having already attained the excellent human state among
                    beings, through what actions does one meet with constant slander, face the enmity of many beings,
                    have an ugly appearance and bad breath, face all sorts of adversity, have a joyless mind and an
                    unhealthy body, and indulge in all kinds of negative actions? </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-19"/>
                <p tid="24">“Blessed One, through what actions will those who have taken ordination in this well-spoken
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Dharma-Vinaya</foreign>, as a mendicant or a noble son or
                    daughter who values peace, never part from the Jewels of Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha throughout their
                    lifetimes and wherever they may be? Through what actions will they behold the blessed buddhas,
                    receive the Dharma from them, delight in it, and accomplish the aims they have set their minds on? </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-20"/>
                <p tid="25">“Given these ten questions of mine, please, Blessed One, spiritual teacher who acts without
                    being requested, who is endowed with great compassion and power, and who discerns all phenomena with
                    unclouded eyes, answer them extensively as a remedy for the innumerable malignant forces.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-21"/>
                <p tid="26">The Blessed One replied, “Pratibhānamati, I will extensively address and answer your
                    questions, just as you have asked them. Listen well!” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-22"/>
                <p tid="27">The merchant Pratibhānamati responded, “Blessed One, I shall do that,” and he listened as
                    the Blessed One had instructed. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-23"/>
                <p tid="28">The Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    attain rebirth as gods. What are these five? (1) First, with loving minds they do no harm to beings but instead protect them and are patient. (2) They give generously since they are not stingy and do
                    not steal the possessions of others. <ref cRef="F.333.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-192"/> (3) They guard all the bases of training given that
                    those who enjoy themselves with the wives of others are impure. (4) They naturally maintain
                    diligence in the purification ceremony and speak the truth. (5) In order to give up their own
                    limitless faults, they forsake intoxicating beverages. Beings who engage in these five actions
                    attain divine bodies.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-24"/>
                <p tid="29">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-25"/>
                <lg tid="30">
                    <l>“Turning away from killing living beings, no god, human, or asura</l>
                    <l>In the world can conquer them; their bodies are long-lived and healthy.</l>
                    <l>They have pure bodies haloed with light—bodies that are glorious, stainless, and perfect.</l>
                    <l>The myriad splendid sense pleasures of the highest gods are always at their disposal.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-26"/>
                <lg tid="31">
                    <l>“As soon they discard this body, they will always become the lord of the gods among gods.</l>
                    <l>Dispersing, distributing, and renouncing inconceivable wealth, they will find gems and
                        opulence.</l>
                    <l>They will always be happy and delighted, dwelling in splendid celestial mansions.</l>
                    <l>Their bodies will be like flowers sprinkled in the pleasant and fine realm of the wish-fulfilling
                        tree.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-27"/>
                <lg tid="32">
                    <l>“They are knowledgeable, without harmful desires, and have bodies with the finest fragrance.</l>
                    <l>Throughout all their lives, their bodies are tremendously beautiful like the finest gold. </l>
                    <l>Constantly among the gods, they acquire great fortune and light streams from their bodies.</l>
                    <l>They are surrounded by a host of sundry goddesses and frolic in the glories of passion.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-28"/>
                <lg tid="33">
                    <l>“They have abandoned the four verbal faults and their mouths have a lovely fragrance in
                        accordance with previous rites.</l>
                    <l>These gods utter supreme words that are clear, unimpeded, and fearless.</l>
                    <l>Their accurate responses are praised and eloquent and others find them most agreeable.</l>
                    <l>Their palaces resound with the melodious and thunderous sound of strings and percussion.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-29"/>
                <lg tid="34">
                    <l>“With unimpaired minds, they abandoned confused and ignoble utterances and thus became gods.</l>
                    <l>Innumerable gods of virtue worship them and they now live in divine abodes.</l>
                    <l>Intelligent, with stalwart bodies, excellent minds, and possessing all forms of
                        conscientiousness,</l>
                    <l>These beings who are always happy and powerful make beneficial speeches.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-30"/>
                <lg tid="35">
                    <l>“When their life ends, should these gods plunge from the divine abodes to a lower state,</l>
                    <l>They will remain free from misdeeds, and after one hundred twenty years return to the divine
                        abodes. <ref cRef="F.334.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-193"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Exhibiting the five merits, their sublime and splendid bodies shine.</l>
                    <l>They act as beacons of the gods and millions of gods resolutely worship them.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-31"/>
                <p tid="36">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    are reborn among humans. What are these five? (1) First, they give with gratitude and provide for
                    the poor, the destitute, and the miserable. (2) They follow the path of the ten virtues without
                    fail. (3) They are patient, harboring no hostility toward anyone. (4) They diligently inspire lazy
                    beings to the virtuous Dharma. (5) With a determined mind, they maintain harmony. Pratibhānamati,
                    beings who engage in these five actions attain human lives and grow very wealthy, long lived,
                    beautiful, and majestic, and become lords of the world.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-32"/>
                <p tid="37">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-33"/>
                <lg tid="38">
                    <l>“Through generosity they will become great kings among humans,</l>
                    <l>And constantly increase their pleasure and affluence.</l>
                    <l>They engage in conduct and generosity equal to Kubera himself.</l>
                    <l>With such status and excellence, they will always be delighted.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-34"/>
                <lg tid="39">
                    <l>“Their discipline unimpaired, they worship the Three Jewels.</l>
                    <l>Because they abandon all evil action, their resolve is firm.</l>
                    <l>They will attain the greatness of longevity and thus be free from death’s passing.</l>
                    <l>Because they will attain happiness, they become faultless and joyful.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-35"/>
                <lg tid="40">
                    <l>“Being gentle people, they do not upset others’ minds.</l>
                    <l>Likewise, though nasty words are lobbed at them, </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-36"/>
                <lg tid="41">
                    <l>They do not criticize in return,</l>
                    <l>And so they will attain the way of supreme virtue and become beautiful.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-37"/>
                <lg tid="42">
                    <l>“Because their intention toward excellent discipline is sublime, their minds are clean.</l>
                    <l>They are replete with great strength and splendor and possess virtues.</l>
                    <l>Because they attain the excellence of military leadership,</l>
                    <l>They shall have dominion over wealth and enjoyment and become like gods. <ref cRef="F.334.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-194"/>
                        </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-38"/>
                <lg tid="43">
                    <l>“They do not covet and are intelligent, knowledgeable, and agreeable.</l>
                    <l>They are grateful and keen to work.</l>
                    <l>They are courageous in venerating the Jewels, their mothers, and so on,</l>
                    <l>And so they never have doubt in any situation.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-39"/>
                <lg tid="44">
                    <l>“Whoever performs these extraordinary virtues</l>
                    <l>Will become the lords of the land.</l>
                    <l>They shall attain unfailing strength, health, wealth, and other qualities.</l>
                    <l>Renowned, they will be respected by important people.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-40"/>
                <p tid="45">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    are reborn among hell beings, where they remain for millions of eons. What are these five? (1) They
                    have no faith in the Jewels of the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha. They disparage them through
                    unflattering speech and belittle the path of noble beings. (2) They destroy the stūpas of the
                    thus-gone ones. (3) In the intermediate times as well, they are extremely disrespectful and
                    disharmonious with monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen, but love having worldly conversations. (4) They
                    steal donations made to the Three Jewels. (5) Through their disparaging words that enrage others, they
                    are disrespectful and create discord between kings, leaders, ministers, fathers, and sons. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-41"/>
                <p tid="46">“In the future, those monks who enter into the teachings of the thus-gone ones, who follow
                    the teacher—the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha—and go forth from the home into homelessness, will
                    pass themselves off as monks yet not maintain the genuine practice of the virtuous Dharma. They will
                    not maintain harmony but will displease their preceptors and instructors and speak harshly. Even
                    though they have been taught correctly, they will not practice those teachings. They will spurn the
                    awakening of the buddhas, praise themselves, and slander <ref cRef="F.335.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-195"/> others. For the most part, they
                    will be proud, conceited, and haughty, and will denigrate spiritual teachers. They will yearn for
                    praise and respect but disparage others. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-42"/>
                <p tid="47">“Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in those five actions will be reborn among the hell
                    beings where they will remain until the trichiliocosm is destroyed. Even when it is destroyed, they
                    will be propelled into other world-systems in which there are hells. When those world-systems are
                    also destroyed, they will be further propelled into still other world-systems in which there are
                    hells. And so, on and on, they will wander amidst all the countless world-systems of hells, and
                    their experience of suffering will find no end.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-43"/>
                <p tid="48">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-44"/>
                <lg tid="49">
                    <l>“Deluded beings are oblivious to the terrible suffering in the world since beginningless
                        time.</l>
                    <l>And do not acknowledge the oceanic qualities of the Buddha.</l>
                    <l>Declaring, ‘He is neither omniscient nor the king of practitioners,’</l>
                    <l>They waste their own lives and deceive other beings.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-45"/>
                <lg tid="50">
                    <l>“They say, ‘If you make a reliquary of the blissful ones, supreme in its materials and beauty, </l>
                    <l>It will be of little virtue and bring down a rain of destruction.’</l>
                    <l>This non-virtue, on the face of it, may seem virtuous;</l>
                    <l>But actually it brings about all manner of evil.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-46"/>
                <lg tid="51">
                    <l>“In this intermediate period of strife, the four types of beings are weakened by hunger.</l>
                    <l>Because of their mutual animosity they fight and belittle spiritual masters.</l>
                    <l>They destroy the enthusiasm of the community of moral discipline,</l>
                    <l>Thus leading them to the terrifying and unpleasant lower realms.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-47"/>
                <lg tid="52">
                    <l>“Kings, fathers, daughters, relatives, and young women</l>
                    <l>Lose their caring minds and become envious of possessions.</l>
                    <l>They laugh at one another like immature children, </l>
                    <l>And hasten to the mire of the fathomless lower realms. <ref cRef="F.335.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-196"/>
                        </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-48"/>
                <lg tid="53">
                    <l>“In future times those who are wantonly evil will not get along.</l>
                    <l>Faking the appearance of mendicants, they will have repugnant forms.</l>
                    <l>They will be of vile character and perform millions of evil deeds.</l>
                    <l>When they die and transmigrate, they will be dragged down by their intense evil deeds and
                        quarreling.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-49"/>
                <lg tid="54">
                    <l>“The five evil deeds perpetrated by people </l>
                    <l>Cannot be confessed for hundreds of eons.</l>
                    <l>Such people are burned in a terrible mountain of fire in the hell of ceaseless torment—</l>
                    <l>A place where even millions of buddhas can offer no protection.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-50"/>
                <p tid="55">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    are reborn among animals. What are these five? (1) The first is corrupt discipline. The others are
                    (2) robbery and theft, (3) taking loans from others and then conspiring against them, (4) murder,
                    and (5) lacking faith, which makes one delight in studying something other than the sublime Dharma
                    and relish perverted ways of life because of finding such studies enjoyable. Pratibhānamati, beings
                    who engage in these five actions are reborn as animals.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-51"/>
                <p tid="56">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-52"/>
                <lg tid="57">
                    <l>“People who always delight in stealing from others</l>
                    <l>Take out loans and then murder the lender.</l>
                    <l>Beasts, lords of death who love killing,</l>
                    <l>Catch such beings in traps and then slaughter them.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-53"/>
                <lg tid="58">
                    <l>“Their minds, weak in faith and the rest,</l>
                    <l>Cannot see the limitless evil deeds they do, thinking it all to be virtuous.</l>
                    <l>Deluded, they do not enjoy discussions on the sublime Jewel of the Dharma.</l>
                    <l>Instead they follow worldly teachings.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-54"/>
                <lg tid="59">
                    <l>“Just as snow tumbles down from a mountain,</l>
                    <l>And water naturally seeps straight underground,</l>
                    <l>In the same way they amass many evil deeds in the realms of gods and humans,</l>
                    <l>And so these fools go swiftly to the animals.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-55"/>
                <lg tid="60">
                    <l>“Born as horses, mules, camels, elephants, <ref cRef="F.336.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-197"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Oxen, cattle, lions, foxes, snakes, pigs, or dogs,</l>
                    <l>They eat grass, flesh, and foliage,</l>
                    <l>And constantly carry the burdens of others until exhaustion.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-56"/>
                <lg tid="61">
                    <l>“Driven by hunger, they eagerly prey on one another.</l>
                    <l>Even after millions of eons, they will never be freed from this state.</l>
                    <l>Just as a one-eyed turtle living in the ocean</l>
                    <l>Could not stick its neck through a floating yoke,</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-57"/>
                <lg tid="62">
                    <l>“Because of their hundreds of downfalls</l>
                    <l>They will not easily obtain the states of gods, humans, or great lords.</l>
                    <l>They will be delivered by a sublime and limitless matrix of the Buddha’s light rays</l>
                    <l>And the light of the mighty bodhisattvas.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-58"/>
                <p tid="63">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    are reborn as hungry spirits. What are these five? (1) The first is being stingy and craving. (2)
                    Next, because they esteem extremely ignorant spiritual teachers and their ilk, they block their own
                    happiness. (3) Because they are inclined to unwholesome ways, they are jealous. (4) Because they are
                    excessively stingy, they are in no way generous towards brothers, sisters, children, wives,
                    servants, laborers, wageworkers, friends, government officials, kinfolk, relatives, the venerable,
                    mendicants, priests, and the poor. They cannot even give anything to their own mothers and fathers,
                    nor do they care for those who are in need of care. (5) They are also not respectful, nor do they
                    venerate spiritual teachers or regard them as precious. Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in these
                    five actions are reborn as hungry spirits.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-59"/>
                <p tid="64">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse: </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-60"/>
                <lg tid="65">
                    <l>“Defeated by the adversity of privation, they are unable to give away their wealth.</l>
                    <l>They only wish to take from others.</l>
                    <l>They are keepers of a treasury whose doors are tightly shut.</l>
                    <l>Thinking it ought to be guarded, they do not care for even their closest kin.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-61"/>
                <lg tid="66">
                    <l>“These squanderers of others’ wealth always live in anxiety. <ref cRef="F.336.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-198"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Even to spiritual teachers they are rude and have no love.</l>
                    <l>To their own wives and servants they give nothing precious,</l>
                    <l>Nor do they understand how to show love and affection.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-62"/>
                <lg tid="67">
                    <l>“They turn away from what is good, and when they pass on</l>
                    <l>They become suffering spirits whose bodies burn over and over.</l>
                    <l>Though they dream for hundreds of years,</l>
                    <l>They never even dream of clothing, food, and drink.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-63"/>
                <lg tid="68">
                    <l>“Their throats are like needles and their stomachs like huge mountains.</l>
                    <l>Desperately they scramble from the eastern to the western ocean.</l>
                    <l>With mouths ablaze they run to Kauverī and to the south.</l>
                    <l>Seeing everything dried up they fall into a blazing fire.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-64"/>
                <lg tid="69">
                    <l>“The henchmen of the Lord of Death grab them by the shoulders,</l>
                    <l>Pile them together, and crush them with boulders.</l>
                    <l>Then they are given molten copper to drink, which is incredibly difficult to bear.</l>
                    <l>Ignorant, they are made to drink disgusting substances as if they were water with eight
                        qualities.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-65"/>
                <lg tid="70">
                    <l>“After their entrails have been burned from their body cavities by the evacuating wind, </l>
                    <l>The powerful ones force these beings to drink again.</l>
                    <l>When these beings die and are reborn in the human world,</l>
                    <l>They will be inferior in their caste, wealth, health, and servants.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-66"/>
                <p tid="71">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    are reborn among the higher castes. What are these five? They are (1) giving material goods and
                    Dharma, (2) not having hostility towards anyone, (3) being respectful of the Three Jewels and one’s
                    parents, (4) being naturally patient, gentle, and exalted, and (5) studying the diversity of the
                    Buddha’s teachings and being diligent in their recitation. Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in
                    those five actions are reborn among the higher castes.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-67"/>
                <p tid="72">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse: </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-68"/>
                <lg tid="73">
                    <l>“Those who are inspired by the rituals for accumulating merit and fortune, <ref cRef="F.337.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-199"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>And who ensure that many beings never grow ill,</l>
                    <l>Will enjoy long life, a fine complexion, great strength, and become foremost in the world.</l>
                    <l>Their beauty will be vast and special, like a jewel mine or the lord
                            of mountains.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-69"/>
                <lg tid="74">
                    <l>“They venerate the incomparable jewel of delighting in discipline and their parents.</l>
                    <l>Thus they are born into large and preeminent households and worshipped by innumerable beings.</l>
                    <l>They are highly capable, their minds free of agitation and their forms noblest of all.</l>
                    <l>They are appealing to the eyes of the entire world, have great fortune, and are of high caste.
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-70"/>
                <lg tid="75">
                    <l>“They are reliable and perfect people, their minds aligned with what is good and virtuous.</l>
                    <l>Such wise and supreme people are diligent in reciting the Buddha’s words.</l>
                    <l>Affluent and well born, they are the most beautiful beings.</l>
                    <l>Formed by virtue, their great bodies are beautified like the ocean.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-71"/>
                <p tid="76">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    become male and female servants. What are these five? They are (1) being disrespectful toward one’s
                    parents, (2) having an indecent mind, (3) being incorrigible and engaging in evil deeds as one
                    pleases, (4) stealing the wealth of others, and (5) absconding with the loans one has taken and
                    going into hiding. Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in these five actions become male and female
                    servants.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-72"/>
                <p tid="77">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-73"/>
                <lg tid="78">
                    <l>“They take birth in a household whose vast merit and wealth shines like snow. </l>
                    <l>Yet these fools are full of themselves and conceited, and so they squabble and are
                        disrespectful.</l>
                    <l>They do not conceive of their parents as being admirable objects of generosity.</l>
                    <l>Due to these negative actions, later they will have little worldly influence and be roguish.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-74"/>
                <lg tid="79">
                    <l>“They do not venerate the peerless Three Jewels but are excessively vicious and rude.</l>
                    <l>They squander all the virtues of love and compassion.</l>
                    <l>They will be powerless and dominated for innumerable lives and know no shame <ref cRef="F.337.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-200"/>.</l>
                    <l>Once free of servitude in the human realm, they will instantly descend.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-75"/>
                <lg tid="80">
                    <l>“Bereft of beauty, authority, high caste, and intellect, they are fools inclined to
                        negativity.</l>
                    <l>Not venerating the Three Jewels, they will be insecure, weak, and ugly.</l>
                    <l>Through deeds lacking dignity and contemplation, they turn evil.” </l>
                    <l>They will have no worldly joy, nothing to celebrate, and live troubled lives.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-76"/>
                <p tid="81">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    become supremely fortunate, have servants and fragrant breath, are unthreatened, pliant in body and
                    mind, beautiful to behold, and praised by many beings. What are these five? They are: (1) perceiving
                    accurately, genuinely, and completely; (2) speaking without exaggeration; (3) not lacking patience
                    towards the nature of the language used in the three vehicles of hearers, solitary buddhas, and
                    bodhisattvas, nor denigrating nor abandoning it but instead retaining, teaching, reading, and
                    reciting it, abandoning the limitless instances of the four faults of speech, and not belittling the
                    path of noble beings; (4) loving and nurturing those beings who persist in counterproductive
                    actions, turning them away from faults, and establishing them in virtue; and (5) not wishing to
                    expose the faults one sees in others. Pratibhānamati, when beings who engage in these five actions
                    are reborn among humans, they possess great fortune, acquire servants, fragrant breath, and mental
                    vigor, are agreeable, and delight many beings. They are without anguish, and their minds are at
                    ease. They are free of anger and do not encounter harm. They obtain a beautiful appearance and are
                    honored.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-77"/>
                <p tid="82">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse: </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-78"/>
                <lg tid="83">
                    <l>“They are deeply respectful of the buddhas and venerate their parents. <ref cRef="F.338.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-201"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Thus, ever free from the faults of speech, they are indeed wondrous beings.</l>
                    <l>The qualities of their speech—pleasant, resonant, and beneficial throughout all lifetimes—</l>
                    <l>Resound sweetly from their mouths in all directions upon breath as fragrant as a blue lotus.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-79"/>
                <lg tid="84">
                    <l>“Loving themselves and others equally, they motivate beings in all forms of virtue.</l>
                    <l>And by distancing themselves from what is evil, immoral, slanderous, and harmful, </l>
                    <l>Upon attaining the world they will have every joy throughout the fortunate eon.</l>
                    <l>They will possess extraordinary riches, live well, and turn away from evil deeds.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-80"/>
                <lg tid="85">
                    <l>“Recollecting the sublime Dharma, they persevere in the teachings and cultivate gentle
                        minds.</l>
                    <l>In this life, their love considers all beings to be like their own parents.</l>
                    <l>They think, ‘All beings were once my own family.’</l>
                    <l>With minds as bright as the moon they benefit them in the present. </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-81"/>
                <lg tid="86">
                    <l>“Forsaking evil deeds, such as competitiveness, haughtiness, and contempt,</l>
                    <l>And with pure minds, these virtuous, well-intentioned beings</l>
                    <l>Speak well of one another while being discrete about the shortcomings of others.</l>
                    <l>They swiftly become incomparable lords of the gods and go on to be virtuous buddhas.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-82"/>
                <p tid="87">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, beings who engage in the following five actions
                    attain sublime human lives, and yet they also receive constant denigration, are disliked by many
                    beings, have bad breath and unhappy minds, are often threatened, and have very unfit bodies. What
                    are these five? They are (1) lying, (2) being always bent on deceiving others through lying, (3)
                    criticizing the discourses one hears when assembled to hear great Dharma talks, (4) abusing and
                    denigrating those whose practice pure conduct, and (5) cultivating a base mind. Pratibhānamati,
                    beings who are endowed <ref cRef="F.338.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-202"/> with those five actions may attain the preeminence of a human life
                    but they receive constant denigration, are disliked by many beings, are ugly, have bad breath and
                    unhappy minds, are often threatened, and have bodies that are unhealthy.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-83"/>
                <p tid="88">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-84"/>
                <lg tid="89">
                    <l>“Their minds viciously upset the minds of others and they commit evil deeds.</l>
                    <l>They delight in perverse speech and in harming others.</l>
                    <l>These inferior beings will experience intense and unrelenting suffering in mind and body. </l>
                    <l>The tongues of these poor beings will be pierced by sharp iron hooks. </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-85"/>
                <lg tid="90">
                    <l>“In the abode of the Lord of Death these people will be force-fed drinks of boiling molten
                        copper.</l>
                    <l>In hell, these beings given to false speech will experience no joy.</l>
                    <l>Once there, they will hear no loving words and their breath will stink like a corpse. </l>
                    <l>All that normally appears pleasant will turn ugly.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-86"/>
                <lg tid="91">
                    <l>“Infamous at the royal court, they have many flaws of being derogatory and quarrelsome.</l>
                    <l>Many millions of people gossip about them being consistent in these flaws.</l>
                    <l>Such beings have base minds and will have unhealthy bodies due to their lies.</l>
                    <l>Thus, as I said before, the result of this flawed trajectory will be manifold suffering.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-87"/>
                <lg tid="92">
                    <l>“Forsaken by humanity, they are powerless and bereft of all happiness.</l>
                    <l>Such beings first go to the hells, and later, when they die and transmigrate,</l>
                    <l>They are born as animals among the five types of beings on the harsh wheel of cyclic
                        existence.</l>
                    <l>The suffering of these wandering beings will be truly inexhaustible.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-88"/>
                <p tid="93">Then the Blessed One said, “Pratibhānamati, mendicants and noble sons and daughters—beings
                    who make peace their primary concern—possess five qualities that ensure that they will always
                    encounter the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha, regardless of where they are born. They will
                    behold the blessed buddhas, hear the Dharma from them, and be delighted. <ref cRef="F.339.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-203"/> They will attain
                    awakening just as intended and gain abundance just as desired. What are these five qualities? (1)
                    Having themselves gone for refuge in the Three Jewels, they establish others in the practice of
                    going for refuge. (2) They skillfully create images of the thus-gone ones that are complete and
                    detailed in all respects. (3) They recognize preceptors and teachers and are respectful towards
                    them. (4) They easily follow instructions and practice them accordingly. (5) With pervasive and
                    unimpeded light rays, they behold all beings as being like themselves or like their only child.
                    These are beings who practice, read, recite, transmit, and explain the discourses exactly as they
                    were set forth. Their contemplation is extensive. Being utterly free from obstacles, they are
                    enthusiastic in their practice and gain accomplishment. Pratibhānamati, mendicants and noble sons
                    and daughters—beings who make peace their primary concern—who possess those five qualities, do not
                    encounter obstacles and are never disconnected from the Jewels of Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha,
                    regardless of where they are born. They behold the blessed buddhas, hear their Dharma teachings, and
                    are delighted. They attain awakening just as they intend and gain abundance just as they wish.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-89"/>
                <p tid="94">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-90"/>
                <lg tid="95">
                    <l>“Those who are stable in the supreme Dharma—the quality of the Buddha—</l>
                    <l>Are able to tame all beings.</l>
                    <l>They make fine representations of the Buddha’s body.</l>
                    <l>These learned ones venerate the words of their masters.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-91"/>
                <lg tid="96">
                    <l>“They consider everyone in every world, in all directions,</l>
                    <l>To be like themselves or their only child. <ref cRef="F.339.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-204"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>They are unequivocally free from the suffering of cyclic existence.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-92"> Lithang, Narthang, Choné, and Lhasa read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sred pa</foreign>, meaning “craving,” or “thirst.” So,
                            this line could also read, “They have gained certainty in freedom from the suffering of
                            craving.” </note>
                        </l>
                    <l>Their awakened minds are extremely pure and they behold the buddhas.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-93"/>
                <lg tid="97">
                    <l>“They who bring about the wealth of great jewel-like wisdom</l>
                    <l>Practice virtue day and night.</l>
                    <l>These beings who are endowed with miraculous light</l>
                    <l>Bring the brightest light to the deepest darkness of the world.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-94"/>
                <lg tid="98">
                    <l>“Perceiving every single phenomenon,</l>
                    <l>They are certain that there is nothing higher than the path to buddhahood.</l>
                    <l>They understand that this is the cause for reaching</l>
                    <l>The ultimate limit of the world, including its gods.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-95"/>
                <p tid="99">As he heard this Dharma teaching, the merchant Pratibhānamati was satisfied and content. He
                    rejoiced and was truly delighted. Joyful and happy, he gained the acceptance that phenomena are
                    unborn. The five hundred merchant children and each of their entourage of five hundred attained the
                    unclouded and stainless Dharma eye that perceives all phenomena. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-96"/>
                <p tid="100">All the gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, humans, and
                    non-humans assembled in the retinue of the Blessed One developed a motivation for one of the
                    vehicles in accord with their inclinations. They abundantly gained whatever they wished for and
                    scattered incalculable masses of flowers, incense, garlands, clothing, and jewelry toward the
                    Blessed One.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-97"/>
                <p tid="101">Then, the merchant Pratibhānamati stood up, draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt
                    on his right knee. With palms together he bowed toward the Blessed One and said, </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-98"/>
                <p tid="102">“Blessed One, the masters of the three realms teach these five qualities. Excellent.
                    Excellent. Hearing about these five qualities, this retinue has understood the meaning, just as is
                    intended. <ref cRef="F.340.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-205"/> When beings in future times hear of this teaching, they will abandon non-virtue,
                    do what is virtuous, and take up religious practice.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-99"/>
                <p tid="103">“Blessed One, please come together with your saṅgha of monks to my home. Please accept this
                    invitation out of compassion for us.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-100"/>
                <p tid="104">The Blessed One agreed out of compassion for the merchant Pratibhānamati. Knowing that the
                    Blessed One had accepted his invitation, Pratibhānamati was satisfied and content. He rejoiced and
                    was truly delighted. Happy and joyful, he bowed his head to the feet of the Blessed One,
                    circumambulated him three times, and departed together with his retinue. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-101"/>
                <p tid="105">When he arrived home, he bowed to the feet of his parents and told them with joined palms,
                    “Father, Mother, I have something to tell you. I have invited he who is rare and supreme in the
                    world, the unsurpassed being, the king of Dharma, he who has transcended the three realms, the
                    Blessed One himself, to come and take his midday meal here with his congregation of monks. Out of
                    compassion for us, he has accepted!”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-102"/>
                <p tid="106">Pratibhānamati’s father and mother were delighted and praised him, “Son, that is excellent!
                    You have done well!” They were excited to venerate the Thus-Gone One. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-103"/>
                <p tid="107">Pratibhānamati then instructed his wife Padma and her servants, “My dear, please prepare
                    fine food and drink with many hundreds of flavors for the blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha
                    and his retinue. Once the food has been prepared, scatter water, sweep the house, set up the
                    canopies, hang the silken tassels, scatter flower petals, <ref cRef="F.340.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-206"/> and perfume the environment with
                    fragrant incense. Lay out seats befitting the Thus-Gone One and his congregation of monks. Once he
                    has been received and the offerings laid before him at his feet, you should invite the sublime
                    Blessed One to take his seat.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-104"/>
                <p tid="108">Pratibhānamati came together with friends, dignitaries, kin, and elders, and they all did
                    exactly as he said. The next morning the Blessed One left Jeta Grove in Anāthapiṇḍada’s park and
                    traveled together with the saṅgha of monks to Śrāvastī out of kindness for beings. They did so
                    accompanied by miraculous displays manifested by the Thus-Gone One’s splendid magical powers.
                    Gradually they made their way to Pratibhānamati’s home.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-105"/>
                <p tid="109">Pratibhānamati and his entourage greeted the Blessed One, received him as a guest, made
                    offerings at his feet, and bowed their heads to his feet. He then entered the home along with his
                    entourage. The Blessed One sat on an excellent cushion, which befitted him, and the congregation of
                    monks took their appropriate seats. Pratibhānamati’s parents, close friends, friends, dignitaries,
                    relatives, and elders were delighted and bowed down; they paid respect to the master and with great
                    affection began to serve the Blessed One and the assembly of monks. Pratibhānamati, holding a bowl
                    filled with flowers and scented water, sat in front of the Teacher.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-106"/>
                <p tid="110">At that time, two friends in anguish came to Pratibhānamati’s home. One of them sat among
                    the saṅgha. However, as he did not ask all the monks whether he could partake of their food and
                    drink <ref cRef="F.341.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-207"/> and, moreover, the Blessed One had not offered the meal prayer, nobody gave him anything. He
                    became enraged and left, thinking, “Ah, nobody has given anything at all to me, the victim. These
                    are terrible mendicants. Their minds are not peaceful, they have no compassion, and neither do they
                    have loving minds. Giving to them is fruitless. Only foolish sponsors would give to that sort. If I
                    were king, I would slice off all their heads with an iron disc.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-107"/>
                <p tid="111">The other fellow, however, inquired whether the monks had abundant food and drink, and he
                    approached after the Buddha had offered the meal prayer. He then received a satisfying abundance of food and
                    drink, and was deeply contented. He went outside and thought, “Ah! These great mendicants who have
                    given me, a sufferer, a satisfying abundance of food and drink are compassionate. They have peaceful
                    minds and loving characters. This will satisfy me for a full week. It is a wise and fine patron who
                    gives to such excellent objects of generosity. Such generosity bears great fruit. Excellent! If I
                    were king, I would honor the saṅgha of monks, including the Buddha, through all means of service for
                    seven days. May it be so!”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-108"/>
                <p tid="112">Then the Blessed One was served the midday meal. He cleaned his bowl, washed his hands, and
                    then spoke to Venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, henceforth speak well of those who do not take food and
                    drink.” Pratibhānamati and his entourage sat in front of the Blessed One, who gave them a
                    delightful, <ref cRef="F.341.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-208"/> praiseworthy, applicable, and lucid Dharma talk that produced roots of virtue
                    in a multitude of beings. Then he rose from his seat and went back to Jeta Grove. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-109"/>
                <p tid="113">Then, those two anguished men wandered about and thus ended up taking rest in different
                    parts of the land. As they laid down, a canopy of clouds filled with lightning and wind hovered in
                    the sky above the meritorious one, thus shading him. At that time, the king of that country passed
                    away. Since there was no one else in the region who had sufficient royal qualities to be entrusted
                    with the country, the citizens, including the merchants, townspeople, village folk, high ministers,
                    ministers, guards, and retainers diligently inquired among diviners, soothsayers, and those skilled
                    in the movements of the stars and planets as to who should become their king. The reply was, “There
                    is a poor man who is qualified. He should become king.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-110"/>
                <p tid="114">So they set out from the royal capital bearing a marvelous throne of incredible
                    value—extensively ornamented and suitable for a king—along with a golden footstool. They carried
                    white parasols with jeweled handles, fans with golden handles and jeweled tails, and many vases
                    filled with perfumed water, as well as baskets of flowers, garlands of jewels, raiment, crowns,
                    headwear and other such ornamentation, and fragrant powders. Accompanied by cymbals, drums, and
                    singing, they searched everywhere for that impoverished man. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-111"/>
                <p tid="115">The diviner saw a region shrouded by a bank of clouds and said to them, “Friends, do you
                    see that pleasant and clear region <ref cRef="F.342.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-209"/> covered by a dark circle of clouds?” They responded,
                    “Friend, we see it!” The diviner said, “That is where the person with the royal attributes rests.
                    His meritorious karma has caused those clouds to gather to shade him.” So they traveled to that
                    spot, announcing themselves with cymbals and song. They bowed down and requested, “Accept the
                    coronation and become our king!” The poor man objected, “How could it be that someone like me is fit
                    to be king?” But they responded, “Because you are someone with merit. Do not say such things. It is
                    undeniable that you must be king!” At that point he agreed.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-112"/>
                <p tid="116">They bade him sit down upon the marvelous seat and put his feet on the footrest. With all
                    manner of auspiciousness, they raised him aloft and performed his coronation. They adorned him with
                    a crown attired with a silk sash and other ornaments, hung a giant parasol over the front of the
                    chariot, and cooled him with a golden-handled fan with a jeweled tail.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-113"/>
                <p tid="117">“Long live the king! May he be victorious!” Praises rang out from all sides as they led him
                    to the royal capital. At the same time, the spinning wheel of the royal chariot cut off the head of
                    the other beggar, who was lying there fast asleep. From then on, the meritorious man lived as the
                    sovereign. His realm, moreover, was without epidemic or calamity. It abounded in wealth,
                    development, well-being, and good harvests, and the land was filled with people and other beings.
                    The king’s name became associated with being richly endowed with all positive qualities.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-114"/>
                <p tid="118">“This prosperity,” the king thought, “is due to someone’s grace. What is the source of my
                    dominion’s great fortune?” Through the power of the Buddha, he remembered the entire confluence of
                    his previous actions. Remembering accurately, he then sent a messenger to the Blessed One bearing
                    the message, “Blessed One, out of compassion for myself and many other beings, please come here!”
                    <ref cRef="F.342.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-210"/> After sending the messenger, he swept and sprinkled water on the entire road from Jeta
                    Grove to his palace on which the Blessed One would travel. He also scattered flowers about, lined
                    the way with parasols, victory banners, flags, and porticos, and fumigated it with incense. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-115"/>
                <p tid="119">Out of compassion, the Blessed One came. He was greeted by the king, townspeople, village
                    folk, high ministers, ministers, guards, and retainers. They offered countless baskets filled with
                    flowers, incense, flower garlands, ointments, and aromatic powders before the Blessed One’s feet.
                    They collectively prostrated to the feet of the Blessed One and the assembly of monks. The king and
                    his retinue honored the Blessed One as a spiritual teacher and, with the greatest possible
                    admiration, requested the Blessed One and the assembly of monks to come to the palace, which was
                    adorned with all kinds of jewels in the midst of a great park. For seven days they were honored with
                    all manner of pleasing objects. The king served the Blessed One the midday meal and knew to clean
                    his plate and wash his hands. Then, for the purpose of hearing the Dharma, he sat down with his
                    entourage in front of the Blessed One. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-116"/>
                <p tid="120">He inquired, “Blessed One, given that I was once lowly and poor, how is it that I have now
                    gained this bountiful dominion?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-117"/>
                <p tid="121">The Blessed One responded, “Great King, in the city of Śrāvastī, there is a sponsor known
                    as Pratibhānamati. Previously, he invited the Buddha and the saṅgha of monks to his home for the
                    midday meal.” The Blessed One proceeded to relate the story of how the two anguished people
                    <ref cRef="F.343.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-211"/> had arrived there and how the chariot’s wheel had sliced off the head of one of them, who
                    then died and was reborn as a hell being. “In his life there,” the Blessed One said, “his head
                    continuously reappears, only to be cut off again by a flaming iron wheel. Only after ten million
                    eons will he be freed from that state. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-118"/>
                <p tid="122">“You, however, have attained the splendor of kingship because you made the aspiration, ‘If
                    I were to become a king, I would offer the Buddha and the assembly of monks the midday meal for a
                    full week!’ And thus your intention was fulfilled. Henceforth, in all your limitless lives, because
                    of your great excellence you will become a distinguished being.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-119"/>
                <p tid="123">Then the Blessed One expressed this in verse:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-120"/>
                <lg tid="124">
                    <l>“Because it is the source of evil in the world,</l>
                    <l>The mind is the root of all poison.</l>
                    <l>Because it is the source of negative speech,</l>
                    <l>The mouth is the very gate of evil.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-121"/>
                <lg tid="125">
                    <l>“The mind thinks all kinds of things,</l>
                    <l>And what follows is the utterance of words.</l>
                    <l>The evil that speech and mind create </l>
                    <l>Is born in the body, begetting suffering.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-122"/>
                <lg tid="126">
                    <l>“Without reflecting on benefit or harm,</l>
                    <l>The unintelligent act negatively.</l>
                    <l>Thus they become vessels of suffering</l>
                    <l>And in this way become afflicted.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-123"/>
                <lg tid="127">
                    <l>“A wheel cuts off the head</l>
                    <l>Of an ignorant man with poor intellect</l>
                    <l>Who in his mind desired to sever</l>
                    <l>The heads of those who are wise.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-124"/>
                <lg tid="128">
                    <l>“It is by the illustrious mind alone</l>
                    <l>That the virtue created by the merit of beings</l>
                    <l>Who are supported by the nectar of the virtuous Dharma</l>
                    <l>Leads to the heavenly realms.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-125"/>
                <lg tid="129">
                    <l>“They speak words thoughtful and from the heart,</l>
                    <l>And thus their speech is good.</l>
                    <l>It is therefore through their bodies</l>
                    <l>That the treasury of merit is obtained.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-126"/>
                <lg tid="130">
                    <l>“People who act with forethought</l>
                    <l>Decide between virtue and non-virtue.</l>
                    <l>So, if they engage in great merit,</l>
                    <l>They perennially become the best of gods.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-127"/>
                <lg tid="131">
                    <l>“When the mind consistently relinquishes</l>
                    <l>Non-virtuous actions, <ref cRef="F.343.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-212"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Then people engage in merit with great delight</l>
                    <l>And avoid committing evil.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-128"/>
                <lg tid="132">
                    <l>“Through countless millions of lives as gods or humans</l>
                    <l>They reach the state of the universal monarch </l>
                    <l>And have all the glories of kingship. </l>
                    <l>In doing so they are like you.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-129"/>
                <lg tid="133">
                    <l>“Lord of Humans, always bear in mind</l>
                    <l>That existence is without any essence,</l>
                    <l>And strive ceaselessly</l>
                    <l>In the teachings of the Buddha.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-130"/>
                <p tid="134">When the king heard this most excellent Dharma teaching from the Buddha, he experienced a
                    supreme state of mind and, together with his retinue, attained the result of a stream enterer. Other
                    beings, thousands in number, beheld the Blessed One and heard the Dharma. In this way they attained
                    the many pleasures of gods and humans and aroused roots of virtue that accord with freedom. When the
                    Blessed One had benefited and nurtured everyone present, he departed for Jeta Grove. Once back in
                    the monastery, he sat down on the seat arranged for the Buddha in the assembly of monks.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-131"/>
                <p tid="135">He then spoke to the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, bear this presentation of the Dharma in
                    mind; memorize it, recite it, and teach it widely! Ānanda, those noble sons or daughters who uphold
                    this Dharma teaching will receive a prophecy from the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Maitreya
                    regarding the vehicle that accords with their aspirations.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-132"/>
                <p tid="136">Venerable Ānanda then asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma
                    teaching? What should we call it?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-133"/>
                <p tid="137">The Blessed One said to Ānanda, “Ānanda, <ref cRef="F.344.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-213"/> you should know this Dharma teaching as
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching That Clarifies Karma</title> and <title xml:lang="en">The
                        Questions of the Merchant Pratibhānamati</title>.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-134"/>
                <p tid="138">Then the entire assembly including Venerable Ānanda, the monks, the bodhisattvas,
                    Pratibhānamati and all his servants, along with the world of the gods, humans, asuras, and
                    gandharvas, rejoiced and extolled what the Thus-Gone One had said.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-135"/>
                <trailer tid="139">This completes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of
                        Pratibhānamati</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="140">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-136"/>
                    <p tid="141">This sūtra was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptor Prajñāvarman,
                        the editor-translator Bandé Yeshé Dé, and others.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="142">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="144">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-listBibl-1">
                    <head type="section" tid="145">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-010-137">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spobs pa’i blo gros kyis zhus
                            pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 151, Degé Kangyur vol. 57 (mdo
                        sde, pa), folios 331.b–344.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-010-138">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spobs pa’i blo gros kyis zhus
                            pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition
                        of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The
                        Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol.
                        57, 879–913.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-010-139">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan
                        [/ lhan] dkar gyi chos ’gyur ro cog gi dkar chag</title>). Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna tshogs,
                        jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-010-140">Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>). Beijing:
                            Mi rigs dpe skrun khang, 2003.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-listBibl-2">
                    <head type="section" tid="146">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-010-141">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher
                            Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte.</title>Wien: Verlag der
                        österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-010-143">Robson, James. “Taking a Meal at a Lay Supporter’s Residence: The
                        Evolution of the Practice in Chinese Vinaya Commentaries” in <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist
                            Monasticism in East Asia: Places of Practice</title>. London: Routledge,
                        2009.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
    <list type="glossary">
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-186">
                <term>five polluting degenerations</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snyigs ma’i rnyog pa lnga</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">སྙིགས་མའི་རྙོག་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <term type="definition">Also known as “five contaminations or degenerations” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snyigs ma lnga</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pañcakaṣāya</foreign>). They are: (1) degeneration of lifespan, (2) degeneration of view or thoughts, (3) degeneration of the five afflictions, (4) degeneration of sentient beings, (5) degeneration of time. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-145">
                <term>acceptance that phenomena are unborn</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</term>
                <term type="definition">An attainment of effortless insight into emptiness and the lack of birth of
                    phenomena. This attainment only occurs on the bodhisattva levels, variously said to occur on the
                    first and eighth bodhisattva levels.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-187">
                <term>Dharma-Vinaya</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’dul ba</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་འདུལ་བ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma-vinaya</term>
                <term type="definition">The name for the canon of monastic discipline recorded in the Tripiṭaka, of the vows and commitments enshrined therein, and of the practice of that discipline.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-146">
                <term>asura</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                <term type="definition">The traditional adversaries of the gods (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">devas</foreign>) who are frequently portrayed in
                    the Brahmanical mythology as having a disruptive effect on cosmological and social harmony. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-147">
                <term>gandharva</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                <term type="definition">A class of generally benevolent nonhuman beings who inhabit the sky and are most renowned as celestial musicians.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-057-010-179" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>blessed one</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of a buddha, used in this text to refer to the Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-181">
                <term>thus-gone one</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
                <term type="definition">A frequently used synonym for a buddha. The expression is interpreted in different ways, but in general it implies one who has arrived at the realization of the ultimate state.</term>
                <term type="definition">Here used as a specific epithet of the Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-182">
                <term>god</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
                <term type="definition">One of the five or six classes of sentient beings, specifically engendered and dominated by exaltation, indulgence, and pride. The <term type="ignore">gods</term> are said to exist in realms higher than that of the human realm within in the world system of desire (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāma­dhātu</foreign>), and also in the world system of form (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">rūpa­dhātu</foreign>).</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-183">
                <term>hell being</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmyal ba pa</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">དམྱལ་བ་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāraka</term>
                <term type="definition">One of the five or six classes of sentient beings, considered to be the karmic fruition of past anger and harmful actions. According to Buddhist tradtion there are eighteen different hells, namely eight hot hells, eight cold hells, neighbouring and ephemeral hells, all of them tormented by increasing levels of unimaginable suffering.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-184">
                <term>hungry spirit</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dwags</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཡི་དྭགས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                <term type="definition">One of the five or six classes of sentient beings, considered to be the karmic fruition of past miserliness. They are particularly known to suffer from great hunger and thirst and the inability to acquire sustenance.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-185">
                <term>three realms</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams gsum</term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས་གསུམ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tridhātu</term>
                <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">three realms</term> are the desire realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāmadhātu</foreign>), form realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">rūpadhātu</foreign>) and the formless realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ārūpyadhātu</foreign>), i.e., the three worlds that make up saṃsāra. The first is composed of the six classes of beings (gods, asuras, humans, animals, hungry spirits and hell beings), whereas the latter two are only realms of gods and are thus higher, more ethereal states of saṃsāra.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-148">
                <term>garuḍa </term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                <term type="definition">A class of nonhuman beings with the form of an eagle-type bird with a gigantic wingspan.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-149">
                <term>hearer</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                <term type="definition">Someone who practices according to the vehicle of the <term type="ignore">hearers</term> (those who hear
                    the teachings from others); or, someone who heard the Dharma from the Buddha.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-150">
                <term>kinnara</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kinnara</term>
                <term type="definition">A class of nonhuman beings whose upper bodies are animal while their lower bodies are human. The term literally means “Is that human?”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-151">
                <term>mahoraga</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                <term type="definition">A class of nonhuman being with the form of a large serpent.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-152">
                <term>mendicant</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge sbyong </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śramaṇa</term>
                <term type="definition">A term used broadly to denote a spiritual seeker.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <!--<item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-153">
                <term>merchant</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshong dpon </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཚོང་དཔོན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śreṣṭhin</term>
                <term type="definition">A leader in the <term type="ignore">merchant</term> community.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>-->
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-154">
                <term>nāga</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                <term type="definition"> A class of nonhuman beings who live in subterranean aquatic environments and who are known to hoard wealth and esoteric teachings. Nāgas are associated with snakes and serpents, and often assume a snakelike appearance.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-155">
                <term>purification ceremony</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gso sbyong </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">གསོ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">poṣadha </term>
                <term type="definition">A twice monthly ceremony performed by monks, nuns, and novices in which the
                    ordained confess and remedy transgressions of their vows, thereby purifying and restoring the
                    vows.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-156">
                <term>stūpa</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod rten </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་རྟེན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">stūpa</term>
                <term type="definition">Literally in the Tibetan, a support of veneration. Usually a heap or circular
                    archeological structure containing relics of the masters of the past.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-157">
                <term>solitary buddha </term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                <term type="definition">An individual who, in his or her last life, attains realization by realizing the
                    nature of interdependent origination without relying upon a spiritual guide.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-158">
                <term>stream enterer</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyun du zhugs pa </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">srotāpanna</term>
                <term type="definition">The first level of Noble Ones on the path of the hearers.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-159">
                <term>ten virtues</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba bcu </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བ་བཅུ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśakuśala </term>
                <term type="definition">Abstaining from killing, taking what is not given, sexual misconduct, lying,
                    uttering divisive talk, speaking harsh words, gossiping, covetousness, ill will, and wrong
                    views.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-160">
                <term>three poisons</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dug gsum </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">དུག་གསུམ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">triviṣa</term>
                <term type="definition">A collective term for desire, anger, and delusion</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-162">
                <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasra­mahāsāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                <term type="definition">The largest universe spoken of in Buddhist cosmology, consisting of one billion
                    smaller world systems. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-163">
                <term>universal monarch</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor lo sgyur ba’i rgyal po </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ལོ་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravartirāja</term>
                <term type="definition">A type of monarch who gains domain over a large fraction or the entirety of the
                    world.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-164">
                <term>yakṣa</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                <term type="definition">A class of nonhuman beings that haunt or protect natural places and cities. They can be malevolent or benevolent, and are known for bestowing wealth and worldly boons.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-180">
                <term>Śākyamuni</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya thub pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni</term>
                <term type="definition">The name of the historical Buddha, Siddhārtha Gautama; he was a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">muni</foreign> (sage) from the Śākya clan.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-165">
                <term>Ānanda</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                <term type="definition">The buddha’s cousin and principal attendant.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-166">
                <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Anāthapiṇḍada</term> was a wealthy merchant in the town of Śrāvastī, famous for his generosity to the poor, who became a patron of the Buddha Śākyamuni. He bought the Jeta Grove from Prince Jeta, and built there a monastery for the Buddha. He is better known in the West by the alternative Pāli form Anāthapiṇḍika.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <!--<item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-167">
                <term>Brahmā</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                <term type="definition">A divine being who rules the <term type="ignore">Brahmā</term> realm</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>-->
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-168">
                <term>Kubera</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus ngan po </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ལུས་ངན་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kubera</term>
                <term type="definition">An epithet for Vaiśravaṇa, the god of wealth.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-169">
                <term>Lord of Death</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                <term type="definition">Ruler of the hell realms.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-170">
                <term>Maitreya</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of loving kindness; the next buddha to follow Śākyamuni.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-171">
                <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pra dz+nyA war ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པྲ་ཛྙཱ་ཝར་མ།</term>

                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman</term>
                <term type="definition">An Indian Bengali paṇḍita resident in Tibet during the late 8th / early 9th
                    centuries. Arriving in Tibet on an invitation from the Tibetan king, he assisted in the translation
                    of numerous canonical scriptures. He is also the author of a few philosophical commentaries
                    contained in the Tibetan Tengyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstan ’gyur</foreign>) collection.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-172">
                <term>Pratibhānamati</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spobs pa’i blo gros </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">སྤོབས་པའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratibhānamati</term>
                <term type="definition">A merchant of the city of Śrāvastī who is the primary interlocutor in this
                    sūtra.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-174">
                <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the late 8th and early 9th
                    centuries.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-176">
                <term>Jeta Grove</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jetavana</term>
                <term type="definition">A park outside Śrāvastī. It was donated to the Buddha by Anāthapiṇḍada, who purchased it at great cost from Prince Jeta, and built there the monastery where the Buddha spent most rainy seasons and is therefore the setting for many sūtras. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-177">
                <term>Kauverī</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus ngan phyogs </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">ལུས་ངན་ཕྱོགས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauverī</term>
                <term type="definition">The term is used as a reference to the northern direction, which is governed by
                    the deity Kubera.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-057-010-178">
                <term>Śrāvastī</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrāvastī</term>
                <term type="definition">Ancient city of northern India.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
    </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>

    
    
    
    </TEI>