<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྒྱ་མཚོས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara (2)</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
          mdo</title>
        <title xml:lang="bo" type="longTitle">འཕགས་པ་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྒྱ་མཚོས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara”</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
        <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under
          the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
        <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-289">Nathaniel Rich</editor>
        <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
        <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
        <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-337">Felin Chung</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
        <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-60">Benjamin Ewing</author>
        <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</consultant>
        <consultant role="dharmaMaster" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
        <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-262">David Higgins</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.11 <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the
          Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
          <licence>
            <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
            <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial -
              No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for
              commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-058-003"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from
          the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2020-10-06</date>
            </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl key="toh154" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 154</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 58 (mdo sde, pha), folios 198.b–205.a</biblScope>
          <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
          <author role="translatorTib">Danasila</author>
          <author role="translatorTib">Munivarman</author>
          <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
          <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="15">
            <volume number="58" start-page="395" end-page="409"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11750" work="W22084"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2023-01-18T15:34:00.229Z" user="celso">18/01/2023 15:34:00</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="" date-time="2019-09-25T06:25:58.148Z" user="andreas">0.1 2019</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.1" date-time="2019-10-07T10:27:24.685Z" user="admin">Publication
          statement updated</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2019-11-28T09:42:55.642Z" user="andreas">2.b</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.2" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated
          version increment</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2020-01-28T06:26:17.404Z" user="mike">2.c</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2020-05-27T07:24:26.446Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-05-27T08:04:05.763Z" user="mike">2.a</note>

        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2020-06-09T15:51:35.136Z" user="mike">v 0.0.1</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2020-06-09T15:51:35.136Z" user="mike">2</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.3" date-time="2020-06-09T15:52:13.855Z" user="mike">v 0.1.3</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2020-09-24T13:17:54.807Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
          (update-contributors)</note>
      
    <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2020-10-06T09:18:15.149Z" user="mike">1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2020-10-06T09:18:15.149Z" user="mike">First published version</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.0" date-time="2020-10-07T15:16:17.108Z" user="john">Summary improved and various edits to the intro; Chinese titles of second Taishō added; some grammatical corrections to the text.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.1" date-time="2020-10-07T19:02:32.087Z" user="john">Tiny typo corrected.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.2" date-time="2020-10-26T10:38:23.462Z" user="john">Added some line breaks to divide topics</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.3" date-time="2020-11-23T13:57:44.998Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.0.0)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.4" date-time="2020-11-25T16:04:26.404Z" user="celso">Updated pending links</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.5" date-time="2020-12-11T14:06:50.919Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.1.5)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.6" date-time="2021-02-12T19:00:09.543Z" user="celso">"scholar" to "preceptor" in colophon</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.7" date-time="2021-04-22T19:38:58.731Z" user="celso">minor correction to markup, new files not needed</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.8" date-time="2021-06-26T04:18:23.129Z" user="celso">kiṃnara to kinnara</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.9" date-time="2022-01-06T20:26:22.995Z" user="celso">activated pending link</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.10" date-time="2023-01-16T16:58:52.361Z" user="celso">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.11" date-time="2023-01-18T14:48:43.396Z" user="celso">Auto (removing-tid-from-back-list-items)</note>
</notesStmt>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="summary">
        <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-1"/>
        <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara</title> presents a discourse given by the Buddha
          Śākyamuni on the importance of considering the effects caused by actions. At the start of his teaching, the Buddha remarks how
          the variety of forms that exist, and in fact all phenomena, come about as the result of virtuous and nonvirtuous
          actions. By understanding this law of cause and effect and by taking great care to engage in virtue, one will avoid
          rebirth in the lower realms and enter the path to perfect awakening. In the rest of his discourse he explains in 
          great detail the advantages of engaging in each of the ten virtues and the problems associated with
          not engaging in them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgment">
        <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-2"/>
        <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the supervision of Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. The
          translation was produced by Benjamin Ewing, who also wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor compared the translation
          with the original Tibetan and edited the text. Felin Chung consulted the Chinese versions.</p>
        <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
          Buddha.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction">
        <head type="introduction" tid="6">Introduction</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-introduction-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-3"/>
          <p tid="8">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara</title> takes place in the unusual setting of the
            nāga king Sāgara’s court deep in the ocean. Here the Buddha gives a discourse on the importance of avoiding the ten
            nonvirtuous deeds. The sūtra begins with the Buddha Śākyamuni explaining how everything, including all the various
            life forms of beings in the ocean and even the awakening of a buddha, is created through the law of cause and effect.
            The Buddha explains the relationship between form and emptiness, showing how despite the essential emptiness of all
            phenomena, beings appear in various shapes and sizes due to their former virtuous and nonvirtuous actions. The
            remainder of the text concerns the ten nonvirtuous acts and the need to abandon them by practising instead
            the ten virtuous acts. First, the Buddha explains the various benefits of abstaining from each of the nonvirtuous
            acts and shows how this will lead to awakening. He then describes the perilous consequences of engaging in the
            nonvirtuous acts. Finally, the Buddha explains how cultivating additional positive qualities while engaging in these
            virtuous acts will lead to even greater spiritual boons. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-4"/>
          <p tid="9">The Degé Kangyur contains three sūtras entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King
            Sāgara</title>. They can be distinguished by their length, one being quite long (<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh153.html">Toh 153</ref>, 164 folio
            pages), one medium-length, which is
            translated here (Toh 154, 14 folio pages), and one very short (<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh155.html">Toh 155</ref>, 1 folio page). All three of these are included
            as individual texts in the early ninth century Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</foreign>) catalog,
            confirming their status as independent scriptures in Tibet during the imperial period.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-5"> See Denkarma: 297.a.6<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html" inst="297.a"/> (Toh 153),
              299.a.5<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html" inst="299.a"/> (Toh 154), and 300.a.2<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html" inst="300.a"/> (Toh 155). See also
              Herrmann-Pfandt 2008: Toh 153 = no. 96 (p. 55), Toh 154 = no. 187 (p. 100), Toh 155 = no. 237 (p. 125). </note> Of
            these, Toh 155 appears to be unrelated to the other two. It seems apparent, however, that at some point in its textual
            life (presumably in India), Toh 154 was taken as an excerpt from Toh 153 and transmitted as an independent text. A large 
            number of minor differences and one whole section that is unique to 
            Toh 154<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-6"> Toh 154 contains a section of nearly two folios that is not included in Toh
              153. We have noted this section in the translation.</note> distinguish these
            two versions, but their shared provenance is nevertheless clear. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-7"/>
          <p tid="10">A further indication that the two texts had already circulated independently in India is that the two sūtras
            were translated into Tibetan by different translation teams. Toh 153 was translated by Jinamitra, Prajñāvarma, and
            Yeshé Dé while Toh 154 was translated by Jinamitra, Dānaśīla, Munivarman, and Yeshé Dé. Interestingly, in two versions
            of the colophon to Toh 154 it is explicitly mentioned that this text is an extract from a larger scripture, although
            Toh 153 is not specified as the source.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-8"> These two colophons are
              those of the Stok Palace and Shey Palace, which both belong to the Thempangma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thems
                spang ma</foreign>) group of Kangyurs. S, Z: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mdo che ba’i nang nas bkod pa
                snang ngo</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-9"/>
          <p tid="11">Both texts were transmitted from India to China, with the longer of the two (Toh 153) appearing four hundred
            years before the shorter. Toh 154 was translated into Chinese twice under two different titles (Taishō 600 and 601).
            Taishō 600 is a translation made between 695 and 700 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> by the Khotanese monk Śikṣānanda (652–710
              <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>) and appears under the title <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Path of the Ten
                Virtuous Actions</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-10"> Chinese: <title xml:lang="zh">十善業道經</title> (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Shishan ye dao jing</title>). 
                This text has been translated into English from the Chinese at least three times: Saddhaloka 1996;
              Rulu 2012; and Wong, n.d.</note> Taishō 601 is a translation made relatively late, between 980 and 1017 
            <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>, by Dānapāla (d. 1017 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>), a monk
            from the area of Uḍḍiyāna in northwestern India who was one of the four chief Indian translators during the Song
            dynasty; its title matches the Tibetan and Sanskrit title here.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-115">Chinese: 
              <title xml:lang="zh">佛為娑伽羅龍王所說大乘經</title> (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Fo wei suo jia luo long wang suoshuo dasheng 
                jing</title>).</note> Given this information, we can surmise that Toh 154 was circulating as an independent text in India prior to
            695 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> and that its subsequent transmission to both China and Tibet was also independent from Toh 153. It is
            difficult, however, to determine exactly when the split occurred. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-11"/>
          <p tid="12">This English translation is based on the Tibetan translation in the Degé Kangyur in consultation
            with the Comparative Edition (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and the Stok Palace Kangyur. We also
            occasionally compared these sources to the two Chinese translations.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="translation">
        <head type="translation" tid="13"> The Translation </head>
        <head type="titleHon" tid="14">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
        <head type="titleMain" tid="15">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-section-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-14"/>
          <p tid="18">
                        <ref cRef="F.198.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-116"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-16"/>
          <p tid="20">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was residing within the ocean in the realm of the nāga king
            Sāgara. He was in the courtyard of the nāga king Sāgara together with a great monastic saṅgha of eight thousand monks
            and an assembly of bodhisattva great beings who had assembled from the worlds of the ten directions, a vast number of
            whom had attained supernatural knowledge. Also present there were Śakra, Brahmā, and the guardians of the world, and
            many trillions of gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-17"/>
          <p tid="21">Then the Blessed One, knowing the assembly in its entirety, spoke to the nāga king Sāgara, “Lord of nāgas,
            alas! The state of this world has been shaped by various kinds of karma. The predispositions to various kinds of karma
            are in turn conditioned by a variety of mental apprehensions. <ref cRef="F.198.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-117"/> This is also what
            causes the variety of beings.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-18"/>
          <p tid="22">“Lord of nāgas, consider all the various forms of the beings that are present here in this retinue and in
            this ocean as well—all the diversity of beings that exist here. Lord of nāgas, all these beings are here in such
            variety due to the variety of their previous engagement in virtue and nonvirtue through activities of mind, body,
            speech, and intellect. The mind is formless, invisible, and ungraspable. In the same way, lord of nāgas, because all
            these forms of beings are fabrications, their present characteristics have no owner, no ownership, and are
            ungraspable. Being simply a variety of productions formed by whatever karma has been accumulated, they have no creator
            whatsoever.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-19"/>
          <p tid="23">“Lord of nāgas, in this way, all phenomena are inconceivable and have the essential quality of being
            illusory. Lord of nāgas, since bodhisattvas are skilled in this regard, they understand that any phenomenon only comes
            to exist by virtue of being constructed. Knowing this, they therefore engage in virtue. Then, because phenomena are
            constructed, when such virtuous actions are performed, the resultant aggregates, elements, and sense sources are
            elegant, lovely to behold, and beautiful. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-20"/>
          <p tid="24">“Lord of nāgas, the body of a thus-gone one is born from merits numbering in the trillions. This body, which
            is adorned with marks, perfectly complete, and splendorous, outshines the worlds of gods and humans and prevails
            uninterruptedly. Consider how even the great brahmā gods, who hold dominion over one million worlds, appear faded, and
            their eyes are blinded, when they look upon the body of a thus-gone one. Lord of nāgas, look at the forms, marks,
            bodies, and adornments of these bodhisattvas. Lord of nāgas, they are all beautifully produced by the performance of
            virtuous actions. <ref cRef="F.199.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-118"/>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-21"/>
          <p tid="25">“Lord of nāgas, this dominion of yours likewise arose from a great amount of merit. Lord of nāgas, all the
            dominions of Śakra, Brahmā, and the guardians of the world, and those of the gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras,
            garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, humans, and nonhumans, likewise arise from merit. Lord of nāgas, the various bodies
            within this ocean—whether they are ugly and unshapely, shapely, large, and strong, or small and thin—all those
            bodies are products of the diversity of virtuous and nonvirtuous actions of mind, body, speech, and intellect that
            each individual engaged in. </p>
          <p tid="26">“Lord of nāgas, because of this, it is said that ‘Beings must be confident in the way karma is appropriated
            and inherited, shapes beings’ birth, and ripens.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-23"> This is a
              standardized formula that is very commonly repeated; a version is even found, for example, in the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Upajjhatthana Sutta</title> of the Pali Canon, as the fifth of the five recollections. These
              recollections are recited daily by many modern Theravāda Buddhists.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-24"/>
          <p tid="27">“Lord of nāgas, you should train in this way. Being confident in the way karma is appropriated and inherited
            and the way it ripens, you will become focused on producing virtuous qualities. You will not debase your view. You
            will not give rise to nihilist or eternalist views. You will please those who are worthy of veneration and, having
            pleased them, you will also show them respect. Then, because of that respect, the entire world, including the gods,
            will show their respect to you. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-25"/>
          <p tid="28">“Lord of nāgas, there is one teaching that severs, for all beings, all the paths that lead to the
            unfortunate destinies, the lower realms, the unfavorable states. What is that one teaching? It is to contemplate
            virtuous qualities while thinking, ‘However I am now, it will pass just like the days go by.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-26"> This translation is tentative. The Tibetan reads, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdag ji ltar gyur cing nyin zhag rnams ’gro zhig gu snyam du dge ba’i chos rnams la rab tu rtog
                pa’o</foreign>.</note> By repeatedly contemplating virtuous qualities in this way, there will be no opportunity
              <ref cRef="F.199.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-119"/> for nonvirtuous thoughts and mental states to arise. Having abandoned nonvirtue
            and being endowed with virtuous qualities in this way, such beings have a pure outlook and they will find company with
            the buddhas and bodhisattvas, and with the noble hearers and solitary buddhas.</p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-27"/>
          <p tid="29">“Lord of nāgas, what are those virtuous qualities? The virtuous qualities are the roots and foundations of
            the excellence of gods and humans. They are the roots and foundations of the awakening of the hearers and solitary
            buddhas. They are the roots and foundations of unexcelled and perfect awakening. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-28"/>
          <p tid="30">“What are those roots and foundations? They are the paths of the ten virtues. What are those paths of the
            ten virtues? They are to forsake the following: killing, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, slander, harsh words,
            meaningless talk, covetousness, malevolence, and wrong views. The abandonment of these constitutes the paths of the
            ten virtues. They are the roots and foundations for both mundane and supramundane excellence. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-29"/>
          <p tid="31">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken killing will obtain ten qualities of pacification. What are these
            ten qualities? They will grant fearlessness to all beings. They will regard all beings with love. They will eliminate
            the tendency for aggression. They will be able to reduce disease. They will plant the seed for extending life. They
            will guard, protect, and shield nonhumans. They will sleep happily, awaken happily, and not have negative dreams. They
            will have the gods’ protection even when asleep. They will be free from animosity and the propensity for animosity.
            And they will have no fear of the lower realms <ref cRef="F.200.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-120"/> and, having died and transmigrated,
            they will be born among the gods in the joyful celestial realms. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken killing will
            obtain those ten qualities of pacification. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking killing toward
            unexcelled and perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, when they attain awakening the power of
            their mind will be such that their lifespans become limitless.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-30"/>
          <p tid="32">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken stealing will obtain ten qualities of confidence. What are these ten
            qualities? They will have great wealth and that wealth will not be taken by kings, thieves, fire, water, enemies, or
            neighbors. They will be well liked because they are pleasing to many beings. They will not have the secondary
            disturbing emotions. They will be trusted by those who have wealth. Their praises will be sung in every direction and they
            will not fear harm from adversaries anywhere. The words and verses of the praises of their virtue will be sublime.
            They will not be timid, engaging with those around them without anxiety. They will obtain abundant life, power,
            beauty, happiness, eloquence, resources, and wealth. They will be inclined toward expansive generosity. And after
            leaving this body, they will be born among the gods in the joyful celestial realms. Lord of nāgas, those who have
            forsaken stealing they will obtain those ten qualities of confidence. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of
            forsaking stealing toward unexcelled and perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, knowing themselves
            to possess the wisdom of a thus-gone one that is free of secondary disturbing emotions, <ref cRef="F.200.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-121"/>
            they will fully awaken to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-31"/>
          <p tid="33">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken sexual misconduct will obtain four qualities that are praised by the
            wise. What are these four qualities? They will have restraint of the senses. They will overcome excitement. They will
            be praised by the whole world. And they will not seduce married women. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken sexual
            misconduct will obtain those four qualities that are praised by the wise. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of
            forsaking sexual misconduct toward unexcelled and perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, they will
            obtain the sheathed genitals, which are a mark of a great being.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-32"/>
          <p tid="34">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken lying will obtain eight qualities that are praised by gods and
            humans. What are these eight qualities? They will have a clean face with the scent of a blue lotus. They will be held
            as authoritative by all beings. They will become singularly powerful because they are beloved by gods and humans. They
            will alleviate the fears of spirits due to their assurances. They will be pure in body, speech, and mind because of
            their excellent altruism. Their happiness will increase because their words are free of confusion. Their voices will
            be heard because their words are worthy of being remembered. And they will be free of wrongdoing among gods and humans
            because they have obtained insight. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken lying will obtain those eight qualities
            that are praised by gods and humans. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking lying toward unexcelled and
            perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, their words will be in accord with the truth. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-33"/>
          <p tid="35">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken slander will obtain five qualities of indivisibility. <ref cRef="F.201.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-122"/> What are these five qualities? They will obtain indestructible bodies because they
            have transcended the terror of being harmed by others. They will obtain unswerving retinues because they do not desire
            that which others own. They will obtain unwavering faith because they trust that karma bears fruit. They will be
            indivisible from the Dharma because they are dedicated to accomplishment. And they will obtain unshakable friendship
            because they are undeceiving. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken slander will obtain those five qualities of
            indivisibility. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking slander toward unexcelled and perfect awakening,
            then, because of those roots of virtue, they will become thus-gone ones with an indivisible retinues; not even all the
            māras and opposing teachers will be able to divide the followers of such thus-gone ones. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-34"/>
          <p tid="36">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken harsh words will obtain eight purities of speech. What are these
            eight? They are timely speech, beneficial speech, appropriate speech, gentle speech, comprehensible speech, audible
            speech, speech that pleases many beings, and dignified speech. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken harsh words will
            obtain those eight purities of speech. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking harsh words toward unexcelled
            and perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, they will become thus-gone ones with voices that
            resound like Brahmā’s speech.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-35"/>
          <p tid="37">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken meaningless talk will obtain three complete certainties. What are
            these three? Because of their timely words they will certainly please the wise. Because they answer<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-36"> Reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">glon</foreign> from S in place
              of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lon</foreign>.</note> questions so well, their minds will certainly reach
            the truth. And because they are genuine friends, they will certainly obtain the greatness of gods and humans. Lord of
            nāgas, those who have forsaken meaningless talk <ref cRef="F.201.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-123"/> will obtain those three complete
            certainties. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking meaningless talk toward unexcelled and perfect
            awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, they will become thus-gone ones who teach continuously and do not
            otherwise speak.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-37"/>
          <p tid="38">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken covetousness will obtain five strengths. What are these five?
            Because they do not have impaired faculties they will obtain strength of body, speech, and mind. Because they are
            unassailable by all enemies they will obtain vast dominion over resources and power. Due to the power of their merit,
            they will experience all the vast pleasures and enjoyments. Because they obtain the supreme joy<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-38"> Reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dga’ ba</foreign> from S, C,
              D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dgab pa</foreign>.</note> they will be honored by kings and lords. And
            because they lack any prior jealousy, the wealth they obtain will be a hundred thousand times greater than what they
            wished for. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken covetousness will obtain those five strengths. If they dedicate the
            roots of virtue of forsaking covetousness toward unexcelled and perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of
            virtue, they will become the sole teachers, thus-gone ones who are revered by the three worlds.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-39"/>
          <p tid="39">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken malevolence will obtain eight qualities that bring peace of mind.
            What are these eight? They will be inclined toward nonviolence. They will be inclined toward pacifying malevolence.
            They will be inclined toward eliminating conflicts and quarrels. They will be inclined toward being honest, kind, and
            gentle. They will be renowned as noble beings. They will have greater ability to benefit all beings through such means
            as delighting in others’ happiness and having loving kindness. They will be honored by many beings since they delight
            in others’ happiness and have much faith. And because they are kind and capable, <ref cRef="F.202.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-124"/> it
            will not be difficult to attain rebirth in the abode of Brahmā. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken malevolence
            will obtain those eight qualities that bring peace of mind. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking
            malevolence toward unexcelled and perfect awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, they will become
            thus-gone ones with unobstructed minds whom one never tires of seeing. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-40"/>
          <p tid="40">“Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken wrong views will obtain ten excellent qualities. What are these ten?
            Their thoughts will become virtuous and they find virtuous friends; because of trusting that actions bear fruit they
            do not commit evil deeds even at the cost of their lives. They consider the Buddha to be their deity and they do not
            consider anyone else to be their deity. They have a sincere view because they do not believe in wonders and luck. They
            associate with gods and humans, but they do not associate with animals and those who live in the realm of the Lord of
            Death. They obtain distinction by practicing virtue. They have entered the path of the noble ones because they do not
            follow false paths. They are free from the belief in the transitory collection and they have abandoned all evil deeds.
            They have unobscured insight because they have journeyed toward perfection and entered perfection; and they are free
            from unfavorable states among gods and humans. Lord of nāgas, those who have forsaken wrong views will obtain those
            ten excellent qualities. If they dedicate the roots of virtue of forsaking wrong views toward unexcelled and perfect
            awakening, then, because of those roots of virtue, they will manifest all the qualities of a buddha. They will become
            thus-gone ones with swift supernatural knowledge.</p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-41"/>
          <p tid="41">“Lord of nāgas,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-42"> The following section detailing the
              negative effects of engaging in the ten nonvirtuous acts, until the beginning of the section on engaging with
              generosity (starting on <ptr target="#UT22084-058-003-53"/>: “Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken
              killing engage in generosity”) is absent from Toh 153. See the introduction (<ptr target="#UT22084-058-003-4"/>) for
              more information on this sūtra.</note> these paths of the ten virtues are the roots and foundations for all the
            mundane and the supramundane excellence up to and including unexcelled and perfect awakening. Their opposites <ref cRef="F.202.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-125"/> are the paths of the ten nonvirtues. If one has predominantly resorted to, cultivated,
            and engaged in them to a great extent, that is cause for birth in the hell realms. If one has engaged in them to a
            middling extent, that is cause for birth in the realm of animals. If one has engaged in them to a lesser extent, then
            that is cause for birth in the realm of the Lord of Death. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-43"/>
          <p tid="42">“Furthermore, lord of nāgas, those who have practiced, cultivated, and engaged in killing to a great extent
            will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of the Lord of Death. Even if they are
            subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: their lives will be shortened, and they
            will be sickly.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-44"/>
          <p tid="43">“Those who steal will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of
            the Lord of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: they
            will have few resources and their resources will be ordinary.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-45"/>
          <p tid="44">“Those who engage in sexual misconduct will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm
            of the Lord of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences:
            their followers will not be trustworthy, and their wives will be adversarial. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-46"/>
          <p tid="45">“Those who engage in lying will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of the Lord
            of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: they will be
            greatly criticized, and they will be deceived by others. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-47"/>
          <p tid="46">“Those who engage in slander will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of the
            Lord of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: their
            attendants will be fractious and have bad characters. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-48"/>
          <p tid="47">“Those who use harsh words will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of the Lord
            of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, <ref cRef="F.203.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-126"/> they will
            experience two consequences: they will hear unpleasant speech and aggressive speech.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-49"/>
          <p tid="48">“Those who engage in meaningless talk will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm
            of the Lord of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences:
            their words will not be valued, and their eloquence will be unreliable.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-50"/>
          <p tid="49">“Those who engage in covetousness will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of
            the Lord of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: they
            will be insatiable, and their desires will increase.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-51"/>
          <p tid="50">“Those who engage in malevolence will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of the
            Lord of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: they will
            crave what is unhelpful and others will do them harm.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-52"/>
          <p tid="51">“Those who hold wrong views will be led to the hell realms, to the animal realm, or to the realm of the Lord
            of Death. Even if they are subsequently born in the human realm, they will experience two consequences: they will
            lapse into degenerate views and they will be deceitful. Therefore, lord of nāgas, these ten nonvirtues will truly give
            rise to an immeasurably great mass of suffering.</p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-53"/>
          <p tid="52">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken killing engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen, and they will have long lives. And when they engage in bodhisattva activity, they
            will be free from any fear of being harmed by others.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-54"/>
          <p tid="53">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken stealing engage in generosity, then
            their wealth will increase. It will not be stolen, and they will become freely generous without consideration for any
            of their possessions. <ref cRef="F.203.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-127"/> And when they engage in bodhisattva activity, they will
            accomplish all the aspects of a buddha and so gain unexcelled qualities.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-55"/>
          <p tid="54">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken sexual misconduct engage in generosity, then their wealth
            will increase. It will not be stolen, and their wives will not be adulterous. And when they engage in bodhisattva
            activity, they will not view any mother, child, or wife with hostility. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-56"/>
          <p tid="55">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken lying engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen, and they will not be slandered but earnestly defended. And when they engage in
            bodhisattva activity, they will act as they say, and they will keep their word. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-57"/>
          <p tid="56">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken slander engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen, and their followers will not be divided. And when they engage in bodhisattva
            activity, they will gain retinues of bodhisattvas because their harmonious attitude. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-58"/>
          <p tid="57">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken harsh words engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen, and their words will be heeded and respected. And when they engage in bodhisattva
            activity, no one in their retinues will be discontent.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-59"/>
          <p tid="58">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken meaningless talk engage in generosity, then their wealth
            will increase. It will not be stolen, and their words will become worth hearing and trustworthy. And when they engage
            in bodhisattva activity, they will be skilled at cutting through all doubts.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-60"/>
          <p tid="59">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken covetousness engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen, and their minds will be inclined toward great pleasures and enjoyments. <ref cRef="F.204.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-128"/> And when they engage in bodhisattva activity, they will aspire to the vast and they
            will be renowned as mighty.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-61"/>
          <p tid="60">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken malevolence engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen. They will be beautiful, and they will delight and please many beings. And when they
            engage in bodhisattva activity, they will have unobstructed intellect, unobstructed minds, and unimpaired
            faculties.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-62"/>
          <p tid="61">“Lord of nāgas, if bodhisattvas who have forsaken wrong views engage in generosity, then their wealth will
            increase. It will not be stolen. They will have faith in the Buddha and be born into households with correct views.
            And when they engage in bodhisattva activity, they will always behold the Buddha, listen to the Dharma, and serve the
            Saṅgha, while never failing to generate the mind set on awakening. </p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-63"/>
          <p tid="62">“Lord of nāgas, if these paths of the ten virtues are adorned with generosity in that way, one will reap
            great fortune. If these paths of the ten virtues are adorned with discipline, then aspirations for all buddha
            qualities will be fulfilled. If these paths of the ten virtues are adorned with patience, then the excellent major and
            minor marks, and the voice of a buddha, will be perfected. Likewise, if they are adorned with diligence, then māras
            and opponents will be overcome and all buddha qualities will be perfected. If they are adorned with concentration,
            then mindfulness, intelligence, understanding, modesty, and joy will be purified. If they are adorned with insight,
            then all degenerate views will be vanquished. If they are adorned with love, then there will be no anger toward any
            being. If they are adorned with compassion, then no beings will be abandoned. If they are adorned with joy, then one
            will not be discouraged. <ref cRef="F.204.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-129"/> If they are adorned with equanimity, then attachment and
            anger will be abandoned. If they are adorned with the means of attraction, then they will ripen all beings. If they
            are adorned with the applications of mindfulness, then one will become expert in the body, feelings, mind, and
            phenomena. If they are adorned with the correct relinquishments, then all nonvirtuous qualities will be abandoned and
            all virtuous qualities will be perfected. If they are adorned with the four bases of miraculous power, then body and
            mind will be light. If they are adorned with the five faculties, then one’s faith will be stable, diligence will
            blaze, there will be no delusion, one will be skilled at training the mind, and one will be skilled at eliminating all
            disturbing emotions. If they are endowed with the powers, then one will not be oppressed and will overcome all poverty and
            misfortune. If they are adorned with the limbs of awakening, then all phenomena will be comprehended exactly as they
            are. If they are adorned with the path, then true wisdom will be obtained. If they are adorned with tranquility, then
            all disturbing emotions will be vanquished. If they are adorned with insight, then there will be the insight and wisdom of
            comprehending all phenomena exactly as they are. If they are adorned with skillful means, then one will attain
            compounded and uncompounded happiness. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-64"/>
          <p tid="63">“Lord of nāgas, in short, by means of these paths of the ten virtues, the ten powers will be perfected.
            Everything from the attainment of the four types of fearlessness and the eighteen unique qualities of a buddha up to
            the attainment of all the qualities of a buddha will be perfected. Therefore, lord of nāgas, you must strive to adorn
            the paths of the ten virtues with these numerous distinctions.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-65"/>
          <p tid="64">“Lord of nāgas, comsider the following analogy: The earth is the foundation for all things established on the ground,
            such as all villages, towns, cities, districts, regions, and kingdoms. <ref cRef="F.205.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-130"/> It is the
            basis for all grass, shrubs, herbs, forests, and farmland, and all seeds, sprouts, and harvests. It is where all
            sowing, ploughing, and cultivation take place. In the same way, lord of nāgas, the paths of the ten virtues are the
            basis for taking birth in the realms of gods and humans. They are the basis for everything from the path of learning
            to achieving the fruition of no-more-learning, and the awakening of the hearers and the solitary buddhas. They are
            also the basis for everything from all buddha and bodhisattva deeds all the way up to all buddha qualities.”</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-66"/>
          <lb/>
          <p tid="65">When the Blessed One had spoken these words, the nāga king Sāgara, the monks, the bodhisattvas, the whole
            assembly, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s
            words.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-67"/>
          <trailer tid="66">This concludes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra “The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara.”</trailer>
        </div>
        <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-colophon">
          <head type="colophon" tid="67">Colophon</head>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-68"/>
          <p tid="68">Translated, edited, and finalized, having been revised according to the new terminological register,
            by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra, Dānaśīla, and Munivarman, and the chief editor-translator Bandé Yeshé Dé and
            others.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes">
        <head type="notes" tid="69">Notes</head>
        <list type="abbreviations">
          <head type="abbreviations" tid="70">Abbreviations</head>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-058-003-69">
            <abbr>D</abbr>
            <expan>Degé Kangyur</expan>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-058-003-79">
            <abbr>Z</abbr>
            <expan>Shey Palace Kangyur</expan>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-058-003-80">
            <abbr>C</abbr>
            <expan>Choné Kangyur</expan>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-058-003-81">
            <abbr>S</abbr>
            <expan>Stok Palace Kangyur</expan>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="listBibl">
        <head type="listBibl" tid="71">Bibliography</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-listBibl-1">
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-70">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg
              pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>).
            Toh. 154, Degé Kangyur, vol. 58 (mdo sde, pha), folios 198b–205a.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-71">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg
              pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>).
            bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
            bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
            Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 58, pp. 519–536. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-72">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg
              pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>).
            Stok no. 134, Stok Palace Kangyur, vol. 66 (mdo sde, ba), folios 282r–291v.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-73">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title>. Toh. 4347, Degé Tengyur,
            vol. 204 (sna tshogs, co), folios 131b–160a.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4347.html"/>
                    </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-74">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan [/ lhan] dkar gyi chos
            ’gyur ro cog gi dkar chag</title>). Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html"/>
                    </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-131">Dharmachakra Translation Committee, trans. <title xml:lang="en">
            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh153.html">The Questions of the Nāga King
              Sāgara (1)</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title>, Toh 153). 84000: Translating the Words of the
            Buddha, 2021.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-75">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog
              der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der
            Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-76">Rulu. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattva Precepts</title>. Bloomington: AuthorHouse,
            2012.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-77">Saddhaloka Bhikkhu, trans. <title xml:lang="en">The Discourse on the Ten Wholesome
              Ways of Action</title>. Hong Kong: Yan Boon Remembrance Committee, 1996.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-132">Sakya Pandita Translation Group (Tsechen Kunchab Ling Division), trans. <title xml:lang="en">
            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh155.html">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara (3)</ref>
          </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title>, Toh 155). 84000: Translating the Words of the
            Buddha, 2011.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-003-78">Wong, Mou-lam, trans. <title xml:lang="en">Shih shan yeh tao ching = The Buddhabhasita
              Dasabhadra Karmamarga Sutra</title>. Translated by Sikshananda-Nanjio. Singapore: n.d.</bibl>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="glossary">
        <list type="glossary">
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-82">
              <term>applications of mindfulness</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa nye bar gzhag pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛtyupasthāna</term>
              <term type="definition">The application of mindfulness with regard to body, feelings, mind, and phenomena.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-83">
              <term>asura</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
              <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">asuras</term>, sometimes called the demigods, are the enemies of
                the gods, fighting with them for supremacy. They are powerful beings who live around Mount Sumeru and are usually
                classified as belonging to the higher realms.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-84">
              <term>bases of miraculous power</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</term>
              <term type="definition">The four supports for supernatural abilities: determination, discernment, diligence, and
                meditative concentration.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-85">
              <term>belief in the transitory collection</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig tshogs la lta ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་ཚོགས་ལ་ལྟ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">satkāyadṛṣṭi</term>
              <term type="definition">This term refers to the mistaken view that identifies the self with the ultimately transient
                collection of mind and body.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-86">
              <term>correct relinquishments</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag par spong ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པར་སྤོང་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyakprahāṇa</term>
              <term type="definition">This term refers to a list of four: relinquishing negative acts that have been committed and
                will be committed in the future, and increasing current and future positive acts.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-87">
              <term>courtyard</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor gyi khyams </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་གྱི་ཁྱམས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maṇḍalamāḍa</term>
              <term type="definition">This term describes a circular open space or a space for assembly. </term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-88">
              <term>eighteen unique qualities of a buddha</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi chos ma ’dres pa bco brgyad </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་མ་འདྲེས་པ་བཅོ་བརྒྱད།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭādaśāveṇika­buddha­dharma</term>
              <term type="definition">Eighteen special features of a buddha’s physical state, realization, activity, and wisdom
                that are not shared by ordinary beings.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-89">
              <term>five faculties</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po lnga </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ་ལྔ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcendriya</term>
              <term type="definition">Faith, diligence, mindfulness, absorption, and knowledge.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-90">
              <term>four types of fearlessness</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’jigs pa bzhi </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཇིགས་པ་བཞི།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturabhaya</term>
              <term type="definition">Fearlessness in declaring that one has (1) awakened, (2) ceased all illusions, (3) taught
                the obstacles to awakening, and (4) shown the way to liberation.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-91">
              <term>gandharva</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
              <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Gandharvas</term>, literally “smell eaters,” are a class of spirits,
                sometimes described as celestial musicians.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-92">
              <term>garuḍa</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
              <term type="definition">A mythical creature which is half bird, half man, and is the enemy of serpents.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-93">
              <term>great brahmā gods</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa chen po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahābrahmā</term>
              <term type="definition">Gods from the higher subdivision of the world of Brahmā.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-058-003-94" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>Kinnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">mi’am ci</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kinnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A race of celestial musicians who are half human and half horse.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-95">
              <term>limbs of awakening</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyaṅga</term>
              <term type="definition">Recollection, analysis, diligence, joy, pliancy, absorption, and equanimity.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-96">
              <term>mahoraga</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
              <term type="definition">Literally “large serpent.” A subterranean semi-divine being that takes the form of a large
                serpent, sometimes with a human torso and head.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-97">
              <term>means of attraction</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsdu ba’i dngos po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བསྡུ་བའི་དངོས་པོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃgrahavastu</term>
              <term type="definition">This is generally given as a list of four qualities or methods for attracting students:
                generosity, kind talk, meaningful actions, and practicing what one preaches.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-98">
              <term>nāga</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
              <term type="definition">A semidivine class of beings who live in subterranean aquatic environments where they are
                known to guard wealth and esoteric teachings. <term type="ignore">Nāgas</term> are associated with serpents and
                often assume a snakelike appearance. In Buddhist art and in written accounts, <term type="ignore">nāgas</term> are
                regularly portrayed as being half human and half snake, and, as mentioned in this sūtra, said to have the ability
                to change into human form. Some <term type="ignore">nāgas</term> are Dharma protectors, but they can also bring
                retribution if they are disturbed. <term type="ignore">Nāgas</term> likewise fight one another, wage war, and
                destroy the lands of others by causing lightning, hail, and flooding.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-99">
              <term>opposing teacher</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phas kyi rgol ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཕས་ཀྱི་རྒོལ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parapravādī</term>
              <term type="definition">One who teaches a false doctrine.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-100">
              <term>retinue</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">g.yog </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">གཡོག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parivāra</term>
              <term type="definition">The Tibetan and Sanskrit terms both carry a dual sense of “servant” or “<term type="ignore">retinue</term>.”</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-101">
              <term>secondary disturbing emotions</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye ba’i nyon mongs </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བའི་ཉོན་མོངས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upakleśa</term>
              <term type="definition">These are “secondary” in the sense that they flow from the primary disturbing emotions of desire,
                aversion, and ignorance. There appears to be no set list.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-102">
              <term>ten powers</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bcu </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་བཅུ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśabala</term>
              <term type="definition">The classical list of the Buddha’s <term type="ignore">ten powers</term>, which appears
                frequently throughout both Pali and Sanskrit sources, refers to the following powers of knowing (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jñānabala</foreign>): (1) Knowing what is possible and what is impossible (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sthānāsthāna</foreign>), (2) Knowing the ripening of karma (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmavipāka</foreign>), (3) Knowing the various inclinations (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nānādhimukti</foreign>), (4) Knowing the various elements (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nānādhātu</foreign>), (5) Knowing the supreme and lesser faculties (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya­parāpara</foreign>), (6) Knowing the paths that lead to all destinations (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sarvatra­gāminī­pratipad</foreign>), (7) Knowing the concentrations, liberations,
                absorptions, and attainments (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna­vimokṣa­samādhi­samāpatti</foreign>), (8) Knowing the recollection of past existences (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūrva­nivāsānusmṛti</foreign>), (9) Knowing death and rebirth (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cyutyupapatti</foreign>), and (10) Knowing the exhaustion of the defilements (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsravakṣaya</foreign>).</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <!--<item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-104">
        <term>vast</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par ’phags pa </term><term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhyudgata</term>
        <term type="definition">This term refers generally to a large number, a great many. It can also mean “to rise above.”</term>
        
      </gloss>
    </item>-->
          <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-105">
              <term>yakṣa</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
              <term type="definition">A class of mostly malevolent spirits.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-106">
              <term>Brahmā</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
              <term type="definition">The creator god of the Hindu pantheon. </term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-107">
              <term>Dānaśīla</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dA na shI la </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དཱ་ན་ཤཱི་ལ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānaśīla</term>
              <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet during the late eighth and early ninth
                centuries.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-108">
              <term>Jinamitra </term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
              <term type="definition">An Indian Kashmiri paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet during the late eighth and early ninth
                centuries. He worked with several Tibetan translators on the translation of several sūtras. He is also the author
                of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nyāya­bindu­piṇḍārtha</title> (Toh 4233)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4233.html"/>, which is
                contained in the Tibetan Tengyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan ’gyur</foreign>) collection.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-109">
              <term>Lord of Death</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
              <term type="definition">The ruler of the lower realms.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-110">
              <term>Munivarman</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu ni bar ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་ནི་བར་མ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Munivarman</term>
              <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet during the late eighth and early ninth
                centuries.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-111">
              <term>Sāgara</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya mtsho </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱ་མཚོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara</term>
              <term type="definition">Literally meaning “ocean,” he is a king of the nāgas, a class of semidivine snake
                creatures.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-112">
              <term>Śakra</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
              <term type="definition">An epithet for Indra, the king of the gods in Hindu mythology.</term>
              
            </gloss>
          </item>
          <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-003-114">
              <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
              <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the late eighth and early ninth
                centuries.</term>
            </gloss>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>

    
    
    
    </TEI>