<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṅkara­vyākaraṇa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">མར་མེ་མཛད་ཀྱིས་ལུང་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad kyis lung bstan pa</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dīpaṅkara­vyākaraṇa­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་མར་མེ་མཛད་ཀྱིས་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa mar me mdzad kyis lung bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-1"><!--Sakya Pandita Translation Group--></author>
                <consultant role="dharmaMaster" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-2">Khenpo Kalsang Gyaltsen</consultant>
                <consultant role="projectManager" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-3">Chodrungma Kunga Chodron</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-4">Khenpo Kalsang Gyaltsen</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-5">Chodrungma Kunga Chodron</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-6">Laura Goetz</author>
                <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-21">George FitzHerbert</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-34">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-52">Martina Cotter</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.0 <date>2025</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s
                    words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability status="1.a">
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial -
                            No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for
                            commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-061-008"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard
                    logic.</note>
                <date>2025-01-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh188" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 188</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios 191.b–199.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-348">Gepal</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-349">Jñānagarbha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-350">Lui Gyaltsen</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="17">
                        <volume number="61" start-page="382" end-page="398"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11807" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#admin" when="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" type="text-version" status="v 0.0.1" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-7">
                    <desc>Automated version increment</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2020-10-28T19:21:21.935Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-8">
                    <desc>0.0.2</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-12-14T15:51:44.284Z" type="translation-status" status="2.h" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-9">
                    <desc>2.h</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-12-14T15:51:44.284Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-10">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-03-30T11:29:08.825Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-11">
                    <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.5" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-12">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-04-16T14:24:35.484Z" type="translation-status" status="2.g" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-13">
                    <desc>2.g</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-04-16T14:24:35.484Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.6" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-14">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-04-16T14:25:09.744Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.7" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-22">
                    <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-04-22T09:24:13.89Z" type="translation-status" status="2.f" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-23">
                    <desc>2.f</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-04-22T09:24:13.89Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.8" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-24">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-06-28T12:35:36.836Z" type="translation-status" status="2.e" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-25">
                    <desc>2.e</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-06-28T12:35:36.836Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.9" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-26">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-06-28T12:36:32.064Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.10" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-35">
                    <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-07-04T08:13:15.356Z" type="translation-status" status="2.d" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-36">
                    <desc>2.d</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-07-04T08:13:15.356Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.11" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-37">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-01T14:54:23.436Z" type="translation-status" status="2.c" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-38">
                    <desc>2.c</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-01T14:54:23.436Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.12" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-39">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-07T14:58:14.704Z" type="translation-status" status="2.b" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-40">
                    <desc>2.b</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-07T14:58:14.704Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.13" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-41">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-13T14:28:04.725Z" type="translation-status" status="2.a" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-42">
                    <desc>2.a</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-13T14:28:04.725Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.14" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-43">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-13T14:28:41.615Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.15" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-53">
                    <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-23T11:06:36.189Z" type="translation-status" status="2" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-353">
                    <desc>2</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-23T11:06:36.189Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-354">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-23T11:09:03.681Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-355">
                    <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#martina-cotter" when="2025-01-30T15:36:05.509Z" type="translation-status" status="1.a" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-358">
                    <desc>1.a</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#martina-cotter" when="2025-01-30T15:36:05.509Z" type="text-version" status="1.0.0" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-359">
                    <desc>First published version.</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <!--Note the "Contents" outline from the Word DOCX has not been included in the script. If the 
                    Outline to the text is quite complex, it is recommended that you paste the outlined contents from the DOCX here as a comment for
                    markup's reference. The actual table of contents will be generated in the Reading Room by the parser.-->
        <front>
            <div type="summary" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-54"/>
                <p tid="2">In<title xml:lang="en"> The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title>, the Buddha narrates the famous story of how, in a former life as
                    a brahmin ascetic many eons ago, he first received the prophecy of his future awakening. This story of the young brahmin ascetic
                    Megha’s encounter with the former Buddha Dīpaṅkara is here told to illustrate for Ānanda the importance of not being complacent
                    about one’s roots of virtue. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-55"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated, introduced, and annotated by Laura Goetz, in consultation with a draft translation by Khenpo Kalsang Gyaltsen
                    and Chodrungma Kunga Chodron of the Sakya Pandita Translation Group.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-56"/>
                <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha. George
                    FitzHerbert edited the translation and the introduction, and Ven. Konchog Norbu copyedited the text. Martina Cotter was in charge
                    of the digital publication process.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="8">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-introduction-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-59"/>
                    <p tid="10">In the context of teaching Ānanda the importance of not being complacent about one’s roots of virtue, the Buddha
                        explains that although he had venerated countless buddhas in the past, it was not until he encountered the Buddha Dīpaṅkara,
                        during a former life as a brahmin ascetic, that he first received a prophecy of his future awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-60"/>
                    <p tid="11">There follows the account of the former Buddha Dīpaṅkara. This begins with his birth, in a far distant past, as the
                        son of a king called Endowed with Islands. This king had himself formerly been the royal priest of a king named Ajātaśatru,
                        who held him in such high esteem that he gave him half his kingdom. The account of the young prince Dīpaṅkara’s early life
                        loosely parallels the biography of the Buddha Śākyamuni himself in the present eon as told in accounts such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara</title>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-61">
                            <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh95.html">The Play in Full</ref>
                            </title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya cher rol pa</title>, Toh 95).</note>—from his transmigration from Tuṣita Heaven into his
                        mother’s womb, to his first encounter with old age, sickness, and death and his decision to abandon his inheritance, to his
                        arrival at the seat of awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-62"/>
                    <p tid="12">In the case of Dīpaṅkara, however, according to the Tibetan version translated here, after his awakening to complete
                        buddhahood he remains at the seat of awakening for fifty years, during which time not a single being approaches him or pays
                        him homage. Dīpaṅkara, realizing that the people of the area are so happy that they have become careless, and wanting to rouse
                        them from their complacency, then magically emanates a city even more impressive than their own. When this does not disturb
                        them, he destroys it in a great blaze, leading the distressed population to finally consider their own impermanence. The
                        Buddha Dīpaṅkara then rises from the seat of awakening and gives his first Dharma teaching. Accepting an invitation from King
                        Ajātaśatru, he then travels to the palace Padmāvatī. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-63"/>
                    <p tid="13">Meanwhile, in the remote mountains, a young brahmin ascetic named Megha, who in a future life will be the Buddha
                        Śākyamuni, is completing his training with the brahmin Ratna, whom he must provide with a fee of a bolt of fabric, a staff, a
                        water flask, and five hundred coins. Lacking the five hundred coins, Megha descends from the mountain to seek the payment for
                        his teacher, and in the city Gone to Bliss he encounters a large offering being made to brahmins by the wealthy Suviśākha.
                        When Megha defeats the brahmin elder Giver of Pieces in a contest of knowledge of the Vedas, mantras, and treatises, Suviśākha
                        offers Megha lavish gifts that include five hundred coins and his daughter Receiver of Goodness. Repulsed by the thought of
                        marriage, Megha takes the gifts but refuses the girl, and he heads back toward the mountains while the girl, firmly
                        considering him to be her husband, follows a few hours behind him.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-64"/>
                    <p tid="14">On the way back, Megha’s course is diverted by one of the gods from the Śuddhāvāsa realm so that he arrives instead at
                        Ajātaśatru’s capital Padmāvatī, which has been cleaned and decorated in honor of Dīpaṅkara’s imminent arrival. As soon as
                        Megha hears of the newly awakened Dīpaṅkara, he looks for flowers with which to make an offering to the Buddha. However, since
                        King Ajātaśatru has decreed that all flowers are to be offered to the Buddha and that no one has permission to buy or sell
                        them, Megha fails to find a single flower anywhere. Meanwhile, the girl Receiver of Goodness has begged seven flowers from a
                        garland maker, and with them she approaches Megha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-65"/>
                    <p tid="15">In the conversation that follows in prose, the girl proposes that she will give her flowers to Megha in exchange for
                        his vow to always be her husband in lives to come, to which he eventually agrees. Here Megha reveals that the flowers are a
                        metaphor for roots of virtue, saying that he “will plant them in a field of merit in which they will grow as soon as they are
                        planted.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-66"/>
                    <p tid="16">The verses that follow, spoken by the Buddha Śākyamuni, retell previous events of the sūtra, giving a much more
                        elaborate account of the conversation between Megha and Receiver of Goodness and then continuing up to their approaching the
                        Buddha Dīpaṅkara and Megha’s intent to receive a prophecy. The prose then resumes with their agreement that they will both
                        offer the flowers and their departure to find the Buddha.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-67"/>
                    <p tid="17">Seeing Dīpaṅkara and, through a miraculous display, all his thirty-two marks of a great being, Megha is overjoyed.
                        While the other people in the gathering lay out costly garments for the Buddha to walk on, Megha lays out his humble, dirty
                        deer skin, which is angrily tossed away by the others. Megha retreats down a side path, away from the crowds, praying that the
                        Buddha will think of him and place his feet on his matted hair. The Buddha then does so, and Megha is able to scatter his
                        flowers over the head of the Buddha, who then prophesies that he will become the Buddha Śākyamuni in a future eon.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-68"/>
                    <p tid="18">The account of the Buddha Dīpaṅkara’s awakening and his prophecy to the young brahmin who would later become the
                        Buddha Śākyamuni has long been a popular tale in the Buddhist world, and accordingly we find a number of retellings, with
                        significant variation, in Tibetan, Sanskrit, Chinese, and Pali literature. Numerous depictions of the meeting between
                        Śākyamuni as a bodhisattva in a former life and the Buddha Dīpaṅkara are found in Gandhāran art from present-day Pakistan and
                        Afghanistan, the northwestern fringes of the Indian cultural sphere.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-69"> Nattier
                            2004, p. 72.</note> Junko Matsumura is perhaps not exaggerating when she writes, “The story is so popular and important in
                        both Northern and Southern Buddhism that there is a plethora of many different versions, so that, if we were to include short
                        references and mentions of the motif, the number of related texts would be almost uncountable.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-70"> Matsumura 2011b, p. 63. For a more extensive and more thoroughly researched overview of texts
                            that share major plot elements with <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title>, see Matsumura 2011a, 2011b,
                            and 2012.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-71"/>
                    <p tid="19">Corresponding narratives extant in Sanskrit are found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-72"> Translation in Rotman 2017, pp. 24ff.</note> and Kṣemendra’s (ca. 990–ca. 1070
                            <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>,<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh4155.html"/> where the young brahmin is called Sumati.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-73"> Matsumura 2011b, p. 65.</note> There are also lengthy accounts in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvastu</title>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-74"> See Jones 1949, pp. 188–203.</note> and
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Teachings on the Bodhisatva</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­piṭaka</title>),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-75">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh56.html">
                                <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Teachings on the
                                    Bodhisatva</title>
                            </ref> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’i sde snod</title>, Toh 56). For more
                            cases, see Anālayo 2010, p. 87, n. 95; and Matsumura 2011b, pp. 1138–39. A retelling of the story of the brahmin boy (not
                            extant in Sanskrit), in which he is called Sumati, can be found in <title xml:lang="en">The Hundred Deeds</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmaśataka</title>, Toh 340), <ref target="https://84000.co/translation/toh340#UT22084-073-001-997">2.288</ref>–<ref target="https://84000.co/translation/toh340#UT22084-073-001-1069">2.341</ref>. </note> where, as in
                        this text, he is called Megha. The story told in <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Teachings on the Bodhisatva</title> is
                        recounted by Butön Rinchen Drup (bu ston rin chen grub, 1290–1364) in his <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’byung</title> (<title xml:lang="en">History of Buddhism</title>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-76"> Butön, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’byung</title>, p. 75.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-77"/>
                    <p tid="20">The parallel Pali story, known as the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Sumedhakathā</title> (Sumedha being the name of the
                        young brahmin), is found in a number of sources.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-78"> See Matsumura 2010.</note>
                        Perhaps the earliest is the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Buddhavaṃsa</title>, but the best known are the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Nidānakathā</title>, an introduction to the Pali jātakas from approximately the fifth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce,</hi>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-79"> Nattier 2004, p. 72. Translation in Ānandajoti,
                            “Nidānakathā.”</note> and Buddhaghosa’s commentary on the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dhammapada</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-80"> Translation in Burlingame 1921, pp. 193–94. See also sources listed in Lamotte 1944, p. 248,
                            n. 2.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-81"/>
                    <p tid="21">There are also a considerable number of Chinese parallels that shed some light on the development of the narrative
                        throughout its history. While we have not given much consideration to these passages here, they are listed and compared in
                        detail in the works of Matsumura.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-82"> See Matsumura 2011b and 2012.</note> While
                        Matsumura notes that the Tibetan version translated here is “the only <emph>extant</emph> independent sūtra on the Dīpaṃkara
                        Prophecy,” she also cites evidence from Chinese sources indicating that several independent versions may have existed.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-83"> Matsumura 2011a, pp. 132–33.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-84"/>
                    <p tid="22">The Tibetan translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title> is listed in both the Denkarma and
                        Phangthangma catalogs (under sūtras consisting of 210 ślokas),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-85"> Denkarma, folio
                            299.a; Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, p. 98; Phangthangma 2003, p. 15.</note> which date to the ninth century. Given that the
                        colophon cites the initial translators as Viśuddhasiṃha and Gepal, who are thought to have lived in the late eighth to the
                        early ninth century, we can safely assume that this translation dates to the same time period. The translation was revised by
                        Jñānagarbha and Lui Gyaltsen.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-86"/>
                    <p tid="23">As the language in this Tibetan translation tends to be rather terse and elliptical, the narrative has been at times
                        clarified using other versions of the story, particularly those in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>, the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvastu</title>, and <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Teachings on the Bodhisatva</title>,
                        and we have noted these readings in the endnotes. We have also benefited from previous translations of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title> by Léon Feer (into French)<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-87"> Feer 1883, pp.
                            305–21.</note> and Matsumura (into English).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-88"> Matsumura 2011a, pp.
                            121–38.</note> While the translation is primarily based on the Degé Kangyur edition, we also consulted the Comparative
                        Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) of the Kangyur and the Stok Palace (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho
                            brang</title>) Kangyur.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-translation">
                <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="24">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="25">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-section-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-91"/>
                    <p tid="29">
                        <ref cRef="F.191.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-331"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="32">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Śrāvastī, in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park, together
                        with a great saṅgha of 1,250 monks. At that time, the Blessed One, surrounded and attended by a retinue of many hundreds of
                        thousands, was teaching the Dharma.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-95"/>
                    <p tid="33">The Blessed One said to the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, you must make your motivation very pure by examining each root
                        of virtue. If you ask why, Ānanda, though I respectfully venerated hundreds of thousands of buddhas, those blessed buddhas did
                        not prophesy that I would achieve unsurpassed complete and perfect awakening, but after I saw the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara and
                        offered him five utpala flowers, I developed confidence in the selflessness of phenomena and gained the acceptance that
                        phenomena are unarisen. That is why, Ānanda, you should not be content with your roots of virtue.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-96"/>
                    <p tid="34">“If you ask why, Ānanda, in the past, long ago—an uncountable, exceedingly uncountable, vast, immeasurable, and
                        inconceivable number of eons ago—at that time, on that occasion, here in Jambudvīpa, there was a king known as Ajātaśatru, who
                        was shapely, handsome, pleasant to behold, and provided with a supremely rich and fine complexion. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-97"/>
                    <p tid="35">“Ānanda, that king, Ajātaśatru, had eighty-four thousand cities, every one of them dazzling and pleasant to behold,
                        with magnificent gardens, magnificent ponds, magnificent flowers, magnificent fruits, delightful good harvests, and a joyful
                        atmosphere. <ref cRef="F.192.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-332"/> They were wealthy, prosperous, and filled with a
                        great multitude of people.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-98"/>
                    <p tid="36">“Ānanda, that king, Ajātaśatru, had a royal palace known as Padmāvatī, and there the king, Ajātaśatru, resided. Now,
                        there was a royal priest of King Ajātaśatru, the brahmin known as Endowed with Islands, who was dear to the king’s heart and
                        never a disagreeable sight. At that time, Ānanda, Ajātaśatru gathered all the people of the four castes and summoned the
                        brahmin Endowed with Islands. Having tied a crown upon his head, he then gave him half his kingdom and proclaimed, ‘Brahmin,
                        you must return to your country and build a royal palace, which you should also name Padmāvatī.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-99"/>
                    <p tid="37">“Then, Ānanda, King Endowed with Islands built a royal palace in his country, and he also named it Padmāvatī. Thus,
                        Ānanda, at that time, on that occasion, here in Jambudvīpa there ruled two kings. One was Ajātaśatru, and the other was
                        Endowed with Islands. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-100"/>
                    <p tid="38">“Then, Ānanda, when Endowed with Islands’ principal queen was sleeping blissfully at the top of the palace, the
                        bodhisattva Dīpaṅkara passed away and transmigrated from Tuṣita Heaven, transforming into a white elephant calf. He emanated
                        light rays and entered his mother’s right side. At that time, the principal queen related this event to King Endowed with
                        Islands. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-101"/>
                    <p tid="39">“Then, Ānanda, King Endowed with Islands gathered brahmins who were skilled in interpreting omens, those skilled in
                        divination, and those skilled in making offerings, and he related to them the events of this dream. A brahmin who was skilled
                        in interpreting omens said, ‘O great king, you have gained a great boon! A son of yours, a precious being, is to be born.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-102"/>
                    <p tid="40">“Then, Ānanda, when King Endowed with Islands heard this dream prophecy, he was transported with satisfaction and
                        delight, and in his great joy he was elated and cheered. King Endowed with Islands gave gifts to everyone within the bounds of
                        his kingdom: for those who desired food there was food, for those who desired drinks there were drinks, and for those who
                        desired a vehicle there was a vehicle. <ref cRef="F.192.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-333"/> He gave what was
                        suitable and not unwholesome—incense, garlands, ointments, and bedding—and he gave anything, whatever was desired. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-103"/>
                    <p tid="41">“Then, Ānanda, ten months passed and the son of King Endowed with Islands was born—shapely, handsome, pleasant to
                        behold, and provided with a supremely rich and fine complexion. As soon as he was born, there emerged from his body a light
                        such as this: by that light, the whole of the royal palace of King Endowed with Islands was illuminated. Then, at that time,
                        Śakra, the lord of the gods, vanished from his own abode and went to where the child was. There, he spoke benedictions to that
                        child, and he said, ‘As soon as he was born, there emerged from his body a light such as this: by that light, the whole of the
                        royal palace of King Endowed with Islands was illuminated. Because of that, the child should be named Dīpaṅkara.’ Then the
                        child was named Dīpaṅkara. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-104"/>
                    <p tid="42">“Then, Ānanda, King Endowed with Islands was transported with satisfaction and delight, and in his great joy he was
                        elated and cheered. Again, he gave gifts to everyone within the bounds of his kingdom: for those who desired food there was
                        food, for those who desired drinks there were drinks, and for those who desired a vehicle there was a vehicle. He gave what
                        was suitable and not unwholesome—incense, garlands, ointments, and bedding—and he gave anything, whatever was desired.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-105"/>
                    <p tid="43">“Later, Ānanda, King Endowed with Islands summoned Prince Dīpaṅkara. Having tied a crown upon his head, he gave him
                        half the kingdom and proclaimed, ‘Youth, you must go and stay among the queen’s retinue and play. Be happy and enjoy
                        yourself!’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-106"/>
                    <p tid="44">“Shortly thereafter, Ānanda, Prince Dīpaṅkara went among the queen’s retinue and mounted a great carriage. Surrounded
                        by a host of ladies, he went to the garden. One of the gods of the Śuddhāvāsa realm displayed people like us—one old and
                        feeble, one struck by illness, <ref cRef="F.193.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-334"/> and one who was dead—and he
                        also set a mendicant among them.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-107"> The translation of this sentence is tentative:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gnas gtsang ma’i ris kyi lha’i bu dag gcig gis bdag cag nyid rgas shing ’khogs
                                pa dang / nad kyis btab pa dang / shi ba yang bstan</foreign> [Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsten</foreign>]
                                <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">te dge sbyong zhig kyang der bzhag pa</foreign>. Possibly there are several
                            gods creating the display, as Feer (1883, p. 308) and Matsumura (2011a, p. 102) have translated the passage. The role of
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdag cag nyid</foreign> (“we ourselves,” or possibly “singly” if translating
                            the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyātma</foreign>) is unclear. It has been rendered here as “like
                            us.”</note> Prince Dīpaṅkara, having seen this, asked the charioteer, ‘Hey, charioteer, what are these various sights?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-108"/>
                    <p tid="45">“The charioteer replied, ‘Youth, these are so-called aging, illness, and death. Youth, as long as there are
                        imputations placed upon the true nature, there will be the phenomena of aging, illness, and death. Youth, it is the same for
                        you and the rest of us, for we are merely the residents of saṃsāra.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-109"/>
                    <p tid="46">“The youth asked, ‘Charioteer, who is this one whose head is shaven, who has donned maroon robes, and who is pacified
                        and gazes the mere length of a yoke?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-110"/>
                    <p tid="47">“ ‘Youth, this is a monk,’ said the charioteer. ‘Having relinquished all sin and developed the sense of delight in
                        regard to liberation, he went forth into homelessness.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-111"/>
                    <p tid="48">“The boy replied, ‘Very good, charioteer! The path of this monk is to be desired,’ and then he turned around and went
                        home.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-113"/>
                    <p tid="50">“Then, Ānanda, right away, Prince Dīpaṅkara went again to the garden. In the garden he saw the seat of awakening,
                        which had supported<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-114"> Reading Yongle, Lithang, Kangxi, Narthang, Choné, and Lhasa
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsten pa</foreign>. The Degé has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstan
                                pa</foreign> (“taught”).</note> many hundreds of thousands of buddhas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-115"/>
                    <p tid="51">“Then, Ānanda, the bodhisattva Dīpaṅkara, having seen that seat of awakening, left behind the entire assembly of men
                        and women a short distance and proceeded in the direction of the seat of awakening. He saw the seat of awakening and
                        circumambulated it three times, and then at the seat of awakening he sat down with his legs crossed. As soon as the
                        bodhisattva Dīpaṅkara took his seat, at that moment, at the first break of dawn, he reached unsurpassed complete and perfect
                        awakening, the highest perfect buddhahood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-116"/>
                    <p tid="52">“Ānanda, as soon as the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara reached unsurpassed complete and perfect awakening, the highest perfect
                        buddhahood, <ref cRef="F.193.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-335"/> there emerged from his body a light such as this:
                        by that light the entire trichiliocosm was illuminated. Then, at that time, Śakra, the lord of the gods, vanished from his own
                        abode and went to where the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara was. There he bowed his head at the feet
                        of the Blessed One and, having made offerings to the Blessed One, he proclaimed these words: ‘Ah! The Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara has
                        emerged in the world! Thus, by that light are all the world realms illuminated.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-117"/>
                    <p tid="53">“The Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara remained at the seat of awakening for fifty years, and not a single being approached to see
                        him, pay homage to him, or serve him. If you ask why, because the residents of the royal city of King Endowed with Islands
                        were happy, they did not approach to see him, pay homage to him, or serve him. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-118"/>
                    <p tid="54">“Then, Ānanda, the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara thought, ‘These residents of the royal city of King Endowed with Islands,
                        because they are happy, have become exceedingly careless. Surely I should cause them a little distress.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-119"/>
                    <p tid="55">“Then, at that time, the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara manifested a display of miraculous
                        power such that through the manifestation of the display of miraculous power, among the residents of the royal city of King
                        Endowed with Islands, he emanated a great city made of beryl that was pleasant to behold and filled with a great multitude of
                        people. Those people, moreover, were more beautiful, more pleasant to behold, and adorned with all types of ornaments.
                        However, the residents of the royal city of King Endowed with Islands, although they were troubled by the people dwelling in
                        the city made of beryl, <ref cRef="F.194.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-336"/> were not in the least bit
                        discouraged.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-120"/>
                    <p tid="56">“The blessed, thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara thought, ‘Since the residents of the royal city
                        of King Endowed with Islands have become exceedingly careless, surely I should also generate in them a little discouragement.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-121"/>
                    <p tid="57">“Then the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara again manifested a display of miraculous power such
                        that through the manifestation of the display of miraculous power he took control of that great city of beryl so that it would
                        blaze with a great fire. As soon as he took control of it, it caught fire. Then, at that time, those beings and that great
                        city were destroyed, came to an end, and disappeared. Having seen this unpleasant sight, those beings<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-122"> That is, the residents of the royal city of King Endowed with Islands.</note> were
                        distressed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-123"/>
                    <p tid="58">“Then, Ānanda, the residents of the royal city of King Endowed with Islands, having seen the fall of the beryl city,
                        were frightened and discouraged such that their hair stood on end. They thought, ‘If there is a reason that that city was
                        destroyed, came to an end, and disappeared, it will not be long before we, too, encounter the circumstances of impermanence in
                        this way. Who will protect us?’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-124"/>
                    <p tid="59">“The thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara then thought, ‘Since these residents of the royal city
                        of King Endowed with Islands have been matured, they are able to understand the Dharma taught by me, they have become worthy
                        of it, and they have developed the competence for it.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-125"/>
                    <p tid="60">“At that moment the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara, knowing the thoughts of those people, rose from the seat of awakening with
                        mindfulness and alertness. <ref cRef="F.194.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-337"/> He then set out for the palace of
                        King Endowed with Islands, together with Śakra, the lord of the gods, as his śramaṇa attendant.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-126"> Degé <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">phyi bzhin ’brang ba’i dge sbyong lha’i dbang
                                po brgya byin dang thabs cig tu</foreign>. Yongle and Kangxi add <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dang</foreign> here, such that there is a śramaṇa attendant in addition to Śakra. It is not clear where this
                            attendant would have come from, so we have read Degé as referring only to Śakra. Matsumura (2011a, p. 109) and Feer (1883,
                            p. 310) agree. Feer further assumed that Śakra appears in the <emph>form</emph> of a śramaṇa (“qui le suivait [sous la
                            forme d’]un ascète”).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-127"/>
                    <p tid="61">“Ānanda, as soon as the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara arrived, then, at that time, on the occasion of the first Dharma teaching
                        of the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara, twenty thousand beings went forth, and all their minds were liberated from defilements without
                        further appropriation. At the time of the second Dharma teaching, thirty thousand beings went forth, and all their minds were
                        liberated from defilements without further appropriation. At the time of the third Dharma teaching, forty thousand beings went
                        forth, and for all of them the eye of Dharma was purified so that it became stainless and free of blemishes with regard to
                        phenomena. At the time of the fourth Dharma teaching, fifty thousand beings went forth, and all their minds were liberated
                        from defilements without further appropriation. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-129"/>
                    <p tid="63">“Ānanda, the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara, surrounded and attended by a large saṅgha of
                        monks, taught the Dharma.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-130"/>
                    <p tid="64">“Then, Ānanda, when King Ajātaśatru heard that a son of King Endowed with Islands was born and had reached unsurpassed
                        complete and perfect awakening, the highest perfect buddhahood, he sent a messenger with the words ‘I request that he come
                        into my presence, for I wish to make an offering.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-131"/>
                    <p tid="65">“When that messenger heard from King Ajātaśatru, he traveled to the royal palace of King Endowed with Islands and then
                        to King Endowed with Islands himself, and there, he relayed the message. King Endowed with Islands then went to the thus-gone,
                        worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara, and having gone there he bowed his head at the Blessed One’s feet. Having sat
                        to one side, he informed him of the situation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-132"/>
                    <p tid="66">“The Blessed One replied, ‘Be at ease, great king, and return home. I will travel to the palace Padmāvatī.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-133"/>
                    <p tid="67">“Then the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara, <ref cRef="F.195.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-338"/> surrounded by the saṅgha of monks and an assembly of bodhisattvas and by gods, nāgas,
                        yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, humans, and nonhumans, set out together with King Endowed with
                        Islands, who was surrounded and attended by royal power, a large royal assembly, great royal displays, great royal
                        possessions, great royal wealth, and great royal pageantry.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-134"> This description of
                            the king’s procession is puzzling in the Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgyal po’i mthu chen po dang /
                                rgyal po’i tshogs mang po dang / rgyal po’i rnam par ’phrul pa chen po dang / rgyal po’i bdog pa chen po dang / rgyal
                                po’i ’byor pa chen po dang / rgyal po’i rnam par rtse ba chen po dang chas te yongs su bskor cing mdun gyis
                                bltas</foreign>. Here we have opted for a literal translation. Matsumura’s (2011a, p. 111 and n. 68) interpretation of
                            this passage, which is based on a set phrase appearing in Chinese translations, perhaps makes more sense: “together with
                            his great army (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mthu chen po</foreign>), his many ministers (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshogs mang po</foreign>), his great, high-ranking officials (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnam par ’phrul pa chen po</foreign>), his great merchants (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdog pa chen po</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śreṣṭin</foreign>?), his great
                            householders (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’byor pa chen po</foreign>), and his great, high-ranking Brahmans
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnam par rtse ba chen po</foreign>).” However, we have not yet confirmed the
                            concordance here.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-135"/>
                    <p tid="68">“Thus, Ānanda, the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara gradually made his way to the palace Padmāvatī. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-137"/>
                    <p tid="70">“At that time, at the king of mountains, Himālaya, there was a brahmin known as Ratna who was instructing some five
                        hundred young brahmin boys in the treatises, the Vedas, and all the secret mantras. Among those five hundred or so brahmin
                        boys, there was a brahmin boy known as Megha, who was in the prime of youth, shapely, handsome, pleasant to behold, provided
                        with a supremely rich and fine complexion, and skilled in all the varieties of secret mantras, treatises, and rituals.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-138"> Reading Stok <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">cho ga shes pa</foreign>.
                            The Degé and other editions consulted read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chog shes pa</foreign>,
                            “contentment.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-139"/>
                    <p tid="71">“At that time, Ānanda, the brahmin boy Megha bowed his head at the feet of the master and said, ‘O master, I will go
                        to the villages, cities, provinces, countries, and royal cities.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-140"> While here
                            Megha’s reason for wanting to leave is not immediately clear, in <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Teachings on the
                                Bodhisatva</title> (Toh 56, <ptr target="#UT22084-040-007-2206"/>) Megha states that he will return to his home
                            country because he has mastered the Vedas (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kye mkhan po bdag gis rig byed lobs te
                                bdag ni yul du mchi na bdag gis bgyi ba ci mchis</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-141"/>
                    <p tid="72">“The master replied, ‘O young brahmin, this is the law among us brahmins: anyone who has mastered all the treatises,
                        Vedas, and secret mantras must give the master five hundred coins,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-142"> Although the
                            Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zong</foreign> is often interpreted to mean articles of merchandise or
                            salable goods, as a translation of the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">paṇa</foreign> it can refer to a
                            type of coin. Sanskrit versions of the story have five hundred <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kārṣāpaṇas</foreign>
                            (e.g., the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>, Rotman 2017, p. 25; and <title xml:lang="en">The Collected
                                Teachings on the Bodhisatva</title>, <ptr target="#UT22084-040-007-2206"/>) or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">purāṇas</foreign> (e.g., the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvastu</title>, Jones 1949, p. 188, n. 9), both also coins
                            of varying values depending on what they were made of. We find this to be more plausible than Megha wandering around with
                            or being handed five hundred “articles of merchandise.”</note> one bolt of fabric, a staff, and a water flask.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-143"/>
                    <p tid="73">“The brahmin boy Megha said, ‘Master, since I have nothing at all except a skin, a staff, and a water flask, I will
                        go.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-144"/>
                    <p tid="74">“After he requested a third time, the master said, ‘So be it!’ ” <ref cRef="F.195.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-339"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-145"/>
                    <p tid="75">“The brahmin boy Megha gradually descended from the king of mountains, Himālaya, and entered the villages, cities,
                        provinces, countries, and royal cities. At that time, in the great city Gone to Bliss,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-146"> On the name of this city, see Matsumura (2011a, p. 113, n. 76), who notes correspondences
                            with Chinese translations. As the Tibetan lacks the usual <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhes bya ba</foreign>
                            (“so-called”) after the name, it would be easy to read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">grong khyer chen po bde bar
                                pha rol tu ’gro ba na</foreign> as “when (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">na</foreign>) he was going (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">pha rol tu ’gro ba</foreign>) to the great city Bliss (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">grong khyer chen po bde bar</foreign>).”</note> there dwelled a brahmin known as Suviśākha.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-147"> Although not attested as the name of this figure in Sanskrit sources, as Viśākha
                            (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sa ga</foreign>) is most likely a proper name referring to the constellation
                            of the same name, we have provided a tentative reconstruction. The name Suviśākha is fairly well attested in Indian
                            literature compared to other possible back-translations.</note> He had a daughter called Receiver of Goodness, who was
                        shapely, beautiful, pleasant to behold, and provided with a supremely rich and fine complexion. Every day, for her sake, he
                        had food given to forty thousand brahmins, thinking, ‘I will give my daughter to whomever is especially exalted among them.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-148"/>
                    <p tid="76">“One of the gods from the Śuddhāvāsa realm showed the brahmin boy Megha the path to the great city Gone to Bliss. The
                        brahmin boy Megha arrived at the site of the offering, and as soon as the brahmin boy Megha reached the site of the offering,
                        the girl said to her parents, ‘Father, if the qualities of this one are indeed as they seem, may he become my husband.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-149"/>
                    <p tid="77">“The brahmin boy Megha then engaged in conversation with all the other brahmins, and among them the brahmin Megha was
                        superior in the treatises and secret mantras. At that time, at the site of the offering, there was a brahmin known as Giver of
                        Pieces, who performed offerings sitting among the elders. The brahmin boy Megha went to where the brahmin Giver of Pieces was.
                        There he engaged in conversation about the Vedas and mantras with the brahmin Giver of Pieces, and it turned out that Megha
                        was superior in the Vedas, secret mantras, and treatises. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-150"/>
                    <p tid="78">“The brahmin boy Megha then said to the brahmin Giver of Pieces, ‘O brahmin, the law among us brahmins is that whoever
                        has understood and mastered the treatises should sit on the best seat.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-151"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Then the brahmin boy Megha again spoke to the brahmin Giver of Pieces: ‘Great brahmin, I will sit here, <ref cRef="F.196.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-340"/> so get up from this seat.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-152"/>
                    <p tid="80">“The brahmin Giver of Pieces replied, ‘Young brahmin, do not make me get up from this seat. I will give you five
                        hundred coins that I have obtained.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-153"/>
                    <p tid="81">“ ‘I do not need them.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-154"> As is often the case in this sūtra, where it is
                            not clear at which point or even <emph>if</emph> the speaker changes, here it is ambiguous which of the brahmins says “I
                            do not need them” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kho bo la mi dgos</foreign>). We follow both Feer and Matsumura
                            and interpret this last statement as being the words of Megha.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-155"/>
                    <p tid="82">“He did not stand, so Megha grabbed him by the neck and made him get up. The brahmin Giver of Pieces said to the
                        brahmin boy Megha, ‘Young brahmin, in making me get up from this seat, you have treated me with contempt and startled me, so I
                        swear that wherever you take birth, your giving will always be interrupted.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-156"/>
                    <p tid="83">“Then the brahmin boy Megha sat on the lion throne. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-157"/>
                    <p tid="84">“The brahmin Suviśākha, holding his daughter Receiver of Goodness with his right hand and carrying a golden staff, a
                        water flask, a bolt of fabric, and five hundred coins, went to where the brahmin boy Megha was. On arriving there, he said to
                        the brahmin boy Megha, ‘Noble son, take these.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-158"/>
                    <p tid="85">“The brahmin boy Megha took the five hundred coins, the bolt of fabric, the staff, and the water flask, but he did not
                        accept the girl. He said, ‘What is the use of this woman? Women are like monkeys—they give rise to agitation and create
                        obstacles to virtue. Since I dwell in hermitages and solitary places, I have no need for this.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-159"/>
                    <p tid="86">“ ‘Noble son, please accept out of compassion for me.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-160"> Again, the
                            speaker here is unclear. According to Matsumura (2011a, p. 118), the girl is speaking. We are inclined to think it is the
                            father, given the girl’s later reprimand of the boy for not remembering her father’s plea (<ptr target="#UT22084-061-008-206"/>). In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>, according to Rotman’s
                            translation (2017, p. 26), the girl speaks: “Accept me, brahman.” It is also said there that “since the king had
                            surrendered the girl with the intention of giving her away as a gift, he wouldn’t take her back again,” which could
                            explain why the girl has to leave in this version.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-161"/>
                    <p tid="87">“He did not accept. The brahmin boy Megha left the place of offering and set out for Himālaya, the king of mountains. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-162"/>
                    <p tid="88">“Then the brahmin Suviśākha said to the girl Receiver of Goodness, ‘Daughter, why do you not follow your husband?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-163"/>
                    <p tid="89">“Having heard his words, the girl set out in the direction of Himālaya, the king of mountains.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-165"/>
                    <p tid="91">“At that time, one of the gods from the Śuddhāvāsa realm had obscured the path to Himālaya, the king of mountains, and
                        made the path that led to the king’s palace, Padmāvatī, clear. Wherever the brahmin boy Megha stopped for a midday meal, the
                        daughter Receiver of Goodness stayed overnight. <ref cRef="F.196.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-341"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-166"/>
                    <p tid="92">“When the brahmin boy Megha spotted the king’s palace, Padmāvatī, which was adorned with silken tassels, scattered
                        with flowers, and set with an arrangement of containers of incense, he asked, ‘Why is this great city so finely
                        decorated?’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-167"/>
                    <p tid="93">“The residents of the royal city of the king’s palace, Padmāvatī, replied to the brahmin boy Megha, ‘Young brahmin,
                        have you not heard? A thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect buddha called Dīpaṅkara has emerged in the world. King
                        Ajātaśatru invited him, and because he has come here, the great city has been finely decorated.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-168"/>
                    <p tid="94">“The brahmin boy Megha thought, ‘If among us brahmins it is rare to find one who is clear in conduct and learned in
                        all the treatises, why mention having such a precious being emerge in the world? I should without a doubt spend these five
                        hundred coins on flowers and offer them to the Thus-Gone One.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-169"/>
                    <p tid="95">“He searched everywhere for flowers but was unable to find them anywhere. The residents of the royal city of the
                        king’s palace, Padmāvatī, said, ‘Young brahmin, have you not heard? King Ajātaśatru has declared, “All flowers must be offered
                        to the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara. Thus, no one has permission to purchase flowers, or to sell them. I will punish severely anyone
                        who buys or sells them.” ’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-170"/>
                    <p tid="96">“When he continued to search for flowers, the girl Receiver of Goodness sat before him and asked, ‘Young brahmin, what
                        are you looking for?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-171"/>
                    <p tid="97">“The brahmin boy Megha replied, ‘I am looking for flowers, girl.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-172"/>
                    <p tid="98">“The girl Receiver of Goodness then went to the house of a garland maker. When she arrived there, she requested the
                        garland maker, ‘Noble son, give me flowers. My husband needs them.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-173"/>
                    <p tid="99">“The garland maker said, ‘Girl, have you not heard? King Ajātaśatru declared thus: <ref cRef="F.197.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-342"/> “All flowers must be offered to the Thus-Gone Dīpaṅkara. Thus, no one has permission to
                        sell flowers, or to purchase them. I will punish severely anyone who buys or sells them.” ’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-174"/>
                    <p tid="100">“Three times the girl asked, until he said, ‘So be it!’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-175"> Here again the
                            change of speaker is assumed but not evident in the Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lan gsum gyi bar du
                                bslang ba dang de bzhin bya’o zer ro</foreign>. Matsumura (2011a, p. 121) agrees with the change of speaker, and Feer
                            (1883, p. 315) has it that the girl continues speaking—“Aprés la troisième demande, elle se leva en disant: il faut bien
                            agir ainsi”—although in note 1 he admits that something is missing, notably in this case that she is taking the flowers
                            without permission.</note> The girl Receiver of Goodness then took up a vase and placed in it seven utpala flowers. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-176"/>
                    <p tid="101">“Departing for the city, she saw the brahmin boy Megha. She sat before him and asked, ‘Young brahmin, what are you
                        looking for?’ </p>
                    <p tid="102">“He replied, ‘I am looking for flowers, girl.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-178"/>
                    <p tid="103">“ ‘Young brahmin, what for?’ she asked. </p>
                    <p tid="104">“He replied, ‘Girl, I will plant them.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-180"/>
                    <p tid="105">“The girl said, ‘I have never heard of or seen an utpala flower that, already plucked, will grow again.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-181"/>
                    <p tid="106">“ ‘Girl, I will plant them in a field of merit in which they will grow as soon as they are planted.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-182">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bu mo gang la bskyed pa tsam gyis skye ba’i bsod nams kyi zhing de lta bu
                                la</foreign> [Yongle, Lithang, Kangxi, Narthang, and Choné <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">las</foreign>]
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bskyed do</foreign>. See Matsumura 2011a, p. 122, n. 109, for a similar
                            passage in the Chinese translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ekottarikāgama</title>. On that basis she interprets
                            Megha’s statements as referring to the Buddha Dīpaṅkara as the field of merit.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-183"/>
                    <p tid="107">“She replied, ‘If you promise that in all lifetimes, wherever and whenever I take birth, you will always be my
                        husband, I will give you these utpala flowers.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-184"/>
                    <p tid="108">“The brahmin boy Megha thought, ‘I am someone who dwells in hermitages and solitary places. Since women create
                        agitation, excitement, and obstacles to roots of virtue, what use is this woman?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-185"/>
                    <p tid="109">“She repeated this seven times, until he said, ‘So be it!’ ”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-186"> Here
                            again the change of speaker is assumed but not evident in the Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lan bdun
                                gyi bar du smras pa dang / de bzhin du gyur cig ces smras so</foreign>. Matsumura (2011a, p. 122) again agrees with
                            the change of speaker, as does Feer (1883, p. 316): “Qu’ainsi soit!”</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-187"/>
                    <p tid="110">Then, at that time, the Blessed One spoke these verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-188"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>“Thus did I hear. In times past</l>
                        <l>The Buddha Dīpaṅkara emerged in the world</l>
                        <l>And traveled to Padmāvatī</l>
                        <l>With a large retinue of seven thousand.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-189"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>“For that reason victory banners were raised.</l>
                        <l>That is why drums, hundreds of them, were beaten.</l>
                        <l>For that purpose the whole city was cleaned,</l>
                        <l>And the four streets were decorated.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-190"/>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>“Seeing that city adorned, </l>
                        <l>The brahmin boy asked,</l>
                        <l>‘Why have victory banners been raised?</l>
                        <l>For what reason are hundreds of drums beaten?</l>
                        <l>Why was the city cleaned</l>
                        <l>And the four streets decorated?</l>
                        <l>Someone please explain this matter!’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-191"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“ ‘Knower of Vedas, have you not heard? <ref cRef="F.197.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-343"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Buddha Dīpaṅkara has emerged,</l>
                        <l>And he comes to Padmāvatī</l>
                        <l>With a large retinue of seven thousand.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-192"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>“ ‘For that reason were victory banners raised.</l>
                        <l>That is why hundreds of drums are beaten.</l>
                        <l>For that purpose the whole city was cleaned</l>
                        <l>And the four streets decorated.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-193"/>
                    <lg tid="116">
                        <l>“Hearing mention of the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>He was impressed by the Buddha’s qualities</l>
                        <l>And traveled there swiftly without hesitation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-194"/>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>“From afar he saw a brahmin girl</l>
                        <l>With darting eyes like utpala flowers.</l>
                        <l>Sitting at the door holding a lotus, </l>
                        <l>She spied the brahmin boy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-195"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>“To converse with pleasant words,</l>
                        <l>With the voice of the kalaviṅka and the peacock,</l>
                        <l>With the pleasing sounds of the goose and the cuckoo,</l>
                        <l>Abandoning cacophony and with the voice of Brahmā,</l>
                        <l>The girl spoke to the brahmin boy:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-196"/>
                    <lg tid="119">
                        <l>“ ‘What is it, boy? When you were in the forest</l>
                        <l>Making burnt offerings and reciting mantras,</l>
                        <l>Were you harassed by the king’s army?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-197"> Translation tentative: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khye’u ci nags kyi nang na de/ /sbyin sreg byed cing rig ’don la/ /rgyal po’i dmag
                                    gis ma gtses sam</foreign>. Here we follow Matsumura’s (2011a, p. 126) interpretation in which the girl is
                                essentially asking why he has come to the city.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>You are disturbed and wander the streets.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-198"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>“ ‘Girl, I have neither home nor family,</l>
                        <l>And I have no possessions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-199"> As a translation of the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">parigraha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yongs su gzung
                                    ba</foreign> (here translated as “possessions”) has a number of meanings relevant to the context, including
                                marriage, a wife, or something that binds or constrains.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>I do not desire the pleasures of the senses,</l>
                        <l>So, girl, the king’s army does not harm me.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-200"/>
                    <lg tid="121">
                        <l>“ ‘I do not eat food that comes from them—</l>
                        <l>Even though I wear robes I do not accept it.</l>
                        <l>I do not knowingly tell lies,</l>
                        <l>So, girl, the king’s army does not harm me.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-201"/>
                    <lg tid="122">
                        <l>“ ‘I live in the forest on fruits and roots,</l>
                        <l>So, girl, the king’s army does not harm me.’ </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-202"/>
                    <lg tid="123">
                        <l>“ ‘Were you attacked by lion cubs, </l>
                        <l>Or were there no fruits or roots in the forest?</l>
                        <l>Why did you come to this settled place?’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-203"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>“ ‘I was not harmed by lion cubs,</l>
                        <l>And in the forest there are fruits and roots.</l>
                        <l>Good lady, it is because I need utpala flowers</l>
                        <l>That I came here to the city.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-204"/>
                    <lg tid="125">
                        <l>“ ‘Perhaps, young brahmin, my utpala flowers</l>
                        <l>Would be suitable to adorn the proud body</l>
                        <l>Of some young man.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-205"/>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>“ ‘I do not buy them for my own garland.</l>
                        <l>I do not desire to carry around utpala flowers.</l>
                        <l>It is for the sake of the compassionate Dīpaṅkara,</l>
                        <l>Good lady, that I beg for these utpala flowers.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-206"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>“ ‘In Gone to Bliss, </l>
                        <l>When you ate my father’s food,</l>
                        <l>You disregarded his pleading words.</l>
                        <l>How can you shamelessly beg for flowers?’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-207"/>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“ ‘Good lady, as payment for your utpalas,</l>
                        <l>I will give these five hundred coins.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-208"> Here, rather than five hundred
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zong</foreign> (“coins”), the Tibetan has five hundred <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbyig</foreign>. According to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>
                                (no. 5959; 155/14), the latter corresponds to the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hiraṇya</foreign>.
                                This might suggest that the coins are made of gold, but it could also refer to any generic wealth or
                            riches.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>May the noble lady grant them to me</l>
                        <l>In my search for qualities of the Buddha. <ref cRef="F.198.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-344"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-209"/>
                    <lg tid="129">
                        <l>“ ‘Good lady, do not be a hindrance.</l>
                        <l>Good lady, being made to settle down</l>
                        <l>Is a hindrance for those who seek alms.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-210"/>
                    <lg tid="130">
                        <l>“ ‘Forget about others, young brahmin.</l>
                        <l>If I give to one who seeks alms,</l>
                        <l>I will not be a hindrance.</l>
                        <l>My aspiration is for this and nothing else.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-211"> It is unclear if the aspiration
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">smon</foreign>) referred to here is the aspiration later made before the
                                Buddha, or if it refers to the marriage vow.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-212"/>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l>“The two of them made the aspiration,</l>
                        <l>And the brahmin boy took the utpalas</l>
                        <l>And, holding the utpala flowers,</l>
                        <l>Bowed at the feet of the Victor:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-213"/>
                    <lg tid="132">
                        <l>“ ‘Even if my body dries up</l>
                        <l>And my bones turn white,</l>
                        <l>Until I receive a prophecy of awakening</l>
                        <l>I will not stand up today.</l>
                        <l>My aspiration is that and nothing else.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-214"/>
                    <p tid="133">“The girl Receiver of Goodness then held up five utpala flowers and gave them to the brahmin boy Megha. ‘Young
                        brahmin,’ she said, ‘take these utpalas and present them in your name. And, young brahmin, present these two utpala flowers in
                        my name.’</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-216"/>
                    <p tid="135">“The brahmin boy Megha, carrying those utpala flowers, went outside the city, where he saw the thus-gone, worthy,
                        complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara, who was handsome and bright, with his faculties tamed and his mind tamed, supremely
                        tamed, one who had attained the perfection of calm and peace, one who had attained the highest perfection of restraint and
                        peace, a great elephant who guarded and controlled his senses, and like a clear and tranquil lake in which emerges an
                        unsullied golden pillar, elevated, resplendent with glory, and blazing with splendor. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-217"/>
                    <p tid="136">“When he also saw the many trillions of beings, the many hundreds of boys and girls, the many gods, asuras, nāgas,
                        yakṣas, gandharvas, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas, and King Ajātaśatru with his retinue of queens, all arriving together
                        holding flowers, flower garlands, incense, and balms in order to make offerings to the Blessed One, he thought, ‘I have heard
                        that the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara <ref cRef="F.198.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-345"/> is a thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect buddha with the thirty-two marks of a great
                        being, yet only thirty marks appear on this thus-gone one. Since two marks do not appear, he is not endowed with the
                        thirty-two marks.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-218"/>
                    <p tid="137">“The thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara, understanding the thoughts of the brahmin boy Megha,
                        then manifested a display of miraculous power such that those thirty-two marks of a great being appeared—thus did he manifest
                        a display of miraculous power. On seeing this, the brahmin boy Megha was transported with satisfaction and delight. With the
                        rising of great joy and happiness, he spread out a skin, but the residents of the royal city Padmāvatī lifted up the skin, and
                        together they tossed it away. They said to the brahmin boy Megha, ‘Brahmin child, are you crazy? In the place where the king’s
                            robes<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-219"> In other versions of the story, the people are laying down costly
                            robes for the Buddha, hence their disgust when Megha throws down his deer skin. See Matsumura 2012, p. 85.</note> should
                        be placed, you lay out this dirty skin!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-220"/>
                    <p tid="138">“The brahmin boy Megha picked up the skin and stepped aside from the road. Sitting down on a side path, he spoke
                        these words of truth: ‘By the truth and these words of truth, if the Thus-Gone One, who is all-knowing and all-seeing, has
                        compassion for the world, may he redirect his path and place his feet upon my matted hair.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-221"/>
                    <p tid="139">“The thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara looked behind him and said to the monks, ‘Monks, where
                        I put my two feet, there you must not stand. If you ask why, it is because that is the matted hair of one who has honored many
                        hundreds of sextillions of buddhas.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-222"/>
                    <p tid="140">“The thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect <ref cRef="F.199.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-346"/> Buddha
                        Dīpaṅkara then stepped away from the road and went to where the brahmin boy Megha was. Arriving there, he placed his two feet
                        on the matted hair. Then the brahmin boy Megha stood up from the ground and scattered the utpala flowers upon the thus-gone,
                        worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara. The moment he scattered them, they came to rest directly above the crown of the
                        Thus-Gone One as a pinnacled temple of utpala flowers built with four corners and four columns, equally proportioned and
                        symmetrical, delightful and attractive. In that pinnacled temple, moreover, appeared the body of the Thus-Gone One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-223"/>
                    <p tid="141">“Then the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Dīpaṅkara said to the brahmin boy Megha, ‘Young brahmin, by
                        these roots of virtue, in future times, after countless eons, you will become the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect
                        buddha known as Śākyamuni, who will be endowed with knowledge and conduct, a well-gone one, a knower of the world, a
                        charioteer who guides beings, an unsurpassed one, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-224"/>
                    <p tid="142">“The brahmin boy Megha, having heard his own prophecy, was transported with satisfaction—with the rising of great joy
                        and happiness, at that moment, he attained the acceptance of phenomena as unarisen. Having attained that acceptance, he rose
                        in the space of the sky above to the height of seven tala trees and manifested six thousand samādhis, and there appeared as
                        many tathāgatas as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges. Then the brahmin boy Megha descended from the sky. Offering
                        prostrations at the feet of the Blessed One, he requested the Blessed One that he might go forth and become a monk. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-226"/>
                    <p tid="144">“Ānanda, if you are doubtful, uncertain, or suspicious, thinking that the one who was, at that time, on that
                        occasion, known as the brahmin boy Megha was someone else, Ānanda, you must not see it that way. <ref cRef="F.199.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-347"/> If you ask why, it was I myself who was, at that time, on that occasion, the
                        one known as the brahmin boy Megha.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-227"/>
                    <p tid="145">“Ānanda, if you are doubtful, uncertain, or suspicious, thinking that the one who was, at that time, on that
                        occasion, known as the brahmin girl Receiver of Goodness was someone else, Ānanda, you must not see it that way. If you ask
                        why, it was the Śākya girl Gopā who was, at that time, on that occasion, the one known as the girl Receiver of Goodness.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-228"/>
                    <p tid="146">“Ānanda, if you are doubtful, uncertain, or suspicious, thinking that the one who was, at that time, on that
                        occasion, known as the brahmin Giver of Pieces, who was sitting in the row of elders making burnt offerings, was someone else,
                        Ānanda, you must not see it that way. If you ask why, it was the ignorant person Devadatta who was, at that time, on that
                        occasion, the brahmin Giver of Pieces. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-229"/>
                    <p tid="147">“This, Ānanda, is why you must not be content with your roots of virtue.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-230"/>
                    <p tid="148">When the Blessed One had spoken those words, the venerable Ānanda and the assembly consisting of the entire world
                        with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-231"/>
                    <trailer tid="149">This completes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra “<title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title>.”</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="150">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-232"/>
                    <p tid="151">Translated by the Indian preceptor Viśuddhasiṃha and the translator Bandé Gepal. The Indian preceptor Jñānagarbha and
                        the great translator-editor Bandé Lui Gyaltsen edited and finalized it.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="152">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="154">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-233">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad kyis lung bstan pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṅkara­vyākaraṇa</title>). Toh 188, Degé Kangyur vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios 191.b–199.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-234">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad kyis lung bstan pa</title>.  bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
                        [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                        Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 61, pp. 510–34.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-235">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad kyis lung bstan pa</title>. Stok Palace Kangyur vol. 74
                        (mdo sde, ’a), folios 42.b–55.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-236">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya cher rol pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara</title>). Toh 95, Degé Kangyur vol. 46 (mdo sde, kha), folios 1.b–216.b. English translation <title xml:lang="en">The Play in Full</title> 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-237">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’i sde snod</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­piṭaka</title>). Toh 56, Degé Kangyur vols. 40–41 (kha–ga), folios 255.b (kha)–205.b (ga). English
                        translation <title xml:lang="en">The Collected Teachings on the Bodhisatva</title> 2023.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-356">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las brgya pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmaśataka</title>). Toh 340, Degé Kangyur vol. 73
                        (mdo sde, ha), folios 1.b–309.a; vol. 74 (mdo sde, a), folios 1.b–128.b. English translation <title xml:lang="en">The Hundred
                            Deeds</title> 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-238">Kṣemendra. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’i rtogs pa brjod pa dpag bsam gyi ’khri
                            shing</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>). Toh 4155, Degé Tengyur vols. 170–71 (skyes
                        rabs, ke–khe), folios 1.b (ke)–329.a (khe).<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh4155.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-239">Butön Rinchen Drup (bu ston rin chen grub). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde gshegs bstan pa’i gsal
                            byed chos kyi ’byung gnas</title> [<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’byung</title>]. Beijing: krung go bod kyi shes rig spe
                        skrun khang, 1988. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-240">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan dkar gyi chos kyi ’gyur ro cog gi
                            dkar chag</title>). Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-241">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye brag tu rtogs par
                            byed pa chen po</title>). Toh 4346, Degé Tengyur vol. 204 (sna tshogs, co), folios 1.b–131.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-242">Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>). Beijing: mi rigs dpe
                        skrun khang, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-243">84000. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh56.html">The
                                Collected Teachings on the Bodhisatva</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattva­piṭaka</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’i sde snod</title>, Toh 56). Translated by The Norwegian Institute of Palaeography
                        and Historical Philology. Online publication. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2023.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-357">84000. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh340.html">The
                                Hundred Deeds</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmaśataka</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las brgya
                            pa</title>, Toh 340). Translated by Dr. Lozang Jamspal (International Buddhist College, Thailand) and Kaia Tara Fischer.
                        Online publication. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-244">84000. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh95.html">The Play
                                in Full</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya cher rol
                            pa</title>, Toh 95). Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee. Online publication. 84000: Translating the
                        Words of the Buddha, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-245">Ānandajoti Bhikkhu, ed. “<ref target="https://www.ancient-buddhist-texts.net/English-Texts/Jataka/000a.htm">The Nidānakathā, or Introduction to the
                            Jātaka Stories</ref>.” Translated by T.W. Rhys Davids. <title xml:lang="en">Ancient Buddhist Texts</title>. Last updated
                        November 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-246">Anālayo. <ref target="https://www.buddhismuskunde.uni-hamburg.de/pdf/5-personen/analayo/genesis-bodhisattva.pdf">The Genesis of the
                            Bodhisattva Ideal</ref>. Hamburg Buddhist Studies 1. Hamburg: Hamburg University Press, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-247">Burlingame, Eugene Watson. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Legends Part I</title>. Harvard
                        Oriental Series 28. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1921.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-248">Eckel, Malcolm David. “Jñānagarbha.” In <title xml:lang="en">Brill’s Encyclopedia of
                            Buddhism</title>, edited by Jonathan Silk et al., vol. 2, <title xml:lang="en">Lives</title>, 261–63. Leiden: Brill,
                        2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-249">Feer, Léon. “Dipankara-vyakarana.” In <title xml:lang="fr">Fragments extrais du
                            Kandjour</title>, 302–21. Annales du Musée Guimet 5. Paris: Ernest Leroux, 1883.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-250">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins
                            Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften,
                        2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-251">Jones, J. J., trans. <title xml:lang="en">The Mahāvastu, Vol. 1</title>. Sacred Books of the
                        Buddhists. London: Luzac, 1949.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-252">Lamotte, Étienne. <title xml:lang="fr">Le traité de la grande vertu de sagesse de Nāgārjuna
                            (Mahāprajñāpāramitāśāstra)</title>. Vol. 1. Bibliothèque du <title xml:lang="fr">Muséon</title> 18. Louvain-la-Neuve:
                        Université de Louvain, 1944.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-253">Matsumura Junko (2010). “The <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Sumedhakathā</foreign> in Pāli
                        Literature and Its Relation to the Northern Buddhist Textual Tradition.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International
                            College for Postgraduate Buddhist Studies <foreign xml:lang="zh">国際仏教学大学院大学研究紀要</foreign>
                        </title> 14 (2010): 101–133.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-254">Matsumura Junko (2011a). “An Independent Sūtra on the Dīpaṃkara Prophecy: Tibetan Text and English
                        Translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-Dīpaṃkara-vyākaraṇa nāma Mahāyānasūtra</title>.”<title xml:lang="en"> Journal
                            of the International College for Postgraduate Buddhist Studies</title>
                        <title xml:lang="zh">国際仏教学大学院大学研究紀要</title> 15 (2011): 81–74.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-255">Matsumura Junko (2011b). “The Story of the Dīpaṃkara Buddha Prophecy in Northern Buddhist Texts: An Attempt
                        at Classification.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Indian and Buddhist Studies</title> 59, no. 3 (March 2011): 63–72.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-256">Matsumura Junko (2012). “The Formation and Development of the Dīpaṃkara Prophecy Story: The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-Dīpaṃkaravyākaraṇa-nāma-mahāyānasūtra</title> and Its Relation to Other Versions.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Indian and Buddhist Studies</title> 60, no. 3 (March 2012): 80–89 (1204–13). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-257">Nattier, Jan. “Buddha(s).” In <title xml:lang="en">Encyclopedia of Buddhism</title>, edited by
                        Robert E. Buswell, Jr., 1:71–74. New York: Macmillan Reference, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-008-258">Rotman, Andy. <title xml:lang="en">Divine Stories: Divyāvadāna Part 2</title>. Classics of
                        Indian Buddhism. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2017.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary" status="excluded" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-260">
                            <term type="translationMain">blessed one</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="translationAlternative">blessed</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-261">
                            <term type="translationMain">saṅgha</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge ’dun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་འདུན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṅgha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-262">
                            <term type="translationMain">mendicant</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śramaṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-352">
                            <term type="translationMain">śramaṇa</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śramaṇa</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>See “mendicant.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-263">
                            <term type="translationMain">god</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">lha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལྷ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">lha’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">ལྷའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">devaputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-264">
                            <term type="translationMain">seat of awakening</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">byang chub kyi snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhimaṇḍa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-265">
                            <term type="translationMain">trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">stong gsum gyi stong chen po’i ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāha­sramahāsāhasra­lokadhātu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-266">
                            <term type="translationMain">miraculous power</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rdzu ’phrul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-267">
                            <term type="translationMain">beryl</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bai dUr+ya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བཻ་དཱུརྱ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiḍūrya</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Although it has often been translated as “lapis lazuli,” the descriptions and references in the
                                    literature, both Sanskrit and Tibetan, match the characteristics of beryl. The Pali form is <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">veḷuriya</foreign>. The Prākrit form <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">verulia</foreign> is the source for the English “beryl.” This normally refers to the blue or aquamarine
                                    beryl, but there are also white, yellow, and green beryls, though green beryl is called emerald.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-268">
                            <term type="translationMain">residents of the royal city</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rgyal po’i pho brang ’khor ba’i mi rnams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་འཁོར་བའི་མི་རྣམས།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Literally “those in the vicinity of the king’s palace.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-269">
                            <term type="translationMain">śramaṇa attendant</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">phyi bzhin ’brang ba’i dge sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཕྱི་བཞིན་འབྲང་བའི་དགེ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paścācchramaṇa</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A junior monk who is an attendant or disciple of an elder monk, literally one who follows behind.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-270">
                            <term type="translationMain">went forth</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rab tu phyung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རབ་ཏུ་ཕྱུང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pra √vraj</term>
                            <term type="translationAlternative">go forth</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>To renounce settled, household life (“going forth from home to homelessness”) to become a monk or wandering
                                    spiritual practitioner.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-271">
                            <term type="translationMain">defilement</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">zag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཟག་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āśrava</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsrava</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-272">
                            <term type="translationMain">without further appropriation</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">len pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལེན་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupādana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-273">
                            <term type="translationMain">nāga</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-274">
                            <term type="translationMain">yakṣa</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-275">
                            <term type="translationMain">gandharva</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-276">
                            <term type="translationMain">asura</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-277">
                            <term type="translationMain">garuḍa</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-278">
                            <term type="translationMain">kinnara</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kinnara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-279">
                            <term type="translationMain">mahoraga</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-280">
                            <term type="translationMain">preceptor</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mkhan po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མཁན་པོ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādhyāya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-281">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vedas</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rig byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རིག་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">veda</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The ancient sacred scriptures of Hinduism.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-282">
                            <term type="translationMain">thirty-two marks of a great being</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">skyes bu chen po’i mtshan sum cu rtsa gnyis po</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་པོ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvātriṃśan­mahāpuruṣa­lakṣaṇa</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The main identifying physical characteristics of both buddhas and universal monarchs, to which
                                    are added the so-called “eighty minor marks.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-283">
                            <term type="translationMain">one hundred sextillion</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bye ba khrag khrig brgya stong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">koṭiniyutaśata­sahasra</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>If the Abhidharma system is followed, this is a number calculated by multiplying a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">koṭi</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bye ba</foreign>), or ten
                                    million, by a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niyuta</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khrag khrig</foreign>), or a hundred billion, and by a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śatasahasra</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brgya stong</foreign>), or one hundred
                                    thousand, which all together equals ten to the 23rd power or a hundred sextillion. This term is often used to
                                    express a number so large as to be inconceivable.</p>
                            </note>
                            <term type="translationAlternative">hundreds of sextillions</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-284">
                            <term type="translationMain">pinnacled temple</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">khang pa brtsegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kūṭāgāra</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A distinctive Indian assembly hall or temple with one ground-floor room and a high ornamental
                                    roof, sometimes a barrel shape with apses but more usually a tapering roof, tower, or spire; it contains at least
                                    one additional upper room within the structure. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Kūṭāgāra</foreign>
                                    literally means “upper chamber” and is short for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kūṭāgāraśālā</foreign>,
                                    “hall with an upper chamber or chambers.” The Mahābodhi temple in Bodhgaya is an example of a kūṭāgāra.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-285">
                            <term type="translationMain">eon</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bskal pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བསྐལ་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-286">
                            <term type="translationMain">endowed with knowledge and conduct</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rig pa dang zhabs su ldan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རིག་པ་དང་ཞབས་སུ་ལྡན་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyācaraṇa­sampanna</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nibandhana</title> explains this as a metaphor of the eye and the
                                    feet, which, operating together, allow one to move. Knowledge, interpreted as either “right view” or as “the
                                    training in wisdom,” is like the eye, while the other seven parts of the noble eightfold path, or the two other
                                    trainings in discipline and samādhi, function as the “feet.” This explanation is also found in the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title> commentary on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>, which further clarifies that <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhabs</foreign> is
                                    here simply the honorific term for “foot” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">caraṇa ni rkang
                                    pa</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-287">
                            <term type="translationMain">samādhi</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-288">
                            <term type="translationMain">royal priest</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mdun na ’don </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མདུན་ན་འདོན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">purohita</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A brahmin who serves as the king’s chaplain and chief ritual officiant for Vedic
                                    sacrifices.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-289">
                            <term type="translationMain">well-gone one</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bde bar gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sugata</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-290">
                            <term type="translationMain">acceptance that phenomena are unarisen</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpatti­kadharmakṣānti</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-291">
                            <term type="translationMain">provided with a supremely rich and fine complexion</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">kha dog bzang po rgyas pa mchog dang ldan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཁ་དོག་བཟང་པོ་རྒྱས་པ་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedDictionary" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paramayā śubhavarṇapuṣkalatayā samanvāgataḥ
                                (Mvy)</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Part of a repeat phrase found in this and other sūtras (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gzugs bzang ba/ mdzes pa/ blta na sdug pa/ kha dog bzang po rgyas pa mchog dang ldan pa</foreign>), probably
                                    more literally meaning having a fullness of excellent color over the entire body. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> suggests this is to be read as a single feature.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-292">
                            <term type="translationMain">true nature</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">chos nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཆོས་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmatā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-293">
                            <term type="translationMain">control</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">byin gyis brlabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhiṣṭhā</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>This term is usually translated into English with “to bless.” However, the verb <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhā</foreign> conveys the notions of control (of one’s environment as a
                                    result of meditative absorption), authority, or protection.</p>
                            </note>
                            <term type="translationAlternative">took control of</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-294">
                            <term type="translationMain">law</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">chos nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཆོས་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmatā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-295">
                            <term type="translationMain">treatise</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bstan bcos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བསྟན་བཅོས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāstra</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>May refer to a specific genre or style of scholastic Sanskritic literature, or simply to scholastic literature in
                                    general; in Buddhist traditions the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāstra</foreign> usually signifies a text that
                                    was composed by a human author, as opposed to texts first spoken, composed, or revealed by an enlightened
                                    being.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-296">
                            <term type="translationMain">utpala flower</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ud pa la</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཨུད་པ་ལ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">ud pal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">ཨུད་པལ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">utpala</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="la">Nymphaea caerulea</foreign>. The “blue lotus” is actually a lily, so it is also known as the
                                    blue water lily.</p>
                            </note>
                            <term type="translationAlternative">utpala</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-297">
                            <term type="translationMain">voice of Brahmā</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">tshangs pa’i sgra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཚངས་པའི་སྒྲ།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A voice that has the qualities of the voice of the god Brahmā. This is one of the thirty-two
                                    marks of a great being.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-298">
                            <term type="translationMain">jātaka</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">skyes rabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྐྱེས་རབས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jātaka</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of the twelve sections of Buddhist scripture; it contains the accounts of the Buddha’s
                                    previous lifetimes.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-299">
                            <term type="translationMain">pillar</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mchod sdong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མཆོད་སྡོང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yaṣṭi</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yūpa</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>“Pillar” is a rather loose rendering for this term, which refers more specifically to
                                    ceremonial or memorial columns, or to the sacrificial posts used in Vedic rituals.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-300">
                            <term type="translationMain">eye of Dharma</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">chos kyi mig </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཆོས་ཀྱི་མིག</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmacakṣus</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of the “five eyes,” representing superior insights of the buddhas and bodhisattvas. The
                                    five eyes consist of five different faculties of vision: the physical eye (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">māṃsacakṣus</foreign>), the divine eye (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">divyacakṣus</foreign>), the wisdom eye (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñācakṣus</foreign>),
                                    the eye of Dharma (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmacakṣus</foreign>), and the Buddha eye (Skt.
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">buddhacakṣus</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-301">
                            <term type="translationMain">kalaviṅka</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ka la ping ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀ་ལ་པིང་ཀ</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">kalaviṅka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-303">
                            <term type="translationMain">Ānanda</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ānanda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-304">
                            <term type="translationMain">Ajātaśatru</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ma skyes dgra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མ་སྐྱེས་དགྲ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedApproximate" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ajātaśatru</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A king in the distant past, at the time of the Buddha Dīpaṅkara. Not to be confused with the
                                    king of the same name during the time of the Buddha Śākyamuni, although it has been suggested that in earlier
                                    versions of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title> this king had a different name and was said to
                                    be a past life of the later Ajātaśatru (Matsumura 2011a, pp. 84–85). In <title xml:lang="en">The Collected
                                        Teachings on the Bodhisatva</title> (<ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh56.html">Toh 56</ref>),
                                    he is known as Jitaśatru.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-305">
                            <term type="translationMain">Endowed with Islands</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gling ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གླིང་ལྡན།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The royal priest of King Ajātaśatru, a king at the time of the Buddha Dīpaṅkara. The name in
                                    the Tibetan, meaning Endowed with Islands, may be a conflation with the name of the city of Dīpaṅkara’s birth in
                                    earlier sources for the narrative related in <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title> (see <ptr target="#UT22084-061-008-71"/>–<ptr target="#UT22084-061-008-81"/>), for example, the city of Dvīpavatī in the
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvāvadānakalpalatā</foreign>. In other sources the father’s (or the priest’s or king’s) name is the
                                    graphically similar Dīpa (Lamp), Dīpavat (Endowed with Lamps), and so forth, which is reflected also in the name
                                    Arcimat (Shining). See, for example, Matsumura 2011b: 1140–43.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-061-008-306" type="person" mode="match">
                            <term type="translationMain">Dīpaṅkara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther" status="verified">dīpaṅkara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">mar me mdzad</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">མར་མེ་མཛད།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A buddha who lived incalculable eons ago, he was the first to prophesy the bodhisattva Megha (also known as Sumati
                                    or by the Pali Sumedha) as the future Buddha Śākyamuni. The Sanskrit name literally means “Light Maker.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-307">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śakra</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śakra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-308">
                            <term type="translationMain">Ratna</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rin po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རིན་པོ་ཆེ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ratna</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The brahmin master of Megha, the future Buddha Śākyamuni, who resides in the
                                Himālayas.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-309">
                            <term type="translationMain">Megha</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sprin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྤྲིན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">megha</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Lit. “Cloud.” A brahmin boy, a past life of the Buddha Śākyamuni during the time of the Buddha
                                    Dīpaṅkara, from whom he received a prophecy of his future awakening. In other iterations of the story he is known
                                    in Sanskrit as Sumati, and in Pali as Sumedha.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-310">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śākyamuni</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">shAkya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śākyamuni</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-311">
                            <term type="translationMain">Gopā</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sa ’tsho ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ས་འཚོ་མ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gopā</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of the wives of Prince Siddhārtha prior to his leaving his kingdom and attaining awakening
                                    as the Buddha.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-312">
                            <term type="translationMain">Receiver of Goodness</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bzang len ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བཟང་ལེན་ལྡན།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The daughter of a wealthy brahmin in the city Gone to Bliss during the time of the Buddha
                                    Dīpaṅkara. She aids the bodhisattva Megha, the future Buddha Śākyamuni, in offering flowers to the newly awakened
                                    Dīpaṅkara. A past life of Śākyamuni’s wife Gopā, when he was still Prince Siddhārtha, although in some accounts
                                    said to become his wife Yaśodharā.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-313">
                            <term type="translationMain">Giver of Pieces</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dum bu byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དུམ་བུ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A brahmin elder in the city Gone to Bliss during the time of the Buddha Dīpaṅkara.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-314">
                            <term type="translationMain">Suviśākha</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sa ga bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ས་ག་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="reconstructedSemantic" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">suviśākha</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A wealthy brahmin in the city Gone to Bliss during the time of the Buddha Dīpaṅkara, father of
                                    the girl Receiver of Goodness. See note 25.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-315">
                            <term type="translationMain">Viśuddhasiṃha</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bi shud+dha sing ha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བི་ཤུདྡྷ་སིང་ཧ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="reconstructedPhonetic" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viśuddhasiṃha</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>An Indian paṇḍita active in Tibet in the late eighth to early ninth century.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-316">
                            <term type="translationMain">Gepal</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A Tibetan translator active in Tibet in the late eighth to early ninth century, also known as
                                    Gewa Pal (dge ba dpal).</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-317">
                            <term type="translationMain">Jñānagarbha</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dz+nyA na gar+bha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཛྙཱ་ན་གརྦྷ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="reconstructedPhonetic" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñānagarbha</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Indian preceptor who, along with Lui Gyaltsen, revised the translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title>. It is unlikely, but not impossible, that this is the famous
                                    eighth-century scholar. (See Eckel 2019, pp. 261–62.)</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-318">
                            <term type="translationMain">Lui Gyaltsen</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">klu’i rgyal mtshan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Tibetan translator who, along with Jñānagarbha, revised the translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy of Dīpaṅkara</title>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-319">
                            <term type="translationMain">Devadatta</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">lhas byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལྷས་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedOther">devadatta</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A cousin of the Buddha Śākyamuni who broke with him and established his own community. His
                                    tradition was still continuing during the first millennium ᴄᴇ. He is portrayed as engendering evil schemes against
                                    the Buddha and even succeeding in wounding him. He is usually identified with wicked beings in accounts of
                                    previous lifetimes.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-321">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvastī</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The capital of the ancient Indian kingdom of Kośala and the setting for many sūtras, as the
                                    Buddha spent most rainy seasons in a park outside the city called Jeta’s Grove. The city has been identified with
                                    the present-day Sāhet Māhet in Uttar Pradesh on the banks of the river Rapti.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-322">
                        <term type="translationMain"> Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park</term>
                        <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga’ ra ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ།</term>
                        <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jetavanam anāthapiṇḍadasyārāmaḥ</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-323">
                            <term type="translationMain">Tuṣita Heaven</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dga’ ldan gyi gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགའ་ལྡན་གྱི་གནས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tuṣita</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-325">
                            <term type="translationMain">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’dzam bu’i gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jambudvīpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-326">
                            <term type="translationMain">Padmāvatī</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">pad ma can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">པད་མ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">padmāvatī</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of the palace of King Ajātaśatru, a king in the distant past during the time of the
                                    Buddha Dīpaṅkara, and also the name of the palace of his royal priest Endowed with Islands, to whom he gave half
                                    his kingdom.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-327">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śuddhāvāsa</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gnas gtsang ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གནས་གཙང་མ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śuddhāvāsa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-328">
                            <term type="translationMain">Himālaya</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gangs ri</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གངས་རི།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">gangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">གངས།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">himālaya</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">himavat</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The mountain or mountain range where Megha resides with his teacher Ratna.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-329">
                            <term type="translationMain">Ganges</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gang gA </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གང་གཱ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" type="attestedOther" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṅgā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-008-330">
                            <term type="translationMain">Gone to Bliss</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bde bar pha rol ’gro ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བདེ་བར་ཕ་རོལ་འགྲོ་བ།</term>
                            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">bde bar pha rol ’gro ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">བདེ་བར་ཕ་རོལ་འགྲོ་བ།</term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A city during the time of the Buddha Dīpaṅkara.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>