<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Prophecy Concerning Strīvivarta</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Strī­vivarta­vyākaraṇa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bud med ’gyur ba lung bstan pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བུད་མེད་འགྱུར་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “The Prophecy Concerning Strīvivarta”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­strī­vivarta­vyākaraṇa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་བུད་མེད་འགྱུར་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bud med ’gyur ba lung bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">《轉女身受記經》（大正藏：《樂瓔珞莊嚴方便品經》）</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-262">David Higgins</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-270">Jonas Doctor</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</consultant>
                <consultant role="dharmaMaster" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-70">Miguel Sawaya</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-61">Catherine Dalton</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-252">Dion Blundell</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-289">Nathaniel Rich</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.4 <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-061-010"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2021-09-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh190" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 190</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios 201.a–224.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bandé Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śīlendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Prajñāvarman</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="48">
                        <volume number="61" start-page="401" end-page="448"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11811" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2022-07-26T06:29:27.435Z" user="admin">26/07/2022 06:29:27</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-01-28T06:16:29.427Z" user="mike">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2021-02-17T07:48:06.953Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2021-02-17T07:48:23.153Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2021-03-08T12:59:11.257Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2021-06-29T08:24:04.465Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.5" date-time="2021-06-29T08:24:04.465Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.6" date-time="2021-07-06T09:20:50.485Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2021-08-06T09:43:51.759Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.7" date-time="2021-08-06T09:43:51.759Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.8" date-time="2021-08-06T11:58:37.168Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2021-08-06T11:59:51.105Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.9" date-time="2021-08-06T11:59:51.105Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2021-08-19T23:26:05.595Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2021-08-19T23:26:05.595Z" user="mike">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2021-08-27T07:40:25.623Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1.a" date-time="2021-09-02T18:32:14.613Z" user="celso">1.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2021-09-02T18:32:14.613Z" user="celso">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2021-09-02T18:34:39.903Z" user="celso">1</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2021-09-02T18:34:39.903Z" user="celso">First published version</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.1" date-time="2022-02-01T07:33:32.39Z" user="andre">definition of Śakra: critical remark removed</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.2" date-time="2022-06-27T10:06:48.1Z" user="admin">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.3" date-time="2022-07-25T15:38:49.551Z" user="martina-cotter">Added pending links.</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.4" date-time="2022-07-26T06:29:19.64Z" user="cabie-sim">Auto (update-titles)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-1"/>
                <p tid="2">In this sūtra, Subhūti, one of the Buddha’s close disciples, enters into a
                    discussion with several individuals in the course of his alms rounds. His
                    primary interlocutor is a laywoman who reveals herself to be a bodhisattva great
                    being named Strīvivarta; her teachings are profound and challenging,
                    consistently pointing in the direction of ultimate truth. The sūtra culminates
                    in the Buddha prophesying Strīvivarta’s future awakening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chokyi
                    Nyima Rinpoche. Miguel Sawaya produced the translation and wrote the
                    introduction. Andreas Doctor and Catherine Dalton compared the translation with
                    the original Tibetan and edited the text. The translators are grateful to Khenpo
                    Tokpa Tulku and Khenpo Gyaltsen from Ka-Nying Shedrub Ling Monastery for their
                    assistance in resolving several difficult passages.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-3"/>
                <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="6">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-introduction-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-4"/>
                <p tid="7">As the Buddha’s disciple Subhūti goes to collect alms one morning, he encounters
                    a laywoman who imparts to him wise and penetrating teachings on the nature of
                    reality. The bulk of the sūtra recounts Subhūti’s encounter and dialogue with
                    this laywoman, who turns out to be a highly developed spiritual being named
                    Strīvivarta. Subhūti himself adheres to the Hearers’ Vehicle, a spiritual path
                    based on the teachings that emphasize the discipline of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātimokṣa</foreign> vows and the lack of any
                    fixed, singular entity that could constitute a personal “self.” By contrast,
                    Strīvivarta is a follower of the Bodhisattva Vehicle, a path toward the
                    development of boundless compassion, the ability to benefit beings on a vast
                    scale, and wisdom that realizes not only the lack of a personal self but also
                    the lack of a fixed, graspable identity in all phenomena. Thus, their exchange
                    serves to contrast these two approaches to awakening. It is worth noting that
                    the name Strīvivarta means “female transformation,” a fact that seems relevant
                    as she in fact transforms into a male at the end of the sūtra.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-5"/>
                <p tid="8">Set in Rājagṛha, where the Buddha is staying with a large number of disciples,
                    the sūtra commences with Subhūti asking the Buddha about his dream the night
                    before. The Buddha explains that Subhūti’s dream indicates that a previously
                    unheard Dharma teaching will be heard; and with that, Subhūti sets off for town
                    to collect alms. Eventually he arrives at the home of Strīvivarta, who
                    immediately poses challenging questions to the monk on a series of profound
                    subjects. In exchange after exchange, Subhūti does his best to reply to the
                    laywoman, but she continuously confronts him with ever more provocative
                    questions.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-6"/>
                <p tid="9">As their dialogue unfolds, we encounter explanations regarding an array of
                    challenging topics. In addition to Strīvivarta’s eloquent ability to outshine
                    Subhūti on topics of profound import, she is also able to read Subhūti’s mind.
                    This fact significantly increases the monk’s consternation—not only does she
                    challenge him regarding what he says, she even directly confronts him about his
                    thoughts! Moreover, others (including disembodied voices from the sky and
                    various gods) appear throughout the sūtra to put Venerable Subhūti to the test.
                    When Subhūti tries to excuse himself and make an exit, he is schooled as to why
                    it is inappropriate to take leave in such a situation.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-7"/>
                <p tid="10">Over the course of their encounter, Strīvivarta delivers a series of formidable
                    teachings that illuminate the nature of the Great Vehicle and the Buddha’s
                    purposes in going for alms. Strīvivarta also explains how she leads beings to
                    spiritual maturity through skillfully bringing them pleasure. Throughout the
                    exchange, the laywoman’s power and authority are highlighted by the fact that
                    periodically, at the close of particular passages of her teaching, members of
                    the audience attain significant levels of spiritual maturity.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-8"/>
                <p tid="11">Later in the sūtra, two of the laywoman’s young male disciples cross paths with
                    Subhūti. They explain the greatness of bodhisattvas in comparison to the hearers
                    and recite verses in praise of their teacher and her skillful means. This
                    skillfulness becomes strikingly clear when Strīvivarta assumes a handsome male
                    form, showing Subhūti the body with which she teaches women. With this, she
                    stuns the monk to the point that he admits he is at a loss for words; and once
                    again, he tries to leave to complete his alms rounds before it grows too late in
                    the day. In response, Strīvivarta confounds his sense of time by showing various
                    buddha realms in various times and by moving the sun’s position in the sky.
                    Convinced of the truth of her teachings, and no longer concerned about time,
                    Subhūti remains.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-9"/>
                <p tid="12">Following meaningful encounters with a celestial being and another inspiring
                    bodhisattva, Subhūti finally returns to the Buddha, to whom he relates his
                    experiences. The Buddha explains that the woman he encountered is in fact a
                    bodhisattva great being who benefits countless beings by skillfully bringing
                    them pleasure. Soon thereafter, the great bodhisattva herself arrives with a
                    large retinue of women. When Subhūti pays the woman homage, the senior monk
                    Śāriputra questions why he makes such a gesture of respect to a woman lacking
                    both the spiritual qualities and the body of a noble one. Strīvivarta then
                    proceeds to teach on what constitutes a noble being, the profound nature of the
                    Great Vehicle and its followers, and the unhindered confidence of bodhisattvas. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-10"/>
                <p tid="13">There are other sūtras that prominently feature female bodhisattvas. The
                    protagonists in <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Girl Vimalaśraddhā</title> (Toh 84),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-406">See Karma Gyaltsen Ling Translation Group, trans., <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh84.html">The Questions of the Girl Vimalaśraddhā</ref>
                            </title> (Toh 84), 2021.</note>
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Vimaladattā</title> (Toh 77),<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh77.html"/> and <title xml:lang="en">The Lion’s Roar
                        of Śrīmālādevī</title> (Toh 92)<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh92.html"/> are princesses. Elsewhere, royal women are the
                    protagonists predicted to future awakening in <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Aśokadattā’s
                        Prophecy</title> (Toh 76),<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh76.html"/> <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Vimalaprabhā</title> (Toh 168),<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh168.html"/>
                    and <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Kṣemavatī’s Prophecy</title> (Toh 192).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-436">See  Subhashita Translation Group, trans., <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh192.html">The Prophecy of Kṣemavatī</ref>
                            </title>, Toh 192 (84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2022).</note> 
                    Less privileged laywomen are the main interlocutors in <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Girl
                        Sumati</title> (Toh 74),<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh74.html"/> <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Gaṅgottara</title> (Toh 75),<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh75.html"/>
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of an Old Lady</title> (Toh 171),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-420">See Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy Division), trans., <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh171.html">The Questions of an Old Lady</ref>
                            </title> (Toh 171), 2011.</note> <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play
                        of Mañjuśrī</title> (Toh 96),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-421">See Jens Erland Braarvig, trans., <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh96.html">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</ref>
                        </title> (Toh 96), 2020.</note> and <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Girl Candrottarā’s
                            Prophecy</title> (Toh 191).<ref rend="pending" inst="add note citation, add bibl" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh191.html"/> Even so, given the longstanding Buddhist tradition of
                    according primacy to males, the focus on Strīvivarta in this scripture is
                    unusual and refreshing. Still, in the end Strīvivarta bows down at the Buddha’s
                    feet, saying that she will not rise again until she has received a prophecy of
                    her future awakening <emph>and</emph> has obtained a man’s body. The five
                    hundred women in her retinue do and say the same. In the Buddha’s prophecy that
                    follows, he says that in the bodhisattva’s future buddha realm “not even the
                    word <distinct>woman</distinct> will exist.” Upon receiving this prophecy,
                    Strīvivarta and the five hundred women rise into the air, overjoyed, and “take
                    on the appearance of sixteen-year-old boys.” The traditional stance on male
                    superiority thus seems to be, after all, reinstated. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-12"/>
                <p tid="14">The original Sanskrit of this sūtra no longer seems to be extant, but no less
                    than five Chinese translations are found in the Taishō canon (Taishō 562-566),
                    the earliest of which is datable to the late third century.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-13"> On
                        the Chinese translations, see Schuster 1984.</note> According to the
                    colophon to the Tibetan translation, the sūtra was translated into Tibetan by
                    the two Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Prajñāvarman, along with the Tibetan
                    translator Yeshé Dé and others. This locates the Tibetan translation in the late
                    eighth or early ninth century. This dating is also confirmed by the text’s
                    inclusion in the Denkarma Catalog of the early ninth century.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-14">
                        The Denkarma catalog is dated to c. 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. See
                        Denkarma, 298.a.6.<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html"/> See also Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, 78, no. 143.</note> In
                    producing this translation, we have based our work on the Degé xylograph while
                    consulting the Comparative Edition (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) and the Stok Palace Kangyur.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="15"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="16">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="17">The Prophecy Concerning Strīvivarta</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-section-1"> 
                    
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-18"/>
                    <p tid="21">
                        <ref cRef="F.201.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-356"/> <ref type="bampo" cRef="B1"/>
                    Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <lb/>
                <p tid="22">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Rājagṛha, at Vulture
                    Peak Mountain, together with a great saṅgha of five thousand monks. <ref cRef="F.201.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-357"/>
                    Also present were eight thousand bodhisattvas. All of them were renowned, had
                    attained the superknowledges, and had unimpeded eloquence, fearlessness, and the
                    acceptance that phenomena are unborn. All of them had generated roots of virtue
                    in the presence of countless buddhas and had become followers of the Great
                    Vehicle. Among them were the bodhisattva great beings Nimindhara, Dharaṇīdhara,
                    Terrace Holder, Holder of the Family of Offering and Giving, Illuminating
                    Intelligence, Completely Pure Intelligence, Purified Intelligence, Viśeṣamati,
                    Anantamati, Vardhamānamati, Priyadarśana, Sudarśana, Surūpa, and the
                    bodhisattva great being Seeing All Meanings. All the bodhisattva great beings of
                    the Good Eon, such as Maitreya, had also gathered and were present in that
                    retinue. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-20"/>
                <p tid="23">While the Blessed One was staying in the city of Rājagṛha, the king and all the
                    princes, merchants, householders, ministers, attendants, and city residents, as
                    well as all the people of that area, venerated him, showed him reverence, served
                    him, and made offerings to him.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-21"/>
                <p tid="24">One morning, Venerable Subhūti put on his lower garment and robes, picked up his
                    alms bowl, and approached the Blessed One. He prostrated, placing his head at
                    the Blessed One’s feet, and then sat to one side. Sitting there, Venerable
                    Subhūti told the Blessed One, “Blessed One, in my dream last night I saw the
                    Thus-Gone One seated upon the seat of awakening. He raised his right hand, which
                    was the color of gold, placed it on the crown of my head, and said, ‘Subhūti,
                    tomorrow you will hear a Dharma teaching that you have not heard before.’
                    Blessed One, <ref cRef="F.202.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-358"/> what does this foretell?”</p>
                
                <p tid="25">The Blessed One replied, “Subhūti, this is an omen that sons and daughters of
                    noble family who long for the Dharma will hear a previously unheard Dharma
                    teaching.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-23"/>
                <p tid="26">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, I will go to the
                    city of Rājagṛha for alms.”</p>
                
                <p tid="27">“If you know that it is time for that, Subhūti, then go,” replied the Blessed
                    One.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-25"/>
                <p tid="28">Having received the Blessed One’s assent, Venerable Subhūti prostrated, placing
                    his head at the Blessed One’s feet, and then went into the city of Rājagṛha for
                    alms. Venerable Subhūti proceeded through the city of Rājagṛha seeking alms,
                    and, arriving at the residence of a particular householder, he stood quietly
                    inside the gate. Emerging from that home came a lovely lady, beautiful and
                    elegantly adorned with jewelry. She wore jewelry of precious stones, pearl,
                    coral, and gold, so that she blazed with splendor. Her complexion was lustrous
                    and beautiful. The lady prostrated, placing her head at Venerable Subhūti’s
                    feet, and asked, “What do you desire, honorable Subhūti, standing at my
                    gate?”</p>
                
                <p tid="29">“Elder sister,” replied Subhūti, “it is because I seek alms that I am here at the
                    gate.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-27"/>
                <p tid="30">“Honorable Subhūti,” asked the lady, “does the notion of alms still occur to you?
                    Have you, honorable Subhūti, not yet fully understood the notion of alms?”</p>
                
                <p tid="31">Subhūti replied, “Indeed, I have fully understood the notion of alms.
                    Nevertheless, elder sister, this body born of parents and developed by consuming
                    rice and porridge cannot subsist without food.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-29"/>
                <p tid="32">The lady asked, “Has honorable Subhūti <ref cRef="F.202.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-359"/> not actualized the cessation of
                    formative factors through the cessation of ignorance; the cessation of
                    consciousness through the cessation of formative factors; the cessation of name
                    and form through the cessation of consciousness; the cessation of the six sense
                    sources through the cessation of name and form; the cessation of contact through
                    the cessation of the six sense sources; the cessation of sensation through the
                    cessation of contact; the cessation of craving through the cessation of
                    sensation; the cessation of grasping through the cessation of craving; the
                    cessation of becoming through the cessation of grasping; the cessation of birth
                    through the cessation of becoming; the cessation of old age and death, as well
                    as misery, lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and agitation, through the
                    cessation of birth?”</p>
                
                <p tid="33">“Elder sister,” replied Subhūti, “I have actualized cessation.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-31"/>
                <p tid="34">“Honorable Subhūti, what is it that ceases? What is it that you cultivate?”</p>
                
                <p tid="35">“Elder sister, cessation is not cultivating anything at all.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-33"/>
                <p tid="36">“Honorable Subhūti, if cessation is not the cultivation of anything at all, how
                    is it that honorable Subhūti’s body will be nourished by means of alms?”</p>
                
                <p tid="37">“Elder sister, having entered the equilibrium of cessation, the body that has
                    arisen from the ceasing of all sensation is nourished by alms.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-35"/>
                <p tid="38">“Honorable Subhūti, if you have passed into nirvāṇa, how is it that your body is
                    to be nourished?”</p>
                
                <p tid="39">“Elder sister, the Blessed One’s hearers wander for alms in order to nourish the
                    body.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-37"/>
                <p tid="40">“Well, hasn’t the Blessed One taught that honorable Subhūti is supreme among
                    those without afflictions?”</p>
                
                <p tid="41">“That is so, elder sister.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-39"/>
                <p tid="42">“Well, does one who is without afflictions wander or move about?”</p>
                
                <p tid="43">“No, elder sister, that is not the case.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-41"/>
                <p tid="44">“Well then, to what end does honorable Subhūti wander about for alms?”</p>
                
                <p tid="45">“Elder sister, I do not wander for alms in order to beautify the body. Rather, I
                    go for alms in order to cease sensations and to remain alive.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-43"/>
                <p tid="46">“Honorable Subhūti, are you still dominated by sensations?” <ref cRef="F.203.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-360"/>
                    </p>
                
                <p tid="47">“Although I am not dominated by sensations, elder sister, I wander for alms in
                    order to cease sensations.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-45"/>
                <p tid="48">“Honorable Subhūti, one who is without afflictions is peerless. And why is that?
                    One who is without afflictions does not experience bodily or mental sensations.
                    One who is without afflictions is not associated with body or mind. One who is
                    without afflictions does not feel pleasure or displeasure. One who is without
                    afflictions is not beset with afflictions for anyone. So, why has the Blessed
                    One taught that honorable Subhūti is supreme among those without afflictions?
                    And why is the absence of afflictions called <distinct>the absence of
                        afflictions</distinct>?”</p>
                
                <p tid="49">Subhūti replied, “Elder sister, the absence of afflictions that is beyond
                    apprehending is free from the flaws of passion.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-47"/>
                <p tid="50">“Honorable Subhūti, is it then the case that if one has no afflictions, one is
                    also free from passion?”</p>
                
                <p tid="51">“That is not the case, elder sister.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-49"/>
                <p tid="52">“Well then, honorable Subhūti, how is it that the absence of afflictions is also
                    freedom from the flaws of passion?”</p>
                
                <p tid="53">“The teaching on the absence of afflictions, elder sister, amounts to nothing
                    more than an explanation.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-51"/>
                <p tid="54">“Well, honorable Subhūti, does this explanation regarding the absence of
                    afflictions not exist?”</p>
                
                <p tid="55">“No, elder sister, it does not.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-53"/>
                <p tid="56">“Honorable Subhūti, if this explanation regarding the absence of afflictions does
                    not exist, what are you explaining here?”</p>
                
                <p tid="57">“Elder sister, the Blessed One’s hearers simply make designations on the
                    conventional level using conventional terms.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-55"/>
                <p tid="58">“Honorable Subhūti, to the degree that there is expression, to that extent there
                    are conventional designations. To the degree that there are conventional
                    designations, to that extent there is error. To the degree that there is error,
                    to that extent there will be contention. To the degree that there is contention,
                    to that extent this is not the Dharma of mendicants.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-56"/>
                <p tid="59">“So then, elder sister, what is the Dharma of mendicants?”</p>
                
                <p tid="60">“Honorable Subhūti, the Dharma of mendicants is without conventions. <ref cRef="F.203.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-361"/> It
                    is unmistaken, and it is free from contention. The Dharma of mendicants is
                    beyond Dharma and non-Dharma. The Dharma of mendicants is free from attachment
                    and nonattachment. The Dharma of mendicants is without objects, and it is not an
                    object. The Dharma of mendicants is without attachment; it is neither bound nor
                    liberated. The Dharma of mendicants is without mind; it is free from mind,
                    mentation, and consciousness. The Dharma of mendicants is contentment. The
                    Dharma of mendicants is letting go of jealousy and attachment. The Dharma of
                    mendicants is having little desire and being content. The Dharma of mendicants
                    is free from all desires. The Dharma of mendicants completely transcends all
                    objects, and it is without grasping. The Dharma of mendicants is definitely
                    freed from the demon of the aggregates. The Dharma of mendicants is without
                    afflictions; it has completely passed beyond the demon of the afflictions. The
                    Dharma of mendicants is unborn. The Dharma of mendicants is free from the demon
                    of the Lord of Death. The Dharma of mendicants is without deceit, arrogance, and
                    concepts; it is unobscured and unfettered. The Dharma of mendicants has
                    completely passed beyond the realm of the demons. The Dharma of mendicants is
                    free from adopting and discarding. The Dharma of mendicants is free from birth
                    and perishing. The Dharma of mendicants is not defiled by the demon of the gods.
                    The Dharma of mendicants is without mental engagement and entirely unsullied.
                    The Dharma of mendicants is without clinging, without marks, and free from all
                    marks. The Dharma of mendicants is not altered by any modes of elements and
                    nonelements; it is without enumeration, separation, and location, and it is
                    equal to space.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-58"/>
                <p tid="61">When the lady gave this teaching on the Dharma of mendicants, 
                    for the four thousand gods among those who had gathered by her gate 
                    to listen to the Dharma, <ref cRef="F.204.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-362"/> 
                    the faultless and stainless eye of Dharma that beholds phenomena was purified.
                    For another five hundred gods who were dedicated to the vast Dharma, the mind set 
                    upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening was brought forth after hearing the lady’s eloquent teaching.</p>
                <lb/>                
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-60"/>
                <p tid="63">Then Venerable Subhūti thought, “It is amazing that this elder sister is so
                    eloquent. Since this elder sister can demonstrate such eloquence, she is surely
                    an emanation of the Thus-Gone One.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-61"/>
                <p tid="64">The lady, who knew what he was thinking, said to the elder Subhūti, “Honorable
                    Subhūti, when you thought, ‘She is surely an emanation of the Thus-Gone One,’
                    you were right indeed. Why is that? Just as the Thus-Gone One has understood
                    suchness, likewise I too have understood suchness. That being so, I am indeed an
                    emanation of the Thus-Gone One. That which is the suchness of the form of the
                    Thus-Gone One, and the suchness of his feelings, perceptions, formations, and
                    consciousnesses, is also my suchness. That being so, I am an emanation of the
                    Thus-Gone One. The suchness of the Thus-Gone One never changes into something
                    that is not suchness. Likewise, my suchness, along with the suchness of all
                    beings, also never changes into something that is not suchness. That being so, I
                    am an emanation of the Thus-Gone One. The Thus-Gone One’s suchness does not only
                    sometimes become suchness; and likewise, my suchness does not only sometimes
                    become suchness. Rather, it is always exclusively suchness. That being so, I am
                    an emanation of the Thus-Gone One. My suchness, along with the suchness of all
                    beings <ref cRef="F.204.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-363"/> and the suchness of all phenomena, is simply suchness, genuine
                    and not otherwise. That being so, I am an emanation of the Thus-Gone One.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-62"/>
                <p tid="65">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, is it by the power of the
                    Thus-Gone One that you knew my mind, or did you know it by means of your own
                    mind?”</p>
                
                <p tid="66">“Honorable Subhūti, all those who know the minds of others, be they hearers,
                    solitary buddhas, bodhisattvas, or sages who possess the five extraordinary
                    abilities, know the minds of others due to the power of the Buddha. In that way,
                    elder Subhūti, the knowledge of the minds of others is knowledge through the
                    power of the Buddha. Honorable Subhūti, to give an analogy, beings with eyes see
                    forms in dependence upon the moon, the sun, fire, jewels, lamps, and stars.
                    Similarly, honorable Subhūti, anyone who knows the minds of others, while living
                    here in the darkness of ignorance, attains this knowledge in dependence upon the
                    Thus-Gone One.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-64"/>
                <p tid="67">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, you are so eloquent! Tell
                    me who you are and whence you came.”</p>
                
                <p tid="68">The lady responded, “Honorable Subhūti, what response could be given if someone
                    were to question an emanation of the Thus-Gone One, saying, ‘Noble son, tell me
                    who you are and whence you came’?”</p>
                
                <p tid="69">“Elder sister, no response whatsoever could be given.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-67"/>
                <p tid="70">“Similarly, honorable Subhūti, knowing that all phenomena are essentially
                    emanations, what is there for me to say? Furthermore, if someone were to
                    question honorable Subhūti, saying, ‘Are you an ordinary being, a learner, or a
                    worthy one?’ how would you respond?”</p>
                
                <p tid="71">While honorable Subhūti was pondering how to respond to the elder sister,
                    <ref cRef="F.205.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-364"/> a voice called out from the sky, “Honorable Subhūti, explain briefly
                    to this elder sister how you know that you are a worthy one, whether it is due
                    to your attainment, realization, experience, or understanding.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-69"/>
                <p tid="72">Hearing this voice from the sky, Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder
                    sister, I am not an ordinary being, nor am I a learner, nor am I a worthy
                    one.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-70"/>
                <p tid="73">“Honorable Subhūti, how am I to understand that?”</p>
                
                <p tid="74">“Elder sister, think of me just like someone designated as an emanation of the
                    Thus-Gone One.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-72"/>
                <p tid="75">“Honorable Subhūti is called ‘the foremost among the worthy ones whose
                    defilements have been exhausted and who are without afflictions, worthy of
                    offerings.’ ”</p>
                
                <p tid="76">“Elder sister, I am not the foremost among the worthy ones whose defilements have
                    been exhausted and who are without afflictions, worthy of offerings.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-74"/>
                <p tid="77">“If you speak in such a way, honorable Subhūti, aren’t you deliberately
                    lying?”</p>
                
                <p tid="78">“Elder sister, if I were to think that I was the foremost and most worthy of
                    offerings among those whose defilements have been exhausted and who are without
                    afflictions, then I would be lying. However, since I do not think that, I speak
                    honestly, and this cannot be called lying.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-76"/>
                <p tid="79">“Honorable Subhūti, aren’t you deceiving the gods who have seen the truths and
                    who have gathered by the gate to listen to the Dharma?”</p>
                
                <p tid="80">“Elder sister, one cannot deceive those who have seen the truths.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-78"/>
                <p tid="81">“Has honorable Subhūti seen the truths?”</p>
                
                <p tid="82">“I have.”</p>
                
                <p tid="83">“If the truths can be seen, they are not the truths. Why not? Because the truths
                    cannot be seen by anyone at all.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-81"/>
                <p tid="84">“Elder sister,” replied Subhūti, “what does the phrase ‘seeing the truths’ mean?”
                    <ref cRef="F.205.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-365"/>
                    </p>
                
                <p tid="85">“ ‘Seeing the truths,’ honorable Subhūti, refers to beholding all phenomena as
                    sameness. Saying ‘I have seen the truths’ refers to seeing that which is
                    mistaken.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-83"/>
                <p tid="86">“What do you mean by that, elder sister?”</p>
                
                <p tid="87">“Honorable Subhūti, seeing the truths is to see that afflictions occur because of
                    being mistaken. Therefore, by seeing that which is mistaken, it is said that one
                    sees the truths.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-85"/>
                <p tid="88">Then the gods who had gathered at the gate to listen to the Dharma revealed the
                    coarse forms of their bodies to elder Subhūti and said, “Honorable Subhūti, you
                    have heard the eloquence of this elder sister; this is a fortunate discovery by
                    you. Anyone who, hearing this teaching, dedicated to it has also met with
                    similar fortune. However, those who appreciate it are not liberated from
                    anything. And why is that? It is because for those who are greatly appreciative,
                    there is no liberation from anything at all. Since those who are greatly
                    appreciative are not bound, they are also not liberated from anything.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-86"/>
                <p tid="89">Then the lady said to Venerable Subhūti, “Honorable Subhūti, aren’t you going for
                    alms? Why have you stopped collecting food?” </p>
                
                <p tid="90">“Elder sister, my food is just this—it will suffice to listen to the Dharma like
                    this. Elder sister, one who worries about Dharma robes and alms is not one who
                    longs for the Dharma. One who longs for gain, esteem, and praise is not one who
                    longs for the Dharma. One who is concerned with his body, life, and alms is not
                    one who longs for the Dharma. Even one who longs for approval is also not one
                    who longs for the Dharma. Elder sister, what are the sons and daughters of noble
                    family who long for the Dharma like?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-88"/>
                <p tid="91">“Honorable Subhūti, one who does not crave pleasure is one who longs for the
                    Dharma. One who is not concerned with the eyes and forms, and who is not
                    concerned with the ears and <ref cRef="F.206.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-366"/> sounds, the nose and odors, the tongue and
                    tastes, the body and tangible objects, or the mind and mental phenomena—that is
                    one who longs for the Dharma. One who does not depend upon any phenomenon
                    whatsoever is one who longs for the Dharma. Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, one
                    who does not long for the aggregates, elements, and sense sources is one who
                    longs for the Dharma. One who does not long for the realms of desire, form, and
                    formlessness is one who longs for the Dharma. One who does not desire to focus
                    on the characteristics of what is observed is one who longs for the Dharma.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-89"/>
                <p tid="92">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, I beg your pardon, as I
                    must take my leave of your gate.”</p>
                
                <p tid="93">“Honorable Subhūti,” replied the lady, “to give an analogy, one does not beg
                    pardon of the earth element. Likewise, honorable Subhūti, one does not beg
                    pardon of someone whose mind is like earth. Honorable Subhūti, one does not beg
                    pardon of water. Likewise, one does not beg pardon of someone whose mind is like
                    water. Honorable Subhūti, one does not beg pardon of fire, wind, or space.
                    Likewise, one does not beg pardon of someone whose mind is like fire, wind, or
                    space. Honorable Subhūti, one does not beg pardon of a ship, platform, bridge,
                    or highway. Likewise, honorable Subhūti, one does not beg pardon of someone
                    whose mind is like a ship, platform, bridge, or highway. Honorable Subhūti,
                    although one begs pardon of immature beings, one does not beg pardon of noble
                    ones. Honorable Subhūti, although one begs pardon of those for whom ill will,
                    wrath, and latent tendencies arise, one does not beg pardon of those for whom
                    these do not arise. Honorable Subhūti, to give an analogy, one might seek to
                    extinguish a blazing fire, but one would not seek to extinguish a fire that is
                    not blazing. Likewise, honorable Subhūti, although one begs pardon of those
                    whose afflictions are blazing, one does not beg pardon of those without
                    afflictions.” <ref cRef="F.206.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-367"/>
                    </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-91"/>
                <p tid="94">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, what is it that you
                    desire as you roar like a lion in this way?” </p>
                
                <p tid="95">“Honorable Subhūti, one who has desire cannot resound with a lion’s roar. It is
                    those who desire nothing at all who resound with a lion’s roar. Why is that? For
                    someone who has reference points, there is desire. But for one who is free from
                    reference points, a lion’s roar does not exist at all. For one who has the view
                    of the transitory collection, there is desire. But for one who does not hold
                    views, there is no lion’s roar at all. Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, what wish
                    liberates the mind from defilements with no further grasping?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-93"/>
                <p tid="96">“Elder sister, for one who has desire there is no liberation whatsoever.”</p>
                
                <p tid="97">“Honorable Subhūti, in that way I have also entered the state where the mind is
                    liberated from defilements with no further grasping. So I too am now liberated.
                    I too have attained an understanding of the realm of phenomena.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-95"/>
                <p tid="98">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, if you explain to me the
                    aspects, signs, and features of the Great Vehicle, I will have no doubt that you
                    have genuinely entered the Great Vehicle.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-96"/>
                <p tid="99">The lady replied, “Honorable Subhūti, do you know the Great Vehicle’s aspects,
                    signs, and features?”</p>
                
                <p tid="100">“Elder sister, without hearing about them, the hearers are unable to know the
                    Great Vehicle’s aspects, signs, and features. So therefore, elder sister, please
                    explain the aspects, signs, and features of the Great Vehicle.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-98"/>
                <p tid="101">“Honorable Subhūti, the <distinct>Great Vehicle</distinct> refers to a vehicle
                    without attachment. It is unobscured wisdom and wisdom beyond distinctions.
                    <ref cRef="F.207.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-368"/> To give an analogy, honorable Subhūti, the chariots of the active gods
                    and those of the moon and the sun spontaneously traverse the sky and shine on
                    beings, doing so without attachment, without obscuration, and without
                    interruption. Similarly, honorable Subhūti, holy beings who have genuinely
                    entered the Great Vehicle act by the strength of the six perfections and shine
                    the light of the Dharma on all beings without attachment, without obscuration,
                    and without interruption. To give an analogy, honorable Subhūti, the four
                    continents belong to the universal monarch, and wherever he goes it is
                    appropriate that he be attended by the people of the four continents. But the
                    universal monarch does not think of those subjects as being unequal to him;
                    rather, he acts with loving-kindness toward them. Likewise, honorable Subhūti,
                    wherever bodhisattvas who have genuinely entered the Great Vehicle go, whether
                    to hamlets, cities, towns, districts, provinces, or royal palaces, it is
                    appropriate that they be attended by all beings. Nevertheless, those
                    bodhisattvas have an attitude of impartiality toward all those beings and do not
                    act differently toward them. When bodhisattvas gather disciples through the four
                    means of attraction, their love for all beings never differs. This is why it is
                    called the <distinct>Great Vehicle</distinct>.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-99"/>
                <p tid="102">“Honorable Subhūti, the <distinct>Great Vehicle</distinct> means that the vehicle
                    is greater. It is worshiped by gods, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nāgas</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yakṣas</foreign>,
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gandharvas</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">asuras</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">garuḍas</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kinnaras</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mahoragas</foreign>, humans, nonhumans, Śakra, Brahmā, the guardians of the
                    world, wise ones, holy beings, knowledgeable ones, those who have gone
                    correctly, and those who have entered correctly. <ref cRef="F.207.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-369"/> This is why it is
                    called the <distinct>Great Vehicle</distinct>. Since the Great Vehicle is
                    unborn, it is inexhaustible. This vehicle is the unbroken lineage of the Buddha.
                    This vehicle is the consolidation of the Dharma lineage. This vehicle upholds
                    the Saṅgha lineage. Since this vehicle provides opportunities for all beings and
                    is without obscurations, it is expansive. Since this vehicle is not a matter of
                    improvement, it is unconditioned. This vehicle brings proficiency by means of
                    the six perfections. This vehicle excellently draws others in through the four
                    means of attraction. Since it follows the eight branches of the path of the
                    noble ones, this vehicle proceeds correctly. Due to the cultivation of
                    tranquility and special insight, this vehicle is a fine conveyance. Because the
                    four applications of mindfulness and the mind of awakening are not forgotten, it
                    is the abode of the excellent helmsman. Because of its great compassion, this
                    vehicle is extremely stable. This vehicle is well-established by the state of
                    omniscience itself. Because it conquers all demons, this vehicle is free from
                    fear. Displaying the light of knowledge, this vehicle is free from darkness.
                    Having gathered and accumulated all roots of virtue, this vehicle is the
                    greatest wealth. This vehicle is revered by the world and its gods. This vehicle
                    cannot be destroyed by any opponent. This vehicle is difficult for any hearer or
                    solitary buddha to comprehend. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-100"/>
                <p tid="103">“This vehicle delights those lacking faith. This vehicle brings loving-kindness
                    to those who are aggressive. This vehicle brings generosity to the miserly. This
                    vehicle brings discipline to those whose discipline is lax. This vehicle brings
                    patience to those who harbor ill will. This vehicle brings diligence to the
                    lazy. This vehicle brings mindfulness to the forgetful. This vehicle brings calm
                    to the distracted. <ref cRef="F.208.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-370"/> This vehicle brings knowledge to those whose
                    knowledge is faulty. This vehicle brings wealth to the poor. This vehicle brings
                    ease to those who suffer. This vehicle brings supreme joy to the wise. This
                    vehicle brings delight to the knowledgeable. This being so, it is called the
                        <distinct>Great Vehicle</distinct>.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-101"/>
                <p tid="104">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, you have excellently
                    articulated the aspects, signs, and features of the Great Vehicle.”</p>
                
                <p tid="105">“Honorable Subhūti,” replied the lady, “even if I were to explain the aspects,
                    signs, and features of the Great Vehicle for an eon, or even longer than that, I
                    would not reach the end. Honorable Subhūti, just as the Great Vehicle is
                    immeasurable, so too are its aspects, signs, and features.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-103"/>
                <p tid="106">Venerable Subhūti continued by asking the lady, “Elder sister, when you asked
                    what I desire in going for alms, you were looking for faults in me. However,
                    since the Thus-Gone One, the master of Dharma himself, also goes for alms, are
                    you looking for faults in the Thus-Gone One as well?”</p>
                
                <p tid="107">“Honorable Subhūti,” said the lady, “if you know of the skillfulness with which
                    the Thus-Gone One goes for alms, please say so.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-105"/>
                <p tid="108">“No, elder sister, with which skillfulness does the Thus-Gone One go for
                    alms?”</p>
                
                <p tid="109">“Honorable Subhūti, the Thus-Gone One goes for alms because he sees twenty-one
                    great purposes. And what are those twenty-one? The Thus-Gone One goes for alms
                    in order to display his excellent form body. Anyone who sees the body of the
                    Thus-Gone One, adorned with the thirty-two marks of a great being and the best
                    of all features, <ref cRef="F.208.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-371"/> engenders the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect
                    awakening in order to attain the marks of the Thus-Gone One’s form body. It is
                    through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone
                    One goes for alms. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-107"/>
                <p tid="110">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when the Thus-Gone One goes to hamlets or cities
                    for alms, those who are blind regain their sight. Those who are deaf can hear
                    again. The mad regain their senses. Those who are naked find clothing. Those who
                    are hungry acquire food. Those who are thirsty find drink. And everyone without
                    exception becomes free from the harms of passion, aggression, delusion, envy,
                    stinginess, wrath, haughtiness, hypocrisy, and anguish. Everyone becomes loving
                    and perceives others as their parents. Since many beings behold these perfect
                    qualities of the Thus-Gone One when he goes to hamlets or cities, they give rise
                    to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is through
                    considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes
                    for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-108"/>
                <p tid="111">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when the Thus-Gone One goes to hamlets, cities,
                    and towns, gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras,
                    mahoragas, Śakra, Brahmā, and the guardians of the world follow close behind, in
                    order to offer him worship. By the power of the Buddha, humans are able to see
                    gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, <ref cRef="F.209.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-372"/> garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas,
                    Śakra, Brahmā, and the guardians of the world worshiping the Blessed One. Seeing
                    this, they admire the Thus-Gone One, thinking, ‘The qualities of the Thus-Gone
                    One are truly amazing and wondrous!’ With this admiration for the Thus-Gone One,
                    they give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is
                    through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone
                    One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-109"/>
                <p tid="112">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when they see the Thus-Gone One going for alms,
                    countless beings who are conceited and obsessed with resources and power, as
                    well as those who are conceited and obsessed with their looks, caste,
                    livelihood, and health, think, ‘It is said that he cast away the kingdom of a
                    universal monarch and became a renunciate going for alms. If he has overcome
                    pride like that, surely we too should vanquish our pride.’ With this
                    observation, they give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect
                    awakening. It is through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that
                    the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-110"/>
                <p tid="113">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when the Thus-Gone One goes to hamlets or cities
                    for alms, the majestic and magnificent gods perceive his state of mind and say,
                    ‘He is not afflicted by hunger or thirst, nor is his body weak. And still,
                    through his ever-increasing affection for others, he goes for alms. That being
                    so, we too should go for alms in a similar fashion, with a mind of
                    ever-increasing affection for others.’ With this observation, they give rise to
                    the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is through considering
                    this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.
                    <ref cRef="F.209.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-373"/>
                    </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-111"/>
                <p tid="114">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, there are lazy and indolent people who never
                    come to see, pay homage to, and honor the Thus-Gone One. However, when the
                    Thus-Gone One goes to hamlets or cities, they are able to see him effortlessly.
                    Then, seeing him in this way, they experience intense pleasure and joy. With
                    that feeling of intense pleasure and joy, they give rise to the mind set upon
                    unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is through considering this great purpose,
                    honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-112"/>
                <p tid="115">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the blessed buddhas are meaningful to behold. If
                    beings even so much as behold the Thus-Gone One with a calm gaze for merely a
                    single conscious moment, this becomes an enduring cause for them to pass into
                    nirvāṇa. Honorable Subhūti, it is through considering this great purpose that
                    the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-113"/>
                <p tid="116">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when the Thus-Gone One goes to hamlets or
                    cities, those who are bound by fetters are freed from their fetters. They think,
                    ‘It is by the power of the Thus-Gone One that we have been freed from these
                    fetters.’ Understanding this, they are appreciative and grateful to the
                    Thus-Gone One, and they give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect
                    awakening. It is through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that
                    the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-114"/>
                <p tid="117">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when sons and daughters of noble family hear
                    praises of the Thus-Gone One’s qualities, they think, ‘My goodness! We must
                    offer alms to the Thus-Gone One. Let’s give him Dharma robes, make offerings,
                    and show respect. Let’s make offerings with whatever is suitable.’ And those who
                    think this way go to see him. <ref cRef="F.210.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-374"/> But there are also those who are under
                    the protection of mothers, fathers, elder siblings, spouses, and partners. Due
                    to such circumstances, they cannot go directly before the Thus-Gone One.
                    Instead, when they see that the Thus-Gone One has come to their hamlet or city,
                    they feel fulfilled and gladdened. Extremely delighted, they experience joy and
                    happiness, and they offer alms to the Thus-Gone One. Moreover, having offered,
                    they give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is
                    through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone
                    One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-115"/>
                <p tid="118">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the gods in the realm of the Four Great Kings
                    offered an alms bowl to the Thus-Gone One, and he accepted it. When beings of
                    meager resources with only little to give, whoever they may be, see the
                    Thus-Gone One’s alms bowl they perceive it as full. However, beings of greater
                    resources with much to give, whoever they may be, see the Thus-Gone One’s alms
                    bowl as not full, and so they offer as much as necessary. Having filled his alms
                    bowl, they give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It
                    is through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone
                    One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-116"/>
                <p tid="119">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when many delicious foods are placed into the
                    Thus-Gone One’s alms bowl, they do not become mixed, but remain apart, as if
                    they were in separate containers. Many gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras,
                    garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas behold such miracles of the Thus-Gone One’s
                    alms bowl, <ref cRef="F.210.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-375"/> and thereby give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and
                    perfect awakening. It is through considering this great purpose, honorable
                    Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-117"/>
                <p tid="120">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, even if the food of all the monks is put into
                    the Thus-Gone One’s alms bowl, it is not filled, nor will it ever become full.
                    Many gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas
                    behold such miracles of the Thus-Gone One’s alms bowl. They are amazed and give
                    rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is through
                    considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes
                    for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-118"/>
                <p tid="121">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the Thus-Gone One’s body is solid throughout; it
                    is not hollow, but solid like a vajra. Although the body of the Thus-Gone One has
                    no stomach, intestines, excrement, or urine, he nevertheless goes for alms and
                    eats food. Even so, he does not swallow the food. Many gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                    gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, humans, and nonhumans witness
                    this and thereby give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect
                    awakening. It is through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that
                    the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-119"/>
                <p tid="122">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, when the Thus-Gone One goes to hamlets or
                    cities, many beings offer alms, whether a lot or a little, excellent or poor.
                    Although those beings may be unable to perfect all the qualities that the
                    Thus-Gone One possesses, they do experience many of the pleasures of gods and
                    humans. <ref cRef="F.211.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-376"/> And those qualities are not exhausted until they pass into
                    nirvāṇa. It is through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that
                    the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-120"/>
                <p tid="123">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the Thus-Gone One is perpetually in equipoise
                    and never leaves the state of absorption. When Brahmā or other majestic and
                    magnificent gods of the form realm see the Thus-Gone One going for alms without
                    wavering from his absorption, they think, ‘He exerts himself for the welfare of
                    beings, but surely he does not long for food.’ With this thought they are elated
                    and give rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. It is
                    through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone
                    One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-121"/>
                <p tid="124">“If, honorable Subhūti, the Thus-Gone One neither went for alms nor ate food,
                    then those sons and daughters of noble family who have gone forth and renounced
                    the householder’s life for the sake of the well-spoken Dharma and Vinaya would
                    also not eat. They would think, ‘We, too, should not go for alms; we, too,
                    should not eat.’ In that way they would go hungry and grow feeble and therefore
                    be unable to realize the unique attainment. It is with their future
                    accomplishment of the unique attainment in mind that the Thus-Gone One goes for
                    alms and partakes of food. It is through considering this great purpose,
                    honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-122"/>
                <p tid="125">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the Thus-Gone One goes for alms in order to
                    fully care for those in the family of the noble ones.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-123"/>
                <p tid="126">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, it is because of his affection for future beings
                    that the Thus-Gone One goes for alms. Otherwise, in the future faithless priests
                    and householders would feel strong aversion for monks and nuns, saying, ‘Why do
                    they go for alms if their teacher himself did not?’ <ref cRef="F.211.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-377"/> Now they will
                    instead think, ‘If even their teacher went for alms, why should they not as
                    well?’ Thus, they will utter praise and give alms. They will say, ‘Going for
                    alms is indeed a sacred tradition. This practice was praised by the Thus-Gone
                    One.’ It is through considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the
                    Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-124"/>
                <p tid="127">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, there are those who have renounced their
                    householder’s lives as kings, ministers, priests, householders, and sons of
                    ministers and have gone forth out of faith in the well-spoken Dharma and Vinaya.
                    Out of shame, they might not go for alms, thinking, ‘If we have been born into
                    such high castes, why should we go from house to house for alms?’ But this way
                    they can go for alms, following in the footsteps of the Thus-Gone One, who
                    himself went for alms in all his majesty. It is through considering this great
                    purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-125"/>
                <p tid="128">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the thus-gone ones intend to act in accord with
                    the world. They act in whichever way brings beings to maturity. It is through
                    considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the Thus-Gone One goes
                    for alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-126"/>
                <p tid="129">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the Thus-Gone One is without obscurations,
                    thirst, feebleness, attachment, or anything that could become attachment. He has
                    no wish for negative deeds, and he does not accumulate negativity. <ref cRef="F.212.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-378"/>
                    Nevertheless, the thus-gone, worthy, and perfect Buddha goes for alms in order
                    to act in accord with the world and bring beings to full maturity. It is through
                    considering this great purpose, honorable Subhūti, that the thus-gone, worthy,
                    and perfect Buddha goes for alms. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-127"/>
                <p tid="130">“That being so, honorable Subhūti, do you also go for alms with such
                    skillfulness, such great compassion, and such pure purpose?”</p>
                
                <p tid="131">“No, elder sister, I am incapable of that. To give an analogy, elder sister,
                    there are no dogs or cats capable of destroying Mount Meru, the king of
                    mountains. And there are no foxes capable, even over the course of eons, of
                    teaching the lion, the king of beasts, how to obtain its powerful abilities and
                    its resounding roar. Similarly, elder sister, there are no hearers or solitary
                    buddhas capable of demonstrating such conduct, skillfulness, or great compassion
                    as the Thus-Gone One.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-129"/>
                <p tid="132">When this account of the Thus-Gone One’s skill in means and his going for alms
                    was given, two thousand eight hundred people from that household, as well as
                    from other households, who had come to listen to the Dharma gave rise to the
                    mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</p>
                
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-131"/>
                <p tid="134">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the lady, “Elder sister, where is your husband
                    now?”</p>
                
                <p tid="135">“Honorable Subhūti,” replied the lady, “my husband does not amount to just one.
                    And why is that? I have as many husbands as there are beings to be tamed by
                    skillfully bringing them pleasure.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-133"/>
                <p tid="136">“Elder sister, the Thus-Gone One does not grant anyone sensual pleasure.”</p>
                
                <p tid="137">“Honorable Subhūti, as befits the circumstances, a monk may own and make use of
                    robes, alms, bedding, seat, healing substances, <ref cRef="F.212.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-379"/> and medicinal goods,
                    and he may approach the households of close ones and those who provide alms. He
                    may please his friends and follow, attend, and serve his preceptors and masters.
                    The Thus-Gone One has referred to these acts in terms of increasing virtuous
                    qualities and decreasing nonvirtuous qualities.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-135"/>
                <p tid="138">“Elder sister, it is just as you have said.”</p>
                
                <p tid="139">“That being the case, honorable Subhūti, it is by such means that the Thus-Gone
                    One grants beings all sensual pleasure.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-137"/>
                <p tid="140">“Elder sister, you must have tamed a lot of beings by skillfully bringing them
                    pleasure.”</p>
                
                <p tid="141">“Honorable Subhūti, if one were to count all the stars in the great
                    trichiliocosm, one could determine their number. However, one cannot do so for
                    the number of beings that I have trained by skillfully bringing them pleasure
                    and have subsequently established in unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-139"/>
                <p tid="142">“Elder sister, what kind of pleasure do you give those beings?”</p>
                
                <p tid="143">“Honorable Subhūti,” replied the lady, “there are beings who are keen for the
                    pleasure of Brahmā. To them, honorable Subhūti, I give the pleasure of the
                    boundless concentrations, so that they attain the state of Brahmā. After giving
                    them this, I cause them to enter into unsurpassed and perfect awakening.
                    Honorable Subhūti, there are beings keen for the pleasure of Śakra, to whom,
                    honorable Subhūti, I give the pleasure of Śakra. After giving them this, I cause
                    them to enter into unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Honorable Subhūti, there
                    are beings who are keen for the pleasures of the gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                    gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas, to whom, honorable
                    Subhūti, I give such pleasures. After giving them these, I cause them to enter
                    into unsurpassed and perfect awakening. <ref cRef="F.213.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-380"/> Honorable Subhūti, there are
                    beings who are keen for the pleasures of a universal monarch’s realm, while
                    others are keen for the pleasures of ministers, townsfolk, countrymen, priests,
                    and the members of the warrior, aristocratic, and commoner castes. There are
                    beings keen for the pleasures of forms, sounds, odors, tastes, and touch. There
                    are beings keen for the pleasures of flowers, fragrant substances, incense,
                    flower garlands, lotions, powders, parasols, victory banners, pennants, and
                    fans. There are beings keen for the pleasures of gold, silver, gems, pearls,
                    beryl, conches, crystal, red pearls, coral, emerald, cat’s eye, and many sorts
                    of precious substances. There are beings keen for the pleasures of the various
                    sounds of instruments, such as the large drum, clay drum, conch, gong, lute, and
                    flute. To those beings, honorable Subhūti, I grant all wishes, pleasures, and
                    amusements. After granting them these, I cause them to enter into unsurpassed
                    and perfect awakening.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-141"/>
                <p tid="144">“Elder sister,” said Subhūti, “the five sense pleasures are to be avoided up
                    until the path of the noble ones. Yet you guide others by giving them such
                    pleasures? This seems to be a contradiction in terms. However, elder sister,
                    although it is indeed difficult to guide others by means of those very things
                    that one should avoid until one is on the path of the noble ones, bodhisattva
                    great beings nevertheless do so. How amazing!” <ref type="bampo" cRef="B2"/>
                    </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-142"/>
                <p tid="145">At this point, two sons of merchants had gathered by the gate to listen to the
                    Dharma. Through her skillful ways of bringing pleasure to others, the lady had
                    already matured both of them for unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Now they
                    said to Venerable Subhūti, <ref cRef="F.213.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-381"/> “Honorable Subhūti, do not judge the
                    knowledge of bodhisattvas by your own knowledge. Why not? Tell us, honorable
                    Subhūti, can a small oil lamp be extinguished by the breath from one’s mouth or
                    by the draft caused by waving one’s hands or clothes?”</p>
                
                <p tid="146">“Sons of noble family, yes, the breath from one’s mouth or the draft caused by
                    waving one’s hands or clothes can extinguish a small oil lamp.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-144"/>
                <p tid="147">“Similarly, honorable Subhūti,” continued the two, “even a single desirous
                    thought eradicates the miniscule light of knowledge and merit of sons and
                    daughters of noble family who belong to the Hearers’ Vehicle. Now tell us,
                    honorable Subhūti, can the mass of the blazing apocalyptic fire be extinguished
                    by the Ganges river, filled with water?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-145"/>
                <p tid="148">“Sons of noble family, if it cannot be extinguished even by a hundred thousand
                    oceans, what need to mention the Ganges river, brimming with water?”</p>
                
                <p tid="149">“Likewise, honorable Subhūti,” they said, “the light of knowledge and merit of
                    bodhisattva great beings should be considered to be like that. Honorable
                    Subhūti, even if bodhisattva great beings were to frolic and enjoy themselves by
                    means of the five sense pleasures and were to engage in lovemaking for eons as
                    numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges river, the light of knowledge and
                    merit of those bodhisattvas could not be exhausted by that. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-147"/>
                <p tid="150">“It is like the following analogy, honorable Subhūti. In order to heal and
                    alleviate the illness of a poor person who is sick, a physician dispenses many
                    inexpensive medicines that are sweet, sour, salty, spicy, bitter, and
                    astringent. The sick person will then decide to take those medicines so that
                    they may experience relief. As the illness diminishes due to the medicines, they
                    finally regain their health. Similarly, honorable Subhūti, those who follow the
                    Hearers’ Vehicle <ref cRef="F.214.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-382"/> experience all sorts of suffering in terms of having
                    to endure ascetic practices, reducing their belongings, having few desires,
                    living in remote places, practicing modesty, and having few resources and little
                    to do. Having experienced such suffering, they eventually pass into nirvāṇa
                    without further grasping. By way of that instruction, honorable Subhūti, you
                    should understand that the liberation of those who follow the Hearers’ Vehicle
                    is like the healing of a poor person. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-148"/>
                <p tid="151">“To give another analogy, honorable Subhūti, consider the efforts to heal a king
                    of the royal caste upon whom royal authority has been conferred. When he falls
                    ill, a physician carefully concocts and proffers medicine worthy of a king;
                    medicine of the most excellent color, smell, and taste; medicine that is
                    delicious when ingested, and easy on the stomach. Thus, he proffers any and all
                    essential elixirs worthy of a king. Moreover, he offers flowers, fragrant
                    substances, incense, flower garlands, and lotions so that the king is not
                    displeased. Gathering appropriate musical instruments and cymbals, he offers
                    song. To the degree that the king is pleased in these various ways, he is
                    released from his illness. Similarly, honorable Subhūti, certain bodhisattvas,
                    being skilled in bringing pleasure to others, experience themselves all sorts of
                    pleasure and awaken to unsurpassed and perfect awakening by means of a vehicle
                    that brings all types of pleasure in its wake. There are indeed such
                    bodhisattvas. Through this explanation, honorable Subhūti, you should understand
                    that the bodhisattvas’ realization of wisdom is like the healing of a king.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-149"/>
                <p tid="152">“Furthermore, honorable Subhūti, the five sense pleasures are without root and
                    without location. And omniscience itself also has no root and no location.
                    <ref cRef="F.214.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-383"/> One with acceptance of this will naturally understand what to do and
                    what to avoid. Whoever has attained the acceptance of not focusing on the five
                    sense pleasures naturally understands what the correct and incorrect paths are
                    like. The five sense pleasures are empty, and so is omniscience. Thus, one with
                    such acceptance does not seek to drive away pleasures. However, he or she will
                    still condemn pleasures and not teach them.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-150"/>
                <p tid="153">Then Venerable Subhūti asked the two sons of merchants, “How did this elder
                    sister come to you two sons of noble family?” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-151"/>
                <p tid="154">At this point the two sons of merchants joined their palms and spoke the
                    following verses to Venerable Subhūti:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-152"/>
                <lg tid="155">
                    <l>“This is our father as well as our mother.</l>
                    <l>This is our best and closest friend.</l>
                    <l>This is our spouse and our support.</l>
                    <l>This is our unsurpassed teacher.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-153"/>
                <lg tid="156">
                    <l>“She, with her power,</l>
                    <l>Has brought about total liberation.</l>
                    <l>Possessed of thusness,</l>
                    <l>She has freed us from the bondage of suffering.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-154"/>
                <lg tid="157">
                    <l>“She reveals all teachings</l>
                    <l>And understands by way of all types of reasoning.</l>
                    <l>She bestowed pleasure upon the two of us,</l>
                    <l>And ushered us into the deathless state.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-155"/>
                <lg tid="158">
                    <l>“Like fish caught </l>
                    <l>With baited hooks,</l>
                    <l>She has skillfully snatched up the two of us</l>
                    <l>Through her manifold meritorious works.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-156"/>
                <lg tid="159">
                    <l>“Just as the effects of the poison of a venomous snake</l>
                    <l>Are allayed with poison,</l>
                    <l>Similarly, the poison of our passion</l>
                    <l>She has quelled with poison.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-157"/>
                <lg tid="160">
                    <l>“Just as a person burned by fire</l>
                    <l>Gains relief when warmed by fire,</l>
                    <l>Similarly, she has freed us from the scorching agony</l>
                    <l>Of our afflictions, by means of the afflictions.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-158"/>
                <lg tid="161">
                    <l>“We two have realized the sacred Dharma</l>
                    <l>And do not pursue desires.</l>
                    <l>Immature beings who pursue desires</l>
                    <l>Are not ones who desire awakening.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-159"/>
                <lg tid="162">
                    <l>“Those things taught to be worldly desires</l>
                    <l>Are like terrifying executioners;</l>
                    <l>Yet the realization of those very things <ref cRef="F.215.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-384"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Is the liberation of those who are wise.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-160"/>
                <p tid="163">Then Venerable Subhūti asked the lady, “Elder sister, is it the case that you
                    only tame sons of noble family through your skills in bringing pleasure to
                    others? Or do you also tame daughters of noble family?”</p>
                
                <p tid="164">“Honorable Subhūti, there is no sentient being I do not tame with my skills in
                    bringing pleasure to others. However, honorable Subhūti, since the minds of
                    women especially crave pleasure, most beings I have tamed skillfully by bringing
                    them pleasure are women.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-162"/>
                <p tid="165">“How is it, elder sister, that you tame women with a female form?”</p>
                
                <p tid="166">At that point, the lady took on the appearance of a twenty-two-year-old man,
                    dressed in fine, immaculate clothes, adorned with men’s jewelry, handsome and
                    pleasing to behold, with the most radiant complexion, and said, “It is with a
                    physical body such as this one, honorable Subhūti, that women are tamed.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-164"/>
                <p tid="167">Then Venerable Subhūti asked that noble son, “Are you a woman, or are you a
                    man?”</p>
                
                <p tid="168">“Honorable Subhūti,” came the response, “are you an ordinary being or a
                    learner?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-166"/>
                <p tid="169">“Noble son, I am not an ordinary being, nor am I a learner.”</p>
                
                <p tid="170">“So it is with me, honorable Subhūti—I am not a woman, nor am I a man.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-168"/>
                <p tid="171">“If you are neither man nor woman,” said Subhūti, “then how should I think of
                    you?”</p>
                
                <p tid="172">“If you, honorable Subhūti, are neither an ordinary being nor a learner, how
                    should I think of you?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-170"/>
                <p tid="173">Venerable Subhūti considered the matter, thinking, “Amazing! This bodhisattva has
                    profound knowledge! Whenever I ask a question, I am questioned in response.”
                    <ref cRef="F.215.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-385"/>
                    </p>
                
                <p tid="174">The noble son mentally investigated Venerable Subhūti’s mind and then said to
                    him, “Honorable Subhūti, you are irresolute and scared of questions. Do not be
                    scared of questions, honorable Subhūti.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-172"/>
                <p tid="175">“I am a worthy one, for whom defilements have been exhausted.”</p>
                
                <p tid="176">“Honorable Subhūti, which are the defilements that have been exhausted? Are they
                    those of the past, those of the future, or those in the present? If you say that
                    those of the past have been exhausted, any past exhaustion does not exist. Those
                    of the future have not yet come about; thus, they also cannot be exhausted.
                    Those in the present do not remain; so they, too, cannot be exhausted.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-174"/>
                <p tid="177">“Noble son,” replied Subhūti, “I am incapable of answering all these questions;
                    and, moreover, it is time for me to go for alms. Thus, I am going for alms,
                    before I run out of time.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-175"/>
                <p tid="178">At this point, the noble son entered the bodhisattvas’ absorption called
                        <distinct>showing all buddha realms</distinct>. As soon as the noble son
                    settled in that way, Venerable Subhūti beheld countless, innumerable buddha
                    realms. He saw that in some, the sun was just coming up. In some, the sun’s heat
                    was just beginning to be felt. In some, it was early morning. In some, it was
                    midmorning. In some, it was approaching midday. In some, it was time for the
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gaṇḍī</foreign> to be sounded. In
                    some, it was time for the early adjournment. In some, the adjournment had just
                    been completed.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-176"> Translation of these two last sentences is
                        tentative. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">la lar ni
                            snga ma bkad pa tsam / la lar ni bkad zin pa tsam</foreign>. Stok palace reads:
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">la lar ni snga ma bkod pa tsam /
                            la lar ni bkod zin pa tsam</foreign>.</note> In some, it was time to sit
                    and eat. In some, it was time to get up. In some, it was time to clean one’s
                    alms bowl. In some, it was early afternoon. In some, it was afternoon time. In
                    some, it was dusk. In some, it was midnight. In some, it was predawn.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-177"> Translation of this sentence is tentative. All witnesses read
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nam chung
                        ’khor/khor</foreign>.</note> In some, there was no moon or sun, but rather
                    an intrinsic radiance. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-178"/>
                <p tid="179">“Honorable Subhūti,” said the noble son to the elder Subhūti, <ref cRef="F.216.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-386"/> “at what
                    time do you take food? About what time is it now?”</p>
                
                <p tid="180">“Noble son,” said Subhūti, “I eat at this very time, but not at the times in the
                    other buddha realms.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-180"/>
                <p tid="181">Then that noble son moved the orb of the sun, which had by now moved to its
                    afternoon position, back to its midmorning position. Through such a miraculous
                    display, he was able to arrest the sun at its midmorning position.</p>
                
                <p tid="182">“Honorable Subhūti,” said the noble son to Venerable Subhūti, “now see what time
                    it has become.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-182"/>
                <p tid="183">Venerable Subhūti saw and believed, and he was no longer hasty. “Noble son,” he
                    asked, “tell me, what is your name?”</p>
                
                <p tid="184">“Honorable Subhūti,” replied the noble son, “what is my name to you? Or, ask the
                    Thus-Gone One himself, and he will answer you. Moreover, honorable Subhūti, all
                    names are non-names. And why is that? Because all names are imputations and
                    inauthentic. So how can one say, ‘Its name is <distinct>this</distinct>,’ with
                    respect to what is imputed and inauthentic?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-184"/>
                <p tid="185">Honorable Subhūti asked, “Is the name <distinct>omniscience</distinct> itself
                    also imputed and inauthentic?”</p>
                
                <p tid="186">“Indeed, honorable Subhūti. And why? Because omniscience also has various names
                    in different buddha realms.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-186"> Translated based on Choné, Lhasa, 
                        Lithang, Narthang, Kangxi, Yongle, and Stok Palace, which all
                        omit <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign> before <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mchis</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-187"/>
                <p tid="187">“Noble son, these various names of omniscience—what are they like?”</p>
                
                <p tid="188">“In some buddha realms, honorable Subhūti, omniscience is called
                        <distinct>power</distinct>. In some it is called
                        <distinct>gathering</distinct>, in some <distinct>illumination of
                        all</distinct>, in some <distinct>stainless</distinct>, in some
                        <distinct>teaching all meanings</distinct>, <ref cRef="F.216.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-387"/> in some
                        <distinct>without degeneration</distinct>, in some <distinct>making
                        offerings</distinct>, in some <distinct>directly perceiving</distinct>, in
                    some <distinct>holding coral</distinct>, in some <distinct>great
                        victory</distinct>, in some <distinct>great sound</distinct>, and in some
                        <distinct>boundless</distinct>. In this way, honorable Subhūti, the various
                    names for omniscience in different buddha realms cannot be fathomed. Similarly,
                    the various names for form, feeling, perception, formation, and consciousness
                    cannot be fathomed either. Likewise, the various names in different buddha
                    realms for the aggregates, elements, sense sources, applications of mindfulness,
                    authentic exertions, bases of miraculous power, faculties, powers, branches of
                    awakening, and the eight branches of the path of the noble ones also cannot be
                    fathomed. That being so, honorable Subhūti, through this explanation you should
                    understand that all names are non-names, and that they are imputed and
                    inauthentic in this way.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-189"/>
                <p tid="189">Then Venerable Subhūti said to the noble son, “Through the presence here of such
                    beings worthy of offerings, the priests and householders of Rājagṛha have
                    encountered fortunate circumstances.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-190"/>
                <p tid="190">“Honorable Subhūti,” asked the noble son, “do you know what characterizes beings
                    worthy of offerings in the world?”</p>
                
                <p tid="191">“I will explain, son of noble family, to the extent that I am confident to do so.
                    Those who observe discipline, who engage in virtue, and whose minds are without
                    confusion are beings worthy of offerings in the world.”</p>
                
                <p tid="192">“Honorable Subhūti, those you have described are not perfect objects of
                    offerings.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-193"/>
                <p tid="193">“Noble son, then what are perfect objects of offerings like?” <ref cRef="F.217.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-388"/>
                    </p>
                
                <p tid="194">“Honorable Subhūti, those in whom great love and great compassion for all beings
                    has arisen, but who do not observe any being whatsoever, are worthy of offerings
                    in the world. Those who do not interrupt the way of the Buddha, Dharma, and
                    Saṅgha are worthy of offerings in the world. Those who endeavor to eliminate the
                    afflictions of all beings are worthy of offerings in the world. Those who have
                    inexhaustible wisdom, inexhaustible knowledge, inexhaustible merit, and
                    inexhaustible eloquence are worthy of offerings in the world. Those who do not
                    associate with ordinary beings, but rather with noble ones, are worthy of
                    offerings in the world. Those completely pure individuals who see the wisdom of
                    beings, merely by seeing those beings, are worthy of offerings in the
                    world.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-195"/>
                <p tid="195">At the time, there was a god who had constantly followed the elder Subhūti, but
                    without gaining certainty. Hearing this teaching on those who are worthy of
                    offerings, he gave rise to the mind intent upon unsurpassed and perfect
                    awakening. He prostrated at the feet of Venerable Subhūti and begged his pardon,
                    saying, “Honorable Subhūti, I will no longer follow you.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-196"/>
                <p tid="196">“Celestial being, why are you begging pardon of honorable Subhūti?” inquired the
                    noble son.</p>
                
                <p tid="197">“Noble son, I have followed honorable Subhūti for twelve years. Yet never before
                    have I heard such a teaching about those who are worthy of offerings. For that
                    reason, as I heard this teaching about those who are worthy of offerings, I
                    formed a good motivation and gave rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and
                    perfect awakening. Thus, I now think that I should go anywhere I can to hear
                    such teachings that gather bodhisattvas who exemplify the pure state of those
                    worthy of offerings.” <ref cRef="F.217.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-389"/>
                    </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-198"/>
                <p tid="198">Venerable Subhūti rejoiced that the god had given rise to such a motivation, and
                    said to him, “Celestial being, you have found something excellent in mentally
                    bowing down to the vast qualities of the Buddha. My mind, celestial being, has
                    been injured with respect to omniscience. Now, since I am not a suitable vessel
                    for the qualities of the Buddha, there is nothing that can be done. Celestial
                    being, since my mind is not liberated, I too should surely give rise to the mind
                    set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Furthermore, celestial being, I
                    should constantly and uninterruptedly attend to a spiritual friend, just like
                    the holy being who is causing you to hear Dharma teachings you have not heard
                    before and not allowing those you have heard to go to waste.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-199"/>
                <p tid="199">Then the noble son said to the god, “Unsurpassed and perfect awakening is
                    difficult to attain, celestial being. One does not fully awaken merely by means
                    of the most basic preparations.”</p>
                
                <p tid="200">“Holy being,” replied the god, “unsurpassed and perfect awakening is indeed
                    difficult to attain. Nevertheless, I will, by any means, make my search
                    meaningful and accomplish it.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-201"/>
                <p tid="201">“How will you accomplish this, celestial being?”</p>
                
                <p tid="202">“I will accomplish it by being impartial toward all beings, by liberating all
                    beings from afflictions, by taking on the burden of the aggregates of all
                    beings, by bringing all beings to maturity, and by understanding all
                    suffering.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-203"/>
                <p tid="203">“Celestial being,” replied the noble son, “for one who conceives of beings, there
                    is no impartiality toward all beings. For one who conceives of afflictions,
                    there is no liberating all beings. For one who conceives of aggregates, there is
                    no taking on the burden of the aggregates of all beings. For one who imputes
                    roots of virtue, there is no bringing beings to maturity. <ref cRef="F.218.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-390"/> For one who
                    conceives of self and other, there is no understanding of all suffering.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-204"/>
                <p tid="204">At that point, through the teaching of these oral instructions, the god attained
                    acceptance with respect to all the concordant teachings. Then, in order to
                    venerate the noble son, the god scattered celestial flowers at the gate. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-205"/>
                <p tid="205">Next, Venerable Subhūti spoke to the god, saying, “Celestial being, I beg your
                    pardon as well, for having delighted in giving Dharma teachings of the hearers
                    without being aware of your motivation.”</p>
                
                <p tid="206">“Honorable Subhūti,” responded the god, “although I prostrate to you, do not
                    limit any sentient being. Do not teach the Dharma to any sentient being, whoever
                    they are, without first investigating their motivation. And what is the reason
                    for that? Honorable Subhūti, for one who longs for awakening, it would be better
                    not to have heard anything than to have listened to teachings belonging to the
                    Hearers’ Vehicle. It would be better, honorable Subhūti, for someone to have
                    gone hungry for a long time than to have eaten food mixed with poison.
                    Similarly, honorable Subhūti, for one who belongs to the Bodhisattvas’ Vehicle,
                    it would be better not to have heard anything than to have listened to the
                    teachings of the Hearers’ Vehicle.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-207"/>
                <p tid="207">Then the noble son once again took on a female appearance and complexion, just
                    like before, and said to Venerable Subhūti, “Please wait for a moment, honorable
                    Subhūti, until I offer you alms.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-208"/>
                <p tid="208">The lady entered her home, assembled some delicious food, and returned outside.
                    She then said to Venerable Subhūti, “Partake of these alms, honorable Subhūti,
                    but do not do so in a way that involves passion. Nor in a way that is divorced
                    from passion. Do not do so in a way that involves aggression. Neither do so in a
                    way that is divorced from aggression. Do not do so in a way that involves
                    delusion. Neither do so in a way that is divorced from delusion. Do not do so in
                    a way that involves afflictions. Neither do so in a way that is divorced from
                    afflictions. <ref cRef="F.218.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-391"/> </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-209"/>
                <p tid="209">“If honorable Subhūti has not understood suffering, has not relinquished its
                    origin, has not actualized cessation, and has not cultivated the path, then, in
                    that case, partake of these alms. If honorable Subhūti has not cultivated the
                    four applications of mindfulness, and has not cultivated the four authentic
                    exertions, four bases of miraculous power, five faculties, five powers, seven
                    branches of awakening, and eight branches of the path of the noble ones, then,
                    in that case, partake of these alms. If honorable Subhūti has also not disturbed
                    the transitory collection and if he has attained the path that has a sole
                    destination, then, in that case, partake of these alms. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-210"/>
                <p tid="210">“If honorable Subhūti has experienced liberation through knowing without
                    destroying ignorance; if he has experienced the unconditioned without bringing
                    about the exhaustion of the conditioned; if he has been liberated without
                    relying on the movement of consciousness; if he has transcended the three realms
                    without forming concepts regarding name and form; if he has meditated on
                    emptiness, which is a gateway to liberation, without indulging in the six sense
                    sources; if he has meditated on the absence of signs, which is a gateway to
                    liberation, without indulging in visual contact; if he has directly experienced
                    the absence of wishes, which is a gateway to liberation, without focusing on
                    sensation; if he has realized suchness without focusing on craving; if he has
                    understood the entirety of the absence of grasping without any thoughts of
                    grasping; if he has understood existence without anything arising; if he has
                    realized birth as non-birth; if he has realized old age and death to be
                    ineffable; and if he has realized all the links of existence to be like this,
                    then, in that case, partake of these alms. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-211"/>
                <p tid="211">“If honorable Subhūti has not beheld the Buddha, nor heard the Dharma, nor relied
                    upon the Saṅgha, then, in that case, partake of these alms. <ref cRef="F.219.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-392"/> If
                    honorable Subhūti has, by means of the sameness of the noble ones, realized the
                    sameness of ordinary beings, then, in that case, partake of these alms.
                    Honorable Subhūti, if you yourself neither go out of existence from this world
                    nor take birth in the next, then, in that case, partake of these alms. If
                    honorable Subhūti has realized the sameness of the absence of afflictions by
                    means of the sameness of passion, aggression, and delusion, and has also
                    realized the sameness of passion, aggression, and delusion by means of the
                    sameness of the absence of afflictions, then, in that case, partake of these
                    alms. If honorable Subhūti has not transcended the level of ordinary beings, nor
                    entered the level of noble ones, then, in that case, partake of these alms. If
                    honorable Subhūti neither appears nor is going to appear, has neither entered
                    saṃsāra nor attained nirvāṇa, and is one who speaks neither falsely nor truly,
                    then, in that case, partake of these alms. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-212"/>
                <p tid="212">“If honorable Subhūti has neither brought defilements to their extinction nor
                    stirred up what is not extinguished; if he engages in concentration free from
                    afflictions with neither wavering from the aggregates, elements, and sense
                    sources, nor indulging in them; and if he does not ever have wishes with respect
                    to anything at all, but has mentally gained understanding of phenomena, then, in
                    that case, partake of these alms. Honorable Subhūti, if you have not realized
                    the teaching of renunciates, then in that case, partake of these alms. Honorable
                    Subhūti, if Subhūti’s absence of afflictions and that of hell-beings are both of
                    the same worth, then, in that case, partake of these alms. <ref cRef="F.219.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-393"/> One would
                    deprecate the noble Subhūti by saying that whatever notions might be harbored
                    about someone being worthy of offerings, none of them would pertain, or apply,
                    to the honorable Subhūti. If, however, honorable Subhūti does have these
                    qualities, then in that case, partake of these alms.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-213"/>
                <p tid="213">As Venerable Subhūti prepared to leave the gate, he raised his right hand and
                    said, “Elder sister, those who speak truthfully will say that I possess such
                    qualities. In doing so, they describe me correctly.” Having said that, he took
                    up the alms.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-214"/>
                <p tid="214">“Excellent,” said the lady to Venerable Subhūti, “Those beings who are worthy of
                    offerings and who receive alms with sameness are indeed rare.”</p>
                
                <p tid="215">Venerable Subhūti said, “Those with excessive pride repudiate and belittle the
                    state of sameness. Doing so leads most of them to take birth in the hell
                    realms.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-216"/>
                <p tid="216">The god said to Venerable Subhūti, “What do you mean, honorable Subhūti, when you
                    say that most of those who repudiate and belittle this Dharma take birth in the
                    hell realms?” </p>
                
                <p tid="217">“Celestial being, consider this: Is it repudiation or belittling to say that some
                    illusory phenomenon has a cause or that it lacks a cause?”</p>
                
                <p tid="218">“No, it is not, honorable Subhūti.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-219"/>
                <p tid="219">“Similarly, celestial being, when all phenomena have been understood to be like
                    illusions, what is there for me to repudiate or belittle? Furthermore, celestial
                    being, the sounds expressed by all beings, whether true or untrue, are all the
                    same to me. Why is that? Because all expressions, due to their illusory essence,
                    are actually non-expressions.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-220"/>
                <p tid="220">When this teaching on receiving alms had been given, one hundred gods purified
                    the faultless and stainless eye of Dharma that beholds phenomena. </p>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-222"/>
                <p tid="222">Then the lady excused herself, saying to noble Subhūti, “Honorable Subhūti,
                    please have some food and then proceed to the Blessed One. <ref cRef="F.220.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-394"/> I, too,
                    will go there to listen to the Dharma.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-223"/>
                <p tid="223">Having taken up the alms, Venerable Subhūti departed from the city of Rājagṛha.
                    Delighted and overjoyed with the Dharma teaching he had heard, he did not
                    consider the food, but thought, “As I have taken up these alms, to whom can I
                    offer them without it being a downfall?”</p>
                
                <p tid="224">At that point the bodhisattva Not Grasping Any Phenomenon knew what Venerable
                    Subhūti was thinking. He went before him, prostrated with his head at Venerable
                    Subhūti’s feet, and said, “Please give me these alms, honorable Subhūti. If you
                    give them to me, it will not be a downfall.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-225"/>
                <p tid="225">“Noble son, are you one who has taken up discipline or one who adheres to
                    discipline?”</p>
                
                <p tid="226">“Honorable Subhūti, there is no phenomenon that can be taken up. Thus, there is
                    also no discipline. Nor is there faulty discipline. Moreover, honorable Subhūti,
                    I engage in killing, stealing, and sexual misconduct due to desire; I lie and
                    speak divisively; I speak harsh words and meaningless words; and I harbor
                    covetousness, ill will, and wrong views.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-227"/>
                <p tid="227">Venerable Subhūti thought, “Since a teaching such as this one has been given by
                    this noble son, there is no doubt that he is a bodhisattva whose progress toward
                    awakening is irreversible. I will ask him about the meaning behind this.” So
                    Venerable Subhūti said to the noble son, “What do you mean, noble son, when you
                    say, ‘I engage in killing, stealing, and sexual misconduct due to desire; I lie
                    <ref cRef="F.220.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-395"/> and speak divisively; I speak harsh words and meaningless words; and I
                    harbor covetousness, ill will, and wrong views’?”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-228"/>
                <p tid="228">The bodhisattva Not Grasping Any Phenomenon then spoke these verses in reply:</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-229"/>
                <lg tid="229">
                    <l>“I have trained in the unsurpassed path,</l>
                    <l>The path of awakening.</l>
                    <l>I have also established billions</l>
                    <l>Of beings on this path.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-230"/>
                <lg tid="230">
                    <l>“I destroy the individual being,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-231"> Here, “individual being”
                            translates the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srog</foreign>, which can also mean “life
                            force,” “vitality,” or “soul.”</note>
                        </l>
                    <l>And it is for that reason that I speak in this way. </l>
                    <l>Those who are trained on the path</l>
                    <l>Are known as <distinct>killers</distinct>.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-232"/>
                <lg tid="231">
                    <l>“The gods do not grant awakening;</l>
                    <l>Śakra and Brahmā do not bestow it.</l>
                    <l>That which was not given, I took</l>
                    <l>And thus I steal.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-233"/>
                <lg tid="232">
                    <l>“In order to benefit all living beings,</l>
                    <l>One takes up a suitable vehicle.</l>
                    <l>For that reason, the Great Vehicle</l>
                    <l>Has been <distinct>taken without being given</distinct>.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-235"/>
                <lg tid="233">
                    <l>“Fully knowing sexual misconduct</l>
                    <l>Is described as desiring the Dharma—this I know.</l>
                    <l>Such types of desire are not desire,</l>
                    <l>And hence I engage in what is <distinct>misconduct</distinct>.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-237"/>
                <lg tid="234">
                    <l>“All words are designations</l>
                    <l>That rightly have been taught to be false.</l>
                    <l>Since they do not exist, they are false;</l>
                    <l>And so, I also speak through <distinct>lies</distinct>.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-238"/>
                <lg tid="235">
                    <l>“There are those beings</l>
                    <l>Who long for the Lesser Vehicle;</l>
                    <l>In order to separate those beings from that vehicle,</l>
                    <l>I establish them in the Great Vehicle. </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-239"/>
                <lg tid="236">
                    <l>“With divisive speech I separate </l>
                    <l>Others who are tīrthikas.</l>
                    <l>Those who have strayed onto negative paths</l>
                    <l>I establish on the genuine path. </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-241"/>
                <lg tid="237">
                    <l>“I have defeated adversaries,</l>
                    <l>And they do not like it in the least.</l>
                    <l>Through speaking harsh words,</l>
                    <l>I have conquered all demons. </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-242"/>
                <lg tid="238">
                    <l>“I speak harsh words,</l>
                    <l>Yet my mind is without wrath.</l>
                    <l>In order to bring beings to maturity</l>
                    <l>I apply the methods of heroic beings.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-243"/>
                <lg tid="239">
                    <l>“I have understood words</l>
                    <l>And the intention behind those words.</l>
                    <l>Thus, with this in mind, I speak comprehensively,</l>
                    <l>And tame millions of beings.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-244"/>
                <lg tid="240">
                    <l>“To some I speak with consideration,</l>
                    <l>Yet some perceive it as lies. <ref cRef="F.221.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-396"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>Thus, as I speak with consideration,</l>
                    <l>I elicit direct understanding of the Dharma.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-245"> Translation of
                            this verse is tentative.</note>
                        </l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-246"/>
                <lg tid="241">
                    <l>“All beings without exception,</l>
                    <l>Each and every one of them,</l>
                    <l>Experience covetousness and crave</l>
                    <l>The pleasures of the nonhuman gods in the world.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-247"/>
                <lg tid="242">
                    <l>“Whoever possesses this pleasure</l>
                    <l>Becomes a benevolent guardian of the world.</l>
                    <l>Thus, wise ones are covetous in wishing</l>
                    <l>That all beings may have such happiness.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-248"/>
                <lg tid="243">
                    <l>“Saying ‘May all beings be victorious!’</l>
                    <l>Wise beings are perpetually covetous.</l>
                    <l>Since covetousness is like that,</l>
                    <l>I also claim to be <distinct>covetous</distinct>.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-249"/>
                <lg tid="244">
                    <l>“At the time when the sacred Dharma is perishing,</l>
                    <l>Mighty beings put an end to that decline.</l>
                    <l>They forgo their own happiness,</l>
                    <l>And do not abandon the Dharma, nor living beings.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-250"/>
                <lg tid="245">
                    <l>“There are those who display ill will</l>
                    <l>In order to bring into harmony</l>
                    <l>All fighting in the world</l>
                    <l>And all disagreement among beings.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-251"/>
                <lg tid="246">
                    <l>“If one were to quarrel with them for an eon,</l>
                    <l>Or even for millions of eons,</l>
                    <l>They would not abandon the sacred Dharma,</l>
                    <l>Nor turn their back in any way.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-252"/>
                <lg tid="247">
                    <l>“Those who are brave with respect to wrong views</l>
                    <l>Are equanimous toward everything conditioned.</l>
                    <l>They understand wrong views,</l>
                    <l>And comprehend authentic views.</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-253"/>
                <lg tid="248">
                    <l>“Whoever possesses such qualities</l>
                    <l>Adheres to a variety of disciplines.</l>
                    <l>Adhering where there is nothing to adhere to,</l>
                    <l>Wise ones realize awakening.”</l>
                </lg>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-254"/>
                <p tid="249">Thereupon, Venerable Subhūti offered the alms to that noble son, saying, “Such
                    holy beings do not cause downfalls through alms offered with faith.” Thus,
                    Venerable Subhūti did not eat. In the afternoon, he rose from his inner
                    absorption and went before the Blessed One. He prostrated with his head at the
                    Blessed One’s feet and then recounted to the Blessed One all that had
                    happened.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-255"/>
                <p tid="250">“Subhūti, do you know who that bodhisattva was?” asked the Blessed One.</p>
                
                <p tid="251">“Blessed One, I do not know.” <ref cRef="F.221.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-397"/>
                    </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-257"/>
                <p tid="252">“Subhūti, that bodhisattva great being is called Strīvivarta. She tames beings by
                    skillfully bringing them pleasure. To give an analogy, Subhūti, consider a
                    chariot filled with two hundred Magadha bushels of mustard seeds. Now, if every
                    hundred years one were to remove a single mustard seed from that chariot, one
                    would soon determine how many mustard seeds fit in such a chariot. However, that
                    is not the case for the beings in this Sahā world system whom the bodhisattva
                    Strīvivarta has brought to maturity in unsurpassed and perfect awakening by
                    skillfully bringing them pleasure; nor is it the case for the many beings she
                    has established in births as gods or humans.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-258"/>
                <p tid="253">Then the lady, with five hundred women surrounding and preceding her, left the
                    city of Rājagṛha and went before the Blessed One at Vulture Peak Mountain. The
                    Blessed One saw at a great distance that the lady was approaching, and he asked
                    Venerable Subhūti, “Subhūti, do you see these five hundred women that are coming
                    this way?”</p>
                
                <p tid="254">“I see them, Blessed One.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-260"/>
                <p tid="255">“The bodhisattva Strīvivarta has brought every single one of them to maturity and
                    established them in unsurpassable and perfect awakening by skillfully bringing
                    them pleasure.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-261"/>
                <p tid="256">Strīvivarta, surrounded by the five hundred women, went before the Blessed One.
                    She prostrated, placing her head at the Blessed One’s feet, and sat to one side.
                    Venerable Subhūti greeted the lady, joining his palms and paying homage. Then
                    Venerable Śāriputra asked Venerable Subhūti, “Venerable Subhūti, why are you
                    paying homage to a woman who has neither the qualities nor the body of a noble
                    one?”</p>
                
                <p tid="257">“Elder Śāriputra,” responded the lady, “if you know who in this world is a noble
                    being <ref cRef="F.222.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-398"/> and who is not, please do tell us.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-263"/>
                <p tid="258">“Elder sister,” said elder Śāriputra, “do you know who in this world is a noble
                    being and who is not?”</p>
                
                <p tid="259">“Yes, honorable Śāriputra, I do.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-265"/>
                <p tid="260">“Which ones are they?”</p>
                
                <p tid="261">“Those who do not sever the lineage of the noble ones, honorable Śāriputra, are
                    noble beings. Those who do not sever the lineages of the Buddha, Dharma, and
                    Saṅgha are noble beings. Noble beings are those who love other noble beings and
                    seek liberation for those who are not noble beings. Moreover, honorable
                    Śāriputra, a woman—elegantly adorned with jewelry, dressed in fine, immaculate
                    clothes, beautified by powders, fragrances, flower garlands, and lotions, and
                    pleasing to the five senses—whose mind is not divorced from the state of
                    omniscience is far preferable to a worthy one who remains isolated and engages
                    in concentration on the eight liberations. Honorable Śāriputra, in order to
                    communicate this very meaning, I will give you an analogy. Now tell me,
                    honorable Śāriputra, would you put a trinket in a container of beryl? Or would
                    you put a priceless jewel in a cesspit?”</p>
                
                <p tid="262">“Elder sister,” replied elder Śāriputra, “neither would I put a priceless jewel
                    in a cesspit, nor would I put a trinket in a container of beryl.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-268"/>
                <p tid="263">“Likewise, honorable Śāriputra, a woman who is pleasing to the five senses and
                    whose mind is not divorced from the state of omniscience is far superior to a
                    worthy one who remains isolated and engages in concentration on the eight
                    liberations.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-269"/>
                <p tid="264">“Elder sister,” asked Venerable Śāriputra, “have you truly entered into the Great
                    Vehicle?”</p>
                
                <p tid="265">“Honorable Śāriputra, in the Great Vehicle <ref cRef="F.222.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-399"/> there is nowhere at all to
                    be, nor is there anything to withdraw from.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-271"/>
                <p tid="266">“Elder sister, if you do not abide anywhere at all within the Great Vehicle, and
                    if, moreover, there is nothing to withdraw from, then what do those who enter
                    into the Great Vehicle enter into?”</p>
                
                <p tid="267">“Honorable Śāriputra, followers of the Great Vehicle do not abide anywhere at
                    all. They do not abide in order to bring about the exhaustion of ignorance up
                    through old age and death. How is that? Honorable Śāriputra, it is because
                    ignorance up through old age and death are inexhaustible. Therefore, they do not
                    arise, nor do they cease. If they arose, then they would also come to an end.
                    However, since they do not arise, they also do not come to an end. Consequently,
                    they are inexhaustible and unborn. The Dharma of mendicants is unarisen. That
                    being so, honorable Śāriputra, that which is dependently originated is unarisen
                    and unceasing.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-273"/>
                <p tid="268">Venerable Śāriputra said to the lady, “Elder sister, as you are worthy of the
                    homage of the world with its gods, as well as of the hearers and solitary
                    buddhas, what need is there to mention the homage of Venerable Subhūti?” </p>
                
                <p tid="269">Venerable Śāriputra then said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, is there any
                    person who can appraise others? This elder sister, elegantly adorned with
                    jewelry, speaks with perfect eloquence.”</p>
                
                <p tid="270">“Honorable Śāriputra,” replied the lady, “I am not confident because of my
                    jewelry.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-276"/>
                <p tid="271">“Well then, what kind of confidence do you have?”</p>
                
                <p tid="272">“Honorable Śāriputra, there are eight ornaments of bodhisattvas, which are as
                    follows: the ornament of not forgetting the mind of awakening; the ornament of
                    maintaining the good motivation of great compassion; the ornament of being
                    without animosity toward any sentient being; the ornament of being insatiable
                    when it comes to seeking out Dharma teachings; the ornament of proper
                    investigation and analysis of the Dharma teachings that one has heard <ref cRef="F.223.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-400"/>
                    and mastered; the ornament of bringing beings to full maturity without observing
                    any phenomenon; the ornament of wisdom that ascertains the profound Dharma and
                    knows dependent origination, as well as the various <term type="ignore">faculties</term> of beings; and the
                    ornament of the Buddha’s blessing and skill in means. Honorable Śāriputra, these
                    are the eight ornaments. A bodhisattva bedecked with these ornaments has
                    unimpeded confidence.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-278"/>
                <p tid="273">Venerable Śāriputra asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, where did this elder
                    sister die before she was born here?” </p>
                
                <p tid="274">At this point the lady emanated a woman with a body exactly like her own in front
                    of Venerable Śāriputra and told him, “Ask this lady, honorable Śāriputra, where
                    she died before she was born here.”</p>
                
                <p tid="275">“This lady is an emanation,” replied elder Śāriputra. “Emanations do not die, nor
                    are they born.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-281"/>
                <p tid="276">“Similarly, honorable Śāriputra, the Thus-Gone One has fully awakened to the fact
                    that all phenomena are essentially emanations. Do not ask questions about the
                    death and birth of those who understand all phenomena to be essentially
                    emanations.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-282"/>
                <p tid="277">“Śāriputra,” said the Blessed One, “this is the bodhisattva great being
                    Strīvivarta. After she died in Manifest Joy, the buddha realm of the Thus-Gone
                    One Akṣobhya, she came here to bring beings to full maturity. Śāriputra, in this
                    Sahā world system the bodhisattva Strīvivarta has ripened countless, innumerable
                    beings into unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-283"/>
                <p tid="278">At this point the bodhisattva Strīvivarta, <ref cRef="F.223.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-401"/> in her female form,
                    prostrated with her head at the feet of the Blessed One and said, “Until I
                    receive a prophecy regarding my unsurpassed and perfect awakening, and until I
                    no longer have this female body but rather a male body, I will not rise from the
                    Blessed One’s feet.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-284"/>
                <p tid="279">The five hundred women also prostrated with their heads at the feet of the
                    Blessed One and said, “Blessed One, we, too, will not rise until our nature
                    changes from female to male, and until a prophecy is given regarding our
                    unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-285"/>
                <p tid="280">The Blessed One smiled. As happens when blessed buddhas smile, the following
                    occurred: instantly, many different kinds of light rays emerged from the Blessed
                    One’s mouth; they were blue, yellow, red, white, crimson, crystal, and
                    silver-colored. The light pervaded boundless and infinite world systems,
                    reaching as far as the Brahmā realm, then returned and disappeared into the crown
                    of the Blessed One’s head.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-286"/>
                <p tid="281">Venerable Ānanda arose from his seat, draped his robe over one shoulder, bowed
                    with joined palms to the Blessed One, and said to him, “Blessed One, the
                    thus-gone ones do not smile without causes and conditions. That being so, what
                    is the cause of your smile, and what are its conditions?”</p>
                
                <p tid="282">“Ānanda,” replied the Blessed One, “did you see the bodhisattva Strīvivarta,
                    surrounded by five hundred women, touching the Thus-Gone One’s feet?”</p>
                
                <p tid="283">“I did, Blessed One.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-289"/>
                <p tid="284">“Ānanda,” continued the Blessed One, <ref cRef="F.224.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-402"/> “incalculable eons from now, this
                    bodhisattva Strīvivarta will fully awaken to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood.
                    In the world she will be known as the thus-gone, worthy, and perfect Buddha
                    Eloquent King of Qualities. When she attains awakening, each of these five
                    hundred women will attain retention, possess unimpeded eloquence, and become a
                    bodhisattva adorned with the eight ornaments described by the bodhisattva great
                    being Strīvivarta in her teaching on the ornaments of good qualities. The
                    Thus-Gone One Eloquent King of Qualities will prophesy the unsurpassed and
                    perfect awakening of those bodhisattvas. Moreover, Ānanda, the buddha realm of
                    the Thus-Gone One Eloquent King of Qualities will be rich and vast, and filled
                    with happiness, good harvests, humans, and many other beings, such that its
                    resources will equal those of the gods in the Heaven of Joy. In that buddha
                    realm, not even the word <distinct>woman</distinct> will exist. Everyone will
                    take miraculous births from the hearts of lotuses. Seated cross-legged, they
                    will be pure and celibate, and will be adorned with those eight ornaments.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-290"/>
                <p tid="285">As they heard the Blessed One’s clear prophesy, the bodhisattva Strīvivarta and
                    the five hundred women, totally delighted and overjoyed, rose up into the sky to
                    the height of seven palm trees. As soon as that happened, they all took on the
                    appearance of sixteen-year-old boys. Descending from the sky, they prostrated to
                    the Blessed One, and the Thus-Gone One placed his hand on the crowns of their
                    heads. Immediately, they all attained retention and the absorption called
                        <distinct>complete illumination</distinct>. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-291"/>
                <p tid="286">The Blessed One said to venerable Ānanda, <ref cRef="F.224.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-403"/> “Remember this Dharma
                    teaching, Ānanda, and teach it correctly and extensively to others.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-292"/>
                <p tid="287">“Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma teaching? How should it be
                    known?”</p>
                
                <p tid="288">“Ānanda,” spoke the Blessed One, “you should remember this Dharma teaching as
                        <distinct>The Ornament That Brings About Eloquence</distinct>. You can also
                    remember it as <distinct>The Prophecy Concerning Strīvivarta</distinct>.”</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-294"/>
                <p tid="289">When the Blessed One had said this, the bodhisattva great being Strīvivarta
                    together with her retinue, venerable Ānanda and the great hearers, the
                    bodhisattvas, and the world with its gods, nāgas, asuras, and gandharvas
                    rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-295"/>
                <trailer tid="290">This completes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra “The Prophecy Concerning
                    Strīvivarta.”</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="291">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-296"/>
                    <p tid="292">This was translated, proofed, and finalized by the Indian preceptors
                        Prajñāvarman and Śīlendrabodhi, together with the translator-editor Bandé
                        Yeshé Dé and others.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="293">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="295">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-listBibl-1"> 
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-350">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bud med ’gyur ba lung bstan pa zhes bya ba
                        theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 190, Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde,
                    tsa), folios 201.a–224.b.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-351">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bud med ’gyur ba lung bstan pa zhes bya ba
                        theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative
                    Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan
                    dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
                    Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang
                    (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 61, pp. 542–98.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-352">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bud med ’gyur ba lung bstan pa zhes bya ba
                        theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Stok Palace Kangyur vol. 74 (mdo sde, ’a),
                    folios 199.a–232.b.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-353">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan dkar gyi chos ’gyur ro cog gi
                    dkar chag</title> [Denkarma]<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html"/>. Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs,
                    jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-418">Braarvig, Jens Erland, trans. <title xml:lang="en">
                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh96.html">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</ref>
                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­vikrīḍita</title>, Toh 96). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha,
                        2020.</bibl>
                    
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-407">Karma Gyaltsen Ling Translation Group, trans. <title xml:lang="en">
                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh84.html">The Questions of the Girl Vimalaśraddhā</ref>
                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dārikā­vimala­śraddhā­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title>, Toh 84). 84000: Translating the Words of
                        the Buddha, 2021.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-354">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein
                        früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>.
                    Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-419">Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy Division), trans. <title xml:lang="en">
                        <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh171.html">The Questions of an Old Lady</ref>
                    </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahallikā­paripṛcchā</title>, Toh 171). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha,
                        2011.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-355">Schuster, Nancy. “Yoga-Master Dharmamitra and Clerical Misogyny in Fifth Century
                    Buddhism.” In <title xml:lang="en">The Tibet Journal</title>, vol. 9, no. 4, 1984, pp. 33–46. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-010-437">Subhashita Translation Group, trans. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh192.html">The Prophecy of Kṣemavatī</ref>
                        </title> (Toh 192). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2022.</bibl>                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-304">
                            <term>mendicant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāmaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Sanskrit term literally means “one who
                                toils,” i.e., an ascetic, and the term is applied to spiritual
                                renunciants or monks, whether Buddhist or otherwise.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-305">
                            <term>aggregate</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">skandha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The fivefold basic grouping of the components
                                out of which the world and the individual self are formed.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-306">
                            <term>elements</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world
                                in terms of eighteen elements: eye, form, and eye consciousness;
                                ear, sound, and ear consciousness; nose, odor, and nose
                                consciousness; tongue, taste, and tongue consciousness; body, touch,
                                and body consciousness; mind, mental objects, and mind
                                consciousness. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-307">
                            <term>sense sources</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                The six “inner” senses (eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind), and their respective six “outer” objects 
                                of forms, sounds, odors, tastes, touch, and mental objects, are sometimes called collectively the “six sense 
                                sources,” but are also sometimes taken as two separate groups, making twelve.
                            </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-308">
                            <term>four applications of mindfulness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa nye bar gzhag pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ་བཞི།</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catvāri smṛtyupasthāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mindfulness of the body, feelings, the mind, and
                                phenomena. These four are part of the thirty-seven factors of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-309">
                            <term>authentic exertions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag par spong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པར་སྤོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyakprahāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Relinquishing negative acts in the present and
                                the future and enhancing positive acts in the present and the
                                future. These four are part of the thirty-seven factors of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-310">
                            <term>bases of miraculous power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">Determination, discernment, diligence, and
                                concentration. These four are part of the thirty-seven factors of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-311">
                            <term>faculties</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Faith, diligence, mindfulness, absorption, and
                                wisdom. These five are part of the thirty-seven factors of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-061-010-312" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>five powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs lnga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañca­bala</term>
                            <term type="alternative">powers</term>
                            <term type="definition">The powers of faith, diligence, mindfulness, absorption, and wisdom. These five are part of the thirty-seven factors of awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-313">
                            <term>branches of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyaṅga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mindfulness, discrimination, diligence, joy,
                                pliancy, absorption, and equanimity. These seven are part of the
                                thirty-seven factors of awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-314">
                            <term>eight branches of the path of the noble ones </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa’i lam yan lag brgyad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པའི་ལམ་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད་པ།</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāṣṭāṅga­mārga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Correct view, intention, speech, action,
                                livelihood, effort, mindfulness, and absorption. These eight are part
                                of the thirty-seven factors of awakening.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">path of the noble ones</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-315">
                            <term>eight liberations </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> rnam par thar pa brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པ་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭavimokṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The liberation of form observing form, the
                                liberation of the formless observing form, the liberation of
                                observing beauty, the liberation of infinite space, the liberation
                                of infinite consciousness, the liberation of nothing whatsoever, the
                                liberation of neither presence nor absence of perception, and the
                                liberation of cessation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-316">
                            <term>gaṇḍī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gaN+DI</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཎྜཱི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇḍī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇḍi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An elongated, shoulder-held wooden bar (or beam)
                                struck with a wooden striker to call the saṅgha community to
                                assembly.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-317">
                            <term>inner absorption</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang du yang dag ’jog pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃlayana</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term can mean both physical seclusion and a
                                meditative state of withdrawal. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-319">
                            <term>Strīvivarta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bud med ’gyur ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བུད་མེད་འགྱུར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Strīvivarta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A female bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-320">
                            <term>Nimindhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu khyud ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་ཁྱུད་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nimindhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-321">
                            <term>Dharaṇīdhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharaṇīdhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-322">
                            <term>Terrace Holder </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bang rim ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བང་རིམ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-323">
                            <term>Holder of the Family of Offering and Giving </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod sbyin rus ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་སྦྱིན་རུས་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-324">
                            <term>Illuminating Intelligence </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snang ba’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྣང་བའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-325">
                            <term>Completely Pure Intelligence </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par dag pa’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་དག་པའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-326">
                            <term>Purified Intelligence </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyangs pa’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱངས་པའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-327">
                            <term>Viśeṣamati </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khyad par blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁྱད་པར་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viśeṣamati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-328">
                            <term>Anantamati </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་ཡས་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anantamati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-329">
                            <term>Vardhamānamati </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phel ba’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕེལ་བའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vardhamānamati</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-330">
                            <term>Priyadarśana </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthong dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐོང་དགའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Priyadarśana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-331">
                            <term>Sudarśana </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs mthong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེགས་མཐོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sudarśana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-332">
                            <term>Surūpa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cher snang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆེར་སྣང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-333">
                            <term>Seeing All Meanings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">don kun mthong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དོན་ཀུན་མཐོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-334">
                            <term>Maitreya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-335">
                            <term>Subhūti </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་འབྱོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his profound understanding of emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-336">
                            <term>Not Grasping Any Phenomenon </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos thams cad mi len pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་ལེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-337">
                            <term>Akṣobhya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’khrugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཁྲུགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha in the realm of Manifest Joy.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-338">
                            <term>Ānanda </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha’s cousin and principal
                                attendant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-339">
                            <term>Eloquent King of Qualities </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yon tan gyi rgyal po spobs pa can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོན་ཏན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་སྤོབས་པ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha that the female bodhisattva
                                Strīvivarta will one day become.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-340">
                            <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pradz+nyA barma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པྲཛྙཱ་བརྨ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian preceptor resident in Tibet during the
                                late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-341">
                            <term>Śīlendrabodhi </term>
                        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shI len+d+ra bo d+hi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱི་ལེནྡྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śīlendrabodhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian preceptor resident in Tibet during the
                                late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-342">
                            <term>Bandé Yeshé Dé </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ban de ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">Yeshé Dé </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-344">
                            <term>Rājagṛha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha </term>
                            <term type="definition">The capital of the ancient kingdom of
                                Magadha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-345">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhra­kūṭa­parvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mountain where many Great Vehicle teachings
                                were delivered by the Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-346">
                            <term>Sahā world system </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed kyi ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sahālokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The present world in which we live.</term>
                        <term type="alternative">Sahā World</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-347">
                            <term>Manifest Joy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par dga’ ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhirati</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha realm of the Buddha Akṣobhya.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-348">
                            <term>Brahmā realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa’i ’jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmaloka</term>
                        <term type="definition">The heaven of Brahmā, the god who rules the Sahā World.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-349">
                            <term>Heaven of Joy </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tuṣita</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six heavens in the desire
                                realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--ADDED-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-404">
                            <term>tīrthika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu stegs can</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthika</term>
                            <term type="definition">Religious or philosophical orders that were
                                contemporary with the early Buddhist order. Initially, the
                                term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthika</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthya</foreign> may have referred to
                                non-brahmanic ascetic orders.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-405">
                            <term>thirty-seven factors of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi phyogs kyi chos sum cu rtsa bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sapta­triṃśad­bodhi­pakṣa­dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Thirty-seven practices or qualities that lead the practitioner to the awakened state: the
                                four applications of mindfulness, the four authentic exertions, the four bases of miraculous
                                power, the five faculties, the five powers, the eight branches of the path of the noble ones, and the seven branches of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-422">
                            <term>prātimokṣa vows</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so so thar pa’i sdom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་སོ་ཐར་པའི་སྡོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātimokśasaṃvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">The vows of moral discipline which are followed by monks and nuns.
                                The term “<term type="ignore">prātimokṣa</term>” can be used to refer both to the disciplinary rules themselves and to the texts from the Vinaya that contain them.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">prātimokṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-423">
                        <term>thus-gone one</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                        <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
                        <term type="definition">A frequently used synonym for a buddha. The expression is interpreted in different ways, 
                            but in general it implies one who has arrived at, or gone to, the ultimate state. When spelled with a capital letter it refers to Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        <term type="alternative">thus-gone</term>
                    </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-424">
                            <term>suchness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ultimate nature of things, or the way things are in reality, as opposed to the way they appear
                                to unawakened beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-425">
                            <term>five extraordinary abilities</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par shes pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcābhijñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Five extraordinary abilities that result from
                                meditative concentration: divine sight, divine hearing, knowing
                                others’ minds, recollecting past lives, and the ability to perform
                                miracles.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-426">
                            <term>four continents</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gling bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གླིང་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturdvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">According to traditional Indian cosmology, our own Sahā world system is said to comprise four continents, namely, Pūrvavideha in the east, Jambudvīpa in the
                                south, Aparagodānīya in the west, and Uttarakuru in the north. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-427">
                            <term>universal monarch</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor los sgyur ba’i rgyal po</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravartin</term>
                            <term type="definition">The term “<term type="ignore">universal monarch</term>” denotes a just and pious king who rules
                                over the universe according to the laws of Dharma. Such a monarch is called a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cakravartin</foreign> because he wields a disk (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cakra</foreign>) that rolls
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vartana</foreign>) over continents, worlds, and world systems, bringing
                                them under his power. A universal monarch is often considered the worldly, political correlate of a buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-061-010-428" type="person" mode="match">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the gods. Also known as Indra, the deity who is called “Lord of the Gods” dwells on the summit of Mount Meru and wields the thunderbolt. The Tibetan translation <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brgya byin</foreign> (meaning “one hundred sacrifices”) follows the traditional Sanskrit semantic gloss that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śakra</foreign> is an abbreviation of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śata-kratu</foreign>, one who has performed a hundred sacrifices. Each world with a central Meru has a Śakra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-061-010-429" type="person" mode="match">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high-ranking deity, presiding over a divine world where other beings consider him the creator; he is also considered to be the “Lord of the Sahā World” (our universe).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-430">
                            <term>solitary buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One who has attained liberation entirely through
                                their own contemplation as a result of progress in previous lives
                                but, unlike a buddha, does not have the accumulated merit and
                                motivation to teach others.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-431">
                            <term>realm of the Four Great Kings</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal chen bzhi’i ris </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་ཆེན་བཞིའི་རིས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cāturmahā­rājakāyika</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the heavens of Buddhist cosmology, lowest
                                among the six heavens of the desire realm. Dwelling place of the
                                Four Great Kings, traditionally located on a terrace of Mount Meru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-432">
                            <term>Mount Meru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Meru</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Buddhist cosmology, the sacred mountain at the center of the world.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-433">
                            <term>dependent origination</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rten cing ’brel par ’byung ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟེན་ཅིང་འབྲེལ་པར་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratītya­samutpāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The relative nature of phenomena, which arises in dependence on causes and conditions. Together
                                with the four truths of the noble ones, this was one of the first teachings given by the Buddha.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">dependently originated</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-434">
                        <term>hearer</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                        <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                        <term type="definition">A follower of those teachings of the Buddha that focus on the monastic
                            lifestyle and liberating oneself from suffering, in contrast to followers of the
                            Bodhisattva Vehicle who seek buddhahood for the sake of all beings.</term>
                    </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-010-435">
                            <term>worthy one</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">A person who has been liberated from saṃsāra. Also used to refer specifically to a person who has accomplished the final fruition of the path of the hearers.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>