<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">གླང་པོའི་རྩལ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Strength of the Elephant</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">གླང་པོའི་རྩལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>    
                    <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Great Vehicle Sūtra “The Strength of the Elephant”</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-7">Translated by the Buddhavacana Translation Group<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-262">David Higgins</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-31">Casey Kemp</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-32">Dennis Johnson</consultant>
    <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-139">Dr. John Canti</editor>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-27">Gregory Forgues</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-32">Dennis Johnson</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-28">Khenpo Konchok Tamphel</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1.15 <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the
                    Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the
                        protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0
                        copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for
                        commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons
                        license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-062-007"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the
                    standard logic.</note>
                <date>2020-06-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh207" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 207</ref>
                        <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, tsha), folios 95.a–109.b</biblScope>
                     <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="29">
                        <volume number="62" start-page="189" end-page="217"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11840" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2023-01-18T16:58:48.496Z" user="celso">18/01/2023 16:58:48</note>

                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-01-27T13:17:18.972Z" user="mike">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2020-03-16T10:22:58.96Z" user="line-tofte">2.f</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-03-17T14:28:23.763Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2020-03-17T14:31:03.663Z" user="line-tofte">2.f</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-03-26T11:34:57.537Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2020-04-16T08:45:06.587Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2020-05-20T13:55:45.519Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-05-20T14:58:23.405Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
            
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2020-05-22T05:56:48.685Z" user="mike">v 0.0.1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2020-05-22T05:56:48.685Z" user="mike">2</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.2" date-time="2020-05-22T06:31:09.619Z" user="mike">sponsor statement removed</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.1" date-time="2020-06-02T14:59:08.235Z" user="john">First published version.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2020-06-02T14:59:26.203Z" user="john">1</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.2" date-time="2020-06-02T15:00:08.202Z" user="john">v 1.1.2</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.3" date-time="2020-07-07T05:14:17.873Z" user="mike">Wiesiek typo corrected</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.4" date-time="2020-07-08T05:53:37.672Z" user="mike">typo corrected in intro</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.5" date-time="2020-07-15T15:37:54.525Z" user="celso">Updated the milestones to only be child of &lt;item&gt;s and never &lt;list&gt; following schema update.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.6" date-time="2020-08-19T10:00:38.153Z" user="john">Minor correction.</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.7" date-time="2020-10-28T19:59:19.063Z" user="celso">fixed small typo in bibliography entry</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.8" date-time="2020-11-18T18:36:54.228Z" user="laura">A few minor corrections to glossary</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.9" date-time="2020-11-23T13:57:44.998Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.0.0)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.10" date-time="2020-11-25T15:47:37.581Z" user="celso">Updated pending links</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.11" date-time="2020-12-11T14:06:50.919Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.1.5)</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.12" date-time="2021-01-15T06:40:51.575Z" user="mike">1.1.12</note>    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.13" date-time="2022-06-27T10:06:48.1Z" user="admin">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.14" date-time="2023-01-16T16:58:52.361Z" user="celso">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.1.15" date-time="2023-01-18T16:58:06.914Z" user="celso">Auto (remove-tid-from-back-list-items)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
                 <front>
                        <div type="summary">
                                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-238"/>
                                <p tid="229">This sūtra contains a Dharma discourse on the profound insight into the 
                                        emptiness of all phenomena, also known as transcendent insight. Following
                                        a short teaching in verse by Śāriputra, the Buddha delivers 
                                        the primary discourse at the behest of Ānanda and Mañjuśrī amid a 
                                        vast assembly of monks, bodhisattvas, and lay 
                                        devotees. He specifically addresses hearers and so-called “outcast
                                        bodhisattvas” who have not realized transcendent insight and who thus 
                                        remain attached to phenomenal appearances. Responding to a series of
                                        questions posed by Mañjuśrī and Śāriputra, the Buddha explains that all 
                                        phenomena are as empty as space, with nothing to be either affirmed or
                                        rejected. Yet that very emptiness is what makes everything possible, including 
                                        the bodhisattvas’ altruistic activities. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="acknowledgment">
                                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="2">Acknowledgements</head>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-239"/>
                                <p tid="230">Translation by the Buddhavacana Translation Group. Translated from the 
                                        Tibetan of the Degé Kangyur by Gregory 
                                        Forgues in collaboration with Dennis Johnson and Khenpo Konchok Tamphel. The English
                                        was edited by Casey Kemp. </p>
                                <p tid="4">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: 
                                        Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="introduction">
                                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-introduction-1">
                                        <head type="section" tid="6">Setting and Storyline</head>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-1"/>
                                        <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Strength of the Elephant</title> is set on Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain where the Buddha presides
                                                over a large assembly of monks and bodhisattvas. One afternoon, after the Buddha is addressed by 
                                                Śāradvatīputra with a brief discourse on the empty nature of all phenomena, he convenes a large audience
                                                of monks, bodhisattvas, and people from the city of Rājagṛha to share Śāradvatīputra’s insight. The Buddha
                                                proceeds to inform Mañjuśrī and the others that previous buddhas have also taught this Dharma discourse on
                                                transcendent insight, which is “like the strength of the elephant,” on Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain, the very place
                                                where their assembly is gathered. At the request of Ānanda, the Buddha gives a series of
                                                teachings, in the form of replies to questions posed by Mañjuśrī, that concern the most beneficial,
                                                though often counterintuitive, forms of knowledge and activities characteristic of bodhisattvas who have
                                                realized emptiness. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-2"/>
                                        <p tid="8">A number of “arrogant monks” in the assembly, however, misunderstand the Tathāgata’s teaching and the Buddha is asked
                                                to clarify the intentions behind this discourse. Upon hearing his explanations, realization dawns in the minds
                                                of the various listeners and the monks affirm their new understanding. Mañjuśrī then inquires into the training
                                                in transcendent insight and the Buddha responds with a concluding teaching on the value and efficacy of this
                                                Dharma discourse. He describes twenty laudable qualities that are possessed by those who have faith in it. He
                                                also recounts how in a previous lifetime he himself became accomplished in it. The Buddha then gives
                                                instructions on the practices of bodhisattvas who wish to realize this profound insight. In the end, the Buddha
                                                commands Ānanda to remember it, and everybody rejoices and praises the Buddha’s words.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-introduction-2">
                                        <head type="section" tid="9">Key Doctrines in the Discourse</head>
                                        <list type="section">        
                                                <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-3"/>
                                                        <label tid="236">The illusory nature of phenomena.</label>
                                        <p tid="10">The sūtra repeatedly draws attention to the empty
                                                and thus illusory nature of all phenomena, which includes everything from sensory appearances up to central
                                                Buddhist conceptions such as the six perfections, monastic discipline, morality, merit, and even the Buddha
                                                himself. The realization of this empty and illusory nature of all phenomena is transcendent insight, which
                                                allows one to rest naturally in a state of absorption. Phenomena as well as transcendent insight are said to be
                                                like space: “Space is not something to be realized, nor is it something to be abandoned. Likewise, no phenomenon
                                                is something to be realized or abandoned.” Because of this empty nature of phenomena, all conceptions about them
                                                as substantial or real are completely mistaken. To realize this is to correctly understand emptiness.</p>
                        </item>
                                                <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-4"/>
                                                        <label tid="237">The unity of the bodhisattva’s insight and skillful means.</label>
                                        <p tid="11">Bodhisattvas accomplish a
                                                wide range of compassionate activities without departing from the profound insight of emptiness, which is
                                                transcendent insight. In this way, bodhisattvas are able to compassionately engage in the different realms of
                                                beings without disregarding their empty nature. Through such practices as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samādhi</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī</foreign> recitation, they are able
                                                to go to buddhafields without actually coming or going and are able to speak different languages without mixing
                                                them up.</p>
                        </item>
                                                <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-5"/>
                                                        <label tid="238">Transcendent insight.</label>
                                        <p tid="12">This sūtra emphasizes that transcendent insight and the
                                                illusory nature of phenomena are difficult to understand for ordinary beings, hearers, solitary realizers, and
                                                bodhisattvas who cling to phenomenal appearances. Those who are unaware of the Tathāgata’s intention behind this
                                                teaching are in danger of completely misunderstanding him. The upshot of this observation is that all
                                                conceptions, even that concerning the Tathāgata, are false, and thus all views are mistaken. This applies not
                                                only to metaphysical views of a self, a being, a soul, and a person, but to conceptions such as “me” or “mine”
                                                and preconceptions such as Buddha, Dharma, and Saṇgha. </p>
                        </item>
                                                <item>
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-6"/>
                                                        <label tid="239">Outcast bodhisattvas.</label>
                                        <p tid="13">One noteworthy feature of this sūtra is its outspoken
                                                condemnation of the shortcomings of “outcast bodhisattvas.” Such bodhisattvas are practitioners who reside in
                                                remote places but have failed to realize transcendent insight and remain attached to their disciplined
                                                practices. Those outcast bodhisattvas will consequently look down on other bodhisattvas who dwell near a village
                                                or town. Such passages may be understood as a criticism targeting “the susceptibility of forest monks to pride
                                                and conceit,”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-7"> Boucher 2009, p. 56.</note> which accords with the
                                                Buddha’s chastisement of “arrogant monks” in this sūtra.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                                </div>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-introduction-3">
                                        <head type="section" tid="14">Source Texts</head>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-8"/>
                                        <p tid="15">There is to our knowledge no extant complete Sanskrit version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title>. Apart from fragments of Khotanese and Sanskrit versions of the text, the
                                                complete text is extant only in Tibetan and Chinese translations.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-9">
                                                                Chen 2012, pp. 273–76.</note> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> was
                                                translated into Chinese by Dharmarakṣa in the third century and by Dharmamitra in the fifth century (Taishō 813 and
                                                814 respectively). The text is found in Kangyur collections of different periods and is also recorded in the
                                                        Denkarma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-10">
                                                                Denkarma, folio 298.b.3. See also Herrmann-Pfandt (2008),
                                                                p. 85.</note> and Phangthangma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-11">
                                                                Phangthangma (2003), p. 13.</note> catalogs
                                                of Tibetan imperial translations. Thus it appears that it was first translated from Sanskrit into Tibetan by an
                                                unknown translator no later than the early ninth century, as the Denkarma is dated to 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. The Tibetan translations do not mention the names of the translators.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-12"> Apple 2014, p. 41.</note> According to the findings of Liu
                                                and Chen, the earliest Chinese and the Sanskrit versions share an earlier source text, while the later Chinese
                                                and the Tibetan and Khotanese versions share a later source text.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-13">
                                                                Liu and Chen 2014, p. 309.</note> This English translation was prepared based on the Tibetan
                                                translation in the Degé Kangyur in consultation with the Comparative Edition
                                                (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and the Stok Palace Kangyur.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-14"/>
                                        <p tid="16">There are a number of references to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> in Buddhist canonical
                                                literature. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> is referred to in chapter six of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sikṣasamuccaya</title>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3940.html"/> 
                                                and it is cited by Kamalaśīla in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­dharmāsvabhāva­siddhi</title> (Toh 3889)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3889.html"/> as well as in the tantric work 
                                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­yāna­melāyana­pradīpa</title> (Toh 3720)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3720.html"/>. A verse ascribed to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> 
                                                is cited by Candrakīrti in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūla­madhyamaka­vṛtti­prasanna­padā</title> (Toh 3860)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3860.html"/> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattva­yogācāra­catuḥśataka­ṭīkā</title> (Toh 3865)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3865.html"/>
                                                commentaries, but, notably, the verse is not found in any versions of the sūtra contained in the
                                                        Kangyur.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-15"> The passage in the 
                                                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattva­yogācāra­catuḥśataka­ṭīkā</title> reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de bzhin du 
                                                                        ’phags pa glang po’i rtsal gyi mdo las/ gal te chos rnams rang
                                                                        bzhin yod ’gyur na/ /rgyal ba nyan thos bcas pas de mkhyen ’gyur/ /ther zug chos ni mya
                                                                        ngan ’da’ mi ’gyur/ /mkhas rnams nam yang spros dang bral mi ’gyur/ /zhes gsungs
                                                                        so</foreign>. (Degé Tengyur, vol. 103 (dbu ma, ya), folio 224.b)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh3865.html"/>.</note> This “missing” citation, as well
                                                as numerous other passages that are found in the Kangyur versions of this sūtra, have been widely quoted
                                                by indigenous Tibetan scholars. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> is also cited a number of
                                                times in the Chinese Buddhist canon, which suggests that it may have once been an important Mahāyāna text that
                                                circulated throughout regions of Central and East Asia.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-16"> Liu and
                                                                Chen 2014, pp. 293f.</note>
                                        </p>
                                </div>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-introduction-4">
                                        <head type="section" tid="17">Remarks on the Title</head>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-17"/>
                                        <p tid="18">Since no Sanskrit source text is available, and because of differing interpretations of the title’s
                                                translations that involve certain linguistic ambiguities, the translation of the sūtra’s title into English
                                                needs to be critically discussed. Liu and Chen’s study<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-323">Liu and Chen 2014, pp. 302–09.</note> includes a detailed discussion of all
                                                the variant titles found in the different translations, and their findings are summarized for the reader in
                                                what follows. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-18"/>
                                        <p tid="19">Concerning first of all the Chinese versions, the Catalog of Nie Daozhen attests the title “The Elephant’s Armpit”
                                                        (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Xiangye</title> or *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣa</title>),
                                                which also corresponds to the title of Dharmamitra’s translation. The sūtra contains no 
                                                direct reference to the armpit of an elephant, but the title bearing this phrase is cited widely in medieval Chinese
                                                Buddhism because of the popularity of Dharmamitra’s works.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-19"> Liu and
                                                                Chen 2014, p. 302.</note> Dharmarakṣa’s translation speaks of “The Metaphor of the Elephant”
                                                        (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Yuxiang</title> or *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastyupama</title>),
                                                which would indicate that the power of the text is equivalent to the effort of an elephant.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-20"> 
                                                        Liu and Chen 2014, p. 304.</note> Also attested based on
                                                his translation is a title that does not make reference to an elephant: “Without Desire” (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Wuxiwang</title> or 
                                                *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akāṅkṣa</title>). The use of
                                                this title, however, is without sufficient evidence and may be due to a misreading or miscopying, possibly based
                                                on Gāndhārī or Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit written in Kharoṣṭhī or Brāhmī scripts, resulting in the readings of
                                                        *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nāstikāṅkṣa</title> or *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Asakāṅkṣa</title> instead of
                                                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-21"> Liu and Chen
                                                                2014, pp. 306f.</note> A paraphrase of the title as “The Stride of an Elephant” (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Xiangbu</title>, 
                                                *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastigati</title> or *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastivikrama</title>) is found in the translations of both Dharmarakṣa and
                                                Dharmamitra. The Tibetan translation could be understood in a similar way, since <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsal</foreign> can mean both 
                                                “effort” and “stride.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-22"> Liu and Chen 2014, pp. 305f.</note>
                                        </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-23"/>
                                        <p tid="20">The Tibetan title (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal</title>) features as an entry in the early ninth century
                                                Sanskrit-Tibetan glossary known as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣyam</title>, 
                                                Mvyut 1339 in section LIX on <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dam pa’i chos
                                                        kyi ming</foreign>). Csoma de Körös’ textual edition of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>, which comes with an accompanying English translation, translates the title as
                                                “The Elephant’s Dexterity (or Girth).”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-24"> Liu and Chen 2014, p. 303,
                                                                n.17.</note> However, note that in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>, the
                                                        Denkarma, and the Phangthangma this is
                                                the only instance where <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakṣya</foreign> corresponds to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsal</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ākrama</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vikrama</foreign> are given as its more
                                                usual correspondents, which would yield Sanskrit forms such as *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastyākrama</title> or
                                                        *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastivikrama</title>. Liu and Chen thus argue that the sūtra itself may
                                                actually be the source for this entry in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>. They indeed note
                                                that <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal</title> “should not be regarded as a correct interpretation of
                                                the Sanskrit word <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title>.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-25">
                                                                Liu and Chen 2014, p. 303. </note>
                                        </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-26"/>
                                        <p tid="21">Turning now to the (Buddhist Hybrid) Sanskrit titles, we can see that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakṣyā</foreign> is derived from the Vedic <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakṣa</foreign>,
                                                which indeed has the meaning of “armpit.” Based on a reading in the Sanskrit manuscript and considering the
                                                primitive form <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣa</title>, Liu and Chen reconstruct the sūtra’s title in its
                                                Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit form as *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikaccha</title>, which later was sanskritized
                                                into <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title>. Liu and Chen note the following: “We have the contemporaneous
                                                appearance of three titles: <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Yuxiang</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastyupama</title>) 
                                                and <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Wuxiwang</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nāstikāṅkṣa</title>, *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akāṅkṣa</title> or *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Asakāṅkṣa</title>) in Taishō 813 and, 
                                                according to the Catalogue, a <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Xiangbu</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastigati</title> 
                                                or *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastivikrama</title>). Then after more than a century, we have <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Xiangye</title> 
                                                (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣa</title> or <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikaccha</title> in its BHS form, 
                                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title> in
                                                its developed Skt. form) in Taishō 814, with its Sanskrit correspondence, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikaccha</title>, 
                                                in the Sanskrit fragment and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title> in the
                                                Tibetan translation. Finally, the word <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title> is transmitted into <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal</title> and <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal lta bu</title>
                                                (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣyopama</title>) in Tibetan.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-27"> Liu and Chen 2014, p. 308.</note> They then conclude that “with the exception of
                                                        <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Wuxiwang</title>, all the others can possibly be affiliated with a
                                                Sanskritization process from Middle Indic via Gāndhārī or BHS.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-28">
                                                                Ibid.</note> As a nominal compound, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hastikakṣya</title> is clearly
                                                a genitive <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tatpuruṣa</foreign> or dependent determinative compound.
                                                According to Monier-Williams’s Sanskrit dictionary, the compound <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hastikakṣya</foreign> 
                                                may have the meaning of “lion” or “tiger.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-29"> It is unlikely that this meaning was intended by this sūtra’s title, although it
                                                                worth noting that, in the text, Vajradhvaja’s teacher is named Siṃhavikrāntagati.</note>
                                                Next, let us look at the individual members of the compound: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hasti</foreign> and 
                                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakṣya</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Hasti</foreign> stands in 
                                                the compound for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hastin</foreign>, which can clearly be established as meaning “elephant.” 
                                                The second member, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakṣya</foreign>, however, has a whole range of possible meanings.
                                                Monier-Williams notes them as “abiding in shrubs or dry grass,” “well fed,” “girth (of an animal),” “the
                                                enclosure of an edifice,” “similarity,” and “effort, exertion.” The Tibetan translation of this member (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsal</foreign>) carries similar meanings, but tends more toward meanings
                                                such as “skill,” “dexterity,” “potency,” “capacity,” “potential,” or “power.”</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-30"/>
                                        <p tid="22">Unfortunately, the sūtra itself does not give any really convincing pointers to the correct interpretation of its
                                                title, since references to both elephants (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hasti</foreign>) and their
                                                supposed strength (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakṣya</foreign>) are few. Toward the beginning of the
                                                sūtra, Śāradvatīputra declines the Buddha’s initial request to assemble the monks and bodhisattvas in the area
                                                by stating that “elephants are difficult to please (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mgu
                                                        ba</foreign>, ‘satisfy, content, please, convince’).” Toward the end of the sūtra, the Buddha
                                                recounts to Ānanda that “beings who yearn for this Dharma discourse will be subdued by the strength of the bull
                                                or the strength of the elephant.” Based on these elements, we decided to translate the title as “The Strength of the Elephant,” although we are aware that further research would be necessary to validate this
                                                reading.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-introduction-5">
                                        <head type="section" tid="23">Relevant Academic Research</head>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-31"/>
                                        <p tid="24">Until recently there had been no extensive academic research on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title>. In the last several years, however, a number of scholars have authored
                                                studies with direct or indirect reference to the sūtra’s contents and development. Chen (2012) addresses newly
                                                identified fragments of a Khotanese translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title>
                                                together with their Chinese parallels. Liu and Chen (2014) include a translation of a Sanskrit fragment of the
                                                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> in light of its Chinese and Tibetan parallels as well
                                                as a lengthy discussion of all title variants and their possible Sanskrit equivalents. Their study looks at the
                                                early development of Mahayāna sūtras and also includes a concordance of the contents found in the different
                                                translations. James Apple (2014) considers the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> from the
                                                perspective of his research on the historical developments of entrusted transmissions of written texts in India
                                                after the fourth century. In the process, he compares the textual differences between the Tibetan translation
                                                and the earlier and later Chinese translations of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title>.
                                                Regarding the narrative variants of the story of Victory Banner of the Vajra told by the Buddha toward the end
                                                of the sūtra, Apple points out that the Dharma discourse is passed on as a Dharma scripture in the Tibetan
                                                version, but in the earlier Chinese versions of Dharmarakṣa and Dharmamitra it is said to be passed on as a
                                                mantra or a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī</foreign> respectively. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-32"/>
                                        <p tid="25">Regarding Tibetan mentions of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title>, Karma Phuntsho<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-324">Phuntsho 2005, p. 236 n29.</note>
                                                briefly states that, according to the master Ju Mipham Gyatso, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title> stands as one of the sūtras teaching the doctrine of mind-only (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems tsam</foreign>) understood as the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cittamātra</foreign> taught in canonical scriptures (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bka’i sems tsam</foreign>) as opposed to <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cittamātra</foreign>
                                                <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">qua</foreign> doctrinal system (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">grub mtha’i sems tsam</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-33"> We would
                                                                like to thank Gyurme Dorje for the following note: “Pekar Zangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad dkar bzang po</foreign>) in his <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde spyi’i rnam bzhag</title>, pp. 278–79, classes this discourse
                                                                among the third turning sūtras and draws a distinction between the provisional purpose of the
                                                                text (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gnas skabs kyi dgos pa</foreign>), which is to
                                                                subdue or overwhelm beings with the strength of the elephant in order to alleviate ailments and
                                                                so forth, and the conclusive purpose (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mthar thug gi dgos
                                                                        pa</foreign>), which is to bring about the attainment of “unsurpassed awakening.” He
                                                                also classifies the sūtra as representative of Yogācāramadhyamaka (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor spyod pa’i dbu ma</foreign>).”</note>
                                        </p>
                                </div>
                        </div>
                </front>
                <body>
                        <div type="translation">
                                <head type="translation" tid="26"> The Translation </head>
                                <head type="titleHon" tid="27">The Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                                <head type="titleMain" tid="28">The Strength of the Elephant</head>  
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-section-1">        
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-37"/>
                                        <p tid="32">
                        <ref cRef="F.95.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-330"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.95.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-331"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
                                        <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-38"/>
                                <p tid="33">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling on Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain together with a large saṅgha of monks
                                        comprised of five hundred monks as well as sixty thousand bodhisattvas who were all renowned,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-39"> Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon
                                                                par grags pa;</foreign> Degé:
                                                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon par grags pas</foreign>.
                                                        </note> had attained the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇīs</foreign>, possessed
                                        unobstructed eloquence, taught the Dharma of nonduality, and displayed inconceivable miraculous powers. They included
                                        the bodhisattva great beings Perseverant Beyond Compare and Wise; Essence of the Splendor of Overwhelming Sound, Blossom
                                        of the Four Jewels; Light Beam of Great Lightning; Seeing Beyond Extremes and Transcending All Sensory Objects; Lofty
                                        Like Mount Meru’s Summit; Gladdened with Supreme Joy; Light Vanquishing with Undefiled Forces; Reaching the Far Shore of
                                        Definitive Meaning to Fulfill Beings’ Aspirations; Possessing Vajralike Solidity; Beyond All Utterances, Speech, and
                                        Sounds; Voice More Majestic Than Brahmā’s; Overcoming Fears with Words of Renown; Accumulation of All Precious Roots of
                                        Virtue; and the bodhisattva great being Youthful Mañjuśrī. These and other such bodhisattvas in attendance were sixty
                                        thousand in number.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-40"/>
                                <p tid="34">In the afternoon, the venerable Śāradvatīputra, after arising from inner absorption, approached the Blessed One who at that
                                        time was sitting in front of another tree, immersed in the absorption known as <distinct>accomplishment of perfect
                                                peace</distinct>. From afar, the venerable Śāradvatīputra saw the Blessed One, who was peaceful. He quickly
                                        gathered some grass and sat down mindfully to one side with his legs crossed and back straightened. <ref cRef="F.96.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-332"/> As soon as
                                        he sat there, thoughts arose in his mind, such as: “How marvelous are the Tathāgata’s perfectly peaceful behavior,
                                        happiness, and bliss! Happy are the beings who realize that all phenomena naturally rest in the state of
                                        absorption!”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-41"/>
                                <p tid="35">The Blessed One, perceiving and understanding this, emerged from his concentration and made the sound of clearing his throat.
                                        Hearing the Blessed One clear his throat, the venerable Śāradvatīputra became filled with joy and inspiration, and
                                        walked toward where the Blessed One was sitting. When he arrived in the Blessed One’s presence, he prostrated to him in
                                        amazement and uttered the following verses: </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-42"/>
                                <lg tid="36">
                                        <l>“In the way I accept that phenomena are empty,</l>
                                        <l>Those who neither conceptualize beings</l>
                                        <l>Nor ever conceptualize phenomena</l>
                                        <l>Remain in the world in <term type="ignore">absorption</term>.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-43"/>
                                <lg tid="37">
                                        <l>“Never ever looking at the confusion of beings,</l>
                                        <l>And considering phenomena to be just like space,</l>
                                        <l>Happy are those who believe in the illusory nature </l>
                                        <l>And do not hold the view of a self. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-44"/>
                                <lg tid="38">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who do not focus on any conception, </l>
                                        <l>Such as ‘these are beings’ or ‘these are not beings,’</l>
                                        <l>Who have no conception of any being,</l>
                                        <l>And do not hold the view that there are beings. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-45"/>
                                <lg tid="39">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who are not attached to any conception of a substantial whole,</l>
                                        <l>Who are without the deluded conception of a substantial thing,</l>
                                        <l>Who neither cause things to arise nor to remain,</l>
                                        <l>And who are without the view of a soul.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-46"/>
                                <lg tid="40">
                                        <l>“Happy are the wise ones who do not differentiate among beings,</l>
                                        <l>Who do not contradict the domain of truth,</l>
                                        <l>Who eliminate all conceptions of personhood,</l>
                                        <l>And who do not think in terms of dichotomies. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-47"/>
                                <lg tid="41">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who always maintain generosity and discipline,</l>
                                        <l>Neither forming the concept of miserliness </l>
                                        <l>Nor fixating on the notion of accumulation,</l>
                                        <l>And who remain free of moral conceit. <ref cRef="F.96.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-333"/> </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-48"/>
                                <lg tid="42">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who excel in the qualities of endurance and determination,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-49">
                                                                Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nges pa’i yon tan</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thab mo
                                                                        dag</foreign>; Stok:
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">des pa’i yon tan</foreign>
                                                                        and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thal mo dag</foreign> (Skt.
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">añjali</foreign>,
                                                                        “supplication”).</note>
                        </l>
                                        <l>Who are free from the notion of conflict, </l>
                                        <l>Who are neither zealous nor lazy, </l>
                                        <l>And who have no preconception concerning patience.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-50"/>
                                <lg tid="43">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who are not fixated on concentration and stability,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-51">
                                                                Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtan pa mi
                                                                        gnas</foreign>; Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtan par mi gnas</foreign>. </note>
                                        </l>
                                        <l>And yet do not think about distractions—</l>
                                        <l>Who understand the qualities of meditative equipoise</l>
                                        <l>And have no preconceptions about concentration.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-52"/>
                                <lg tid="44">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who are free from preconceptions about anything, </l>
                                        <l>Who have no insight regarding anything and yet are not under the sway of ignorance,</l>
                                        <l>Who are neither learned nor deluded,</l>
                                        <l>And who have no preconceptions about wisdom. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-53"/>
                                <lg tid="45">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who dwell in a city as if in retreat,</l>
                                        <l>Who treat them equally, with similar conceptions of both—</l>
                                        <l>Who do not disparage city life</l>
                                        <l>But also do not idealize retreat. </l>
                                </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-321"/>
                                        <lg tid="232">      
                                        <l>“Happy are those practice alms-begging as a householder </l>
                                        <l>Without any preconception about this alms-begging.</l>
                                        <l>Without entertaining thoughts such as ‘I am a mendicant,’ </l>
                                        <l>They have no preconceptions about alms-begging. </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-322"/>
                                        <lg tid="233">         
                                        <l>“Happy are those who pick up refuse-rags</l>
                                        <l>And wear them on their body.</l>
                                        <l>They do not think ‘I have miserable clothing,’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-54"> The Degé edition reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">blangs nas bdag gis lus la ’chad par byed/ /bdag ni gos ngan snyam du de mi
                                                                        sems</foreign>; the Stok edition reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">blangs nas lus la ’chang bar byed pa dag /bdag ni gos
                                                                        ngan snyam du de mi shes</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                                        <l>And they do not put down others. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-55"/>
                                <lg tid="46">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who wear nothing but the three Dharma robes </l>
                                        <l>Approved by the Buddha and praised by the sugatas,</l>
                                        <l>Yet do not think ‘I am fearless,’</l>
                                        <l>And remain without pride. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-56"/>
                                <lg tid="47">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who teach the supreme and sacred Dharma</l>
                                        <l>In which there is neither self nor being.</l>
                                        <l>They do not even think ‘I am a master teacher,’</l>
                                        <l>But they also do not amount to nothing. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-57"/>
                                <lg tid="48">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who are free from preconceptions regarding any virtue, </l>
                                        <l>Who do not conceive of anything as an essence or a substance,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-58"> The Degé edition reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snying po med pa rjes su ’du shes med</foreign>;
                                                                        the Stok edition reads
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snying po dang ni rdzas su ’du shes med</foreign>.</note>
                                        </l>
                                        <l>Who do not think of anything as virtuous or nonvirtuous,</l>
                                        <l>But who do not behave in a dualistic way.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-59"/>
                                <lg tid="49">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who stand but have no preconception about standing,</l>
                                        <l>Who sit but have no preconception about sitting,</l>
                                        <l>Who at all times cultivate diligence as they move about</l>
                                        <l>And remain without mental elaboration.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-60"/>
                                <lg tid="50">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who are free from preconceptions about abiding or non-abiding,</l>
                                        <l>Who do not conceive of some special knowledge as the state of peace, <ref cRef="F.97.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-334"/>
                        </l>
                                        <l>Who make no distinction between tathāgatas and non-Buddhists, </l>
                                        <l>And who are without assumptions about what is “the best.” </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-61"/>
                                <lg tid="51">
                                        <l>“Happy are those for whom there is neither number nor enumeration,</l>
                                        <l>Who do not disregard equality that is like the expanse of space,</l>
                                        <l>Who do not think of themselves and others as distinct, </l>
                                        <l>And who have no special achievements. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-62"/>
                                <lg tid="52">
                                        <l>“Happy are those who appear as an illusion and behave as if in a dream,</l>
                                        <l>Who resemble optical illusions but are not deluded,</l>
                                        <l>Who are active in the worlds like reflections of the moon in water,</l>
                                        <l>And who do not strive in any way. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-63"/>
                                <lg tid="53">
                                        <l>“Happy are the beings who are wise and behold the ultimate,</l>
                                        <l>Who understand that names and conventions have no essence,</l>
                                        <l>Who realize that phenomena are in the state of peace,</l>
                                        <l>And who remain unbound by the range of conceptual signs.” </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-64"/>
                                <p tid="54">Thereupon the Blessed One congratulated the venerable Śāradvatīputra: “Śāradvatīputra, supreme is this teaching that
                                        engages in this way in the profound wisdom! It is excellent, excellent! Therefore, Śāradvatīputra, assemble all the
                                        monks and bodhisattvas abiding in inner absorption on this Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain, as many as there may be.” </p>
                                <p tid="55">“Blessed One,” replied Śāradvatīputra, “I would prefer not to do so. Why? Because elephants are difficult to please.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-66"/>
                                <p tid="56">At that very moment, the Blessed One emitted light rays from his body and he summoned the bodhisattvas abiding in infinite
                                        world systems. They reached the place where the Blessed One was residing on Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain and hovered in the sky.
                                        All the monks and bodhisattva great beings who had been abiding in inner absorption also arrived where the Blessed One
                                        was residing, as did hundreds of thousands of beings from the great city of Rājagṛha.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-67"/>
                                <p tid="57">Then the Blessed One, knowing that all were present in the assembly, looked at the face of Youthful Mañjuśrī <ref cRef="F.97.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-335"/> and
                                        smiled. At that moment, Youthful Mañjuśrī rose from his seat, draped his robe over one shoulder, and knelt on his right
                                        knee. He bowed in the direction of the Blessed One with joined palms and asked him, “As the tathāgatas, the worthy ones,
                                        the complete and perfect buddhas do not smile without causes and conditions, what are the causes for your smile, what
                                        are the conditions for it?”</p>
                                        
                                <p tid="58">The Blessed One replied to Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, ten thousand buddhas have expounded the Dharma discourse known as
                                        ‘Like the Strength of the Elephant’ on this Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-69"/>
                                <p tid="59">When the venerable Ānanda heard what the Blessed One had said, he swiftly rose from his seat, draped his robe over one
                                        shoulder, and knelt on his right knee. He bowed in the direction of the Blessed One with joined palms and made this
                                        request: “Blessed One, it would be excellent if you could now teach me this Dharma discourse known as ‘Like the Strength
                                        of the Elephant.’ Sugata, it would be excellent if you could explain this to me. It is rare nowadays to hear a Dharma
                                        discourse that would cause you, Blessed One, to smile upon seeing the face of Youthful Mañjuśrī. Such a Dharma discourse
                                        must be wonderful. It must be as profound as it seems to be.” </p>
                               
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-325"/>
                                        <p tid="60">“Ānanda,” replied the Blessed One, “you are indeed skilled in the practice of discernment and your analysis is excellent,
                                        excellent. Therefore, Ānanda, listen very well and keep this in mind. I will explain it to you.” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="61">“Excellent, Blessed One,” the venerable Ānanda agreed, and he listened as requested. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-72"/>
                                <p tid="62">The Blessed One made a sign to Youthful Mañjuśrī in order to have him make inquiries about this Dharma discourse.
                                        Consequently, Mañjuśrī thought to himself, “I will ask the Tathāgata <ref cRef="F.98.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-336"/> what is this profound discourse that is
                                        not within the realm of hearers, solitary realizers, or bodhisattvas who have fallen into conceptual signs.” After
                                        Youthful Mañjuśrī had reflected upon this, he proposed, “If the Blessed One is giving me this opportunity to make
                                        inquiries so that the questions can be answered, then I will pose questions on various topics to the Blessed One, the
                                        tathāgata, the worthy one, the complete and perfect Buddha.” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="63">“Since everyone in this assembly has come together, Mañjuśrī, ask whatever you wish,” the Blessed One replied.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-74"/>
                                <p tid="64">Mañjuśrī then asked the following: “Blessed One, how do bodhisattvas accomplish all their activities while also maintaining
                                        all virtuous qualities? How do they both remain in all buddhafields like the moon’s reflections in water, and also fully
                                        ripen countless beings?” </p>
                                
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-326"/>
                                        <p tid="65">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “your concise and meaningful questions are excellent, excellent! Listen attentively to
                                        this detailed explanation I will give you and keep it in mind.” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="66">“Blessed One, I will do so,” answered Youthful Mañjuśrī, and he listened as requested. </p>
                                        <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-77"/>
                                <p tid="67">The Blessed One then gave the following reply: “Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess six qualities, they will completely
                                        accomplish their tasks and also maintain all virtuous qualities. What are these six? If bodhisattvas practice
                                        generosity, then although they are benefactors who let go of all their possessions, they do not regard themselves as
                                        having completely reversed miserly behavior. Although they observe discipline, they not consider themselves as being
                                        beyond actions that result from inferior discipline. Although they possess patience and determination, they do not
                                        regard themselves as being free from behavior based on malicious thoughts. <ref cRef="F.98.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-337"/> Although they cultivate diligence,
                                        they do not exert themselves bodily or mentally. Although they are skilled in all concentrations, liberations,
                                        absorptions, and all meditative states, they are not stuck in a one-pointed mental state. Although they exist within the
                                        domain of insight, they regard themselves as not being fully liberated from transmigration. Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas
                                        possess these six qualities, they completely accomplish their tasks and also maintain all virtuous qualities.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-78"/>
                                <p tid="68">“Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess another six qualities, they can accomplish their tasks, and also maintain all virtuous
                                        qualities. What are these six? Bodhisattvas assume the state of a hell being while at the same time experiencing the
                                        qualities of the higher realms. They assume the state of an animal, while at the same time experiencing the great extent
                                        of human qualities. They assume a birth in the lower castes,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-79"> The Tibetan
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs</foreign> can refer to various concepts related to
                                                        the Indian traditional organization of society: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">varṇa</foreign>,
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jāti</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kula</foreign>, 
                                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gotra</foreign>. In the present context,
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rigs</foreign> could refer to <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">varṇa</foreign> 
                                                or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jāti</foreign>. An
                                                        alternative term to “caste” would be “class.”</note> while at the same time experiencing the
                                        pleasures of a cakravartin’s kingdom. They manifest within all modes of existence, while at the same time experiencing
                                        the activities associated with a specific realm. They are skilled in going to all buddhafields, while at the same time
                                        not moving from their location. They neither come nor go, and yet appear in all buddhafields like the moon’s reflections
                                        in water. They speak all languages yet do not mix them up. Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess these six qualities, they
                                        completely accomplish their activities and also maintain all virtuous qualities.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-80"/>
                                <p tid="69">“Blessed One,” Youthful Mañjuśrī inquired, “how do bodhisattvas assume the state of a hell being while at the same time
                                        experiencing the qualities of the higher realms?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="70">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, <ref cRef="F.99.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-338"/> “bodhisattva great beings assume the state of a hell being by entering the
                                        absorption known as <distinct>great lotus</distinct>, while at the same time experiencing all the joys of the gods,
                                        including the most subtle of them. For their part, hell beings perceive these bodhisattvas as hell beings because they
                                        are themselves hell beings. Through this appearance, bodhisattvas expound the Dharma to those denizens of the hell who
                                        have the potential to be extricated from the hells. They completely liberate many thousands of beings from the hells.
                                        Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas assume the state of a hell being while at the same time experiencing the state of the
                                        higher realms.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-82"/>
                                <p tid="71">“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī, “how do bodhisattvas assume the state of an animal, while at the same time experiencing the
                                        great extent of human qualities?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="72">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “bodhisattvas assume the state of an animal by entering the absorption known as
                                                <distinct>settling in complete peace</distinct>, and without experiencing any impairment to their mental
                                        faculties, they experience the great extent of human qualities. Through this appearance, they explain the Dharma to
                                        beings that have become animals and so establish many thousands of beings in the Dharma. Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas
                                        experience the condition of an animal while at the same time experiencing the great extent of human qualities.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-84"/>
                                <p tid="73">“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī, “how do bodhisattvas embrace a birth in the lower castes, while at the same time experiencing
                                        the pleasures of a cakravartin’s kingdom?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="74">The Blessed One replied, “Mañjuśrī, in order to do this, bodhisattvas enter the absorption known as <distinct>subduing and
                                                illuminating</distinct>. By means of this absorption, which is conquering and illuminating, they embrace a birth
                                        in the lower castes, while at the same time experiencing the pleasures of a cakravartin’s kingdom. <ref cRef="F.99.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-339"/> Through
                                        these skillful means, they establish many thousands of beings in the Dharma. Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas embrace a
                                        birth in the lower castes, while at the same time experiencing the happiness of a cakravartin’s kingdom.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-86"/>
                                <p tid="75">“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī, “how do bodhisattvas both manifest within all modes of existence and also experience the
                                        activities of one specific realm?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="76">The Blessed One replied, “Mañjuśrī, in order to do this, they enter the absorption known as <distinct>particular display
                                                illuminating the abandonment of all activities</distinct>. Abiding in that absorption, they both manifest within
                                        all modes of existence and also experience the activities of one specific realm. In this way, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas
                                        manifest within all modes of existence while experiencing a particular realm.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-88"/>
                                <p tid="77">“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī, “how do bodhisattvas excel in going to all buddhafields while at the same time not moving from
                                        their location? Although they neither come nor go, how do they appear in all buddhafields in the same way the moon is
                                        reflected in water?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="78">The Blessed One replied, “Mañjuśrī, in order to do this, bodhisattvas enter the absorption known as <distinct>conquering all
                                                forms</distinct>. Then, abiding in that absorption, they at once manifest their bodies throughout the world
                                        systems of the ten directions, without moving from their location, without going or coming. By remaining in equanimity,
                                        they see the Buddha, the Blessed One, and hear the Dharma. Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas excel in being reborn in all
                                        buddhafields while at the same time not moving from their location. They neither come nor go, and yet they appear in all
                                        buddhafields in the same way the moon is reflected in water.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-90"/>
                                <p tid="79">Mañjuśrī then asked, “Blessed One, how can bodhisattvas speak all kinds of languages <ref cRef="F.100.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-340"/> and yet not mix them up?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="80">“Mañjuśrī, replied the Blessed One, “bodhisattvas possess the dhāraṇī known as <distinct>infinite recitation</distinct>. As a
                                        result of that, they can engage with the infinite thoughts of the minds of beings, understand infinite languages, and
                                        comprehend infinite individual ways of being. By possessing this dhāraṇī, they both speak all languages and also do not
                                        mix them up. Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas speak all languages and yet do not mix them up.”</p>
                                        <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-92"/>
                                <p tid="81">Mañjuśrī then inquired further: “Blessed One, the bodhisattvas’ skillful means are difficult to manifest. Nonetheless,
                                        Blessed One, how should this Dharma discourse be understood by the bodhisattvas who wish to understand it?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="82">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “those bodhisattvas who wish to understand this Dharma discourse should understand it to
                                        be like space.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-94"/>
                                <p tid="83">“How is it like space, Blessed One?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>
                                
                                <p tid="84">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “it may be illustrated as follows: Space is not desirous, nor angry, nor ignorant.
                                        Likewise, no phenomenon is desirous, angry, or ignorant. It may be illustrated as follows: Space is not the excellence
                                        of generosity, and so forth, up to and including the excellence of insight. Likewise, no phenomenon is the excellence of
                                        generosity, and so forth, up to and including the excellence of insight. It may be illustrated as follows: Space is not
                                        something to be realized, nor is it something to be abandoned. Likewise, no phenomenon is something to be realized or
                                        abandoned. It may be illustrated as follows: Space is not something to be cultivated, nor is it something to be
                                        actualized. Likewise, no phenomenon is something to be cultivated or actualized. <ref cRef="F.100.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-341"/> It may be illustrated as
                                        follows: Space is not obscurity, nor is it light. Likewise, no phenomenon is obscurity or light. It may be illustrated
                                        as follows: Space is not something to be apprehended. Likewise, no phenomenon is something to be apprehended. It may be
                                        illustrated as follows: Space is not a destination attained either through the genuine path or through a bad path.
                                        Likewise, no phenomenon is a destination attained, either through the genuine path or through a bad path. It may be
                                        illustrated as follows: Space is not a destination attained through the Hearers’ Vehicle, the Solitary Realizers’
                                        Vehicle, or the Great Vehicle. Likewise, no phenomenon is a destination attained through the Hearers’ Vehicle, the
                                        Solitary Realizers’ Vehicle, or the Great Vehicle. It may be illustrated as follows: Space is not an agent that reflects
                                        or knows. Likewise, no phenomenon is an agent that reflects or knows. It may be illustrated as follows: Space is not an
                                        agent that accepts or rejects, nor is it an object to be accepted or rejected. Likewise, no phenomenon is an agent that
                                        accepts or rejects, nor is it an object to be accepted or rejected. It may be illustrated as follows: Space cannot be
                                        defiled by anything whatsoever. Likewise, no phenomenon belonging to supreme nirvāṇa can be defiled in any possible way.
                                        Thus, it will neither be assuaged nor pacified. It may be illustrated as follows: Space is not an abode because it is
                                        not abiding, nor does it abide, waver, or vacillate. Likewise, bodhisattvas should regard each and every phenomenon as
                                        abiding in non-abidingness. Having correct understanding, they do not vacillate, waver, abide, or cause anything to
                                        abide. <ref cRef="F.101.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-342"/>
                    </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-96"/>
                                <p tid="85">“Mañjuśrī, since the nature of all phenomena is like this, those who wish to see the Tathāgata hold a mistaken view. Those
                                        who view this as mistaken<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-97"> This passage seems to play on a semantic
                                                        ambivalence between “mistaken view” and “view as mistaken,” which are two ways of understanding the
                                                        compound <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">log par lta ba</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mithyādṛṣṭi</foreign>).</note> have correct understanding. For those who have
                                        correct understanding, generosity has neither great result nor great benefit. Those for whom generosity has neither
                                        great result nor great benefit are objects of generosity in the world. For those who are objects of generosity in the
                                        world, there is no karmic ripening from generosity. Those for whom there is no karmic ripening from generosity have
                                        perfected non-conception. Those who have perfected non-conception will quickly attain the acceptance that all phenomena
                                        do not arise.” </p>
                                        <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-98"/>
                                <p tid="86">As sixty arrogant monks in the assembly heard this teaching, they thought to themselves, “This is the path of confusion. Even
                                        the Tathāgata teaches the path of confusion. It is as follows: Some non-Buddhists also teach these words. Since the
                                        Tathāgata teaches these words too, his speech is comparable to those of some non-Buddhists, such as Kaśyapa, Maskari
                                        Gośāliputra, Ajita Keśakambalī, Sañjayi Vairattīputra, Kakuda Kātyāyana, and Nirgrantha Jñatiputra.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-99"/>
                                <p tid="87">The Blessed One read the thoughts of these sixty arrogant monks, and he remarked to Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Thus, Mañjuśrī, if
                                        the Dharma I have expounded is comparable to what those other non-Buddhists teach, then those non-Buddhists do not
                                        understand the Dharma taught by the Tathāgata.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-100"/>
                                <p tid="88">After the Blessed One had spoken these words, the arrogant monks became very distressed, depressed, displeased, and dejected.
                                        Still not understanding this Dharma exposition, they rose from their seats and left. Then the venerable Śāriputra asked
                                        these monks, “Venerable ones, where are you going?” <ref cRef="F.101.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-343"/>
                    </p>
                                
                                <p tid="89">“Venerable Śāriputra,” they answered, “we do not seek this Dharma exposition.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-102"/>
                                <p tid="90">“Venerable ones,” Śāriputra replied, “you should know that the Tathāgata is teaching in these ways with an intention.
                                        Therefore, stay for a while until you ask the Tathāgata what his intention was when he taught in these ways.”</p>
                                
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-327"/>
                                        <p tid="91">After hearing the venerable Śāriputra’s words, the monks went back to their seats. At that point, the venerable Śāriputra
                                        made this request: “Blessed One, in order to clarify these monks’ doubts, I beseech you to explain what the intention of
                                        the Tathāgata was when he taught in these ways.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-104"/>
                                <p tid="92">“Śāriputra, what do you think?” asked the Blessed One. “Would monks whose minds are liberated from defilements with no
                                        further appropriation become apprehensive, frightened, or terrified by any sound?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="93">“No, Blessed One, they would not,” answered Śāriputra. “Monks who see the truth do not become apprehensive, frightened, or
                                        terrified by any sound. What need is there to mention those monks whose minds are liberated from defilements with no
                                        further appropriation!” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-106"/>
                                <p tid="94">“Śāriputra,” continued the Blessed One, “in the present case, some foolish persons have investigated unreal phenomena and
                                        have become and remain exceedingly proud.” </p>
                                <lb/>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-328"/>
                                        <p tid="95">Śāriputra then made this request: “I beseech the Blessed One to expound a teaching that, when heard, will remove the doubts
                                        of all those present in this assembly.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-108"/>
                                <p tid="96">“Śāriputra,” said the Blessed One, “those who see the Tathāgata as a dream and an illusion see him truly. Those who truly see
                                        him do not conceive of the Tathāgata in terms of truth, essence, substance, a real entity, or a partless whole. Those
                                        who do not conceive of the Tathāgata in terms of truth, essence, substance, a real entity, or a partless whole regard
                                        all constructs as false. <ref cRef="F.102.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-344"/> Those who see all constructs as false know all phenomena to be mistaken. The
                                        Tathāgata has taught that all those who know every phenomenon to be mistaken have perfected the view of mistakenness.
                                        They also understand that all those who have resorted to views are mistaken. This is why some are referred to as holding
                                        a mistaken view. Śāriputra, according to this discourse, those who wish to view the Tathāgata are referred to as holding
                                        a mistaken view. Śāriputra, some view the Tathāgata’s body unerringly. But those who understand the Tathāgata’s body as
                                        mistaken have no conception of the Tathāgata. Śāriputra, those who know this to be mistaken see the Tathāgata.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-109"/>
                                <p tid="97">“Blessed One, how have those who view this as mistaken correctly understood?” asked Śāriputra.</p>
                                
                                <p tid="98">The Blessed One replied, “Śāriputra, ordinary beings discriminate and conceptualize, examine and analyze, reveal and
                                        thoroughly reveal, rely and dwell, accept and reject. They embrace the view of a self, a being, a life, and a person,
                                        and they cling to the belief in ‘I’ and are attached to the belief in ‘mine.’ They conceive their conduct, knowledge,
                                        movements, and conceptual elaborations along these lines. They understand these things, which do not actually exist, in
                                        just this way. Śāriputra, the word <distinct>nonexistent</distinct> is a designation for what is unreal. That which is
                                        unreal is a lie. The word <distinct>lie</distinct> is a designation for what is false. Those who see how mistaken are those
                                        beings who believe in the unreal are said to have discerned reality. Śāriputra, according to this very
                                        explanation, those who see this as wrong have correct understanding.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-111"/>
                                <p tid="99">“Blessed One,” Śāriputra asked, “in what way do those with correct understanding neither reap great result nor receive great
                                        benefit when they are generous?” <ref cRef="F.102.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-345"/> </p>
                                
                                <p tid="100">“Śāriputra,” replied the Blessed One, “for those who have correct understanding through this approach, generosity is directed
                                        toward nirvāṇa. It flows and has flowed into nirvāṇa, and it will culminate in nirvāṇa. However, nirvāṇa is neither a
                                        small nor a great result, neither a small nor a great benefit. Why? Because nirvāṇa is free from all results and is
                                        therefore neither a designation nor an object of designation.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-113"/>
                                <p tid="101">“Well then, Blessed One,” asked Śāriputra, “how did the Tathāgata teach the particular advantages of infinite virtuous
                                        qualities with respect to nirvāṇa that does not exist for designation?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="102">“Śāriputra,” replied the Blessed One, “the Tathāgata taught particular advantages of infinite virtuous qualities with respect
                                        to nirvāṇa, even though it does not exist for designation, in order to inspire beings subject to the world of birth who
                                        assert selfhood, beings, life forms, and persons. However, Śāriputra, one should not consider noble beings to be those
                                        who engage in generosity, but rather those who are free from attachment and who turn away from generosity. Śāriputra, it
                                        may be illustrated as follows: When farmers have planted barley seeds in a field, husks, stalks, and leaves are produced
                                        from the barley. In that case, Śāriputra, do you think that the husks, stalks, and leaves are the fruits produced by the
                                        actions of those farmers?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="103">“No, Blessed One, I do not,” Śāriputra replied.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-116"/>
                                <p tid="104">“Śāriputra,” continued the Blessed One, “it may be illustrated as follows: It is on account of the barley itself—namely,
                                        those barley seeds planted by the farmers—that the husks, stalks, and leaves are produced, as well as other ears of
                                        barley. Likewise, when noble beings practice generosity, great resources come to them with little difficulty. In
                                        addition, all fruits resulting from craving for the exhaustion of afflictions wither. <ref cRef="F.103.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-346"/> It may be illustrated as
                                        follows: Those who want barley think, ‘This is not the fruits of these barely seeds, nor is this the ears of barley
                                        produced by those seeds.’ As a consequence, they are neither pleased by the husks nor delighted by the stalks and
                                        leaves. Likewise, it should not be taught that practicing generosity in the field of the unconditioned gives a result
                                        that is conditioned. Śāriputra, according to this discourse, generosity brings neither great result nor great benefit
                                        for those who have correct understanding.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-117"/>
                                <p tid="105">“Blessed One,” asked Śāriputra, “how can those noble beings be objects of generosity in the world when their generosity
                                        yields neither great result nor great benefit?”</p>
                                
                                <p tid="106">“Śāriputra,” replied the Blessed One, “generosity will not arise for those who do not conceive of results as great or small.
                                        Those for whom generosity does not arise will become objects of generosity in the world with its gods. In that case,
                                        Śāriputra, the practice of generosity in the inexhaustible field of generosity neither becomes a flower nor turns into a
                                        fruit. Thus, according to this discourse, Śāriputra, those for whom there is neither a great result nor a great benefit
                                        when they are generous are objects of generosity in the world.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-119"/>
                                <p tid="107">“Blessed One, why does generosity not ripen for those who are objects of generosity in the world?” asked Śāriputra.</p>
                                
                                <p tid="108">“What do you think, Śāriputra?” the Blessed One asked in return. “Is the generosity that culminates in nirvāṇa subject to
                                        karmic ripening?” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-121"/>
                                <p tid="109">“No, Blessed One, it is not,” Śāriputra replied. “Blessed One, if the generosity that culminates in nirvāṇa were subject to
                                        karmic ripening, noble beings would not be distinguished as being unconditioned.” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="110">“Excellent, Śāriputra, excellent,” said the Blessed One. “According to this discourse, generosity does not entail karmic
                                        ripening for those who are objects of generosity in the world.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-123"/>
                                <p tid="111">Śāriputra then asked, “Blessed One, how have those for whom generosity does not ripen perfected non-conception?” <ref cRef="F.103.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-347"/> </p>
                                
                                <p tid="112">“What do you think, Śāriputra?” the Blessed One asked in return. “Do those who know the very nature of all phenomena exist?
                                        Or, do they not exist?” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-125"/>
                                <p tid="113">“Blessed One,” answered Śāriputra, “those who understand the very nature of all phenomena understand the very nature of
                                        illusions. Blessed One, this nature is nonexistent. It does not exist. Why? Blessed One, you taught that all phenomena
                                        have an illusory nature. That which is like an illusion is nonexistent. Those who understand the very nature of all
                                        phenomena have no conceptions. Why? Because nothing, no actual phenomenon whatsoever, is perceived by them.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-126"/>
                                <p tid="114">“Excellent, Śāriputra, excellent,” said the Blessed One. “It is just like that. Śāriputra, if some phenomena were
                                        substantially or truly existent, beings would not attain nirvāṇa, even in the future. Śāriputra, it is precisely because
                                        all phenomena are unreal, nonexistent, and insubstantial that beings as numerous as the grains of sand in the river
                                        Ganges have attained nirvāṇa. Yet, because beings do not exist, there is nothing at all related to those beings that is
                                        brought to an end. Therefore, Śāriputra, whoever neither apprehends the conception of the nonexistence of all beings,
                                        nor the beings themselves, has perfected non-conception. Śāriputra, according to this discourse, those for whom there is
                                        no ripening of generosity have perfected non-conception.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-127"/>
                                <p tid="115">“Blessed One,” asked Śāriputra, “how will they swiftly accept the non-arising of all phenomena through this conception of
                                        having perfected non-conception?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="116">“Śāriputra,” replied the Blessed One, “those who have directly realized nonexistence understand this. But what is
                                        nonexistence? The term <distinct>nonexistence</distinct> pertains to the metaphysical views of self, beings, life force,
                                        and persons, as well as the views of nihilism and eternalism. The term <distinct>nonexistence</distinct> pertains to the
                                        conceptions of Buddha, Dharma, Saṅgha, and nirvāṇa. <ref cRef="F.104.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-348"/> No matter how much one applies one’s mind, practices,
                                        understands, acts, or speculates, all this is nonexistent. Therefore, Śāriputra, those who are in this way completely
                                        free from such incorrect reifications understand. According to this discourse, Śāriputra, those who have perfected
                                        non-conception will quickly accept that all phenomena do not arise.”</p>
                                        <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-129"/>
                                <p tid="117">When this exposition of the teaching was being presented, forty-two thousand bodhisattvas accepted that all phenomena do not
                                        arise. Six thousand male lay vow holders set their minds on unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening. Thirty-six
                                        thousand sons of the gods gained the realization of wisdom. As for the sixty exceedingly proud monks, their minds became
                                        liberated from defilements with no further appropriation. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-130"/>
                                <p tid="118">With minds free from defilements, these sixty arrogant monks spoke the following words in unison: “Blessed One, from this day
                                        forth, we shall become renunciants who follow the six teachers. From this day forth, our teacher is no longer the Buddha
                                        and we shall rely neither on the Dharma nor on the Saṅgha. From this day forth, we shall be proponents of the
                                        nonexistence of action, causation, karma, karmic ripening, and moral conduct.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-131"/>
                                <p tid="119">At that moment, several thousand beings in the assembly thought to themselves, “These monks have thus become proponents of
                                        such untruths! Will they now give up the precepts they received from the Blessed One and take up the traits of the
                                        non-Buddhists?”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-132"/>
                                <p tid="120">The venerable Śāriputra clairvoyantly understood what those beings in the retinue were thinking. Therefore, he asked the
                                        monks, “Venerable ones, what was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall become renunciants who
                                        follow the six teachers’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="121">“Venerable Śāriputra,” answered the monks, “from this day forth, we perceive all our teachers as identical to the six
                                        teachers, as being of a single character, without any difference. <ref cRef="F.104.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-349"/> Perceiving all teachers as undifferentiated,
                                        we are renunciants following renunciants without conceptualizing.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-134"/>
                                <p tid="122">Śāriputra then asked, “What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, our teacher is no longer the Buddha’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="123">“From this day forth,” they answered, “we will rely on ourselves, but not on others. We will take refuge in ourselves, but
                                        not in others. We are our own teachers and no one else is. Therefore, from this day forth, our teacher is no longer the
                                        Buddha. Why? Aside from oneself, there is no buddha. Aside from a buddha, there is no self.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-136"/>
                                <p tid="124">Śāriputra then asked, “What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall rely neither on the Dharma nor
                                        on the Saṅgha’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="125">“From this day forth,” they answered, “we do not perceive any phenomenon whatsoever that anyone should rely upon or conform
                                        to. Therefore, from this day forth, we shall rely neither on the Dharma nor on the Saṅgha.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-138"/>
                                <p tid="126">Śāriputra then asked, “What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall be proponents of the
                                        nonexistence of action’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="127">“From this day forth,” they answered, “we know that all phenomena are unproduced. We have realized that phenomena undergo no
                                        production or change anywhere. Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of action.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-140"/>
                                <p tid="128">Śāriputra then asked, “What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall be proponents of the
                                        nonexistence of causation’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="129">“For us,” they answered, “the cause of birth in all destinies of cyclic existence has ended today. We have realized that
                                        phenomena are without any causes and conditions anywhere. Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the
                                        nonexistence of causation.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-142"/>
                                <p tid="130">Śāriputra then asked, “What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of
                                        karmic ripening’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="131">“From this day forth,” they answered, “we perfectly understand that all phenomena are without any karma nor karmic ripening
                                        anywhere and completely beyond suffering. Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of
                                        karmic ripening.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-144"/>
                                <p tid="132">Śāriputra then asked, “Venerable ones, what was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we are proponents of the
                                        nonexistence of moral discipline’?” <ref cRef="F.105.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-350"/> </p>
                                
                                <p tid="133">“Venerable Śāriputra,” they answered, “from this day forth, we perfectly understand the fact that there is neither moral
                                        discipline, nor discourses on it, nor non-discipline, and that all phenomena are utterly disciplined. Therefore, from
                                        this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of moral discipline.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-146"/>
                                <p tid="134">Having thus heard this teaching regarding these arrogant monks, the minds of three thousand six hundred other monks were
                                        liberated from defilements with no further appropriation. Then the Blessed One said to them, “Excellent! Monks, that
                                        which is devoid of the realization of any phenomenon is the attainment of truth. Thus, it is excellent, excellent.” </p>
                                        <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-147"/>
                                <p tid="135">Then Youthful Mañjuśrī asked, “Blessed One, what phenomena are designated by that realization termed ‘realization of
                                        realization’?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="136">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “that term ‘realization of realization’ is a designation for the acceptance that all
                                        phenomena do not arise.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-149"/>
                                <p tid="137">“How should those bodhisattvas, who seek to attain the acceptance that all phenomena do not arise, train, conduct themselves,
                                        and engage in practice?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>
                                
                                <p tid="138">At that time the Blessed One uttered the following verses in order to explain to Youthful Mañjuśrī the training in accepting
                                        that all phenomena do not arise: </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-151"/>
                                <lg tid="139">
                                        <l>“Those who wish to obtain the wisdom of the Buddha,</l>
                                        <l>The unsurpassed omniscience, </l>
                                        <l>Should neither take up </l>
                                        <l>Nor cast away any phenomenon.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-152"/>
                                <lg tid="140">
                                        <l>“One does not discover any phenomena at all</l>
                                        <l>That come into being.</l>
                                        <l>Yet childish people accept these phenomena as arising,</l>
                                        <l>Although they are devoid of arising. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-153"/>
                                <lg tid="141">
                                        <l>“When beings are taught that phenomena</l>
                                        <l>Are to be understood and rejected,</l>
                                        <l>Childish people who experience arising </l>
                                        <l>Will not have faith in non-arising. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-155"/>
                                <lg tid="143">
                                        <l>“Having abandoned the <term type="ignore">noble</term> path to awakening </l>
                                        <l>And the teachings pertaining to the path,</l>
                                        <l>Childish people cling to duality</l>
                                        <l>And do not understand nonduality. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-156"/>
                                <lg tid="144">
                                        <l>“In myriad illusions,</l>
                                        <l>Childish people perceive distinctions <ref cRef="F.105.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-351"/>
                        </l>
                                        <l>Where there are none,</l>
                                        <l>For all these illusions are of a single character. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-157"/>
                                <lg tid="145">
                                        <l>“Those who are called ‘ordinary beings’</l>
                                        <l>And the skillful buddhas of the world systems</l>
                                        <l>Are not two and are not separable into two.</l>
                                        <l>They are the same in their illusory character. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-158"/>
                                <lg tid="146">
                                        <l>“Some childish people say,</l>
                                        <l>‘One day our attachment will end,</l>
                                        <l>And our hatred and ignorance will be pacified;</l>
                                        <l>One day there will be no afflictions.’</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-159"/>
                                <lg tid="147">
                                        <l>“For those who have taught emptiness </l>
                                        <l>In order to annihilate the attachment and hatred</l>
                                        <l>That conceive of the nonexistent as existent,</l>
                                        <l>Their exhaustion is nirvāṇa.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-160"/>
                                <lg tid="148">
                                        <l>“Nirvāṇa is perfectly taught </l>
                                        <l>As being without cessation or arising.</l>
                                        <l>Yet far from my teaching are those</l>
                                        <l>Who strive for something unceasing or unarisen. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-161"/>
                                <lg tid="149">
                                        <l>“Those who delight in conceptions</l>
                                        <l>Of generosity, moral conduct, and awakening</l>
                                        <l>Remain within the domain of phenomenal appearances, </l>
                                        <l>And therefore do not realize my awakening.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-162"/>
                                <lg tid="150">
                                        <l>“Childish people deluded about nonexistence</l>
                                        <l>Do not understand that phenomena are hollow,</l>
                                        <l>And thus they establish distinctions</l>
                                        <l>Regarding phenomena that are of a single character. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-163"/>
                                <lg tid="151">
                                        <l>“For those who understand these phenomena, </l>
                                        <l>Devoid of phenomenal appearance by nature,</l>
                                        <l>Just as a hand consists of five fingers,</l>
                                        <l>It will not be difficult to attain awakening. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-165"/>
                                <lg tid="153">
                                        <l>“Awakening is far from no one.</l>
                                        <l>Awakening is close to no one. </l>
                                        <l>But far from awakening are those </l>
                                        <l>Immersed in discursive and dichotomous thought.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-166"/>
                                <lg tid="154">
                                        <l>“Since childish people denigrate each other </l>
                                        <l>When they get involved with one another,</l>
                                        <l>They lack self-discipline.</l>
                                        <l>Those who lack self-discipline are not tamed. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-167"/>
                                <lg tid="155">
                                        <l>“Phenomena are like dreams</l>
                                        <l>And all conditioned things are unreal. </l>
                                        <l>Considering arising as an illusion,</l>
                                        <l>The wise do not grasp them as something essential. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-168"/>
                                <lg tid="156">
                                        <l>“In truth, they have no discipline, </l>
                                        <l>And yet they truly have no lack of discipline. </l>
                                        <l>Since phenomena are dependently arisen,</l>
                                        <l>They do not have a self. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-169"/>
                                <lg tid="157">
                                        <l>“Throughout a million eons,</l>
                                        <l>The Guide tirelessly practiced generosity </l>
                                        <l>And maintained supreme and stainless discipline.</l>
                                        <l>Yet he never proclaimed a self.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-170"/>
                                <lg tid="158">
                                        <l>“It is taught that awakening has been attained </l>
                                        <l>When one is free from any conception about oneself,</l>
                                        <l>And when all conceptions of generosity,</l>
                                        <l>As well as discursive thought, have been abandoned. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-171"/>
                                <lg tid="159">
                                        <l>“It is taught that through generosity one will become resourceful, <ref cRef="F.106.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-352"/>
                        </l>
                                        <l>And through discipline one will be reborn in the higher realms. </l>
                                        <l>However, not observing the slightest thing anywhere </l>
                                        <l>Is the unsurpassable awakening. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-172"/>
                                <lg tid="160">
                                        <l>“Childish people fixate on their perceptions:</l>
                                        <l>‘I have attained the acceptance that phenomena </l>
                                        <l>Do not arise and are not conditioned.’ </l>
                                        <l>Such is the way unskilled people think. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-173"/>
                                <lg tid="161">
                                        <l>“Yet, even if they strive for ten million eons,</l>
                                        <l>This acceptance is difficult to attain </l>
                                        <l>For those who believe that those phenomena, </l>
                                        <l>Devoid of arising, do arise. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-174"/>
                                <lg tid="162">
                                        <l>“Phenomena are designated with names, </l>
                                        <l>But phenomena are beyond production.</l>
                                        <l>Devoid of root and foundation, </l>
                                        <l>They all have the character of space. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-175"/>
                                <lg tid="163">
                                        <l>“Even if many tens of millions of buddhas expounded</l>
                                        <l>The supremely pure teaching</l>
                                        <l>On abandoning attachment and hatred,</l>
                                        <l>The teachings would still never come to an end.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-177"/>
                                <lg tid="165">
                                        <l>“If these phenomena were real, </l>
                                        <l>They could all really come to an end.</l>
                                        <l>But since they are not real,</l>
                                        <l>An endpoint is never found.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-178"/>
                                <lg tid="166">
                                        <l>“Endless are attachment and hatred,</l>
                                        <l>And so too is delusion.</l>
                                        <l>Devoid of a root are those things</l>
                                        <l>That are devoid of an end.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-180"/>
                                <lg tid="168">
                                        <l>“If there are neither seeds nor sprouts,</l>
                                        <l>How can leaves and fruits originate?</l>
                                        <l>In the same way, that which has no leaves,</l>
                                        <l>Has no flowers.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-181"/>
                                <lg tid="169">
                                        <l>“Within the non-arising of phenomena, </l>
                                        <l>The seeds of beings cannot be found. </l>
                                        <l>Since there are no seeds of beings, </l>
                                        <l>There is no arising and no nirvāṇa.</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-182"/>
                                <lg tid="170">
                                        <l>“Barren women</l>
                                        <l>Have no children.</l>
                                        <l>Thus, if they have no children,</l>
                                        <l>They are free from sorrow regarding those children! </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-183"/>
                                <lg tid="171">
                                        <l>“Likewise, those wandering in saṃsāra</l>
                                        <l>Who realize and understand </l>
                                        <l>That all phenomena are devoid of arising</l>
                                        <l>Are free from fear of suffering. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-184"/>
                                <lg tid="172">
                                        <l>“Childish people are deluded by nonexistence </l>
                                        <l>And therefore do not recognize the nature of phenomena. </l>
                                        <l>Encumbered by space as if it were a burden,</l>
                                        <l>Weary will be those who are unwise! </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-185"/>
                                <lg tid="173">
                                        <l>“But free from sorrow </l>
                                        <l>Are those who know phenomena</l>
                                        <l>As nonexistent, endless,</l>
                                        <l>Innumerable, and measureless. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-186"/>
                                <lg tid="174">
                                        <l>“I have taught that all limits in the sense of a beginning</l>
                                        <l>Or an ending are nonexistent.</l>
                                        <l>Likewise, all limits, such as an ending</l>
                                        <l>Or a middle, are of a single character. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-187"/>
                                <lg tid="175">
                                        <l>“Limits resulting from conceptual thought are devoid of limit.</l>
                                        <l>Thus, limits are fictitious and nonexistent.</l>
                                        <l>If all things have been understood in this way,</l>
                                        <l>There will never be two separate entities. <ref cRef="F.106.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-353"/>
                        </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-188"/>
                                <lg tid="176">
                                        <l>“Because limits have the character of space,</l>
                                        <l>The limits of beings are inconceivable. </l>
                                        <l>Because limits are like sensory distortions,</l>
                                        <l>One does not realize wisdom. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-189"/>
                                <lg tid="177">
                                        <l>“If one engages in discursive thought,</l>
                                        <l>How will negativity ever end?</l>
                                        <l>One will likewise fancy,</l>
                                        <l>‘One day I will become a buddha.’ </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-190"/>
                                <lg tid="178">
                                        <l>“Since buddhas are unborn,</l>
                                        <l>For them there is no arising.</l>
                                        <l>And yet, childish people accept phenomena </l>
                                        <l>That do not arise, as arising. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-191"/>
                                <lg tid="179">
                                        <l>“One cannot take space as a foundation, </l>
                                        <l>Or abide in, or settle in space. </l>
                                        <l>Space is without abiding, </l>
                                        <l>Obstruction, or substance. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-192"/>
                                <lg tid="180">
                                        <l>“Just as space is not a substantial thing, </l>
                                        <l>So too should we understand awakening. </l>
                                        <l>Just as we should understand awakening, </l>
                                        <l>So too should we understand the world. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-193"/>
                                <lg tid="181">
                                        <l>“Identical are the expanse of space, </l>
                                        <l>Awakening, and the constitutions of beings. </l>
                                        <l>For those who know these to be equal,</l>
                                        <l>Awakening is easy to attain. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-194"/>
                                <lg tid="182">
                                        <l>“For those who neither strive for awakening,</l>
                                        <l>Nor direct their mind in the appropriate way,</l>
                                        <l>Nor analyze phenomena, </l>
                                        <l>Awakening is easy to attain. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-195"/>
                                <lg tid="183">
                                        <l>“Awakening cannot be analyzed.</l>
                                        <l>However much one analyzes,</l>
                                        <l>One can never realize unsurpassable awakening</l>
                                        <l>Through the achievements of mind. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-196"/>
                                <lg tid="184">
                                        <l>“When one thinks that awakening is attained through generosity,</l>
                                        <l>There is no attainment of awakening at all,</l>
                                        <l>Whether there is a generous intention or any other intention.</l>
                                        <l>Nonattainment is the supreme awakening! </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-197"/>
                                <lg tid="185">
                                        <l>“Those who are fixated on having a disciplined mind, </l>
                                        <l>Who conceive of diligence as truth itself</l>
                                        <l>And become engaged in conceptions,</l>
                                        <l>Do not practice my teaching. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-198"/>
                                <lg tid="186">
                                        <l>“I have given instructions about the practice</l>
                                        <l>Without attachments to any phenomena. </l>
                                        <l>That which is free from the slightest undertaking </l>
                                        <l>Is the unsurpassable practice. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-199"/>
                                <lg tid="187">
                                        <l>“Mistaken are the thoughts </l>
                                        <l>Of those who think:</l>
                                        <l>‘These phenomena are undefiled’</l>
                                        <l>Or ‘Those phenomena are defiled.’ </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-200"/>
                                <lg tid="188">
                                        <l>“But unsurpassed is the insight of those </l>
                                        <l>Who regard phenomena as inconceivable,</l>
                                        <l>As being similar to space, </l>
                                        <l>And who are neither bound nor liberated. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-201"/>
                                <lg tid="189">
                                        <l>“Conceiving of anyone as having discipline </l>
                                        <l>Or lacking discipline</l>
                                        <l>Are both explained as inferior discipline. <ref cRef="F.107.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-354"/>
                        </l>
                                        <l>That which is nondual is supreme discipline. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-202"/>
                                <lg tid="190">
                                        <l>“Thus, those who perceive and understand phenomena </l>
                                        <l>As indistinguishable,</l>
                                        <l>Without differences or defining characteristics, </l>
                                        <l>Uphold my teaching. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-203"/>
                                <lg tid="191">
                                        <l>“Those whose minds are like space</l>
                                        <l>Proceed in the direction of nonattachment.</l>
                                        <l>Likewise, perfect is the virtuous endeavor </l>
                                        <l>Of those free from attachment to wisdom. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-204"/>
                                <lg tid="192">
                                        <l>“Awakening is not hard to attain</l>
                                        <l>For those who do not analyze the slightest thing, </l>
                                        <l>Without any kind of deliberation</l>
                                        <l>And no ideas of beings or phenomena. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-205"/>
                                <lg tid="193">
                                        <l>“Awakening is not hard to attain </l>
                                        <l>For those who are not confined to the limits of attachment, </l>
                                        <l>Yet are also not separating from attachment</l>
                                        <l>Or trying to gain victory over attachment. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-206"/>
                                <lg tid="194">
                                        <l>“Awakening is not hard to attain</l>
                                        <l>For those who never lose courage throughout the eons, </l>
                                        <l>And who neither become afraid of limits,</l>
                                        <l>Nor terrified of saṃsāra.”</l>
                                </lg>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-207"/>
                                <p tid="195">After the Blessed One had uttered these verses, he said to Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, twenty laudable
                                        qualities will certainly be possessed by those who have faith in this Dharma discourse, do not doubt it, do not question
                                        it, but transmit it, memorize it, recite it, accomplish it, and also correctly teach it in detail to others. </p>
                                 <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-329"/>
                                 <p tid="234">“What are
                                        these twenty qualities? (1) They will be protected by the gods, (2) the nāgas, (3) and the yakṣas. (4) Their minds will
                                        remain undistracted. (5) They will recall their former lives after they are reborn. (6) They will obtain the five
                                        extrasensory powers. (7) They will immediately see the bodhisattva Maitreya when they die. (8) If they thus keep this
                                        Dharma discourse in mind without any distraction and also eliminate indolence, they should expect to see the Buddha and
                                        bodhisattvas in their dreams. (9) If they have faith in this Dharma discourse, they should expect to accept that
                                        phenomena are in complete harmony with it. (10) If they contemplate this Dharma discourse, they should expect to be free
                                        from malicious thoughts in this very life. (11) Even if they come into contact with swift-acting venom, they should
                                        expect to be free from fear, provided that they keep this Dharma discourse in mind. (12) Furthermore, they should expect
                                        to put an end to all opposition. <ref cRef="F.107.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-355"/> (13) They should also expect to attain the all-illuminating absorption. (14)
                                        Once they directly understand this Dharma discourse, they should expect to purify all karmic obscurations. (15)
                                        Moreover, if they explain this Dharma discourse, they should expect to gain access to countless Dharma gates. (16) They
                                        will also certainly remember the thought of awakening and possess the dhāraṇī <distinct>infinite recitation</distinct>.
                                        (17) Furthermore, if they keep in mind this Dharma discourse, they will certainly not be encircled by māras. (18) They
                                        will also certainly be reborn in the presence of the Buddha. (19) All their aspirations will certainly be fulfilled.
                                        (20) They will certainly be protected from all species of venomous beings, including those without legs, and those with
                                        two, four, or more legs. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-208"/>
                                <p tid="235">“Hence, they will certainly be free from fears that upset even human kings. Mañjuśrī, Dharma teachers who do not doubt this
                                        Dharma discourse, and who do not question it, but memorize it, hold it, recite it, accomplish it, and further, correctly
                                        teach it in detail to others will certainly possess these twenty laudable qualities.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-209"/>
                                <p tid="197">Youthful Mañjuśrī then spoke these words: “Blessed One, it may be illustrated as follows: All medicinal trees pacify the
                                        diseases of beings. Likewise, this Dharma discourse should also be regarded as completely pacifying all diseases.” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="198">“So it is, Mañjuśrī, so it is,” the Blessed One replied. “Your words are well spoken. This Dharma discourse completely
                                        pacifies all diseases. Why? Because, Mañjuśrī, countless eons in the past, a tathāgata, a worthy one, a complete and
                                        perfect buddha called Walking Like a Lion appeared in the world. <ref cRef="F.108.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-356"/> From afar, he expounded this Dharma discourse
                                        to many hundreds of thousands of beings. At that time, he summoned and included in his retinue a bodhisattva called
                                        Victory Banner of the Vajra, who heard this Dharma discourse from that tathāgata. Thereupon, with a mind free from
                                        distraction, doubt, or disbelief, he retained this Dharma discourse with its twenty laudable qualities and became
                                        accomplished in it. He came to possess the power of faith. He traveled to towns, villages, valleys, lands, provinces,
                                        and royal palaces where he proclaimed himself as a healer. Thereafter, thousands of beings tormented by various diseases
                                        swiftly arrived where the bodhisattva Victory Banner of the Vajra was staying so that he could save their lives. The
                                        bodhisattva, with a mind abiding in the power of faith, offered them this Dharma scripture. The mantra syllables of
                                        knowledge that arose from this Dharma discourse offered them protection, salvation, and assistance. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-211"/>
                                <p tid="199">“Mañjuśrī, what is the sounding of this particular mantra of knowledge? </p>
                                
                                <p tid="200" rend="mantra">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tadyathā alata vitāla vibhrina atirtha abhrida anuḍa vibramha nahikhagarunga
                                                māyāsukha <term type="ignore">ānanda</term> jālada nadamitra amitra jotrahita sarvadatrala aṃgamaṃga arthayuta sabrāmāyiśa</mantra>
                    </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-213"/>
                                <p tid="201">“The utterance of this mantra of knowledge protected those beings. On account of this, beings intensely tormented by various
                                        diseases were fully freed from all their afflictions, whether they had ingested poison, or were harmed by non-humans,
                                        possessed by any noxious type of creatures, consumed by a disease, afflicted by leprosy, or struck by a sickness related
                                        to wind, bile, or phlegm. Thus, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattva Victory Banner of the Vajra, who abided by this Dharma
                                        discourse, <ref cRef="F.108.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-357"/> fully freed those beings from disease. What do you think, Mañjuśrī? If you think I was somebody
                                        other than the bodhisattva called Victory Banner of the Vajra at that time, in that life, you should abandon that view.
                                        Why? Because at that time, in that life, I myself was the bodhisattva called Victory Banner of the Vajra. I had faith in
                                        this Dharma discourse and acted for the sake of those very beings. According to this discourse, Mañjuśrī, you should
                                        understand it in this way: regard this Dharma discourse as the source of all medicines.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-214"/>
                                <p tid="202">“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī, “how should bodhisattvas who memorize, keep, and realize the words of this mantra of knowledge
                                        put it into practice?” </p>
                                
                                <p tid="203">The Blessed One answered, “Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas who recite this mantra of knowledge should practice cleanliness and should
                                        not eat meat. They should not massage their feet or engage in social distractions. They should again and again develop
                                        feelings of kindness toward all beings. They should not resent those who happen to hurt them. Furthermore, they should
                                        not chant this Dharma discourse without performing ablutions. Neither should they keep it in a filthy place.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-216"/>
                                <p tid="204">“Blessed One, it seems to me that bodhisattvas who teach this Dharma discourse should even disregard their own body and
                                        life,” said Mañjuśrī.</p>
                                
                                <p tid="205">“So it is, Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One. “It is just as you have said it is.”</p>
                                 <lb/>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-218"/>
                                <p tid="206">Then, the Blessed One spoke to the venerable Ānanda: “Because this Dharma discourse will benefit many beings, Ānanda, you
                                        should remember it. Ānanda, beings who yearn for this Dharma discourse will be subdued by the strength of the bull and
                                        the strength of the elephant. Ānanda, <ref cRef="F.109.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-358"/> those who arouse faith in this Dharma discourse will stride like a lion,
                                        like a bull. Ānanda, this Dharma discourse delights bodhisattvas and makes them appear. After I have passed away, it
                                        will come into the hands of bodhisattvas, into their scriptures and repositories. It will not come into the hands,
                                        scriptures, or repositories of outcast bodhisattvas.”</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-219"/>
                                <p tid="207">“Blessed One, I will hold this Dharma discourse in precisely the way it was explained by the Tathāgata,” promised the
                                        venerable Ānanda.</p>
                                
                                <p tid="208">“Excellent, Ānanda,” replied the Blessed One. “It is excellent that you will commit yourself to teaching this Dharma
                                        discourse, just as you have received it, to the beings for whom it was given.” </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-221"/>
                                <p tid="209">After the Blessed One had uttered these words, the venerable Ānanda, the venerable Śāriputra, Youthful Mañjuśrī, and the
                                        worlds of the gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-222"/>
                                <trailer tid="210">This completes the Great Vehicle sūtra “<title xml:lang="en">The Strength of the Elephant</title>.”</trailer>
                </div>
                        </div>
                </body>
                <back>
                        <div type="notes">
                                <head type="notes" tid="211">Notes</head>
                        </div>
                        <div type="listBibl">
                                <head type="listBibl" tid="213">Bibliography</head>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-listBibl-1">
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-240">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal gyi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra</title>). Toh
                                        207, Degé Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, tsha), folios 95.a–109.a.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-241">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang po’i rtsal gyi mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur],
                                        krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the
                                        China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                                        Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 62, pp. 254–88.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-242">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Denkarma</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang 
                                        ldan dkar gyi chos ’gyur ro cog gi dkar chag</title>). Toh 4364<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh4364.html"/>, Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios
                                                294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-243">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Phangthangma</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>). Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang,
                                        2003.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-244">Apple, James B. “The Phrase <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmaparyāyo hastagato</foreign> in Mahāyāna Buddhist Literature: Rethinking the Cult of the Book in
                                        Middle Period Indian Mahāyāna Buddhism.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the American Oriental Society</title> 134.1 (2014), pp. 25–50.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-245">Boucher, Daniel. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattvas of the Forest and the Formation of the Mahāyāna: A Study and Translation
                                                of the Rāṣṭrapālaparipṛcchā-sūtra</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawai’i Press, 2009.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-246">Chen, Huaiyu. “Newly Identified Khotanese Fragments in the British Library and Their Chinese Parallels.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society</title> 22.2 (2012), pp. 265–79.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-247">Conze, Edward. <title xml:lang="en">The Large Sutra on Perfect Wisdom: With the Divisions of the Abhisamayālaṅkāra</title>.
                                        Berkeley: University of California Press, 1975.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-248">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher
                                                Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Vienna: Verlag
                                                der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-249">Phuntsho, Karma. <title xml:lang="en">Mipham’s Dialectics and the Debates on Emptiness: To Be, Not to Be or Neither</title>.
                                        London: Routledge, 2005.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-250">Ray, Reginald A. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Saints in India: A Study in Buddhist Values
                                                and Orientations</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 1994. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-007-251">Zhen, Liu and Chen, Huaiyu. “Some reflections on an early Mahāyāna text Hasti­kakṣya­sūtra.” <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of
                                                the School of Oriental and African Studies</title> 77.2 (2014), pp. 293–312.</bibl>
                         </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="glossary">
  <list type="glossary">
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-252">
        <term>absorption</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi </term>
        <term type="definition">A general term for the practice of meditative <term type="ignore">absorption</term> aimed at developing profound states of concentration.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-253">
        <term>accomplishment of perfect peace</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu zhi ba sgrub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་སྒྲུབ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">Name of a meditative absorption.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-062-007-254" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>Become a renunciant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" status="verified">rab tu byung</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pravrajate</term>
                            <term type="alternative">become renunciants</term>
                            <term type="definition">Refers to one who has left the life of a householder and embraced the life of a wandering, renunciate follower of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-255">
        <term>cakravartin</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor los sgyur ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravartin</term>
        <term type="definition">A <term type="ignore">cakravartin</term> is a king who rules over at least one continent, and gains his territory by the rolling of his magic wheel over
          the land. Therefore he is called a king with the revolving wheel. This is as the result of the merit he has accumulated in previous lifetimes.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-256">
        <term>conceptual signs</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་མ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nimitta</term>
        <term type="definition">Conceptual characteristics or reifications that lead to distraction and a false understanding of reality.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-257">
        <term>conquering all forms</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs thams cad rnam par gnon pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་གནོན་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">Name of a meditative absorption.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-258">
        <term>defilement</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟག་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asrava</term>
        <term type="definition">Literally “outflows,” these are mental <term type="ignore">defilements</term> or contaminations that “flow out” toward the objects of cyclic existence,
          binding us to them.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-259">
        <term>dhāraṇī</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
        <term type="definition">This term is used in various ways. For instance, it refers to the mental capacity of not forgetting, enabling one in particular
          to cultivate positive forces and to ward off negativity. It is also very commonly used as a term for mystical verses similar to mantras, the usage of
          which will grant a particular power.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-260">
        <term>discernment</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhag mthong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷག་མཐོང་།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vipaśyana</term>
        <term type="definition">The mental factor or power that discerns phenomena and ascertains the true nature of things.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-261">
        <term>domain of truth</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
        <term type="definition">The expanse of phenomena, the sphere of ultimate reality.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-262">
        <term>five extrasensory powers</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par shes pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcābhijñā</term>
        <term type="definition">(1) The divine eye, (2) the divine ear, (3) knowledge of others’ minds, (4) recollection of past lives, and (5) miracles.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-263">
        <term>gandharva</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
        <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Gandharvas</term> (literally “odor eaters”) are generally regarded as a class of menacing divine offspring, but in Abhidharma the term
          is often used differently—as a synonym for the mental body assumed by any sentient being of the world system of desire (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāma­dhātu</foreign>) during
          the intermediate state between death and rebirth.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-264">
        <term>great lotus</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad mo chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མོ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāpadma</term>
        <term type="definition">Name of a meditative absorption.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-062-007-265" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śravaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Followers, literally “<term type="ignore">hearers</term>,” of those teachings of the Buddha that focus on the monastic lifestyle and liberating oneself from suffering, in contrast to followers of the Bodhisattva Vehicle who seek buddhahood for the sake of all beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-266">
        <term>infinite recitation</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas par ’khyil pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་ཡས་པར་འཁྱིལ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">Name of a dhāraṇī.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-267">
        <term>inner absorption</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang du yang dag ’jog pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃlayana</term>
        <term type="definition">This term can mean both physical seclusion and a meditative state of withdrawal.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-268">
        <term>lay vow holder</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བསྙེན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāsaka</term>
        <term type="definition">An unordained male practitioner who observes the five vows not to kill, lie, steal, be intoxicated, or commit sexual
          misconduct.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-269">
        <term>māra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māra</term>
        <term type="definition">The demon who assailed Śākyamuni prior to his awakening; any demonic force; the personification of conceptual and emotional
          obstacles.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-062-007-270" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>meditative state</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyam par bzhag pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉམ་པར་བཞག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samāhita</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally meaning correct (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyak</foreign>) acquisition (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āpatti</foreign>) of truth or reality, this is a term used in early Buddhism to refer to the succession of <term type="ignore">meditative states</term> leading to the attainment of nirvāṇa. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-271">
        <term>mendicant</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod snyoms spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསོད་སྙོམས་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">piṇḍa­pāta­cārikin</term>
        <term type="definition">One who engages in asceticism.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-272">
        <term>moral discipline</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུལ་བ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vinaya</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the three Piṭakas, or “Baskets,” of the Buddhist canon; the one dealing specifically with the code of monastic
          disipline.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-273">
        <term>nirvāṇa</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</term>
        <term type="definition">Literally “extinction,” the state beyond sorrow, it refers to the ultimate attainment of buddhahood, the permanent cessation of
          all suffering and of the afflicted mental states that lead to suffering. Three types of <term type="ignore">nirvāṇa</term> are identified: (1) the residual <term type="ignore">nirvāṇa</term> where the
          person is still dependent on conditioned psycho-physical aggregates, (2) the non-residual <term type="ignore">nirvāṇa</term> where the aggregates have also been consumed within
          emptiness, and (3) the non-abiding <term type="ignore">nirvāṇa</term> transcending the extremes of phenomenal existence and quiescence. </term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-274">
        <term>noble (one)</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārya</term>
        <term type="definition">An honorific term used to refer to anything of exalted status. Thus, it can refer to a <term type="ignore">noble</term> person, one of a higher class or
          caste. In the context of Buddhism, it refers to one who has gained realization on the path of seeing and thus understands selflessness.</term>
        <term type="alternative">noble</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-275">
        <term>non-Buddhist</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu stegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་སྟེགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthika</term>
        <term type="definition">Adherents of <term type="ignore">non-Buddhist</term> spiritual traditions.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-276">
        <term>outcast bodhisattvas</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’ gdol ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གདོལ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhi­sattva­cāṇḍāla</term>
        <term type="definition">Bodhisattvas who are attached to disciplined practices and living in remote areas.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-277">
        <term>particular display illuminating the abandonment of all activities</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyod pa thams cad la btang ba snang ba’i khyad par ston pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བཏང་བ་སྣང་བའི་ཁྱད་པར་སྟོན་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">Name of a meditative absorption.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-279">
        <term>settling in complete peace</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar zhi ba la ’jug pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བ་ལ་འཇུག་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upaśamapraveśa</term>
        <term type="definition">Name of a meditative absorption.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-280">
        <term>solitary realizers</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
        <term type="definition">Literally, “buddha for himself,” or “solitary realizer.” Those who attain buddhahood in a time when a buddha’s doctrine is no
          longer available in the world, and who remain either in solitude or among peers, without teaching the path of liberation to others. They are
          sometimes called “rhinoceros-like” for their preference to stay in solitude.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-281">
        <term>subduing and illuminating</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par gnon cing rnam par gsal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་གནོན་ཅིང་རྣམ་པར་གསལ་བ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vispaṣṭa</term>
        <term type="definition">Name of a meditative absorption.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-282">
        <term>sugata</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sugata</term>
        <term type="definition">An epithet of the buddhas meaning “one who has gone to bliss.” Here used also as an epithet of the Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-283">
        <term>tathāgata</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
        <term type="definition">A frequently used synonym for <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddha</foreign>, literally meaning “One Who Has Thus Gone.” The expression is interpreted in
          different ways, but in general it implies “one who has departed in the wake of the buddhas of the past,” or “one who has manifested the supreme
          enlightenment dependent on the reality that does not abide in the two extremes of existence and quiescence.”</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-284">
        <term>thought of awakening</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub tu sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</term>
        <term type="definition">In Mahāyāna Buddhism, this refers to the altruistic resolve to achieve complete and perfect buddhahood for the sake of oneself
          and all sentient beings.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-285">
        <term>three Dharma robes </term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos gos gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་གོས་གསུམ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tricīvara</term>
        <term type="definition">These include the outer robe (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bla gos</foreign>), the lower robe (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthang gos</foreign>), and the monk’s shawl (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snam
            sbyar</foreign>).</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-286">
        <term>transcendent insight</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</term>
        <term type="definition">The sixth of the six perfections, it refers to the profound understanding of the emptiness of all phenomena, the realization of
          ultimate reality.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-287">
        <term>venerable</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe dang ldan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ayuṣmat</term>
        <term type="definition">A respectful form of address between monks and also lay companions of equal standing. Literally, one who has a [long]
          life.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-288">
        <term>world system</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">lokadhātu</term>
        <term type="definition">This can refer to one world with its orbiting sun and moon, and also to groups of these worlds in multiples of thousands, in
          particular a world relam of a thousand million worlds, which is said to be circular, with its circumference twice as long as its diameter.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-289">
        <term>worthy one</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
        <term type="definition">One who has achieved the fourth and final level of attainment on the śrāvaka path, and who has thus attained liberation with the
          cessation of all mental afflictions.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-290">
        <term>Accumulation of All Precious Roots of Virtue</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i rtsa ba rin po che thams cad bsags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཐམས་ཅད་བསགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-291">
        <term>Ajita Keśakambalī</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dkar ba skra’i la ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དཀར་བ་སྐྲའི་ལ་བ་ཅན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ajita Keśakambalī</term>
        <term type="definition">An Indian ascetic who propounded the extreme of annihilation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ucchedavāda</foreign>).</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-292">
        <term>Ānanda</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
        <term type="definition">A monk of the Buddha’s order, brother of Devadatta, who for twenty-five years served as the Buddha’s personal attendant. Second
          in the apostolic succession that carried on the Buddha’s teachings after his parinirvāṇa.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-293">
        <term>Beyond All Utterances, Speech, and Sounds</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrar rjod pa dang dbyangs dang nga ro thams cad las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲར་རྗོད་པ་དང་དབྱངས་དང་ང་རོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-062-007-294" type="person" mode="match">
                            <term>blessed one</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="definition">“One who has bhaga,” which has many diverse meanings including “good fortune,” “happiness,” and “majesty.” In the Buddhist context, it means one who has the good fortune of attaining enlightenment. The Tibetan translation has three syllables defined to mean “one who has conquered (the maras), possesses (the qualities of enlightenment), and has transcended (saṃsāra, or both saṃsāra and nirvāṇa).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-295">
        <term>Blossom of the Four Jewels</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin po che bzhi’i me tog rgyas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་པོ་ཆེ་བཞིའི་མེ་ཏོག་རྒྱས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-296">
        <term>Essence of the Splendor of Overwhelming Sound</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par gnon pa’i sgra sgrogs gzi brjid snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་གནོན་པའི་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་གཟི་བརྗིད་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-297">
        <term>Gladdened with Supreme Joy</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par dga’ bas mgu ba skyed pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་དགའ་བས་མགུ་བ་སྐྱེད་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-298">
        <term>Ju Mipham Gyatso</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’ju mi pham rgya mtsho </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇུ་མི་ཕམ་རྒྱ་མཚོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">A famous polymath of the Tibetan Ancient (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnying ma</foreign>) tradition (1846-1912) whose collected writings fill thirty-three
          volumes.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-299">
        <term>Kakuda Kātyāyana</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpon po kA tyA ya na </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔོན་པོ་ཀཱ་ཏྱཱ་ཡ་ན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kakuda Kātyāyana</term>
        <term type="definition">A teacher associated with Maskari Gośāliputra and the doctrine of non-action (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akriyāvāda</foreign>), a type of
          antinomianism.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-300">
        <term>Kaśyapa</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kaśyapa</term>
        <term type="definition">An Indian sage, also known as Pūraṇa Kaśyapa, who maintained the doctrine of non-action <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">(akriyāvāda</foreign>). Not to be
          confused with one of the Buddha’s foremost disciples, who had the same name.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-301">
        <term>Light Beam of Great Lightning</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glog chen sgron ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གློག་ཆེན་སྒྲོན་མ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-302">
        <term>Light Vanquishing with Undefiled Forces</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpung pa dri ma med pas ’od zer bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔུང་པ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པས་འོད་ཟེར་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-303">
        <term>Lofty Like Mount Meru’s Summit</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab brtsegs pa ltar mngon par ’phags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རབ་བརྩེགས་པ་ལྟར་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-304">
        <term>Maskari Gośāliputra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ska ri ’ga’ ba ya la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་སྐ་རི་འགའ་བ་ཡ་ལ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maskari Gośāliputra</term>
              <term type="definition">An Indian teacher associated with the Ājīvika sect. His doctrine is known as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra­viśuddhi</foreign>, i.e., the doctrine of
          purity for getting rid of the cycle of birth and death.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-305">
        <term>Nirgrantha Jñatiputra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gcer bu pa nye du’u bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཅེར་བུ་པ་ཉེ་དུའུ་བུ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirgrantha Jñatiputra</term>
        <term type="definition">Also known as the Mahāvīra, the founder of the Jaina sect.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-306">
        <term>Overcoming Fears with Words of Renown</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grags pa’i sgras ’jigs pa bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲགས་པའི་སྒྲས་འཇིགས་པ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-307">
        <term>Perseverant Beyond Compare and Wise</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus dpe med blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དཔེ་མེད་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-308">
        <term>Possessing Vajralike Solidity</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje lta bur brtan pa thob pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟན་པ་ཐོབ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-309">
        <term>Reaching the Far Shore of Definitive Meaning to Fulfill Beings’ Aspirations</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can gyi bsam pa nges pa’i don gyi pha rol tu bgrod par dong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེམས་ཅན་གྱི་བསམ་པ་ངེས་པའི་དོན་གྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་བགྲོད་པར་དོང་བ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-311">
        <term>Sañjayi Vairattīputra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun rgyal ’be’i ra ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་རྒྱལ་འབེའི་ར་ཏིའི་བུ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sañjayi Vairattīputra</term>
        <term type="definition">A proponent of the doctrine of scepticism (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikṣepavāda</foreign>).</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-312">
        <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ra dwa ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha, renowned for his pure observance of discipline. Also known as Śāriputra.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-313">
        <term>Śāriputra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ri bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་རི་བུ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the major hearers, paired with Maudgalyāyana, and noted for having been praised by the Buddha as foremost of the wise;
          hence, the most frequent target for Vimalakīrti’s attacks on the śrāvakas and on the Hinayāna in general. Also known as Śāradvatīputra.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-314">
        <term>Seeing Beyond Extremes and Transcending All Sensory Objects</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas par lta zhing yul thams cad las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་ཡས་པར་ལྟ་ཞིང་ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-315">
        <term>Victory Banner of the Vajra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje’i rgyal mtshan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajradhvaja</term>
        <term type="definition">The name of a past bodhisattva.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-316">
        <term>Voice More Majestic Than Brahmā’s</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa’i sgra gzi brjid mngon par ’phags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་སྒྲ་གཟི་བརྗིད་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <term type="definition">The name of a bodhisattva in the Buddha’s audience.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-317">
        <term>Walking Like a Lion </term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge’i stabs su ’gro ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེའི་སྟབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha­vikrānta­gati</term>
        <term type="definition">The name of a past Buddha.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-318">
        <term>Youthful Mañjuśrī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nur gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta</term>
        <term type="definition">Mañjuśrī who takes the form of a youth, an epithet by which the well-known bodhisattva is often referred. He is considered to be
          the embodiment of the transcendent perfection of insight and is portrayed wielding a sword in his right hand that cuts through delusion and a volume
          of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñā­pāramitā­sūtra</title> in his left that contains teachings on transcendent insight.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-319">
        <term>Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgod kyi phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhrakūṭa</term>
        <term type="definition">Also known as “Vulture Peak,” a hill located in modern-day Bihar, India, and in the vicinity of the ancient city of Rājagṛha. A
          location where many sūtras were taught and which continues to be a sacred pilgrimage site for Buddhists to this day.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-007-320">
        <term>Rājagṛha</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
        <term type="definition">The capital city, literally “royal city,” of the Indian region of Magadha during the Buddha’s time. </term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
  </list>
</div>
                </back>
        </text>

    
    
    
    </TEI>