<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsum la skyabs su ’gro ba</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">གསུམ་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Triśaraṇa­gamana</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Taking Refuge in the Three Jewels</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་གསུམ་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gsum la skyabs su ’gro ba zhes
                    bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “Taking Refuge
                    in the Three Jewels”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­triśaraṇa­gamana­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-59">Benjamin Collet-Cassart</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <consultant role="dharmaMaster" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay, Dr.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.5 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to
                    make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-063-006"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means
                    that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2020-09-22</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh225" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 225</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 63 (mdo sde, dza), folios 174.a–175.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Sarvajñādeva</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Paltsek</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="3">
                        <volume number="63" start-page="347" end-page="349"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11868" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2022-09-24T23:40:01.428Z" user="admin">24/09/2022 23:40:01</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="3" date-time="2020-09-14T06:37:39.325Z" user="line-tofte">3</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.1" date-time="2020-09-14T06:37:39.325Z" user="line-tofte">0.0.1</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2020-09-14T06:38:02.194Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2020-09-18T12:04:18.599Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2020-09-18T12:04:37.367Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.5" date-time="2020-09-18T12:04:51.167Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-09-18T12:15:58.975Z" user="line-tofte">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.6" date-time="2020-09-18T12:15:58.975Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.7" date-time="2020-09-18T12:19:35.987Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.2" date-time="2020-09-21T07:27:04.989Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2020-09-21T09:36:07.032Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.3" date-time="2020-09-21T09:36:07.032Z" user="mike">0.1.3</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2020-09-21T13:51:19.697Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2020-09-22T09:48:56.871Z" user="mike">1</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2020-09-22T09:48:56.871Z" user="mike">First Published version</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.1" date-time="2020-11-23T13:57:44.998Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.0.0)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.2" date-time="2020-12-11T14:06:50.919Z" user="admin">Auto (TEI migration 2.1.5)</note>
            
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.3" date-time="2021-02-02T10:58:16.324Z" user="mike">Andreas' corrections added</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.4" date-time="2021-11-22T16:09:18.3Z" user="celso">added references to Peter Skillings 2021 anthology</note>
    <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.5" date-time="2022-09-24T23:39:57.419Z" user="andre">Update to the glossary</note>
</notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-1"/>
                <p tid="2">In <title xml:lang="en">Taking Refuge in the Three Jewels</title>, the
                    venerable Śāriputra wonders how much merit accrues to someone who takes refuge
                    in the Three Jewels: the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha. He therefore seeks
                    out the Buddha Śākyamuni and requests a teaching on this topic. The Buddha
                    proceeds to describe how even vast offerings, performed in miraculous ways,
                    would not constitute a fraction of the merit gained by someone who takes refuge
                    in the Three Jewels.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-2"/>
                <p tid="4">This text was translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under
                    the guidance of Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. Benjamin Collet-Cassart translated the
                    text from Tibetan. Andreas Doctor compared the draft translation with the
                    original Tibetan, edited the text, and wrote the introduction.</p>
                <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
                <!--<lb/>
                <p>[Sponsored by XXXXXX]</p>-->
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="6">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-introduction-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Taking Refuge in the Three Jewels</title>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-4"> Although the title in
                            the Degé version only reads <title xml:lang="en">Taking Refuge in the
                                Three</title>, we have added <distinct>Jewels</distinct> based on
                            the title as it appears in the Stok Palace manuscript. This is also
                            clearly the subject and meaning of the text.</note> unfolds in the Jeta
                        Grove at Śrāvastī, where the Buddha Śākyamuni is residing with a large
                        gathering of monks. The sūtra begins as the venerable Śāriputra, who is
                        practicing meditation alone in the forest, wonders how much merit is
                        obtained by those who take refuge in the Three Jewels: the Buddha, the
                        Dharma, and the Saṅgha. After finishing his meditation practice,
                        Śāriputra goes before the Buddha Śākyamuni and requests the Buddha to teach
                        on that topic. In his answer, the Buddha presents an analogy that is meant
                        to describe the enormous merit that such devotees obtain. Even if someone
                        could magically erect a stūpa the size of the entire world and make vast,
                        miraculous offerings to it for eons on end, the merit gained thereby would
                        not constitute even a fraction of the merit gained by those who take refuge
                        in the Three Jewels. After the Buddha has delivered this teaching, the earth
                        quakes, lightning strikes, and the gods in the heavens play divine music to
                        celebrate the teaching. Finally, the Buddha instructs Ānanda to remember the
                        teaching so that he can pass it on to others.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-5"/>
                    <p tid="8">Very little is known about the history of this text in India. The
                        Sanskrit version of this sūtra is no longer extant, and it seems to have
                        never been translated into Chinese. Hence, the only witness of this sūtra
                        available today is the Tibetan translation included in the Kangyur. The
                        colophon of the Tibetan translation states that it was produced by the
                        Indian paṇḍita Sarvajñādeva and the Tibetan translator-editor Paltsek, thus locating its translation in the late eighth or early ninth
                        century. This dating is also confirmed by the text’s inclusion in the
                        Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhan/ldan dkar ma</foreign>) catalog of
                        the early ninth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-6">The Denkarma catalog is dated to
                            ca. 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. See Denkarma, folio 301.a.3. See also Herrmann-Pfandt
                            (2008), p. 162, no. 298. </note> The text has previously been translated
                        into English by Kenneth Liberman with the assistance of Jampa Losel in 1988, and most recently, there is another English translation by Peter Skilling, along with some helpful 
                        notes, found in his 2021 anthology <title xml:lang="en">Questioning the Buddha: A Selection of Twenty-Five Sutras</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-47">Skilling (2021), pp. 189–98.</note> 
                        The translation presented here was made primarily based on the
                        Degé edition, in consultation with the Comparative Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) and the Stok Palace manuscript
                        edition. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="9"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="10">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="11">Taking Refuge in the Three Jewels</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-section-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-7"/>
                    <p tid="12">
                        <ref cRef="F.174.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-44"/> Homage to the Three Jewels!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-8"/>
                    <p tid="14">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was residing at Jeta
                        Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s park at Śrāvastī, together with a great saṅgha of
                        1,250 monks. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-9"/>
                    <p tid="15">At that time, while the venerable Śāradvatīputra was alone in the
                        forest, this thought arose in his mind: “I should go before the Teacher so
                        that I can ask the Blissful One, the Dharma Lord, this question: ‘How much
                        merit is accumulated by faithful noble sons or noble daughters who take
                        refuge in the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha of monks?’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-10"/>
                    <p tid="16">At dusk the venerable Śāriputra emerged from his meditative
                        seclusion and went to see the Blessed One. When he arrived, he bowed his
                        head to the Blessed One’s feet and sat to one side. While seated to the
                        side, the venerable Śāriputra asked the Blessed One, “Honored One, while I
                        was staying alone in the forest in meditative seclusion, this thought arose
                        in my mind: ‘How much merit is accumulated by faithful noble sons or noble
                        daughters who take refuge in the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha of
                        monks?’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-11"/>
                    <p tid="17">The Blessed One replied to the venerable Śāriputra, “Śāriputra, you
                        have asked this question in order to benefit and bring happiness to many
                        beings. Out of love for the world, you seek to help a vast number of beings,
                            <ref cRef="F.174.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-45"/> gods and humans alike, by
                        accomplishing their welfare and happiness. That is excellent, excellent!
                        Śāriputra, as you have thought to come and question the Thus-Gone One about
                        this matter, I will reply with an analogy to make you understand.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-12"/>
                    <p tid="18">“Imagine that someone endowed with magical powers were to transfer
                        into another world all the beings that live in Jambudvīpa—the land of
                        Jambudvīpa and its subcontinents, which measure seven thousand leagues
                        across and lengthwise. Having made the ground even like the palm of a hand,
                        that person would then build a stūpa made of the seven precious gems—gold,
                        silver, beryl, crystal, red coral, emerald, and white coral. It would be the
                        size of Jambudvīpa, and its summit would reach the Brahmā realms. That
                        person would then worship that stūpa with offerings of divine incense,
                        divine flowers, divine garlands, and divine parasols, banners, and flags.
                        This person endowed with these magical powers would then pour all the water
                        of the four great oceans into another world system and replace it with four
                        oceans filled with maruka oil.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-13"> Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ma ru ka’i til mar</foreign>.</note> He would then
                        place a wick the size of Mount Sumeru into the oceans so that for many eons
                        this oil lamp would continuously burn.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-14"/>
                    <p tid="19">“Śāriputra, tell me, would that person accumulate a lot of merit on
                        that basis?”</p>
                    <p tid="20">“Blessed One, yes, a lot! Blissful One, yes, a lot! This is beyond all the hearers and solitary buddhas. Blessed One, this is the
                        domain of the thus-gone ones. Blissful One, this is the domain of the
                        thus-gone ones.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-15"/>
                    <p tid="21">“Śāriputra, that amount of merit would not match even a hundredth,
                            <ref cRef="F.175.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-46"/> a thousandth, or even a hundred
                        thousandth of the merit created by a noble son or noble daughter who takes
                        refuge in the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha. This difference could not
                        be illustrated by any numbers, examples, or calculations.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-16"/>
                    <p tid="22">When this Dharma teaching was given, the whole great trichiliocosm
                        began to quiver, tremble, quake, wobble, rock, sway, vibrate, shudder, and
                        reel. Great lightning flashes struck, and the gods caused the sound of drums
                        to be heard.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-17"/>
                    <p tid="23">The venerable Ānanda asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, what is
                        the name of this Dharma teaching? How should it be remembered?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-43"/>
                    <p tid="24">The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, you should remember this Dharma
                        teaching as <title xml:lang="en">Accomplishing Limitless
                            Gateways</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-18"> Translated based on Choné, Lithang, Kangxi, Yongle, and
                            Narthang: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sgo mtha’ yas
                                pa</foreign>. Degé and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sgo mtha’ yas pas</foreign>.</note> This is how you should see its
                        meaning, and this is how you should remember it.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-19"/>
                    <p tid="25">When the Blessed One had spoken, the venerable Śāriputra and the
                        other monks praised the Blessed One’s words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-20"/>
                    <trailer tid="26">This concludes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra “Taking Refuge in
                        the Three Jewels.”</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="27">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-21"/>
                    <p tid="28">This was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian upādhyāya
                        Sarvajñādeva and the translator-editor Bandé Paltsek.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="29">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="30">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-22">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gsum la skyabs su ’gro ba zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­triśaraṇa­gamana­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 225, Degé
                        Kangyur vol. 63 (mdo sde, dza), folios 174.a–175.a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-23">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gsum la skyabs su ’gro ba zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­triśaraṇa­gamana­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Stok 196, Stok
                        Palace Kangyur (stog pho brang bris ma) vol. 72 (mdo sde, zha), folios
                        336.a–338.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-24">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa gsum la skyabs su ’gro ba zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative
                        Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
                        bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China
                        Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe
                        skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 63, pp.
                        471–74. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-25">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang
                            stod thang ldan[/ lhan] dkar gyi chos ’gyur ro cog gi dkar
                        chag</title>). Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios
                        294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-26">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische
                            übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Vienna: Verlag der
                        Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-27">Liberman, Kenneth. “The Going for Refuge
                        Sutra.” <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of Tibetology</title>, new series no.
                        1 (1988): 35–36.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-063-006-48">Skilling, Peter. <title xml:lang="en">Questioning the Buddha: A Selection of Twenty-Five 
                        Sutras</title>. Somerville: Wisdom Publications, 2021. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-28">
                            <term>great trichiliocosm </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po’i ’jig rten gyi
                                khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tri­sāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest universe spoken of in Buddhist
                                cosmology, consisting of one billion smaller world systems.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-29">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Primarily referring to those disciples of the
                                Buddha who aspire to attain the state of a worthy one by seeking
                                personal liberation. The term is usually defined as a person who
                                hears the teaching from the Buddha and makes it heard to
                                others.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-30">
                            <term>meditative seclusion </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang du yang dag ’jog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prati­saṃlayana</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term can mean both physical seclusion and a
                                meditative state of withdrawal.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-31">
                            <term>solitary buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyeka­buddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Individuals who, in their last life, attain
                                realization by realizing the nature of dependent origination without
                                relying upon a spiritual guide.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-32">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The personal attendant and cousin of the Buddha,
                                who compiled the sūtras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-33">
                            <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term type="definition">A wealthy householder of Śrāvastī renowned for
                                his generosity. He spent a small fortune to purchase the grove of
                                Prince Jeta, built a monastery there, and offered both to the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-34">
                            <term>Paltsek</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་བརྩེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <!--<term type="definition"><term type="ignore">Paltsek</term>, from the
                                village of Kawa north of Lhasa, was one of Tibet’s preeminent
                                translators. He was one of the first seven Tibetans to be ordained
                                by Śāntarakṣita and is counted as one of Guru Rinpoche’s twenty-five
                                close disciples. In a famous verse by Ngok Lotsawa, <term type="ignore">Paltsek</term> is named along with Chokro Lui
                                Gyaltsen and Zhang Nanam Yeshé as part of a group of translators
                                whose skills were surpassed only by Vairotsana. He translated works
                                from a wide variety of genres, including sūtra, śāstra, vinaya, and
                                tantra, and was an author himself. <term type="ignore">Paltsek</term> was also one of the most important editors of
                                the early period, one of nine translators installed by Trisong
                                Detsen to supervise the translation of the Tripiṭaka and help
                                catalog translated works for the first two of three imperial
                                catalogs (the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan kar ma</title> and
                                    <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam yas mchims phu ma</title>
                                catalogs).</term>-->
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-35">
                            <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ra dwa ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Along with Maudgalyāyana, <term type="ignore">Śāradvatīputra</term> (also known as Śāriputra) was one of the
                                two main disciples of the Buddha. He was renowned for his pure
                                discipline and was praised by the Buddha as being foremost in terms
                                of insight.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-36">
                            <term>Śāriputra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra </term>
                            <term type="definition">The same as Śāradvatīputra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-37">
                            <term>Sarvajñādeva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sarba dz+nyA de ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སརྦ་ཛྙཱ་དེ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarvajñādeva</term>
                            <!--<term type="definition">According to traditional accounts, the Kashmiri
                                abbot <term type="ignore">Sarvajñādeva</term> was among the “one
                                hundred” paṇḍitas invited by Trisong Detsen (r. 755–797/800) to
                                assist with the translation of the Buddhist scriptures into Tibetan.
                                    <term type="ignore">Sarvajñādeva</term> assisted in the
                                translation of more than twenty-three works, including numerous
                                sūtras and the first translations of Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra</title> and Nāgārjuna’s
                                    <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Suhṛllekha</title>. Much of this work
                                was likely carried out in the first years of the ninth century and
                                may have continued into the reign of Ralpachen, who ascended the
                                throne in 815 and died in 838 or 841 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>.</term>-->
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-38">
                            <term>Brahmā realms</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa’i ’jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmāloka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The heaven of Brahmā, usually located just above
                                the desire realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kāmadhātu</foreign>) as one of the first levels of the form
                                realm (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">rūpadhātu</foreign>)
                                and equated with the state that one achieves in the first meditative
                                absorption (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhyāna</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-39">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu’i gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continent (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvīpa</foreign>) on which we live, shaped like a
                                rose apple (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jambū</foreign>)
                                according to ancient South Asian cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-40">
                            <term>Jeta Grove</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jetavana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The grove of Prince Jeta in Śrāvastī purchased
                                by Anāthapiṇḍada; the Buddha taught many of his discourses there,
                                especially during the rainy season retreat.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-41">
                            <term>Mount Sumeru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumeru</term>
                            <term type="definition">The great mountain at the center of the universe
                                according to ancient Indian cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-063-006-42">
                            <term>Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term type="definition">During the life of the Buddha, <term type="ignore">Śrāvastī</term> was a major city in the kingdom of
                                Kosala, in present day Uttar Pradesh.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>

    
    
    
    </TEI>