<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་རྟོགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh">《吉祥軍譬喻經》</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-19">Translated by the Lokākṣi Translator Group<lb/>
                    under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-271">Karen Lang</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-123">Ruth Gamble</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-123">Ruth Gamble</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-125">John Powers</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-124">Harmony DenRonden</editor>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-126">Tenzin Ringpapontsang</author>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-262">David Higgins</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Tom Tillemans</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-289">Nathaniel Rich</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.5 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the
                    Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the
                        protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0
                        copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for
                        commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons
                        license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-076-003"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the
                    standard logic.</note>
                <date>2021-03-19</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh349" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 349</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 76 (mdo sde, ah), folios 31.b–50.a</biblScope>
                        <author role="translatorTib">Dharmaśrībhadra</author>
                        <author role="translatorTib">Sherab Lekpa</author>
                        <author role="translatorTib">Rinchen Zangpo</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="38">
                        <volume number="76" start-page="62" end-page="99"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12038" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2022-06-29T16:04:10.098Z" user="admin">29/06/2022 16:04:10</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-11-19T09:53:56.455Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-01-28T06:21:45.49Z" user="mike">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.h" date-time="2020-03-16T10:59:57.706Z" user="line-tofte">2.h</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.1" date-time="2020-10-20T11:28:10.758Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.2" date-time="2020-10-20T11:29:10.266Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.3" date-time="2020-10-20T11:30:32.107Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2020-10-20T11:31:08.704Z" user="line-tofte">2.g</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2020-10-20T11:31:08.704Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.5" date-time="2020-11-06T09:17:15.641Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-11-06T09:18:41.394Z" user="line-tofte">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.6" date-time="2020-11-06T09:18:41.394Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2021-01-12T12:35:08.998Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.7" date-time="2021-01-12T12:35:08.998Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2021-01-12T14:01:11.73Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.8" date-time="2021-01-12T14:01:11.73Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.9" date-time="2021-01-27T12:29:52.802Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2021-02-09T07:59:03.477Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.10" date-time="2021-02-09T07:59:03.477Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.11" date-time="2021-02-26T20:22:55.245Z" user="mike">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2021-02-26T20:23:19.124Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.12" date-time="2021-02-26T20:23:19.124Z" user="mike">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2021-03-08T09:22:10.699Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2021-03-08T09:22:10.699Z" user="mike">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2021-03-08T13:20:39.984Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2021-03-19T00:50:36.398Z" user="mike">1</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2021-03-19T00:50:36.398Z" user="mike">First published version</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.1" date-time="2021-03-19T17:47:55.543Z" user="konchog">Made about a dozen tiny fixes throughout.</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.2" date-time="2021-04-15T08:25:40.236Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.3" date-time="2021-06-09T12:15:29.604Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.4" date-time="2022-06-27T10:06:48.1Z" user="admin">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.5" date-time="2022-06-29T16:04:02.517Z" user="cabie-sim">Auto (update-titles)</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
               <front>
                        <div type="summary">
                                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-1"/>
                                <p tid="2">
                                        In this discourse, the Buddha Śākyamuni describes his past life as King Śrīsena of Ariṣṭa, a bodhisattva renowned 
                                        for his unstinting generosity and spiritual resolve.
                                        In that life, a sage orders his disciple to ask King Śrīsena for his beautiful wife, Jayaprabhā. Out of compassion, King Śrīsena
                                        gives his wife to the disciple. Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, then claims that King Śrīsena is also able to give away his own
                                        body. The other gods have doubts about this, so to prove his point, Śakra disguises himself as an old brahmin whose
                                        lower body has been eaten by a tiger, and then asks King Śrīsena to gift him his own lower body. With altruistic
                                        motivation, King Śrīsena agrees to the request and orders carpenters to saw him in half. He offers the bottom half to
                                        the brahmin, whose body is magically made whole again. King Śrīsena claims he has felt no regrets and by the power of
                                        his words, his own body is restored. During this ordeal, Śakra has kept the king alive and carefully monitored his
                                        reactions. Observing nothing but pure altruism, Śakra then confirms that the king is a true bodhisattva who is capable
                                        of the highest acts of generosity. 
                                        With this past life story, the Buddha illustrates the kinds of personal sacrifice a bodhisattva will make to attain awakening, 
                                        even when these go against the protestations of those closest to him.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="acknowledgment">
                                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-2"/>
                                <p tid="4">This translation was produced by the Lokākṣi Translator Group: Tenzin Ringpapontsang, Ruth Gamble, John Powers, and Harmony
                                        DenRonden. </p>
                                <p tid="215">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                                of the Buddha.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="introduction">
                                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-introduction-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-3"/>
                                <p tid="6">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</title> belongs to one of the most beloved narrative genres in
                                        Buddhism, the past life story (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avadāna</foreign>). It deals with one of the most powerful and
                                        pervasive themes in this genre, the bodhisattva’s bodily sacrifice for the benefit of living beings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-4">
                                                It is worth noting that although the subject of <term type="ignore">giving</term> away one’s life, bodily parts, or family members is
                                                treated in this and similar texts as a rather commonplace aspect of a bodhisattva’s training, it is made
                                                abundantly clear in the commentarial treatises that Buddhist tradition does not teach these kinds of “great
                                                <term type="ignore">giving</term>” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gtong ba chen po</foreign>) or “exceptionally great <term type="ignore">giving</term>”
                                                        (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shin tu gtong ba</foreign>) to ordinary practitioners
                                                who have not yet attained one of the ten bodhisattva levels (and many texts specify the three highest or
                                                “sublime” levels). Only such advanced bodhisattvas have both fully realized emptiness, and also given rise to
                                                the vast altruistic intentions that make such an act viable and meaningful. In the meantime, such stories of
                                                “ultimate <term type="ignore">giving</term>” are intended to inspire a commensurate attitude of selfless generosity in the reader.</note>
                                        In this <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avadāna</foreign>, the act of bodily sacrifice performed by the Buddha’s
                                        previous incarnation, the bodhisattva king Śrīsena, forms the centerpiece of an elaborate morality tale extolling the
                                        virtues and far-reaching benefits of selfless generosity.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-5"/>
                                
                                
                                <p tid="7">Most past-life stories of the Buddha are found within two genres of Buddhist literature: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avadāna</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jātaka</foreign>. The term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avadāna</foreign>, broadly meaning “narrative” or “tale,” denotes a type of
                                        exemplary story that is common to most Indian religious traditions. In the Buddhist context, avadāna is traditionally
                                        specified as the tenth of the twelvefold subdivision of Buddhist scripture (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pravacana</foreign>), classified according to content, thematic structure, and literary style. Although this
                                        class of works is as varied as it is voluminous, the stories typically illustrate the results of good and bad karma,
                                        indicating how past deeds have shaped present circumstances. In this vein, many avadānas, the present one included, set
                                        out to show how the exemplary lives of the Buddha, or, more often, his followers, have resulted from their meritorious
                                        deeds in past lives. Avadānas may also, in certain cases, include prophecies of future spiritual attainments. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-6"/>
                                <p tid="8">Avadānas recounting past deeds, such as the one translated here, typically follow a three-part narrative structure: a story
                                        from the present life of the Buddha or another protagonist, a story of an exemplary past deed, and a connecting
                                        conclusion that shows how the past protagonist and his circle were prior incarnations of the present protagonist and his
                                        circle. In this regard, avadānas bear a close relationship to jātakas (“birth stories” of the Buddha). One notable
                                        difference, however, is that the protagonist of an avadāna is often not the Buddha himself, as it is in most jātaka
                                        stories, but one of his followers or prospective followers.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-7"> Jātakas typically relate stories from the
                                                Buddha’s past lives, in which the Buddha is either the protagonist of the story or a witness to other events.
                                                See Appleton 2010, pp. 3–6, and Rothenberg 1990, pp. 4–5.</note> Another difference is that avadānas generally
                                        concern past <emph>human</emph> lives of realized beings, not those of animals or nonhumans, as is the case in many
                                        jātaka tales. Finally, while jātaka stories had wide popular appeal, with plots, characters, and motifs drawn from
                                        pan-Indian folklore, the avadānas seem to have originally been intended primarily for monastics, as suggested by their
                                        frequent references to attendant monks, their moral tone, and their specific prescriptions for Buddhist practice that
                                        are interspersed throughout the narratives. Yet, in the course of their historical diffusion, these edifying tales of
                                        spiritual and moral accomplishment eventually gained wide popularity and came to inspire and educate Buddhist monastics
                                        and lay followers alike.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-8"/>
                                <p tid="9">To our knowledge, there is no extant Sanskrit version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>. Colophons of the
                                        Tibetan canonical translations of this text indicate that it was translated from Sanskrit by the Indian
                                        preceptor Dharmaśrībhadra, a chief editor called Sherab Lekpa, and the famous translator Rinchen Zangpo (958–1055 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>), who is said to have learned Sanskrit in Kashmir after traveling there in 975 to
                                        study Buddhism. It is interesting to note that the only compilation of Buddhist birth stories in any other language to
                                        include <title xml:lang="en">The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</title> was also produced in Kashmir and at roughly the
                                        same time as Rinchen Zangpo’s sojourn. This collection was the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-9"> For a critical edition and partial translation of this
                                                work, see Rothenberg 1990. For text-critical remarks on the text, see de Jong 1979.</note> a literary retelling
                                        of many Buddhist avadānas that was composed in Sanskrit by the famous Kashmiri poet Kṣemendra (ca. 990–ca. 1070 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-10"> On Kṣemendra’s life and works, see Chakraborty 1991 and
                                                Chattopadhyay 1994. </note>
                                </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-11"/>
                                <p tid="10">In the version of the Śrīsenā narrative translated here, the deeds of its protagonist are related by the Buddha Śākyamuni. At
                                        the beginning of the text, the Buddha explains to his disciples that King Śrīsena was a bodhisattva who ruled from the
                                        city of Ariṣṭa. He was aided in his royal duties by his devoted queen Jayaprabhā and chief minister Mahāmati. He is
                                        renowned for his generosity and the prosperity he has brought to his kingdom. After he performs the exceedingly generous
                                        act of <term type="ignore">giving</term> away his queen, his fame reaches the god realms. At this point, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, decides to test
                                        the authenticity of Śrīsena’s generosity by disguising himself as the victim of a tiger attack who is missing the lower
                                        half of his body, and who has been brought to the king to beg for the monarch’s lower body as a replacement. As Śrīsena
                                        sets out to fulfil the man’s request, his loyal subjects rise in protest and none will agree to help. It is only after
                                        Śakra enchants two of the king’s carpenters that they agree to perform the grisly task. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-12"/>
                                <p tid="11">The bodhisattva king passes Śakra’s test by not only suffering the pain of having his body cut in half, but by undertaking,
                                        enduring, and recalling the ordeal with nothing but joy, love, and equanimity. He is able to do this, the account
                                        explains, because he is motivated by the mind of awakening—the wish to attain awakening for the benefit of all sentient
                                        beings. At the end of the story, the Buddha reveals that he was King Śrīsena in a past life, his wife Yaśodharā was
                                        Queen Jayaprabhā, his ordained disciple Śāriputra was his minister Mahāmati, his lay disciple King Bimbisāra was the god
                                        Śakra, and his duplicitous cousin Devadatta was one of the carpenters.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-13"/>
                                <p tid="12">Like most of the past life tales of the Buddha, both avadāna and jātaka, <title xml:lang="en">The Account of the Noble Deeds of
                                                Śrīsena</title> is a morality tale that explains and illustrates the relationship between karma and its results.
                                        It demonstrates how the performance of good deeds causes beings to experience happiness and, conversely, the performance
                                        of harmful deeds causes them to suffer. It also highlights variations in the efficacy of good and bad deeds—good and bad
                                        deeds can be big and small, powerful and trifling. Even small deeds, however, can significantly impact an individual’s
                                        future behavior and experiences, whether positively or negatively. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-14"/>
                                <p tid="13">As the narrative demonstrates, much of a deed’s power comes not from the action itself, but from the intention behind it. The
                                        two carpenters did not reap the severe karmic consequence that would typically result from sawing a bodhisattva in half
                                        because they were enchanted while they performed the deed and had no control over what they did. Nevertheless, their
                                        inability to withstand the enchantment did not bode well for them, and we are told that they will continue to act out of
                                        ignorance in future lives. The bodhisattva’s actions, by contrast, were deemed to be both powerful and virtuous because
                                        they were inspired by the mind of awakening. From the Buddhist perspective, this intention infuses ordinary positive
                                        actions with tremendous power and makes extraordinary actions universally significant. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-15"/>
                                <p tid="14">All the various traditions of Buddhism agree that the Buddha awakened by perfecting these practices over eons, and many past
                                        life stories exemplifying this process can be found throughout Buddhist literature. Many of these stories exist in
                                        multiple versions, which vary according to the guiding aims and presuppositions of the traditions that have preserved
                                        them. Within these traditions, there are dissimilar lists of the behaviors that need to be perfected; some lists include
                                        ten behaviors that need to be perfected, others suggest only six. These six perfections appear in all the lists:
                                        generosity<!--(Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dāna</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sbyin pa</foreign>)-->, discipline<!--(Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śīla</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshul khrims</foreign>)-->, patience<!--(Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bzod pa</foreign>)-->, diligence<!--(Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vīrya</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtson
                                                ’grus</foreign>)-->, concentration<!--(Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhyāna</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsam gtan</foreign>)-->, and insight<!--(Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñā</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shes rab</foreign>)-->.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-16"/>
                                <p tid="15">The perfection of generosity heads these lists, and it is a central theme in many past life stories, and certainly the main
                                        focus of <title xml:lang="en">The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</title>. Within this narrative, the Buddha
                                        demonstrates how important it is not just to perform an act of generosity, but to do so with altruistic motivation and
                                        to dedicate any merit that results. King Śrīsena’s altruistic motivation is noted no fewer than thirteen times in the
                                        course of the text, and he repeatedly dedicates the benefit accruing from his acts of compassion to the welfare of
                                        others.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-17"/>
                                <p tid="16">This account not only describes an act of perfect generosity, but also highlights the moral and spiritual implications of
                                        this deed. Throughout the sūtra, there is a recurring discussion about the purpose of <term type="ignore">giving</term> away one’s body. King
                                        Śrīsena is presented with many reasons from loved ones why he should not perform this act, such as the grief it will
                                        cause his family, the detriments it will inflict on his subjects, and the pointlessness of <term type="ignore">giving</term> up such a rare and
                                        precious life. King Śrīsena responds to all these objections by patiently explaining that although he is fortunate to
                                        have met with such a valuable opportunity, he will not have fulfilled his life’s potential if he does not perform the
                                        deeds of a bodhisattva. When his relatives and friends beg him not to leave them, he reminds them that saṃsāra’s
                                        impermanent nature means that sooner or later all those who are close to each other must part. If, however, he awakens
                                        to buddhahood, he will have the ability to lead all sentient beings out of this cycle of meeting and parting. Time and
                                        again, he responds to those in his circle who beg him to forego his own suffering with a plea to think about the greater
                                        cycles of suffering that he and others will all endure if they do not attain liberation from saṃsāra.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-18"/>
                                <p tid="17">The conversations that King Śrīsena has about generosity, and the narrative details concerning his sacrificial deed, are
                                        reminiscent of other past life stories featuring bodily sacrifice. Reiko Ohnuma calls these “gift-of-the-body stories”
                                        and describes how they are found throughout all Buddhist canons, most commonly in avadāna and jātaka works but elsewhere
                                        as well.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-19"> See Ohnuma 2007, p. 22.</note> A few of these bodily sacrifice stories were well known across
                                        Buddhist traditions. Indeed, as Śrīsena argues with Mahāmati about the merits of his impending deed, he cites several
                                        previous gift-of-the-body stories to make his case. These include the stories of a king of Śibi who gives his eyes to a
                                        brahmin, another king of Śibi who gives his flesh to a hawk in order to save a pigeon, and King Candraprabha who gives
                                        his head to a brahmin.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-20"> Ohnuma (2007) discusses all these tales and the connections between them in her
                                                work. She also provides a list of the various versions of the texts in her work’s first appendix, pp.
                                                273–83.</note>
                                </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-21"/>
                                <p tid="18">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</title> not only alludes to these other, more famous
                                        gift-of-the-body stories, but also follows their literary conventions closely. There are some obvious thematic
                                        similarities. Like the bodhisattvas in the other perfection of giving stories, for example, King Śrīsena is overjoyed at
                                        having the opportunity to perform such an enormous act of generosity. It is not every day that a person comes and asks a
                                        bodhisattva for his or her body. From the bodhisattva’s perspective, the opportunity to give away one’s body presents an
                                        opportunity to perfect generosity in a very direct way. It is also seen as an opportunity to shorten the time it will
                                        take the aspirant to become a buddha. As in related works, the bodhisattva in this story exercises equanimity in
                                        offering his body; indeed, it is a stranger that asks for his body, while his close relatives and friends plead with him
                                        not to perform the act. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-22"/>
                                <p tid="19">These bodhisattva bodily sacrifice narratives also share many symbols and tropes. Tigers, for example, and other flesh-eating
                                        animals, like hawks, are often involved. Limbs and eyes are the most commonly offered body parts, and, perhaps by
                                        necessity, swords, saws, and other types of knives also make regular appearances in these stories, as well as sharp
                                        teeth.</p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-23"/>
                                <p tid="20">Along with the content of these texts—their symbols, language, and narratives—the form of gift-of-the-body stories is also
                                        similar. Most of them follow the standard avadāna narrative structure, beginning with
                                        the Buddha teaching monks and concluding with the Buddha explaining who the people in the story famously became,
                                        typically the Buddha himself and his closest disciples. By way of this framing narrative, the Buddha emphasizes the
                                        importance of giving wisely—giving, that is, because the bodhisattva sees saṃsāra for what it is: unsatisfactory,
                                        impermanent, and empty of selves. The Buddha-as-narrator then reappears throughout the tale to remind his audience of
                                        monks of the importance of the altruistic deed that is about to be performed, thus repeatedly reinforcing the moral of
                                        the story. </p>
                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-24"/>
                                <p tid="21">In producing this translation, we have based our work on the Degé xylograph while consulting
                                        the Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>), as well as the Stok Palace manuscript.</p>
                </div>
                        </div>
                </front>
                <body>
                        <div type="translation">
                                <head type="translation" tid="22"> The Translation </head>
                                <head type="titleMain" tid="24">The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</head>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-section-1">
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-25"/>
                                        <p tid="25">
                        <ref cRef="F.31.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-303"/>
                                                Homage to the Three Jewels! </p>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-26"/>
                                        <p tid="26">When they were at Śrāvastī, the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, I know the fruits of generosity. I also know
                                                how the fruits of generosity ripen. What if, like me, sentient beings too knew the fruits of generosity?
                                                What if, like me, they knew how the fruits of generosity ripen? Were this so and were someone to ask
                                                them for their last mouthful, the last remaining mouthful of their food, they would not eat it so long as they
                                                had not offered it or shared it. The growth of miserliness would not continue to completely entangle their
                                                minds. I know the fruits of generosity. I also know how the fruits of generosity ripen. But unlike me,
                                                sentient beings do not know the fruits of generosity. Unlike me, they do not know how the fruits of generosity ripen. 
                                                This ignorance is why their minds grasp at everything, why they are not generous, and why they
                                                eat without generosity. The growth of miserliness continues to completely entangle their minds.” <ref cRef="F.32.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-304"/>
                    </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-27"/>
                                        <p tid="27"> This is what the Blessed One said. After the Well-Gone One had said this, the Teacher<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-28"> Blessed One
                                                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagavān</foreign>), Well-Gone One (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sugata</foreign>), and the Teacher (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śāstṛ</foreign>) are all epithets for the Buddha. The repetition of terms referring
                                                        to the Buddha is most probably for emphasis.</note> also said:</p>
                                        
                                        <lg tid="28">
                                                <l>“As the great sages have said,</l>
                                                <l>The ripening of sharing is a matter of great import.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-32"/>
                                        <lg tid="30">
                                                <l>“Thus, if sentient beings knew about this,</l>
                                                <l>They would not eat so long as they could offer.</l>
                                                <l>They would not be miserly,</l>
                                                <l>And never would they give rise to grasping minds.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-33"/>
                                        <lg tid="31">
                                                <l>“But ignorance obscures immature beings.</l>
                                                <l>Since they do not know, their minds are grasping.</l>
                                                <l>Thus they always eat without first offering, </l>
                                                <l>They become miserly, and their minds are overcome.”</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-34"/>
                                        <p tid="32">When the Blessed One delivered this discourse, the earth shook in six different ways and light rays shone from the
                                                Blessed One’s body. When the monks saw the Blessed One’s inconceivable and marvelous miracles, they were amazed
                                                and inquired of the Buddha, the Blessed One, “Honorable One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha would not display 
                                                such marvelous miracles without causes or conditions. That being so, Honorable One, what are the causes and conditions 
                                                of such marvelous miracles?”</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-35"/>
                                        <p tid="33">“Monks, would you like to hear what caused a miracle like this?” asked the Blessed One. The monks requested just
                                                this. Then the Blessed One replied, “Monks, if this is so, listen carefully, remember my words, and I will tell
                                                you.</p>
                                        <p tid="34">“Monks, at one time there was a royal estate called Ariṣṭa.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-37"> We chose to translate <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">pho brang</foreign> as “royal estate” instead of the more usual
                                                        “palace” as the text says this “palace” included fields and the dwellings of the king’s subjects. A
                                                        palace is a building; it does not include grounds, fields, or villages. </note> It was wealthy, vast,
                                                joyous, with good harvests, and full of people. It was twelve leagues long and seven leagues wide.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-38"> Here we have read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chur</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshur</foreign>.</note> It was partitioned into quadrants.
                                                Parasols, victory banners, and flags were erected over its archways.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-39"/>
                                        <p tid="35">“At this royal estate lived a king named Śrīsena, <ref cRef="F.32.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-305"/> who was a universal monarch who ruled through force.<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-40"> “A universal monarch who ruled through force” is our translation of the Sanskrit term
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bala cakravartin</foreign> (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs kyi ’khor los sgyur ba</foreign>). This is a specific type
                                                        of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cakravartin</foreign> who rules the four continents and is
                                                        willing to use force (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bala</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs</foreign>) if necessary.</note>--> He had a lovely physique,
                                                and was beautiful, pleasing to the eye, and had a good complexion. He possessed the best attributes in
                                                abundance. He could remember his past lives naturally, and he was righteous. He was a Dharma king who ruled
                                                Jambudvīpa through righteousness. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-41"/>
                                        <p tid="36">“King Śrīsena’s power caused the plants to blossom and bear fruit continuously, the gods to make the rains fall at
                                                the right times, and the harvests to be exceedingly abundant. The beings there were free from illness and they
                                                all maintained a loving attitude toward each other.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-42"/>
                                        <p tid="37">“The king’s noble queen was called Jayaprabhā. She had a lovely figure and was beautiful and pleasing to the eye. She
                                                had all her major and minor body parts. She was the perfect daughter of that land, and King Śrīsena loved,
                                                adored, and cherished her.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-43"/>
                                        <p tid="38">“Monks, King Śrīsena levied no taxes on any of Jambudvīpa’s people; he collected neither road tolls nor boat fares.
                                                The harvests made all the people wealthy, and they were peaceful. Families<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-44"> This translation
                                                        follows the Narthang edition, which reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khyim ba</foreign>. The
                                                        Degé edition reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khyim bya</foreign>, meaning “chicken.” We
                                                        assume this is a misspelling. </note> filled the lands, cities, towns, countryside, and the king’s
                                                estate.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-45"/>
                                        <p tid="39">“Monks, King Śrīsena was a bodhisattva, so he gave away everything. He let go of everything completely—indeed, he let
                                                go of everything completely and without attachment. Absorbed in great <term type="ignore">giving</term>, he even gave away his own flesh.
                                                There was nothing that he would not give away or let go. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-46"/>
                                        <p tid="40">“Monks, at the eastern edge of the city, at Ariṣṭa Estate, King Śrīsena created a site for gift offerings from which
                                                he distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds. He distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds at
                                                the city’s southern, western, and northern gates as well, and he distributed gifts and performed meritorious
                                                deeds at its intersections. He would, for example, give food to the hungry and drink to the thirsty. He
                                                distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds by giving food, drink, lamps, flower garlands, <ref cRef="F.33.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-306"/> scents,
                                                perfumes, clothes, blankets, mattresses, back supports, shelters, images, horse-carts, elephants, horses,
                                                ornaments, golden containers filled with silver dust, silver containers filled with gold dust, oxen with golden
                                                horns and silver hoofs, bronze milking containers that were twice covered with cloth, and maidens who were
                                                adorned with various ornaments.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-47"/>
                                        <p tid="41">“Monks, King Śrīsena gave gifts until everyone in Jambudvīpa was affluent, prosperous, and deeply contented. At that
                                                time, 960 million people lived in the city where the king’s royal estate, Ariṣṭa, was located. King Śrīsena was
                                                loved and adored by all. What was more, when men and women saw him, they experienced insatiable delight. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-48"/>
                                        <p tid="42">“Monks, King Śrīsena had twelve thousand ministers. The supreme one among them was called Mahāmati. He was learned,
                                                bright, wise, his charisma affected all, and he took great care<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-49"> This translation follows the
                                                        Degé edition, which reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skyong ba</foreign>. The Comparative
                                                        Edition, Narthang, and Lhasa editions read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skyob pa</foreign>,
                                                        which means “to protect.”</note> of the king. King Śrīsena loved, adored, and esteemed him. 
                                                Mahāmati would never tire of gazing upon the king’s form, his complexion, his features, or his shape. He could not be
                                                separated from the king for even a moment.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-50"/>
                                        <p tid="43">“Monks, King Śrīsena acquainted all of Jambudvīpa’s people with the path of the ten virtuous actions. 
                                                He said to them, ‘People of Jambudvīpa, you must follow the path of the ten virtuous actions. You must adopt 
                                                the path of the ten virtuous actions correctly.’ Monks, this is how King Śrīsena instructed his subjects. 
                                                Thus, during the reign of this universal monarch, when people in Jambudvīpa would die and their bodies would perish, 
                                                <ref cRef="F.33.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-307"/> they were reborn in one of the six god realms.
                                                Most were born in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, and
                                                the divine city Darśanīya was filled with crowds of gods from the Heaven of the Thirty-Three. When it became too
                                                crowded and there was not enough space in the divine city, the gods dwelled on the outskirts of Darśanīya at the
                                                <!--Kalpavṛkṣa (The Wish-Fulfilling Tree)-->Pārijāta and in groves such as Caitraratha<!-- (The Garden of Chariots)-->, Nandanavana<!--(The Pleasure Grove)-->, and so forth. Following this influx, the gods who had been born earlier in the Heaven of
                                                the Thirty-Three viewed the perfect accomplishments of the newcomers and were overjoyed. They spoke to Śakra,
                                                <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, saying, ‘Kauśika, how is it that Mount Sumeru is filled with gods, and the divine assembly has
                                                increased, while the demigods’ assembly has decreased? We are beholding something marvelous.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-51"/>
                                        <p tid="44">“After hearing about this from the gods, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, inspected Mount Sumeru, and as soon as he did, he
                                                too saw that Mount Sumeru was teeming with multitudes of gods. Seeing this, he thought, ‘What causes and
                                                conditions led this many sentient beings to be born here?’ With this in mind, he began to inspect all of
                                                Jambudvīpa, and as soon as he did, he saw that it was a result of King Śrīsena’s influence. Then, with great
                                                joy, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, said to the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three:</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-52"/>
                                        <lg tid="45">
                                                <l>“ ‘Friends, you must listen! </l>
                                                <l>There is a king, a ruler of Jambudvīpa,</l>
                                                <l>Who is renowned as Śrīsena.</l>
                                                <l>He is always inclined toward the Dharma.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-53"/>
                                        <lg tid="46">
                                                <l>“ ‘This great king lives by the Dharma. </l>
                                                <l>In the beginning, middle, and end, he is always virtuous.</l>
                                                <l>He delights in helping all sentient beings </l>
                                                <l>And, principally, he continually brings humans to virtue.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-54"/>
                                        <lg tid="47">
                                                <l>“ ‘He is constantly compassionate,</l>
                                                <l>He gives away his external possessions, </l>
                                                <l>And to those who ask for his flesh,</l>
                                                <l>He gives this away too, with love.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-55"/>
                                        <lg tid="48">
                                                <l>“ ‘Whether that which is asked for is external or internal, </l>
                                                <l>Without any sense of grasping</l>
                                                <l>He bestows everything with kindness </l>
                                                <l>And works diligently to achieve awakening.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-56"/>
                                        <lg tid="49">
                                                <l>“ ‘Like refined gold, <ref cRef="F.34.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-308"/>
                        </l>
                                                <l>He accomplishes the wishes of all beings.</l>
                                                <l>Through the encouragement of this king</l>
                                                <l>Everyone is inspired to pursue higher rebirths.</l>
                                                <l/>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-57"/>
                                        <lg tid="50">
                                                <l>“ ‘Because of the influence </l>
                                                <l>Of this great, intelligent king</l>
                                                <l>No one will be born in hell,</l>
                                                <l>In the preta realm, or the animal realm.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-59"/>
                                        <lg tid="52">
                                                <l>“ ‘This king’s resplendent radiance </l>
                                                <l>Illuminates their migrations.</l>
                                                <l>They take joy in giving and discipline, </l>
                                                <l>And they play joyfully in Nandanavana.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-60"/>
                                        <lg tid="53">
                                                <l>“ ‘Those who follow Śrīsena</l>
                                                <l>Are respectful and live</l>
                                                <l>In pleasurable divine worlds, </l>
                                                <l>Where they shine with joy.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-61"/>
                                        <p tid="54">“When the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three heard these words, their minds were overjoyed, and they celebrated.
                                                With such joy in their minds, they exclaimed, ‘This king aspires to fulfill his wish to give away his major and
                                                minor body parts—this is marvelous! Yet it is difficult to give away one’s major and minor body parts. Since
                                                there is no one as dear as oneself, he will not be able to give away his major and minor body parts without
                                                concern for his own suffering. This act of giving is not something that one can simply infer.’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-62">
                                                        In other words, it has to be seen to be believed.</note>
                    </p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="55"> “ ‘Friends,’ replied Śakra, ‘do not say these things! This king is powerful. He has magical powers and intense
                                                compassion. This is why he can give away even his own flesh. There is nothing that he cannot relinquish.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-64"/>
                                        <p tid="56">“Shortly thereafter, on another occasion, Śrīsena’s queen, Jayaprabhā, went to sleep on her large mattress, and just
                                                before dawn she dreamt four dreams. First, she dreamt that Śrīsena carried her down off the mattress and then
                                                lifted her back onto it. Then he gouged out his own eyes, but they were later restored. He chopped off his right
                                                arm, which fell to the ground, but it was also restored. Finally, she dreamt of a nonhuman that resembled a
                                                stone grinder, made from silver. It suddenly pulled off King Śrīsena’s left arm. After it was thus stolen,
                                                however, that too was restored. Then she woke up. Filled with fear, she gasped and the hairs on her body stood
                                                on end. She thought, ‘Either the lord<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-342"> The term rendered here as “lord” is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lha</foreign> (Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">deva</foreign>), which literally means “god” but is here used as a term of respect for the king
                                                        in his role as the omnibenevolent protector of the populace.</note>--> or I <ref cRef="F.34.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-309"/> will experience nothing but suffering.’ She told King Śrīsena of
                                                her dreams. He had been trained to interpret dreams, so he thought, ‘As she has seen in her dream, someone will
                                                soon come to ask for my wife.’ But he comforted her and said, ‘Do not be afraid—what is the point of thinking
                                                about illusion-like dreams? Do you not see Śrīsena sitting on his mattress? My eyes are as they were, and my
                                                right and left arms are intact.’ The queen sat silently. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-65"/>
                                        <p tid="57">“The second night after this, the supreme one among the ministers, the one named Mahāmati, dreamt a dream in which
                                                King Śrīsena’s mansion, which was built of various precious stones, collapsed. The precious stones were then
                                                taken away by fearful-looking demons. Later, however, he dreamt that the mansion was rebuilt. He awoke terrified
                                                and distressed, with the hairs on his body standing on end. He thought, ‘Could someone come to ask for Lord
                                                Śrīsena’s body? Could they ask for the body of he who pleases and is affectionate toward all sentient beings,
                                                the lord who offers everything, who gives everything completely, he who gives without attachment? There is
                                                nothing that he would not give to lesser, blind, hungry, suffering, and deprived beings. I will not speak of my
                                                dream to King Śrīsena. He would be too delighted about it!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-66"/>
                                        <p tid="58">“He then called a soothsayer and commanded him, ‘Wise one, you must foretell the significance of the dream that I
                                                had.’ The soothsayer said, ‘According to the dream, someone will come soon to ask for the lord’s body.’ When he
                                                heard the significance of the dream, the great minister Mahāmati was struck by deep sorrow. His eyes filled with
                                                tears, he rested his hand on his cheek, and <ref cRef="F.35.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-310"/> he sat depressed, pondering how the force of impermanence
                                                had arrived too soon for the loving and compassionate King Śrīsena, he who had been so affectionate toward all
                                                sentient beings and possessed so many great qualities. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-67"/>
                                        <p tid="59">“Then, on the third night, twelve thousand ministers dreamt five dreams. 
                                                They dreamt that ten thousand beings robbed King Śrīsena of his parasol and crown, but they were then handed back to him;
                                                that everyone’s heads were chopped
                                                off, but then restored; that the eyes of every human in Jambudvīpa were gouged out, but then restored; that the
                                                hands and feet of every human in Jambudvīpa were chopped off, but then restored; and that King Śrīsena attempted
                                                to ascend the lion throne again after he had descended from it. The terrified, distressed, and despairing
                                                ministers thought, ‘Will the force of impermanence come for King Śrīsena? Will it be the end of this protector
                                                of a vast land, he who is so loving and compassionate, he who brings joy and rouses affection in all sentient
                                                beings? Will we live without the king? Will we be separated? Will we be parted? Will we be alone? Will
                                                Jambudvīpa lose its protector and defender?’</p>
                                        <p tid="60">“The ministers then called for soothsayers to ask about the dreams’ significance. After a while, the soothsayers
                                                foretold that things would be just as they had dreamt. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-69"/>
                                        <p tid="61">“After hearing about the dreams, the populace of Ariṣṭa city was wretched and started to weep aloud. Word spread from
                                                person to person, and soon everyone in Jambudvīpa wailed because of their suffering and intense grief. King
                                                Śrīsena heard of this and thought, ‘How pleasing and delightful that someone would ask for my body!’ Thus, he
                                                made an announcement: ‘Wise ones, people of Jambudvīpa, engage in virtue with joy and calmness. What is the
                                                point of thinking about illusion-like dreams?’ <ref cRef="F.35.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-311"/> When the people of the world heard King Śrīsena’s
                                                announcement, they were relieved.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-70"/>
                                        <p tid="62">“In those days, five hundred sages lived on a mountain about two miles<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-71"> One <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyang grags</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">krośa</foreign>) is approximately two miles.</note> north of the royal estate of
                                                Ariṣṭa. A short time after the dreams, one of the sages came to the king’s estate to do the sages’ bidding. At
                                                that time, King Śrīsena and Queen Jayaprabhā were strolling in the garden. The sage exclaimed, ‘May the king be
                                                victorious and live for a long time!’ The sage also saw Queen Jayaprabhā adorned with ornaments. In a past life
                                                the queen had been his wife. The influence of this previous desire and their previous relationship caused him to
                                                have inappropriate thoughts. Thinking these inappropriate thoughts, he walked along the path, completed his
                                                chores in Ariṣṭa city, and went back to his dwelling.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-72"/>
                                        <p tid="63">“A little while later, on another occasion, a student of this same sage, a brahmin boy, completed his recitation of
                                                the Vedas, touched his preceptor’s feet, and asked in gratitude, ‘Preceptor, what wealth can I offer you?’</p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="64">“The sage replied, ‘Son, if you wish, go ask for King Śrīsena’s supreme queen, Jayaprabhā. Give her to me as your
                                                offering, a gift for your preceptor, an homage to your guru.’ </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-74"/>
                                        <p tid="65">“When this was said, the brahmin boy was overwhelmed by great sorrow and acute despair; he was like a deer whose
                                                vital organ has been pierced. He thought, ‘This situation will only come about with difficulty, and it will be
                                                no easy task to acquire her. How could a troubled brahmin like me ask the king to give him Queen Jayaprabhā? Why
                                                am I being asked to get something that is unattainable? <ref cRef="F.36.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-312"/> The preceptor clearly wants to place a curse on
                                                me.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-75"/>
                                        <p tid="66">“The change in the boy’s facial expression allowed the sage to realize his thoughts, and the sage said, ‘Son, do not
                                                be afraid. Why are you so depressed? The king is a great being. He gives away everything. He lets go of
                                                everything. He lets go of everything completely and without attachment. He would even give away his own flesh.
                                                There is nothing that he would not relinquish in this way. Therefore, son, do not despair; the king will give
                                                you his supreme queen.’ </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-76"/>
                                        <p tid="67">“Then the boy thought, ‘If I do not go, I will be cursed.’ And out of fear of this curse, he said to the sage,
                                                ‘Preceptor, if that is so, I will go.’ After touching the sage’s feet, he traveled to the king’s estate, Ariṣṭa. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-77"/>
                                        <p tid="68">“Having applied dust to his body, wearing tree-bark cloth, and holding a staff and a little vase in his hands, the
                                                boy went to the site where King Śrīsena was and exclaimed, ‘May the king be victorious and may his life be
                                                long!’ Then he thought, ‘Should I ask? Or will he give her to me without my having to ask? Or will he not give
                                                her to me? Will my wishes be fulfilled or not?’ And he stood in front of the king with an unsettled look on his
                                                face, castigating himself, not speaking.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-78"/>
                                        <p tid="69">“Thinking that the brahmin boy had come to beg something from him, King Śrīsena asked him, ‘Brahmin, what is it that
                                                you want? Today, I will fulfill your wishes completely.’ </p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="70">When the king said this, the brahmin boy gained confidence and replied to the bodhisattva, ‘This is good. Lord, on a
                                                certain mountain my preceptor lives with his companions; they are five hundred sages who recite the Vedas. I
                                                have completed my Vedic studies with him. Great King, through your compassion give me Queen Jayaprabhā, and I
                                                will offer her to my preceptor as a gift, <ref cRef="F.36.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-313"/> an homage to my guru.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-80"/>
                                        <p tid="71">“When these words were spoken, King Śrīsena was distraught. He loved the queen. ‘If Queen Jayaprabhā were separated
                                                from me,’ he thought, ‘will we survive?’ For a while, all the members of the king’s and queen’s retinues were as
                                                quiet as the oceans’ depths. Then it was as if a great pain were piercing their vital organs. ‘What is this?’
                                                they cried out. ‘What is this?’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-81"/>
                                        <p tid="72">“The bodhisattva remained silent, in thought. ‘Unsurpassed and perfect awakening cannot be attained without giving up sons, wife,
                                                and so forth,’ he pondered. ‘Therefore, I must happily give my wife to this brahmin.’ This thought lifted him
                                                out of his sadness at losing a loved one. He descended from the lion throne immediately, and keeping in mind the
                                                aspirational mind of awakening, he took the goddess-like, intensely beautiful Queen Jayaprabhā with his left
                                                hand and held a golden vase in his right. The queen felt great pain at the prospect of being separated from her
                                                husband and sighed heavily. Her eyes filled with tears and her face dropped. She suffered as if she had fallen
                                                into a deep, dark abyss. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-82"/>
                                        <p tid="73">“ ‘Come here, come here great brahmin,’ the king said to the brahmin boy:</p> 
                                             <lg tid="216">   
                                                <l>“ ‘Handsome, fine brahmin,</l> 
                                                <l>You may take my beloved wife.</l>
                                                <l>May this act of generosity swiftly bring</l>
                                                <l>The attainment of true awakening.’</l>
                                             </lg>   
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-83"/>
                                        <p tid="217">“Then, maintaining the
                                                mind of awakening, he poured water onto the brahmin’s palm.</p>
                                        <p tid="74">“Monks, at the very instant that King Śrīsena poured the water, the earth shook in six different ways. Having
                                                witnessed how a bodhisattva gives, a great act of <term type="ignore">giving</term>, an extremely difficult act of <term type="ignore">giving</term>, the brahmin boy
                                                was utterly seized with wonder. The act even caused hundreds of thousands of sky-dwelling gods to murmur in
                                                amazement. Instantly, meteors fell, blazing in all directions, and the celestial gods beat their drums. <ref cRef="F.37.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-314"/> </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-84"/>
                                        <p tid="75">“Fearing that the king might change his mind, the brahmin boy praised the bodhisattva, uttered some prayers for his
                                                prosperity, and left quickly for home, taking Queen Jayaprabhā with him. He then gave the queen to his teacher.
                                                For Queen Jayaprabhā, being separated from her beloved was like being a fish taken out of water. She was
                                                wretched, but she knew that thinking about or following the bodhisattva would be in vain, like wandering from
                                                shadows into pitch darkness. Therefore, she merely lamented, ‘Alas, Great King. Alas, Great King.’ Her sadness
                                                even caused her to refuse food. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-85"/>
                                        <p tid="76">“As the queen suffered, the shaking caused by King Śrīsena’s deed rattled even Śakra’s abode. The gods spontaneously
                                                know what happens below them but not what happens above them. Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, therefore wondered:</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-86"/>
                                        <lg tid="77">
                                                <l>“ ‘The earth quakes with a tremendous sound.</l>
                                                <l>Whose power is behind this sign?</l>
                                                <l>What kind of power is it?</l>
                                                <l>I must know this very clearly.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-87"/>
                                        <p tid="78">“He began to search all over Jambudvīpa. After a while, he discovered that the shaking was a result of the
                                                bodhisattva’s extremely difficult act. When he understood this, he was awed. To the gods of the Heaven of the
                                                Thirty-Three, he said, ‘Consider the incredible, amazing act King Śrīsena has performed. Who can give away such
                                                a loving, beautiful, and dear wife without any hesitation, as if they were <term type="ignore">giving</term> away straw? Friends, through
                                                this act we know the great being will give away even his major and minor body parts, without hesitation.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-88"/>
                                        <p tid="79">“ ‘Kauśika,’ replied the gods, ‘we believe that he can give away his sons and daughters. But we do not believe he can
                                                give away his major and minor body parts. It is too difficult.’</p>
                                        <p tid="80">“Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, responded, ‘Friends, leave it be, leave it be. Do not measure the ocean against a drop of water so small it
                                                rests on the tip of a hair strand. <ref cRef="F.37.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-315"/> Do not measure space with your arms. Do not compare the light of a
                                                firefly to the sun. Do not compare the size of a seed to Mount Sumeru. I will produce evidence for you all.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-90"/>
                                        <p tid="81">“At dawn, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, spoke again to the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three. ‘Look, friends! Now you
                                                shall understand!’ That morning, he and four other gods from the Heaven of the Thirty-Three descended to earth,
                                                alighting in a forest near Ariṣṭa city. Śakra transformed himself into an old brahmin whose body had been hacked
                                                away below the navel, as if by a saw. Blood gushed from all sides of the wound. The other four gods of the
                                                Heaven of the Thirty-Three emanated as this old brahmin’s sons. They lifted him onto a stretcher while wailing
                                                wretchedly at the agony of losing their father. They left the forest at sunrise, traveling toward the city,
                                                intending to claim that the old brahmin’s lower body had been eaten by a tiger. They arrived at the city gate
                                                quickly. Hawks, gulls, and vultures hovered in the sky above them, drawn by the smell of the old brahmin’s
                                                blood. Dogs and foxes trailed behind them on the ground. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-91"/>
                                        <p tid="82">“The old brahmin looked pitiful. His plight moved the men and women who saw him. Some asked each other, ‘Friends, how
                                                is the old brahmin still alive when he has no lower body? How are his organs intact?’ Others speculated, ‘He
                                                must be a nonhuman demon who has come to devour us. How else would someone survive without his lower body?’ When
                                                the fainthearted heard this, they ran away out of fear. But one brave man thought, ‘He must be a demon. If he
                                                isn’t a demon, how could he appear to have his faculties despite his imperiled state? <ref cRef="F.38.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-316"/> I will ask him if
                                                he is a nonhuman or a demon. It will be difficult for him to speak, but if he does, that would be astonishing.’
                                                A while later, one of the others who saw the spectacle asked, ‘Brahmin! Are you a human or a demon? Who cut off
                                                the lower half of your body and left you in this state? Where did you come from?’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-92"/>
                                        <p tid="83">“Then Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, in the form of the old brahmin, lying on the stretcher and acting as if he were in
                                                tremendous pain, replied in verse:</p>
                                        <lg tid="84">
                                                <l>“ ‘Man of Śibi, be not afraid.</l>
                                                <l>I am a brahmin, not a demon.</l>
                                                <l>Because of past deeds, </l>
                                                <l>I have ended up in this state.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-94"/>
                                        <lg tid="85">
                                                <l>“ ‘Were I to explain everything, </l>
                                                <l>My time would run out. </l>
                                                <l>The <term type="ignore">Lord</term> of Death is coming quickly.</l>
                                                <l>He will snatch my life away.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-95"/>
                                        <lg tid="86">
                                                <l>“ ‘Please report all this </l>
                                                <l>To your Dharma king.</l>
                                                <l>It is certain that I must experience</l>
                                                <l>The fruits of past actions today.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-96"/>
                                        <lg tid="87">
                                                <l>“ ‘Where can I gaze upon the great one?</l>
                                                <l>Where is the one adorned with all good qualities,</l>
                                                <l>The one who is as peaceful as the moon,</l>
                                                <l>The one who loves giving and discipline?</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-97"/>
                                        <lg tid="88">
                                                <l>“ ‘Where does the Dharma king live?</l>
                                                <l>Where lives the one who is as deep as the ocean,</l>
                                                <l>The one who is as stable as Mount Sumeru, </l>
                                                <l>He who is chief among all beings?</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-98"/>
                                        <lg tid="89">
                                                <l>“ ‘Where is he who is a refuge for the fearful?</l>
                                                <l>Where is the one to whom all beggars travel,</l>
                                                <l>The one who speaks pleasantly, </l>
                                                <l>He who gives generously and upholds discipline?</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-99"/>
                                        <lg tid="90">
                                                <l>“ ‘Quickly, death is looming before me.</l>
                                                <l>Tell me, people of Śibi, where can I see him?</l>
                                                <l>No one but the great compassionate one</l>
                                                <l>Will give me half his own body.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-100"/>
                                        <p tid="91">“In this manner, the old brahmin kept wailing pitifully, uttering weak and disheartened words as he made his way
                                                along the path toward the gate of King Śrīsena’s royal estate. Hundreds and thousands of astonished beings
                                                followed after him. As they proceeded, crowds of gods, nāgas, yakṣas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas,
                                                <ref cRef="F.38.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-317"/> those who understood the physical damage and bodily pain King Śrīsena was about to endure, were
                                                tormented by sadness and began to lament. ‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘it is painful to learn that the loving,
                                                compassionate King Śrīsena, who is peaceful and affectionate toward all sentient beings, is about to suffer and
                                                will be overpowered by impermanence.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-101"/>
                                        <p tid="92"> “Hearing this, the throngs of people began to lament, too. At this time, the whole of Jambudvīpa descended into
                                                turmoil and chaos spread everywhere. Smoke darkened the land, meteors fell blazing in all directions, and the
                                                celestial gods beat their drums.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-102"/>
                                        <p tid="93"> “While all this was happening, the brahmin who lived in the mountains, who had been offered Queen Jayaprabhā,
                                                noticed her distress at being separated from her husband. He noticed that she sighed heavily, refused to eat,
                                                and gave no thought to him. His heart trembled with compassion for her, and he thought, ‘I should give her back
                                                to King Śrīsena.’ Queen Jayaprabhā was greatly relieved when he assured her that he would do this.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-103"/>
                                        <p tid="94">“He also saw that the whole of Jambudvīpa had descended into great turmoil, and chaos had spread everywhere. Seeing
                                                this, he said to his disciple, the brahmin boy, ‘Brahmin boy, Jambudvīpa is dark with smoke in every direction;
                                                it has descended into great turmoil, and chaos has spread everywhere. Not even the sun and moon are shining,
                                                bright and steady. Surely, in a short time Jambudvīpa’s great being will cease to exist.’ Then the brahmin
                                                recited the following verses:</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-104"/>
                                        <lg tid="95">
                                                <l>“ ‘The kinnaras, the forest-dwelling gods,</l>
                                                <l>And even the celestial gods complain.</l>
                                                <l>The moon has no light; the sun cannot dispel the darkness.</l>
                                                <l>Not even musical instruments make a sound today.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-105"/>
                                        <lg tid="96">
                                                <l>“ ‘Trees with fruit and flowers are falling,</l>
                                                <l>As if blown over by the wind.</l>
                                                <l>Given that everyone has heard the fearsome and awful sounds, </l>
                                                <l>It is clear that the city will experience unbearable sorrow. <ref cRef="F.39.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-318"/> </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-106"/>
                                        <lg tid="97">
                                                <l>“ ‘All the residents in the delightful city Ariṣṭa are suffering.</l>
                                                <l>Expressing grief and pain among themselves, </l>
                                                <l>They say, “We are definitely defeated.”</l>
                                                <l>Young women with faces like goddesses<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-107"> This
                                                        translation follows the Narthang and Lhasa editions of the text, which read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lha mo zla ba’i bzhin</foreign>. The Degé edition reads
                                                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lha mo lta bu’i bzhin ldan</foreign>. The
                                                        combination of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lta bu</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bzhin</foreign> is exceedingly strange. </note>--> wail on rooftops.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-108">The use of <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog</foreign>
                                                                        to describe a house is ambiguous; it could mean “the
                                                                                best of houses” or “the (roof)top of a house.” Clues for how to translate the
                                                                                line were found in a similar line from the Newari version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candra­prabhāvadāna</title>
                                                                        (<title xml:lang="en">The Noble Deeds of
                                                                                Candraprabha</title>). This line reads: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">etāś candranibhānanā yuvatayo rodanti veśmottame</foreign> (Matsumura 1980, p. 101, n. 34). This line could be
                                                                                translated as: “These young women, whose faces resemble the moon, cry on the
                                                                                (roof)tops of their houses.” As this text provides more context for the young
                                                                                women’s actions, we have rendered 
                                                                        <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog</foreign>
                                                                        as “(roof)top.” We thank our anonymous reviewer for this
                                                                                reference.</note>
                                                </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-109"/>
                                        <lg tid="98">
                                                <l>“ ‘The people weep profusely as if they were in a terrifying cemetery. </l>
                                                <l>These clouds hanging in the sky thunder but do not rain.</l>
                                                <l>Even the waterholes resting in the earth are drying up. </l>
                                                <l>Peacocks scream as if the forest were crushing them. </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-110"/>
                                        <lg tid="99">
                                                <l>“ ‘People rush between their homes in turmoil. </l>
                                                <l>Their lands shake as if they were a ship at sea, battered by winds. </l>
                                                <l>Gales blast piles of garbage and dust into the air.</l>
                                                <l>There are many signs of demise in Ariṣṭa. </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-111"/>
                                        <lg tid="100">
                                                <l>“ ‘Brahmin boy, today in this land with which you have a karmic connection,<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-112">
                                                                Reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rjes
                                                                        ’thun</foreign>
                                                                as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rjes
                                                                        mthun</foreign>.</note>--></l>
                                                <l>There are many inauspicious signs. </l>
                                                <l>It is only reasonable that we set off </l>
                                                <l>Toward a place that is auspicious.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-113"/>
                                        <p tid="101">“ ‘Alas, brahmin boys,’ the sage continued, ‘just as these trees are being blown in the direction of the Ariṣṭa royal
                                                estate, so it is certain, brahmin boys, that there will long be tremendous fear of harm and destruction in
                                                Ariṣṭa.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-114"/>
                                        <p tid="102">“At the same time, in Ariṣṭa, the bodhisattva was seated on the top floor of his mansion. Hearing a large crowd of
                                                people lamenting below, he came down from his mansion made of precious stones and sat on his large lion throne.
                                                Urgently he asked, ‘Wise ones, what is it? What is happening?’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-115"/>
                                        <p tid="103">“The four gods carried Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, into the king’s court on his stretcher, and then placed the stretcher
                                                on the floor. Blood dripped from his bisected body, but he still extended his right hand and in a pitiable voice
                                                called out salutations of victory and long life to the bodhisattva. As his eyes filled with tears, he displayed
                                                his bisected body to the bodhisattva, and implored him, <ref cRef="F.39.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-319"/> ‘You are this world’s compassionate one. You
                                                suffer the pains of others. Lord, protect me. Give me half your body.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-116"/>
                                        <p tid="104">“Hearing this request, Mahāmati, supreme among ministers, said, ‘Lord, this person is not human. He must be a demon
                                                or someone possessed by demons. A human would not survive being sliced in half at the waist. It is impossible
                                                and unheard of.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-117"/>
                                        <p tid="105">“To this, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, responded, ‘People of Śibi, you need not be afraid. I am not a demon. On the
                                                contrary, I am a brahmin. I left my wife and children because we were poor and, intent on creating wealth, I
                                                traveled in King Śrīsena’s direction. I came to the royal estate slowly, and by the time I arrived the sun had
                                                set, and the city’s gates were closed. I stayed at a manor not far from the city. While I was there, I was
                                                overcome by the weariness of traveling and fell into a deep sleep. Because of my previous negative deeds, during
                                                the night a tiger came along and used its sharp, saw-like teeth to cut my body in half and steal away the lower
                                                half. When I awoke, I experienced an extreme sensation. The tiger may have used its saw-like teeth to cut my
                                                body in half, but because I recognized this was caused by my previous actions, I did not die. Still, my
                                                suffering was incomparable. It was incomparably violent. It was incomparably harsh. It was incomparably intense.
                                                It was an incomparably overwhelming pain, and how I screamed in my misery!</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-118"/>
                                        <p tid="106">“ ‘When the celestial gods overheard my cries, they consoled me. A goddess said:</p>
                                        
                                        <lg tid="107">
                                                <l>“ ‘ “Be not afraid, best of brahmins, be not afraid. </l>
                                                <l>We foresee a long life for you. </l>
                                                <l>Once you have swiftly traveled to Ariṣṭa, </l>
                                                <l>You will be fine.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-120"/>
                                        <lg tid="108">
                                                <l>“ ‘ “A king lives there who grants everything.</l>
                                                <l>He is known as Śrīsena. <ref cRef="F.40.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-320"/> </l>
                                                <l>If you beg him for half his body, </l>
                                                <l>He will certainly give it to you.”</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-121"/>
                                        <p tid="109">“ ‘Having said this, the goddess disappeared. As I heard these words from the goddess, my hope of survival grew, and
                                                the pain subsided. Then I became dejected again as I realized I could not get up, let alone walk, with only half
                                                of my body. Coincidentally, at dawn, my four kin arrived. They started to cry when they saw my desperate state
                                                and thought I would die. To console them, I told them in detail about the goddess’s words. They placed me on
                                                this stretcher and carried me here.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-122"/>
                                        <p tid="110">“Having spoken these words, the face of Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, was awash with waves of tears. He then said to the
                                                bodhisattva: </p>
                                        
                                        <lg tid="111">
                                                <l>“ ‘Great King, I am poor and sick.</l>
                                                <l>I am also an old man and a brahmin.</l>
                                                <l>Please give me half your body,</l>
                                                <l>To grant me this life so difficult to find.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-124"/>
                                        <lg tid="112">
                                                <l>“ ‘Please compassionately grant me</l>
                                                <l>The gift of preserving my life.</l>
                                                <l>Please give me half your body,</l>
                                                <l>Such a gift being the highest of aims.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-125"/>
                                        <lg tid="113">
                                                <l>“ ‘By giving me half of your body</l>
                                                <l>The merit accrued will be as vast as the ocean.</l>
                                                <l>Similarly, the merit you will gain</l>
                                                <l>Will be as limitless as space.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-126"/>
                                        <lg tid="114">
                                                <l>“ ‘Having seen my excruciating pain</l>
                                                <l>And my unbearable hunger and thirst,</l>
                                                <l>Exercise supreme compassion</l>
                                                <l>And give me half your body!</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-127"/>
                                        <lg tid="115">
                                                <l>“ ‘Virtuous bodhisattva, you abide by the Dharma. </l>
                                                <l>If you claim to become the equal of an omniscient one,</l>
                                                <l>Then please give me half your body today. </l>
                                                <l>Let me keep this life so difficult to find.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-128"/>
                                        <lg tid="116">
                                                <l>“ ‘Great King, give to me half of your body,</l>
                                                <l>Which is so difficult to give;</l>
                                                <l>If you do, the Dharma, and likewise your fame,</l>
                                                <l>Will spread throughout the entire world.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-129"/>
                                        <p tid="117">“Upon hearing these words, the bodhisattva’s past habits of virtue and his stores of positive predispositions infused
                                                his mind, causing him to shake with compassion. <ref cRef="F.40.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-321"/> ‘Great brahmin,’ he consoled him, ‘do not be afraid.
                                                Your body will soon be whole. Your wishes will be fulfilled. With an unwavering mind, I offer you half my body.’
                                                His heart filled with joy, the bodhisattva then spoke the following verses:</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-130"/>
                                        <lg tid="118">
                                                <l>“ ‘O, soon you will see me</l>
                                                <l>Give away my body.</l>
                                                <l>It will not be very difficult </l>
                                                <l>To give away my limbs.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-131"/>
                                        <lg tid="119">
                                                <l>“ ‘Although I am my father’s only son,</l>
                                                <l>You can take my body.</l>
                                                <l>Offering my body will result in great awakening.</l>
                                                <l>May it alleviate the intense suffering of all beings.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-132"/>
                                        <p tid="120">“The bodhisattva had heard Śakra’s words, which he had spoken in the form of a brahmin. Therefore, with an entirely
                                                satisfied mind and his eyes open, he said, ‘Brahmin, I will give you half my body. Take it without any
                                                qualms.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-133"/>
                                        <p tid="121"> “Looking around, he saw his attendants and said to one of them, ‘O, you, go quickly and bring me an exceedingly sharp saw.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-134"/>
                                        <p tid="122"> “As he had been enchanted by Śakra, the attendant quickly found a saw and brought it to the bodhisattva. ‘Lord,’ he
                                                said, ‘here is a saw.’</p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="123"> “Promptly, the bodhisattva said to his ministers, ‘Quickly cut off my lower body and give it to the brahmin, before
                                                the <term type="ignore">Lord</term> of Death takes him to the other world. I offer it to the brahmin.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-136"/>
                                        <p tid="124"> “The sound of the bodhisattva’s utterly horrifying words created panic in the city as if they were lightning
                                                        strikes.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-137">
                                                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rdo rje lhung</foreign> is a Tibetan
                                                                translation of the Sanskrit term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vajrapāta</foreign>, which means “the fall of a thunderbolt” or a
                                                                “lightning strike.”</note> ‘Oh, the sorrow, the sorrow!’ the people cried in secret and
                                                from on high. Then Mahāmati, the great minister, was wretched with intense pain, as if a vital organ had been
                                                pierced, and his face was as wet from crying as from the rain. He feared the bodhisattva would give away his
                                                body without any attachment to it, <ref cRef="F.41.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-322"/> and seeking to change his mind, he bowed down at his feet and said,
                                                ‘Lord, this is not possible. If your body is cut by a saw, you will certainly die. If you die, you will become a
                                                useless corpse. A useless corpse is no good to this brahmin. Giving your life to him is pointless. Cutting one
                                                person’s limb off and attaching it to another does not work. Your divine efforts will be in vain. Please, be
                                                patient. Do not kill yourself in vain. Do not give up your life.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-138"/>
                                        <p tid="125"> “Consoling the great minister Mahāmati, the bodhisattva replied, ‘Mahāmati, leave it be, leave it be. At some point,
                                                I hope to attain unsurpassed, perfect awakening and liberate saṃsāra’s beings. Do not hinder my
                                                awakening. It is the nature of our existence that we must all separate, even from those who have been very dear
                                                to us for a long time, like our children.’ Having said this, he glanced once again at the saw and said, ‘This
                                                saw is an incomparable object that will direct my merit toward unsurpassed and perfect awakening.’ This is how
                                                he thought of it, and again he said to his minister, ‘Cut off the lower half of my body as soon as you can,
                                                before the brahmin dies. Otherwise, my intent will be fruitless.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-139"/>
                                        <p tid="126"> “Mahāmati, the great minister, knew then that the bodhisattva was determined to give away his body. He held the
                                                bodhisattva’s feet in both his hands and kissed them. As tears flowed down his face like rain, he despaired and,
                                                overwhelmed with compassion, said to the bodhisattva, ‘Alas, the force of impermanence will strike the lord
                                                today. The lord takes care of all of Jambudvīpa, he is the compassionate one, he has innumerable qualities, and
                                                he pleases and is affectionate to all sentient beings. <ref cRef="F.41.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-323"/> But, alas, impermanence is powerful! Whoever has
                                                seen the lord was fortunate.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-140"/>
                                        <p tid="127">“Having spoken, he stared at the bodhisattva’s face for a long time without blinking. Then, as he contemplated how he
                                                could not bear to witness the bodhisattva’s death, his eyes closed and he fell to the ground unconscious. The
                                                bodhisattva then spoke to two carpenters who happened to be present: ‘Good people,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-141"> We have
                                                        read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhin bzangs</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bzhin bzang</foreign>. The Lhasa edition of the text reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bzang</foreign>.</note> will you help me complete the perfection
                                                of generosity? Will you take this saw and quickly cut off the lower half of my body? Let us fulfill the
                                                brahmin’s wish. Let us fulfill my wish to attain awakening.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-142"/>
                                        <p tid="128">“Tears of immense sadness covered the two carpenters’ faces like stormy weather. They touched the bodhisattva’s feet
                                                and said, ‘Lord, your words are inappropriate. If someone else were to challenge you, we could oppose them. But
                                                how are we to use a weapon against you? You are compassionate, loving, pleasing, and affectionate toward all
                                                sentient beings. You take care of all of Jambudvīpa. If we were to use this saw to cut through your body, our
                                                actions would cause us to fall instantly into hell.’</p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="129">“ ‘Sons,’ responded the bodhisattva, ‘do not block the final outpouring of the immortal elixir of a bodhisattva’s
                                                patience. Come here, help me to awaken. Cut off the lower half of my body while the brahmin is still alive.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-144"/>
                                        <p tid="130">“Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, used his power to compel the two carpenters to begin the process. A little while later, hundreds of thousands
                                                of people had gathered in the royal estate and hundreds of thousands of gods had <ref cRef="F.42.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-324"/> gathered in the sky.
                                                They had flocked to see the bodhisattva perform this extremely difficult task, a task so difficult it made their
                                                body hairs stand on end. The bodhisattva stepped down instantly from his lion throne. His intention to give away
                                                his body gave him extreme joy, and he was overwhelmed by his love for the brahmin who asked for it.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-145"/>
                                        <p tid="131">“Monks, at the very instant the bodhisattva Śrīsena stepped down from his lion throne, all of Jambudvīpa’s parasols,
                                                banners, and flags bent toward Ariṣṭa Estate. Meteors fell toward it from the four directions. But those who
                                                dwelled in the city wailed with the pain of separation. ‘This evil brahmin is going to kill King Śrīsena!’ they
                                                shouted. ‘Throw him out of here!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-146"/>
                                        <p tid="132">“Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, prevented the people from hearing what was happening. They were stupefied. The yakṣas,
                                                those who dwell in space and on the ground, came to know that the bodhisattva was unconcerned with his body and
                                                wailed in the torment of their immense sorrow. ‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘King Śrīsena! He who takes care of everyone
                                                in Jambudvīpa, he who is compassionate toward all sentient beings, he will give up his entire body!’ A deity who
                                                lived on the royal estate also came to know that he would give up his entire body, and lamented aloud, ‘King
                                                Śrīsena, he who is endowed with so many qualities, is not going to survive because of this beggar!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-147"/>
                                        <p tid="133">“After this, the bodhisattva looked around in the four directions. ‘Gods, nāgas, yakṣas, and kinnaras, all you who
                                                dwell in this city, listen! Make pure prayers for me! I am making this gift today. <ref cRef="F.42.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-325"/> I am making the
                                                greatest of gifts, the gift of one’s body. I am not making this gift for myself, the king, nor to attain rebirth
                                                in a higher realm. I am not making it for Śakra or for Brahmā. I am not making it to become a universal monarch.
                                                I make this gift to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening. I make it to liberate sentient beings who are not
                                                yet liberated. I make it to console those who need consoling, to unbind those who are bound. By the truth of my
                                                words, may it be accomplished. May some small sign of my awakening appear!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-148"/>
                                        <p tid="134">“To the brahmin, he said, ‘By this action, may you attain all you have imagined.<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-149"> Reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kun du rtog pa</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kun tu rtog pa</foreign>. </note>--> May all your wishes be fulfilled. And may I realize
                                                unsurpassed awakening completely.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-150"/>
                                        <p tid="135">“The bodhisattva asked his relatives and the city’s inhabitants for patience. He consoled the poor and stricken,
                                                before speaking to the two carpenters. ‘Good people, come here. Before the brahmin’s time runs out, saw at my
                                                navel. May I protect all beings who suffer!’ In this way, with love suffusing all, and with the help of a man
                                                who supported him, he promptly lay down on his back and stretched out his legs. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-151"/>
                                        <p tid="136">“Monks, as the bodhisattva was lowered onto the ground, the great earth shook in six different ways. The ladies of
                                                the court<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-152"> In the Degé edition, it reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btsun mo bud
                                                                med</foreign>. The Comparative Edition notes (p. 140, n. 6) indicate that the
                                                        Narthang edition has “queen’s women” or women of the court.</note>--> were deeply tormented when they heard
                                                the news and rushed to the bodhisattva’s side. Tears poured down their faces like rain. They let their hair fall
                                                and beat their chests in mourning. ‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘the pain!’ They were no longer attractive like
                                                goddesses. <ref cRef="F.43.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-326"/> They touched the bodhisattva’s feet briefly and wailed, ‘Please have mercy!’ ‘Alas,’ they
                                                cried, ‘it pains us that the power of impermanence is now at hand and today will separate, isolate, detach, and
                                                remove us from our relationships with this lord. He is the lord who protects all of Jambudvīpa, who pleases and is affectionate toward all
                                                sentient beings, who has immense compassion, and who has innumerable good qualities.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-155"/>
                                        <p tid="137">“ ‘Lord,’ they persisted, ‘please have patience with us! Please don’t leave all of the communities of people living
                                                in Jambudvīpa without a protector by taking your own life. 
                                                Lord, please look at the ladies of the court and your vast treasuries and storehouses filled with myriad precious gems. 
                                                Look at Jambudvīpa’s people, who are always experiencing many types of happiness. Look at the city of Ariṣṭa, which resembles 
                                                a divine park complete with an abundance of fine features, where so many joyful people live.
                                        </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-156"/>
                                        <lg tid="138">
                                                <l>“ ‘Protector, you have always taken care of everyone</l>
                                                <l>As if they were your own children. </l>
                                                <l>How will these beings survive </l>
                                                <l>When they are surely scorched by the fire of losing you? </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-157"/>
                                        <lg tid="139">
                                                <l>“ ‘If separated from you, </l>
                                                <l>We will all be overpowered by the <term type="ignore">Lord</term> of Death. </l>
                                                <l>O Protector, if we are separated from you,</l>
                                                <l>We will not be able to survive!</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-158"/>
                                        <lg tid="140">
                                                <l>“ ‘If the queen is stricken by suffering,</l>
                                                <l>And if sentient beings all suffer as one,</l>
                                                <l>We pray that you look upon us, ruler of humans,</l>
                                                <l>With the compassion of one who embodies compassion.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-159"/>
                                        <lg tid="141">
                                                <l>“ ‘Lord who is affectionate toward all beings,</l>
                                                <l>Please take care of us—don’t give away your life!</l>
                                                <l>Who will be our protector, our hero, if you pass on?</l>
                                                <l>Who will protect the world?’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-160"/>
                                        <p tid="142">“After hearing their pitiable lament, the bodhisattva’s heart was heavy with compassion. ‘Your lament is
                                                understandable,’ he said to console them, <ref cRef="F.43.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-327"/> ‘but it is the way of the world that we must separate even
                                                from those we have known for a long time. For this reason, you should always be mindful of virtuous deeds.’ Then
                                                he turned to the two carpenters again and said, ‘Good people, come here. Without taking too much time, cut my
                                                body.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-161"/>
                                        <p tid="143">“Because Śakra had enchanted them, the two carpenters immediately began sawing the bodhisattva’s body at his navel.
                                                Mahāmati, revived and imagining the unbearably intense pain the bodhisattva was experiencing, rebuked the two
                                                carpenters. ‘Alas,’ he cried, ‘alas! What are the two of you doing! How can you kill the compassionate one? How
                                                can you kill the one who is pleasing and affectionate to everyone, he who has numerous good qualities, he who
                                                takes care of all of Jambudvīpa, he who is faultless and harms none? How can you ignorant people take joy in
                                                killing a Dharma king? How does this great land’s goddess allow you to live? Why haven’t you been pierced by the
                                                single-pointed vajra? The weapon-wheel? The great arrow? The single-pointed weapons of the gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                                                asuras, gandharvas, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas? You have committed such an ignoble act. How is it that
                                                your bodies have not exploded into a thousand pieces? Why haven’t you fallen instantly into hell, in this very
                                                body? Didn’t this great being also treat you as his sons? You ignorant beings!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-162"/>
                                        <p tid="144">“He said these things and many others besides. ‘Alas, lord!’ he cried, and getting up from his seat, Mahāmati, the
                                                great minister, <ref cRef="F.44.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-328"/> grabbed the saw with his own two hands, and as his tears wet the bodhisattva’s body, he
                                                pushed the two carpenters away. To console the discouraged Mahāmati, the bodhisattva said, ‘Son, leave it be,
                                                leave it be. Do not lament. It is certain that we will be separated from those dear to us, those we love, those
                                                who draw near to us, and those of whom we are extremely fond. We will be isolated, divided, and separated. Moreover, son: </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-163"/>
                                        <lg tid="145">
                                                <l>“ ‘The end of all accumulation is dispersion.</l>
                                                <l>The end of rising is falling. </l>
                                                <l>The end of meeting is parting.</l>
                                                <l>The end of living is dying.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-164"> This stanza is widely quoted in Buddhist literature across
                                                                traditions. It is found, for example, in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title> and
                                                                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Udānavarga</title>.</note>
                                                </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-165"/>
                                        <p tid="146">“ ‘Therefore, do not stop those who ask for my body. Mahāmati, in the past, another person tried to ask for my body
                                                but goddesses stopped them. Not only did those goddesses prevent me from achieving unsurpassed awakening, they
                                                also created much nonvirtue. If the goddesses had not prevented that person asking for my body, I would have
                                                attained unsurpassed and perfect awakening by now. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-166"/>
                                        <p tid="147">“ ‘What is more, son, in this very place I met a tigress whose hunger pains were so intense that she wanted to eat
                                                her own cubs. Out of supreme compassion, I gave myself to her immediately so that she might be saved. By so
                                                doing, I surpassed<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-167"> Here the Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phyir lus</foreign>, which usually
                                                                means “turn back” but can also be a Tibetan translation of the Sanskrit term
                                                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avapṛṣṭhīkṛtaḥ</foreign>. A synonym
                                                        of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">paścān­mukhīkṛtaḥ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avapṛṣṭhīkṛtaḥ</foreign>
                                                        also has the figurative meaning of “surpassed, outdone.” This is the only
                                                                meaning that makes sense in the context of this story, so we have chosen to translate
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phyir lus</foreign> as
                                                                “surpassed.” The obtuseness of this usage is most probably compensated for by the familiarity
                                                                most readers of the avadāna would have with the story of the Buddha offering his body to the
                                                                tigress.
                                                </note> the deeds of the bodhisattva Maitreya, who had set out for buddhahood forty eons before that.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-168"> The Tibetan grammar in this short rendition of a famous tale is less than clear. It could
                                                        be read to suggest that Maitreya lengthened his period as a bodhisattva by offering his life to the
                                                        tiger. The idea that such an action would increase the time it took to attain buddhahood runs counter to
                                                        the rest of the narrative, however, in which Śrisena, a past rebirth of the Buddha Śākyamuni, is trying to
                                                        hasten buddhahood by offering his body. It also contradicts several other renditions of this tale, all
                                                        of which explain that a previous incarnation of Maitreya could not offer himself to the tigress but a
                                                        previous incarnation of the Buddha Śākyamuni did, thereby surpassing the deeds of the bodhisattva Maitreya,
                                                        who had set out for buddhahood forty eons earlier than the Buddha Śākyamuni. This tale is not only told in
                                                        both the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candra­prabhāvadāna</title>, but also in the <title xml:lang="en">Suvarṇaprabhāsa Sūtra</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh555.html" inst="is it 555 or 556?"/>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh556.html" inst="is it 555 or 556?"/>
                                                        (See translation in Emmerick 1970, pp. 85–97). This last work identifies Maitreya as the older brother Mahāpraṇāda, who had
                                                        set out for buddhahood forty eons earlier, but does not offer his body to the tigress and is
                                                        consequently surpassed by his younger brother who does make this sacrifice. Ohnuma (2007, pp. 9–14)
                                                        discusses this story. She concludes (p. 14) that “[i]t was his (Maitreya’s) failure to act in the same
                                                        exalted manner as Śākyamuni that made him lose the cosmic race toward perfect buddhahood.” Among all the
                                                        other retellings of the tigress tale, one that is particularly helpful for understanding this passage is
                                                        a parallel passage in the Sanskrit and Tibetan editions of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candra­prabhāvadāna</title>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh348.html"/> (Matsumura 1980). This avadāna includes a reminiscence by another of
                                                        the Buddha Śākyamuni’s incarnations, Candraprabha, about the same offering to the tigress. The passage in
                                                        question reads, in Sanskrit: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">esa eva devate sa pradeśo yatra
                                                                mayā vyāghryātmanam parityajya catvārimsat-ka[lpa sam]prasthito maitreyo bodhisatvaḥ ekena
                                                                śirasā parityāgena avapṛṣṭhīkṛtaḥ</foreign> (Matsumura, pp. 111–12). And, in Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lha mo gang du ngas stag mo la bdag nyid yongs su btang ste / lus
                                                                yongs su gtong ba gcig gis byang chub sems dpa’ byams pa bskal pa bzhi bcur zhugs pa / phyir
                                                                ’dums par byas pa’i sa phyogs ni ’di yin no //</foreign> (Matsumura 1980, p. 267). It could be
                                                        translated: “Goddess, this is the very place in which I gave myself to the tigress. By this one act of
                                                        completely <term type="ignore">giving</term> my head (body in Tibetan), I surpassed the bodhisattva Maitreya who had set out (for
                                                        buddhahood) forty eons earlier (than I).” In this passage, the use of the Sanskrit pronoun <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mayā</foreign> clearly indicates that it was Candraprabha’s
                                                        previous incarnation (and, therefore, the Buddha Śākyamuni’s and Śrīsena’s previous incarnation) who offered
                                                        his body (or head) to the tigress, not the previous incarnation of the bodhisattva Maitreya. As explained in the preceding note, the use of ambiguous phrases in the
                                                                present rendition of this tale was probably compensated for by the familiarity most readers had
                                                                with the tale of the hungry tigress. We are much indebted to one of our anonymous reviewers for
                                                                helping to understand this short but complicated vignette and to refine our translation of
                                                                it.
                                                </note>
                    </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-169"/>
                                        <p tid="148">“ ‘Another time, Mahāmati, when I was king of the Śibi people, an old brahmin came seeking the gift of sight. Moved
                                                by compassion, I immediately extracted my unimpaired eyes and gave them to him, while they were still stained
                                                with blood. My eyes had been as unstained as an utpala flower, a blue lotus. They were extremely beautiful and
                                                captured the hearts and attention of all people—indeed, all beings.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-170"/>
                                        <p tid="149">“ ‘Yet another time, Mahāmati, when I was a king named Candraprabha, <ref cRef="F.44.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-329"/> a brahmin rudely asked me for not only
                                                my eyes but also my head. Groups of nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, siddhas,
                                                vidyādharas, and hundreds of thousands of gods tried to stop me from making this gift. Despite all this
                                                opposition, I saw that sentient beings had no protector, and with the loving intention to liberate them from
                                                saṃsāra’s wilderness, I aspired to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening. My sword was the blue color of an
                                                utpala flower. It was decorated with precious gems, gold, silver, beryl, diamonds, sapphires, and emeralds. I
                                                picked it up and chopped off my head as if it were a blade of grass, and then I gave it to the brahmin.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-171"/>
                                        <p tid="150">“ ‘Another time, Mahāmati, when I was again king of the Śibi people, I saw an unprotected, terrified pigeon, ducking
                                                and diving as it was chased by a hawk. As I watched the unprotected pigeon seek refuge, I shook with supreme
                                                compassion. To protect the pigeon from the hawk and to deceive the hawk, I cut off a piece of my own flesh and
                                                gave it to the hawk.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-172"/>
                                        <p tid="151">“ ‘In the past, in this very land, I have given thousands of legs, hands, sons, and wives for the sake of unsurpassed
                                                and perfect awakening, and no one stopped me. You should understand this, Mahāmati. And you should not stop the
                                                brahmin seeking my body.’ </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-173"/>
                                        <p tid="152"> “Following this, the great minister Mahāmati understood that the bodhisattva had given rise to great miraculous
                                                powers, and he developed profound faith in him. This great minister remained silent while waves of tears flowed
                                                down his face continually. He thought, ‘Alas, these beings are unfortunate. They will soon lose their Dharma king. 
                                                Alas, the Dharma’s victory banner is about to fall.</p>
                                                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-345"/>
                                                <lg tid="218">
                        <l>“ ‘The lamp of Dharma will be extinguished.</l> 
                                                <l>The lamp of Dharma will disappear.</l>
                                                <l>The Dharma drum is about to break.</l>
                                                <l>The ocean of Dharma will dry up. <ref cRef="F.45.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-330"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg> 
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-346"/>
                                                <lg tid="219">
                        <l>“ ‘The great mountain of Dharma will soon crumble.</l> 
                                                <l>The city of Dharma will soon be looted.</l> 
                                                <l>The ship of Dharma will soon disintegrate.</l> 
                                                <l>When the Dharma tree is uprooted, it is painful indeed.</l>
                    </lg> 
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-174"/>
                                        <lg tid="153">
                                                <l>“ ‘The wheel of time is about to crush </l>
                                                <l>The father of the entire world, </l>
                                                <l>Who has helped all beings. </l>
                                                <l>The great king will be no more. </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-175"/>
                                        <lg tid="154">
                                                <l>“ ‘Yet, in this unbearable moment,</l>
                                                <l>Why hasn’t this great being’s mind </l>
                                                <l>Been shattered into a thousand pieces,</l>
                                                <l>But is instead like a great vajra?</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-176"/>
                                        <lg tid="155">
                                                <l>“ ‘The good times are all gone. </l>
                                                <l> Unbearable times are now at hand. </l>
                                                <l>There will not be many wise people left</l>
                                                <l>And worldly ones will also be destroyed. </l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-177"/>
                                        <lg tid="156">
                                                <l>“ ‘Through many omens of the earth,</l>
                                                <l>Which can be clearly seen,</l>
                                                <l>It is certain that it won’t be long </l>
                                                <l>Before the lion king is no more.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-179"/>
                                        <lg tid="158">
                                                <l>“ ‘This stainless sun of humanity,</l>
                                                <l>So difficult to find, is about to set.</l>
                                                <l>Before long, it will no longer</l>
                                                <l>Shine forth in this world.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-180"/>
                                        <lg tid="159">
                                                <l>“ ‘In the absence of this great king</l>
                                                <l>Who benefits all sentient beings,</l>
                                                <l>When his light no longer illumines the world,</l>
                                                <l>Who will there be to protect the world?’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-181"/>
                                        <p tid="160">“After this speech, the two carpenters whom Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, had enchanted recovered enough from their grief to reapply the saw
                                                to the bodhisattva’s body. The bodhisattva encouraged them. ‘Well done, good people! Cut off the lower half of
                                                my body more quickly! Won’t my travail be fruitless if the brahmin dies?’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-182"/>
                                        <p tid="161">“There was a great crowd of people wailing, mourning, and attempting to stop the two carpenters from following the
                                                bodhisattva’s instructions and cutting his body, but Śakra had stupefied them. The bodhisattva kept silent,
                                                aspiring for awakening and joyously intending to fulfill the gift seeker’s wishes. After a while, a great deal
                                                of blood gushed from the bodhisattva’s middle where the saw was cutting. Seeing this, the great minister
                                                Mahāmati <ref cRef="F.45.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-331"/> became despondent and fell unconscious, thinking, ‘It is too painful to see the lord
                                                killed.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-183"/>
                                        <p tid="162">“Wracked by intense grief, masses of sky-dwelling gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and
                                                mahoragas started to cry. As their tears flowed, the crowds of people below wondered what was happening and
                                                looked up at the sky. There they saw hundreds of thousands of weeping gods, which made them fall further into
                                                grief. They saw the bodhisattva in great pain and, becoming utterly confused, they thought, ‘Alas! It is so very
                                                painful to see the lord killed!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-184"/>
                                        <p tid="163">“A few moments later, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, gazed with intense compassion and concern upon the hundreds of
                                                thousands of beings who were stricken by the bodhisattva’s tragedy. Then compassionate thoughts suddenly arose
                                                in him. ‘It is not right to cause intense pain to this great being who is so kind and affectionate toward all
                                                sentient beings and who gives away everything out of compassion. I will do the opposite. I will make him
                                                immortal.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-185"/>
                                        <p tid="164">“As the two carpenters cut his body with the sharp saw, the bodhisattva suffered intense pain. But he had the power
                                                to keep his mind stable and generate a loving attitude toward the gift seeker. ‘If I have understood the nature
                                                of saṃsāra’s faults and thereby gained firm and lasting perseverance but am nonetheless suffering this much pain
                                                as my body is cut in half, what can be said of the excruciating painful sensations suffered by the majority of
                                                sentient beings when they previously took rebirth in hell!’ Thinking thus, the bodhisattva established a loving
                                                mind <ref cRef="F.46.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-332"/> that encompassed all sentient beings, and with a lion’s roar, he declared, ‘By attaining
                                                unsurpassed and perfect awakening, I must free sentient beings from such suffering!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-186"/>
                                        <p tid="165">“In order to uplift his own mind that was wracked by such intense pain, the bodhisattva also said the following: </p>
                                        
                                        <lg tid="166">
                                                <l>“ ‘Look at the world’s suffering, mind, and abandon your faults!</l>
                                                <l>Be very steady and develop vastness in scope.</l>
                                                <l>Be mentally stable in patient endurance so as to protect</l>
                                                <l>These beings tormented by the pain of birth, aging, sickness, and death.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-188"/>
                                        <p tid="167">And again he said:</p>
                                        
                                        <lg tid="168">
                                                <l>“ ‘Alas, these poor sentient beings!</l>
                                                <l>Because you are the cause for all beings</l>
                                                <l>To cross over the ocean of saṃsāra,</l>
                                                <l>It would be unreasonable for you</l>
                                                <l>To not patiently endure such harms.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-190"/>
                                        <p tid="169">“These were the ways the bodhisattva truly settled his mind and established a compassionate attitude toward all
                                                sentient beings. He thought to himself, ‘Alas! The suffering of beings who are stuck in saṃsāra is unbearable.
                                                For the sake of these beings in saṃsāra, by rejoicing in patiently enduring all saṃsāra’s suffering, may no
                                                sentient being have the misfortune of suffering!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-191"/>
                                        <p tid="170">“Monks, the very instant the bodhisattva generated this mind of awakening, the pain produced by his body being sawed
                                                abruptly ceased. The bodhisattva wondered, ‘Why did the pain of my body being sawed in two cease? Did they stop
                                                sawing?’ He checked, but he could still see the saw. Having seen it, he felt extremely distressed and started to
                                                shake. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-192"/>
                                        <p tid="171">“Reading the king’s mind, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, said:</p>
                                        
                                        <lg tid="172">
                                                <l>“ ‘King, why do you shake so, </l>
                                                <l>Like a feeble, sickly person? </l>
                                                <l>Look at how my body is cut in half,</l>
                                                <l>Yet my mind is not shaken.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-194"/>
                                        <lg tid="173">
                                                <l>“ ‘You are renowned all over the earth</l>
                                                <l>For saying that you give everything away.</l>
                                                <l>So it doesn’t make sense to feel regret,</l>
                                                <l>Or else your words would be lies.’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-195"/>
                                        <p tid="174">“ ‘Brahmin,’ responded the bodhisattva, ‘this is not why my body shakes. I have no regrets <ref cRef="F.46.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-333"/> whatsoever. I am
                                                shaking at this thought: “The saw has penetrated deep into my body, but so far my lower body has not been
                                                severed. What if I am unable to make this gift? What if I am not able to fulfill the gift seeker’s wish?” I
                                                would be happy if they were to saw my body with more force.’ Hearing this, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, was
                                                completely in awe of the bodhisattva and fell silent.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-196"/>
                                        <p tid="175">“In the meantime, the two carpenters whom Śakra had enchanted finished cutting the bodhisattva’s body in half. They
                                                placed the lower half of his body on the ground and it began to twitch. Without thinking of his own
                                                suffering—the suffering of having his body cut in half—the bodhisattva addressed the two men: ‘Good people,
                                                join my lower half to the brahmin’s body without delay.’ They did as he instructed. At the moment the two body
                                                halves were joined, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, imbued the body with a blessing that made its wounds heal, the
                                                joints join together well, and the two bodies’ skin tones match. He showed everyone the body, and to please the
                                                bodhisattva, he, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, stood up from his stretcher, walked around, stood still, and then sat
                                                down.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-197"/>
                                        <p tid="176">“Seeing that his labors had borne fruit, that the gift seeker had a complete body and his wishes had been fulfilled,
                                                the bodhisattva’s mind overflowed with joy. ‘I have saved this brahmin’s life,’ he thought to himself, ‘and
                                                staved off his fear of death by giving him my body. May the seed of this virtue cause me to attain unsurpassed
                                                and perfect awakening. Then may I be able to rescue <ref cRef="F.47.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-334"/> this brahmin from the suffering of saṃsāra and
                                                establish him in nirvāṇa where he will experience the ultimate happiness.’ </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-198"/>
                                        <p tid="177">“As he thought this, the bodhisattva was overwhelmed. Even as he aspired to awaken, he slipped into unconsciousness,
                                                and his eyes began to close. Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, revived him immediately. He used medicines and care to
                                                treat and heal him. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-199"/>
                                        <p tid="178">“Monks, in the instant King Śrīsena’s body was cut in half, the trichiliocosm shook in three different ways: it
                                                shook, shook a lot, and shook extremely much. It also rocked, rocked a lot, and rocked extremely much. This
                                                great earth was unable to support the bodhisattva’s great act of generosity. It was a marvelous gift of
                                                everything and thus it resounded—it resounded as if all the world’s cauldrons had been beaten at once.
                                                Mountains, ravines, rivers, and oceans all emitted horrifying noises. Terrifying smoke appeared from the four
                                                directions. Meteors fell from all sides. Falling stars blazed in every direction. The gods beat drums in the
                                                sky.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-200"/>
                                        <p tid="179">“The trichiliocosm first darkened and then turned pitch black. Even the gods traversing the center of the sky
                                                chattered about a bodhisattva tormented with sorrow. They arranged utpala flowers above the bodhisattva and
                                                showered him with pink and white lotus flowers. They also sprinkled agaru, tagara, cinnamon-leaf, and sandalwood
                                                incense on him, and the flowers of the gods’ tree, the mandārava.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-201">
                                                                Puṇḍarīka is a white lotus flower, <foreign xml:lang="la">Nelumbium
                                                                speciosum</foreign>. Agaru is agarwood, taken from the inside of the
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="la">Aquilaria</foreign> and
                                                                <foreign xml:lang="la">Gyrinops</foreign>
                                                        trees after they have been attacked by mold. Tagara incense is made from the
                                                                milky sap of <foreign xml:lang="la">Tabernaemontana divaricata</foreign>. Indian tradition has it that the mandārava tree growing in Indra’s
                                                                garden is the <foreign xml:lang="la">Erythrina variegata</foreign>, or Indian coral tree.</note> They even draped their clothes on
                                                him, danced, and played divine music loudly. All of Jambudvīpa’s people were deeply puzzled by these noises.
                                                <ref cRef="F.47.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-335"/>
                    </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-202"/>
                                        <p tid="180">“When the city’s inhabitants, hundreds and thousands of people, saw the bodhisattva’s body cut, they were tormented
                                                by intense grief. With a single voice they cried out in their grief, ‘Alas, seeing the lord killed is
                                                painful!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-203"/>
                                        <p tid="181">“Some rolled on the ground, others flailed their arms and wailed. The voices of some became hoarse from passionate
                                                sobbing. They were unable to clearly voice their words, yet still they screamed and beat their chests. Others
                                                remained silent, their minds mournful and unsettled, thinking, ‘Impermanence is powerful indeed!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-204"/>
                                        <p tid="182">“Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, was convinced that the bodhisattva’s resolve to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening
                                                was as immovable as Mount Sumeru. He marveled at how the bodhisattva had given so completely. The hairs on his
                                                body stood on end. He was filled with joy and witnessed something outstanding. Marveling at this, he opened his
                                                eyes, and together with the other four gods, he dissolved his brahmin semblance, and he and the four gods
                                                appeared in their own forms. Śakra then spoke to the bodhisattva: ‘Great King! I am no brahmin, I am Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term>
                                                of the gods. Well done, Great King, well done! How amazing, your diligence! How amazing, your uncontrived
                                                resolve! How amazing that you gave your body so completely, without clinging! How amazing, your compassion
                                                toward sentient beings and love for them! Your joy in giving! Well done, well done! Great King, even though you
                                                were overwhelmed by intense suffering, you did not change your mind about giving away your body. Great King, I
                                                have a question for you: what was the reason you underwent such hardship and such a prolonged trial?’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-205"/>
                                        <p tid="183">“ ‘Kauśika,’ replied the bodhisattva, ‘by giving away my body, I wish to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening. I
                                                wish to liberate sentient beings from saṃsāra.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-206"/>
                                        <p tid="184">“Śakra then asked, ‘Great King, as your body was deteriorating, as you offered your body, as you gave it away
                                                completely, did you have any regrets? Did your mental state change at all?’ <ref cRef="F.48.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-336"/> </p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="185">“ ‘Kauśika, I had no regrets,’ replied the bodhisattva.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-208"/>
                                        <p tid="186">“ ‘How can we know this?’ Śakra asked.</p>
                                        
                                        <p tid="187">“ ‘Kauśika,’ said the bodhisattva, ‘to prove it, I will allow you to place the lower half of my body wherever you
                                                like.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-210"/>
                                        <p tid="188">“Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, then put the lower half of the bodhisattva’s body in a place of his liking. The bodhisattva
                                                established a loving attitude toward all sentient beings, and invoking truth at that time, he spoke the
                                                following verses:</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-211"/>
                                        <lg tid="189">
                                                <l>“ ‘As I wish for awakening, </l>
                                                <l>I did not experience miserliness or sadness</l>
                                                <l>When I let go of my body compassionately.</l>
                                                <l>Now, I have no regrets.</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-212"/>
                                        <lg tid="190">
                                                <l>“ ‘And as I have no regrets, Śakra,</l>
                                                <l>May the truth of my words and goodness of my actions</l>
                                                <l>Now restore my body,</l>
                                                <l>Exactly as it was before.</l>
                                                <l>May all my senses be complete!’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-213"/>
                                        <p tid="191">“Monks, as soon as he spoke these verses, the bodhisattva’s body was restored. The sky-dwelling gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                                                garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas who witnessed this were wide-eyed in amazement and started babbling and
                                                laughing. The crowds of people gathered there were also awed and amazed. Both gods and humans were overjoyed at
                                                this magical display. When they saw that the bodhisattva’s body was completely restored, they developed wonder
                                                as if they had found their own lives after having lost them. They said, ‘How amazing! Let us gaze upon this
                                                marvel of your resurrection! The beings of this world, those on the land and in the forest, are fortunate
                                                indeed!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-214"/>
                                        <p tid="192">“When Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, saw that the bodhisattva’s body had been restored to its original state, he was
                                                overwhelmed. To please the bodhisattva, he said, ‘Great King, your mind is <ref cRef="F.48.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-337"/> heroic. Your aspiration is
                                                steadfast, and you engage with sentient beings out of great compassion. Well done, well done! You are not afraid
                                                of anyone who attempts to frighten you. Due to your efforts, you will, therefore, attain unsurpassed and perfect
                                                awakening in a short while.’ Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, then recited the following verses:</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-215"/>
                                        <lg tid="193">
                                                <l>“ ‘Ah! Your diligence is great and fierce.</l>
                                                <l>Your steadfastness is unsurpassed.</l>
                                                <l>Ah! Your compassion for beings!</l>
                                                <l>Ah! Your determination to awaken!</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-216"/>
                                        <lg tid="194">
                                                <l>“ ‘Ah! How wonderful would the world be</l>
                                                <l>If you, lord, were its ruler!</l>
                                                <l>You will travel beyond suffering’s fearful and ferocious ocean; </l>
                                                <l>You will attain nirvāṇa!’</l>
                                        </lg>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-217"/>
                                        <p tid="195">“As he said these words, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, shed tears like rain, and in a hoarse voice he sought forgiveness
                                                from the bodhisattva. 
                                                
                                                ‘O Great King,’ he said, ‘thinking that you might meet with failure, I coerced you to suffer excruciating pain. Please forgive me.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-218">
                                                        Translated based on Narthang and Lhasa, which read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bzod par mdzod</foreign>.
                                                        <!--The Degé edition of this line is missing a number
                                                        of words and has several misspellings. This makes the line almost impossible to understand. In
                                                        translating it, the Comparative Edition notes (p. 142, notes 6, 7, and 8) were invaluable. -->
                        </note> And please think 
                                                of me when you attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-219"/>
                                        <p tid="196">“ ‘Kauśika,’ replied the bodhisattva, ‘I am patient. I will do as you ask and remember you.’ In that instant, due to
                                                the bodhisattva’s power, a variety of divine, enchanting, precious gems rained down upon all of Jambudvīpa. All
                                                of Jambudvīpa was ornamented by myriad precious stones, and it became even brighter than the realms of the
                                                gods.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-220"/>
                                        <p tid="197">“The sage who lived in the mountains had witnessed all these marvels, and he was overwhelmed. ‘What are these
                                                marvels?’ he thought. ‘Have such marvels ever been seen before? Whose power occasions this?’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-221"/>
                                        <p tid="198">“A god who lived in the same place as he told him the story in detail. As he listened to the story of the
                                                bodhisattva’s extraordinary, awe-inspiring austerities, <ref cRef="F.49.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-338"/> the sage came to genuinely admire him. ‘This
                                                great being is <term type="ignore">worthy</term> of veneration,’ he thought. After that, he hastily led his five-hundred-strong retinue and
                                                Queen Jayaprabhā to the bodhisattva. There they uttered salutations of victory and long life to the king. In
                                                unison with Śakra, the sage said, ‘Lord, you have protected these fine, goddess-like, beautiful women. Now
                                                please enjoy life with this virtuous woman. I offer you back the beautiful queen. She has not been unhappy with her husband.<!--<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-222"> Although the Degé edition reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’phyo</foreign>,
                                                        which means “to soar,” we have followed the Lithang edition and translated it as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phyo</foreign>, without a prefix. </note>--> Please
                                                do not give her away again to anyone else who asks for her.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-223"/>
                                        <p tid="199">“The bodhisattva compassionately accepted the request of the sage and Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, by remaining silent. Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of
                                                the gods, then summoned Viśvakarma, the architect of the gods. ‘Viśvakarma,’ he said, ‘please set up a divine
                                                lion throne quickly. I would like to honor King Śrīsena myself.’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-224"/>
                                        <p tid="200"> “ ‘That is excellent, Kauśika,’ Viśvakarma responded. ‘I will do as you instruct.’ <lb/>Indeed, at the very moment
                                                he was listening to Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, Viśvakarma, the architect of the gods, magically created a lion
                                                throne. It was decorated with a variety of precious gems, and it was garlanded with pearls on all sides. Śakra,
                                                <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, took the bodhisattva with both his hands and escorted him onto the divine lion throne.
                                                Hundreds of thousands of gods played and sang melodious music for him. Having shown great respect in this way,
                                                they crowned him. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-225"/>
                                        <p tid="201">“During the coronation, the bodhisattva’s power caused the earth to shake in six different ways. Out of joy and
                                                satisfaction, the gods showered flowers and precious gems on Jambudvīpa. So many fell that the flowers and gems
                                                were piled up to the peoples’ knees. In sheer amazement at seeing this amount of wealth, the gods and humans
                                                exclaimed, <ref cRef="F.49.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-339"/> ‘Amazing! How powerful is King Śrīsena’s merit! Amazing! It is wondrous!’</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-226"/>
                                        <p tid="202">“After thoroughly pleasing the bodhisattva, Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, along with hundreds of thousands of other gods,
                                                returned to his abode. The sage and his retinue of five hundred also returned home, after openly praising the
                                                bodhisattva. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-227"/>
                                        <p tid="203">“After these events, the much-venerated bodhisattva ruled as a Dharma king for a long time. He satiated Jambudvīpa’s
                                                poor, blind, hungry, and destitute by granting them wealth, and he led everyone along the path of the ten
                                                virtuous actions. He thoroughly satisfied all six classes of gods in the desire realm. At another time, he
                                                caused them, along with hundreds of thousands of others, to be reborn in Tuṣita heaven.”</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-228"/>
                                        <p tid="204">After telling this tale, the Blessed One said, “Monks, do not have any doubts or confusion that King Śrīsena was
                                                someone other than me. At that time, I was the king and I gave away my body. Monks, the one who was King
                                                Śrīsena’s wife back then, Queen Jayaprabhā, is none other than Yaśodharā. The supreme one among the ministers,
                                                Mahāmati, is none other than the monk Śāriputra. Śakra, <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods, is none other than King Bimbisāra.
                                                Those who were the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three at that time are none other than the eighty
                                                thousand gods who realized the truth simultaneously with King Bimbisāra. The masses of people in the city of
                                                Ariṣṭa are none other than <ref cRef="F.50.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-340"/> the brahmins and householders of Magadha who come to me along with King
                                                Bimbisāra. Monks, the sage who lived in the mountains is none other than the monk Maudgalyāyana. The young
                                                brahmin boy who came to me to beg for Queen Jayaprabhā is none other than the Śākya lady Gopā. Monks, the two
                                                who were carpenters at that time are Devadatta and Kokālika.</p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-229"/>
                                        <p tid="205">“It is due to the power of his prayers that such miracles of the Thus-Gone One manifested. 
                                                Monks, therefore, you too must train in this way. You must train by telling yourselves, ‘I will 
                                                practice generosity and perform meritorious acts.’ ”</p>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-230"/>
                                        <p tid="206">When the Blessed One had said these words, the monks rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words. </p>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-231"/>
                                        <trailer tid="207">
                        <title xml:lang="en">This completes “The Account of the Noble Deeds of King Śrīsena</title>.”</trailer>
                                </div>
                                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-colophon">
                                        <head type="colophon" tid="208">Colophon</head>
                                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-233"/>
                                        <p tid="209">This was translated by the Indian preceptor Dharmaśrībhadra and the chief editor-translator Sherab Lekpa. It was then
                                                revised and finalized by the translator Rinchen Zangpo.</p>
                                </div>
                        </div>
                </body>
                <back>
                        <div type="notes">
                                <head type="notes" tid="210">Notes</head>
                        </div>
                        <div type="listBibl">
                                <head type="listBibl" tid="212">Bibliography</head>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-listBibl-1">
                                        <head type="section" tid="213">Source Texts</head>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-234">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>). Toh 349, Degé Kangyur vol. 76 (mdo sde, ah), folios 31b–50a.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-236">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>). bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                                                Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa
                                                dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 76, pp. 91–136. </bibl>
                                        
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-343">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>). Stok Palace Kangyur (stog pho brang
                                                bris ma bka’ ’gyur) vol. 68 (mdo sde, tsa), 370b–398a.</bibl>
                                        
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-238">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>). bka’ ’gyur (lha sa), vol. 76, pp. 101–61. Lha sa: Zhol bka’ ’gyur par khang. </bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-240">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>). bka’ ’gyur (shel mkhar bris ma), vol. 47, (mdo sde, tsa), folios 340a–365a.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-242">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde’i rtogs pa brjod pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsenāvadāna</title>). bka’ ’gyur (urga), vol. 76, pp.
                                                        64–104. New Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture, 1990. </bibl>
                                </div>
                                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-listBibl-2">
                                        <head type="section" tid="214">Secondary Sources</head>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-244">Appleton, Naomi. <title xml:lang="en">Jātaka Stories in Theravāda Buddhism: Narrating the Bodhisatta
                                                Path</title>. London: Ashgate, 2010.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-246">Chakraborty, Uma. <title xml:lang="en">Kṣemendra, the Eleventh Century Kashmiri Poet: A Study of His Life
                                                and Works</title>. Delhi, India: Sri Satguru Publications, 1991. </bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-248">Chattopadhyay, J. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattva Avadānakalpalatā: A critical study</title>. Calcutta: Atisha Memorial Pub. Society, 1994. </bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-250">de Jong, J. W. <title xml:lang="en">Textcritical Remarks on the Bodhisattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title> (Pallavas
                                                42–108). Tokyo, Japan: Reiyukai Library, 1979. </bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-252">Emmerick, R. E., tr. <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Golden Light: Being a Translation of the Suvarṇabhāsottamasūtra</title>. London: Luzac &amp; Company, Ltd.,
                                                1970.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-253">Kṣemendra (1997). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Rtogs brjod dpag bsam ’khri shing gi rtsa
                                                ’grel</title>. (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>). Zi
                                                ling: Mtsho sngon mi rigs dpe skrun khrung.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-254">——— (1981). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Rtogs brjod dpag bsam ’khri shing</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>). Delhi: Karmapae Chodhey.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-255">——— (1959). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>. Darbhanga: Mithila Institiute.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-256">Matsumura, Hisashi, ed. “Four Avadānas from the Gilgit Manuscripts.” PhD diss., Australian National University, 1980.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-258">Ohnuma, Reiko. <title xml:lang="en">Head, Eyes, Flesh, and Blood: Giving Away the Body in Indian Buddhist
                                                Literature</title>. New York: Columbia University Press, 2007.</bibl>
                                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-076-003-260">Rothenberg, Bonnie Lynne. “Kṣemendra’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvāvadāna­kalpalatā</title>: A Textcritical Edition and Translation of Chapters One to Five.” PhD diss., University of Wisconsin–Madison, 1990. </bibl>
                                </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="glossary">
  <list type="glossary">
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-262">
        <term>desire realm</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་ཁམས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāmadhātu</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the three realms of saṃsāra, it is comprised of the traditional six realms of saṃsāra, from the hell realm to the realm
          of the gods, including the human realm. Rebirth in this realm is characterized by intense cravings via the five senses and their objects.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-263">
        <term>diligence</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་འགྲུས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</term>
        <term type="definition">Fourth of the six perfections and one of the seven limbs of awakening, the five abilities, the four bases of magical power, and
          the five powers.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-076-003-264" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>giving</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">See ”generosity.“</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-265">
        <term>infer</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rjes su dpag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྗེས་སུ་དཔག་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anumāna</term>
        <term type="definition">In Buddhism, inference is one of the two sources of valid knowledge (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pramāṇa</foreign>), the other being direct perception
            (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyakṣa</foreign>).</term>
        <!--<term type="alternative">to infer, be inferred</term>-->
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-266">
        <term>god (lord)</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
        <term type="definition">A being in the paradises from the base of Mount Meru upward. It can also refer to a deity in the human world and is sometimes
                (as in the present work) used as a term of endearment for a ruler or leader (translated as “lord”).</term>
        <term type="alternative">god</term>
        <term type="alternative">lord</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-267">
        <term>preceptor</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mkhan po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཁན་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādhyāya</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-268">
        <term>predispositions</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bag chags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བག་ཆགས།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vāsanā</term>
        <term type="definition">Latent propensity to certain behaviors.</term>
       <!-- <term type="alternative">latent tendencies</term>-->
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-270">
        <term>royal estate</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕོ་བྲང་།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
        <!--<term type="alternative">palace</term>-->
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-076-003-271" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>generosity</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The act of giving motivated by the wish to attain awakening for all sentient beings. It is the first of the six or ten perfections, often explained as the essential starting point and training for the practice of the others perfections. Also translated here as “giving.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-272">
        <term>universal monarch who rules through force</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs kyi ’khor los sgyur </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala­cakra­vartin</term>
              <term type="alternative">universal monarch who ruled through force</term>
              <term type="definition">In Buddhist mythology, a universal monarch who rules the four continents and is willing to use force (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bala</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs</foreign>) if necessary.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-273">
        <term>unsurpassed and perfect awakening</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa’i byang chub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anuttara­samyak­saṃbodhi</term>
        <term type="definition">The awakening of the buddhas, so-named to distinguish it from the limited realizations of lesser beings such as arhats, solitary
          buddhas, and the like.</term>
         <term type="alternative">unsurpassed, perfect awakening</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-274">
        <term>vajra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajra</term>
        <term type="definition">The term stands for indestructibility and perfect stability. According to Indian mythology, the vajra is the all-powerful god
          Indra’s weapon, likened to a thunderbolt, which made him invincible. It also relates to the diamond which is the hardest physical material.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-275">
        <term>Veda</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་བྱེད།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Veda</term>
        <term type="definition">Name of the ancient sacred scriptures of Hinduism, the most famous of which is the Ṛg Veda.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-276">
        <term>worthy</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhant</term>
              <term type="definition">A person who has accomplished the final fruition of the path of the hearers and is liberated from saṃsāra.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-277">
        <term>Bimbisāra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs can snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bimbisāra</term>
        <term type="definition">The king of Magadha.</term>
        <term type="alternative">King Bimbisāra</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-278">
        <term>Maitreya</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
        <term type="definition">The bodhisattva and future buddha, Maitreya.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-279">
        <term>Devadatta</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhas byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷས་བྱིན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Devadatta </term>
        <term type="definition">The Buddha’s disloyal cousin.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-280">
        <term>Gopā</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’tsho ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་འཚོ་མ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gopā</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the wives of Prince Siddhārtha, prior to his leaving his kingdom and attaining awakening as the Buddha.</term>
        <term type="alternative">Śakya lady Gopā</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-281">
        <term>Jayaprabhā</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal ba’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jayaprabhā</term>
        <term type="definition">King Śrīsena’s wife.</term>
        <term type="alternative">Queen Jayaprabhā</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-282">
        <term>Kokālika</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ko ka li ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀོ་ཀ་ལི་ཀ</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kokālika</term>
        <term type="definition">Devadatta’s companion.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-283">
        <term>Mahāmati</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmati</term>
        <term type="definition">King Śrīsena’s chief minister.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-284">
        <term>Maudgalyāyana</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maudgalyāyana</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the Buddha’s two principal monastic disciples.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-286">
        <term>Śakra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra </term>
        <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">lord</term> of the gods. More commonly known in the West as Indra, the deity that is called “<term type="ignore">lord</term> of the devas” dwells on the
          summit of Mount Sumeru and wields the thunderbolt. The Tibetan translation <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brgya byin</foreign> (meaning “one hundred sacrifices”) is based on an
          etymology that śakra is an abbreviation of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śata-kratu</foreign>, one who has performed a hundred sacrifices. Each world with a central Sumeru has a
                Śakra. He is also called “Kauśika.”</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
          <item>
                 <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-341"> 
                         <term>Kauśika</term>
                  <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kau shi ka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ</term>
                  <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauśika</term>
                         <term type="definition">Another name of Śakra; see definition for “Śakra.”</term>
                 </gloss>
          </item>
          
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-287">
        <term>Śāriputra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the Buddha’s two principal monastic disciples.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-288">
        <term>Śrīsena</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīsena</term>
        <term type="alternative">King Śrīsena</term>
              <term type="definition">A king, who was a past life of the Buddha. He was a bodhisattva renowned 
                      for his unstinting generosity and spiritual resolve.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-289">
        <term>Viśvakarma</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las sna tshogs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལས་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viśvakarma</term>
        <term type="definition">Literally “maker of sundry things,” Viśvakarma is the architect of the gods. He was an important deity in the Vedic tradition.
          In the Ṛg Veda, he is regarded as the personification of ultimate reality, the abstract creative power inherent in deities, living, and nonliving
          being in this universe.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-290">
        <term>Yaśodharā</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grags ’dzin ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲགས་འཛིན་མ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yaśodharā</term>
        <term type="definition">The principal wife of Prince Siddhartha, prior to his leaving his kingdom and attaining awakening as the Buddha.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-291">
        <term>Ariṣṭa</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a riSh+Tha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨ་རིཥྛ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ariṣṭa</term>
        <term type="definition">King Śrīsena’s royal estate.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-292">
        <term>Caitraratha</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing rta sna tshogs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་རྟ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཅན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Caitraratha</term>
              <term type="definition">“The Garden of Chariots”; one of the four parks in Sudarśana city, home of Śakra (Indra) and his thirty-two gods, located on the summit of Mount Meru. </term>
        <!--<term type="alternative">The Garden of Chariots</term>-->
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-293">
        <term>Darśanīya</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blta na sdug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བལྟ་ན་སྡུག</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Darśanīya</term>
        <term type="definition">A divine city filled with crowds of gods.</term>
        <!--<term type="alternative">The Spectacular</term>-->
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-294">
        <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trayastriṃśa</term>
        <term type="definition">The second heaven of the desire realm located above Mount Meru and reigned over by Indra, otherwise known as Śakra, and
          thirty-two other gods.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-295">
        <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu’i gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
        <term type="definition">
                The continent (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvīpa</foreign>) on which we live, shaped like a rose-apple (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jambū</foreign>) according to ancient South Asian cosmology.
                <!--According to Buddhist cosmology, the central one of the seven continents surrounding Mount Sumeru. -->
                            </term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-296">
        <term>Pārijāta</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs ’du </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོངས་འདུ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pārijāta</term>
              <term type="definition"><!--“The Wish-Fulfilling Tree”;-->In Indian mythology, a tree in Indra’s heaven that is said to fulfill all desires.</term>
        <!--<term type="alternative">The Wish-Fulfilling Tree</term>-->
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-297">
        <term>Magadha</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ga d+hA</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་ག་དྷཱ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Magadha </term>
              <term type="definition">A kingdom on the banks of the Ganges (in the southern part of the modern day Indian state of Bihar), 
                      whose capital was at Pāṭaliputra (modern day Patna). During the life of the Buddha Śākyamuni, it was the dominant kingdom 
                      in north central India and is home to many of the most important Buddhist sites, including Bodh Gayā, Nālandā, and 
                      its capital Rājagṛha.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-298">
        <term>Mount Sumeru</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri’i rgyal po ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རི་རབ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumeru parvatarāja</term>
        <term type="definition">The great mountain at the center of the universe according to ancient Indian cosmology. At its summit lies Sudarśana city, home
                of Śakra (Indra) and his thirty-two gods. The mountain is also referred to as Mount Meru.</term>
        <term type="alternative">Mount Meru</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-299">
        <term>Nandanavana</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བའི་ཚལ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nandanavana</term>
              <term type="definition">“The Pleasure Grove”; the chief of the parks in Sudarśana city, where the resident gods of the city, headed by Śakra (Indra), go for their
          amusement.</term>
        <!--<term type="alternative">The Pleasure Grove</term>-->      
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-301">
        <term>Śibi</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shi bi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤི་བི།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śibi</term>
        <term type="definition">(1) A name sometimes used for King Śrīsena’s country. (2) The name of a country he once ruled in previous lifetimes.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-302">
        <term>Tuṣita heaven</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་ལྡན།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tuṣita</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
              <term type="alternative">Tuṣita</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
          <item>
                  <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-076-003-344">
                          <term>preta</term>
                          <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡི་དགས།</term>
                          <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                          <term type="definition">One of the five or six classes of sentient beings, considered to be the karmic fruition of past miserliness. In Sanskrit, literally “the departed”; they are analogous to the ancestral spirits of Vedic tradition, the pitṛs, who starve without the offerings of descendants. They live in the realm of Yama, the <term type="ignore">Lord</term> of Death. They are particularly known to suffer from great hunger and thirst and the inability to acquire sustenance. </term>
                  </gloss>
          </item>
  </list>
</div>
                </back>
        </text>
</TEI>