<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­buddhāṅgavatī­dhāraṇī</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yan lag dang ldan pa’i gzungs</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་གཟུངས།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="zh">《諸佛支具陀羅尼》（大正藏：《諸佛集會陀羅尼經》）</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Dhāraṇī “Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sarva­buddhāṅgavatī­nāma­dhāraṇī</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yan lag dang ldan pa zhes bya ba’i gzungs</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">འཕགས་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གཟུངས།</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-62"/>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-226">David Gitlen</author>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay, Dr.</editor>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-280">Kammie Takahashi</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-252">Dion Blundell</editor>
                <consultant role="projectManager" ref="contributors.xml#person-226">David Gitlen</consultant>
                <editor role="projectEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.6 <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into
                    modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0
                            copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal
                            compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-088-007"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard
                    logic.</note>
                <date>2021-05-03</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh513" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 513</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 88 (rgyud ’bum, na), folios 26.a–27.b (in 1737 par phud printing), folios 43.a–44.b (in later printings)</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Dānaśīla</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bandé Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="4">
                        <volume number="88" start-page="85" end-page="88"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC21415" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12235" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
                <bibl key="toh856" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 856</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 100 (gzungs ’dus, e), folios 76.a–77.b</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="4">
                        <volume number="101" start-page="149" end-page="152"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20568" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12618" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2022-09-06T14:19:35.869Z" user="admin">06/09/2022 14:19:35</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2019-06-21T07:07:37.133Z" user="john">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2019-07-28T02:10:47.602Z" user="dion-blundell">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-10-09T05:59:48.729Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-01-28T06:22:15.913Z" user="mike">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.1" date-time="2021-02-12T09:08:07.163Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.2" date-time="2021-02-12T09:08:24.603Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2021-02-19T15:15:36.608Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.3" date-time="2021-02-19T15:15:36.608Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2021-02-19T15:29:51.266Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.4" date-time="2021-02-19T15:29:51.266Z" user="line-tofte">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.5" date-time="2021-03-08T09:28:30.034Z" user="mike">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2021-03-08T09:29:34.725Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1.6" date-time="2021-03-08T09:29:34.725Z" user="mike">Auto
                    (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2021-03-11T14:37:35.648Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2021-03-11T14:37:35.648Z" user="mike">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2021-03-16T13:38:13.858Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2021-04-27T15:25:00.971Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2021-05-03T11:55:33.253Z" user="mike">1</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.0" date-time="2021-05-03T11:55:33.253Z" user="mike">First published version</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.1" date-time="2021-05-03T12:57:32.115Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.2" date-time="2021-05-03T13:40:16.746Z" user="john">minor edits</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.3" date-time="2021-05-06T10:46:16.807Z" user="mike">Typo fixed</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.4" date-time="2022-06-27T10:06:48.1Z" user="admin">Auto (script-increment-version-published)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.5" date-time="2022-07-26T07:29:26.805Z" user="cabie-sim">Auto (update-titles)</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="1.0.6" date-time="2022-09-06T14:19:31.849Z" user="martina-cotter">Updated typo.</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="4">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-1"/>
                <p tid="5">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas</title> details a brief exchange between the Buddha
                    and the four <distinct>guardian kings</distinct> of the world, that is, the four divine beings who rule over the cardinal directions in the
                    Indian Buddhist tradition. Pursuant to a description of the fears that plague mankind, the Buddha declares that he will provide remedies for
                    them. Invoking the presence of numberless buddhas in the limitless world systems described in Buddhist cosmology, the Buddha and the four
                    kings provide several mantras of varying lengths meant for daily recitation, with the stated benefits not only of averting all manner of
                    calamities—untimely death, illness, and injury chief among them—but of attracting the attention and blessings of all the buddhas and
                    bodhisattvas, and ensuring good health and benefit for the practitioner and all beings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="6">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-2"/>
                <p tid="7">The translation was produced by David Gitlen, who also wrote the introduction. The translator would like to express his gratitude to
                    Khensur Geshe Wangdak Rinpoche, Phil Stanley, Sarah Harding, and Acharya Lama Tenpa Gyaltsen for their help and guidance.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="8">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-introduction-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-3"/>
                <p tid="9">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas </title>records an encounter between the Buddha and
                    the four guardians of the world at an unspecified site on the banks of the Ganges River. The Buddha himself initiates the dialogue,
                    describing four great fears—aging, sickness, decrepitude, and death—declaring death to be the chief among them, and promising to provide
                    remedies for them. With a snap of his fingers, the Buddha summons the attention and presence of buddhas throughout the reaches of space in
                    the ten directions, and they recite, in unison, the longest of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī</foreign> incantations
                    found in the text. Each of the four guardians, in turn, goes on to pledge his assistance and provides a shorter dhāraṇī mantra as a
                    supplement to the main one. The Buddha succinctly describes the various applications and benefits of the recitation, reading, writing, and
                    wearing of these mantras, accruing not only to the individual, but to the very place in which they are recited and to those with whom they
                    are connected. Finally, he explains how such practices fit in with commonly accepted ideas of accumulating merit through acts of
                    devotion.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-4"/>
                <p tid="10">The original Sanskrit text for <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas </title>has not been
                    located, but a Chinese translation does exist (Taishō 1346). The Chinese text lists the translator as Devendraprajñā, whose exact dates are
                    uncertain, but who was active in China as a translator under Tang dynasty patronage by the last decade of the seventh century. The Chinese
                    version is quite close to the Tibetan (although it has a different title),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-5"> The Chinese title is
                        simply <title xml:lang="en">The Gathering of All Buddhas Dhāraṇī Scripture</title>
                        <title xml:lang="zh">諸佛集會陀羅尼經</title>.</note> but it does contain a number of differences and additional lines or fragments, as well as
                    a short section at the end, not found in the Tibetan versions, describing a ritual procedure for constructing altars and making
                        offerings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-6"> The translations of this section and the other variations are included as notes
                        inserted in the relevant places.</note> In the Degé Kangyur <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī Endowed with the Attributes of All the
                        Buddhas</title> is included among the tantras belonging to the Action (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kriyā</foreign>) class (Toh 513) and it is also reproduced in the Dhāraṇī
                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzungs ’dus</foreign>) section (Toh 856).
                    <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-74">
                        <p key="toh513" tid="39">Note that there is a discrepancy among various databases for
                            cataloging the Toh 856 version of this text within vol. 100 or 101 of the Degé Kangyur. See Toh 856, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh856.html#end-note-UT22084-088-007-74">note 3</ref>, for
                            details.</p>
                        <p key="toh856" tid="40">This text, Toh 856, and all those
                            contained in this same volume (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus, e</foreign>), are listed as being located in volume
                            100 of the Degé Kangyur by the Buddhist Digital Resource Center (BDRC). However, several other Kangyur databases—including
                            the eKangyur that supplies the digital input version displayed by the 84000 Reading Room—list this work as being located
                            in volume 101. This discrepancy is partly due to the fact that the two volumes of the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs
                                ’dus</foreign> section are an added supplement not mentioned in the original catalog, and also hinges on the fact that
                            the compilers of the Tōhoku catalog placed another text—which forms a whole, very large volume—the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimala­prabhā­nāma­kālacakra­tantra­ṭīkā</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dus ’khor ’grel bshad dri
                                med ’od</title>, Toh 845), before the volume 100 of the Degé Kangyur, numbering it as vol. 100, although it is almost
                            certainly intended to come right at the end of the Degé Kangyur texts as volume 102; indeed its final fifth chapter is
                            often carried over and wrapped in the same volume as the Kangyur <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chags</foreign>
                            (catalog). Please note this discrepancy when using the eKangyur viewer in this translation.</p>
                    </note> The attribution in the colophon of the Tibetan version
                    to the translators Jinamitra, Dānaśīla, and Yeshé Dé puts its translation somewhere around the end of, or shortly after, the reign of King
                    Trisong Detsen, at the turn of the ninth century. Its inclusion in the Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ldan dkar
                        ma</foreign>) catalog of the canon, compiled in 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>, supports this.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-7"> Denkarma, 302.b.6. See also Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, 222, no. 389.</note> Lastly, it should be mentioned that an
                    English translation of this text by Joan Nicell was published online in 2007.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-8"/>
                <p tid="11">This English translation was produced based on both Toh 513 and Toh 856 in the Degé Kangyur in consultation with the Comparative
                    Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>), the Stok Palace Kangyur, and the Chinese translation (Taishō 1346). </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="12"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="13">The Noble Dhāraṇī “Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas”</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-section-1">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-10"/>
                    <p tid="17">
                        <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.26.a" key="toh513"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.43.a" key="toh513" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-73"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.76.a" key="toh856" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-69"/>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-75">
                            <p key="toh513" tid="41">Two sets of folio references have been included in this translation due to a discrepancy 
                                in volume 88 (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud ’bum</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">na</foreign>) of the Degé Kangyur between the 1737 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">par 
                                    phud</foreign> printings and the late (post <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">par phud</foreign>) printings. In the latter case, 
                                an extra work, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­maṇḍasyālaṃkāra­lakṣa­dhāraṇī</title> (Toh 508, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub 
                                    snying po’i rgyan ’bum gyi gzungs</title>), was added as the second text in the volume, 
                                thereby displacing the pagination of all the following texts in the same volume 
                                by 17 folios. Since the eKangyur follows the later printing, both references 
                                have been provided, with the highlighted one linking to the eKangyur viewer.</p>
                            <p key="toh856" tid="42">In the Toh 513 version of the text there is a slight discrepancy in the folio numbering between the 1737 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">par phud</foreign> printings and the late (post <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">par phud</foreign>) printings of the Degé Kangyur. Although the discrepancy is irrelevant here, further details concerning this may be found in <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh513.html#end-note-UT22084-088-007-75">note 5</ref> of the Toh 513 version of this text.</p>
                        </note> 
                        Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    
                    <p tid="18">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling on the bank of the great river Gaṅgā together with the four guardians
                        of the world. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-13"/>
                    <p tid="19">At that time, the Blessed One said to those four great kings including Vaiśravaṇa, <ref cRef="F.76.b" key="toh856" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-70"/> “All men, women, young boys, and girls have four great fears. Which four? These four: aging, sickness,
                        decrepitude, and death.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-14"> The Chinese here lists the more frequently encountered “birth, old
                            age, sickness, and death” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">生老病死</foreign>.</note> Among them, the single greatest fear is of the
                        Lord of Death, in that death is cruel,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-15"> I am following the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> in translating <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btsam pa med pa</foreign>, the reading found in the
                            Narthang, Peking, and Yongle editions, as Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niṣṭhura</foreign>, “cruel.” The Degé and
                            others have the variant reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brtsam pa med pa</foreign>.</note> cannot be remedied, and is
                        always in close pursuit.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-16"> Instead of this line, the Chinese only states that the fear of
                            death is “the most difficult to get rid of” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">然於其中死怖一種最難除遣</foreign>.</note> Great kings, I will
                        now pronounce the remedy for this single great fear.”</p>
                    
                    <p tid="20">The four great kings replied,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-18"> In the Chinese text, the four great kings rise from
                            their seats and bow with their palms joined before speaking.</note> “Blessed One, it is our great fortune that the Blessed One will
                        care for all beings by bestowing life for their sake!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-19"/>
                    <p tid="21">The Blessed One was seated facing<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-20"> Translated based on Yongle, Lithang, Peking, and
                        Cone versions, where the word <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thugs</foreign> is missing. It appears, however, in both the
                            Degé and Stok Palace editions. In the Chinese version the Buddha rises from his seat before turning to the east. </note> east, and
                        with the sound of a finger snap he invoked all the tathāgatas, saying, “May all the tathāgatas, the worthy ones, the perfect buddhas,
                        who have fully awakened to unsurpassable and perfect awakening out of love for sentient beings, assist me! Having been blessed here by
                        all the buddhas, I will avert the untimely deaths of all beings! I will turn a second wheel of Dharma that has not been turned before!”
                        <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.26.b" key="toh513"/>
                        <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.43.b" key="toh513" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-66"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-21"/>
                    <p tid="22">Likewise, he invoked all the tathāgatas of the south, west, north, above, and below, saying, “May all the tathāgatas, the worthy
                        ones, the perfect buddhas, who have fully awakened to unsurpassable and perfect awakening out of love for sentient beings, assist
                        me!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-22"/>
                    <p tid="23">Likewise, in every intermediate direction he spoke these words, so that beings’ <ref cRef="F.77.a" key="toh856" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-71"/> life spans, physical strengths, and complexions would be perfect, and so that fear of an untimely
                        death would not arise, saying, “May all the buddhas assist me!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-23"/>
                    <p tid="24">Then there appeared before the Buddha’s eyes as many world systems as there are elements of earth throughout the ten directions,
                        filled with blessed buddhas like a sesame pod. These tathāgatas pledged their assistance, and all spoke the following:<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-24"> While there is a fair amount of variation in some of the mantra syllables across the various Kangyur
                            witnesses, these have not been noted here.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-25"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="25">
                        <mantra type="dharani" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tadyathā calā calā cale vinati svastike cakrāṅgati praśamantu sarvarogānatre kunaṭe
                            mahākunaṭe care carere hemagiri hemagauri hemaniśunti hemasisi kaurave kauravave hekurare kurare kumati piṣasamaṇe śiṣuvi cale cale
                            vicale mā vilamba humu humu svāhā</mantra>!</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-26"/>
                    <p tid="26">The lords of the guhyakas, as many as there were, from their places beside all
                        those tathāgatas, also spoke, saying “<mantra type="dharani" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṁ hūṁ si si svāhā</mantra>!” and the tathāgatas vanished from
                        sight.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-27"/>
                    <p tid="27">Then the great king Vaiśravaṇa said, “Blessed One, I, too, with the blessing of the tathāgatas, will act as a guardian, and will
                        avert untimely death! <mantra type="dharani" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tadyathā śvete śvete lelili</mantra>!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-28"/>
                    <p tid="28">Virūḍhaka also spoke, saying <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.27.a" key="toh513"/>
                        <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.44.a" key="toh513" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-67"/> “<mantra type="dharani" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mātaṅge mātaṅge mātaṅgini śūmā śūmū</mantra>!” </p>
                    
                    <p tid="29">Dhṛtarāṣṭra also spoke, saying “<mantra type="dharani" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">care carere svāhā</mantra>!” </p>
                    
                    <p tid="30">Virūpākṣa also spoke, saying “<mantra type="dharani" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">balampipa</mantra>!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-31"/>
                    <p tid="31">The Blessed One responded, “Great Kings, when a son or daughter of noble family recites at least once a day, every day, these
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vidyāmantras</foreign> seen<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-32"> The Chinese has
                            here “born from all Buddhas and known by all Buddhas” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">從於一切諸佛所生。一切諸佛共所知見</foreign>.</note> by all
                        the buddhas, that son or daughter of noble family should be regarded as a teacher. <ref cRef="F.77.b" key="toh856" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-72"/> That son or daughter of noble family will never again be reborn in the three lower realms and will be
                        of benefit to the lives of all beings. Anyone who recites these words once a day for the benefit of all beings, or even reads them, will
                        have no fear of untimely death. Their bodies will be free of disease. At no time will they drown, or be killed by fire, by weapons, by
                        poison, or by lightning. It should be known that wherever a child of the victors recites these <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vidyāmantras</foreign>, he or she will secure the attention of all the buddhas and bodhisattvas. Anyone who writes this down, or
                        has it written down, will be serving the blessed buddhas with every respect and honor. If one wonders why this is, it is because the
                        tathāgatas have declared that serving sentient beings is serving the buddhas. If someone, having written this, affixes it to a
                            limb,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-33"> The Chinese version states “Whoever wishes to protect their body should write
                            down this mantra and wear it on their body” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="term">若有專欲擁護其身。當書此呪佩著身上</foreign>. It additionally inserts
                            “Wherever it is, there will be sons and daughters of noble family, and others, with deep faith in the Dharma” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">若所在之處有深信法善男子善女人等</foreign>.</note> all their limbs will be protected.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-34"> The Chinese text includes an entire additional section here: “First find a pure, clean place, cover the ground in sandalwood, and
                            construct a square altar with dimensions of seven cubits. Beginning on the eighth day of the lunar month, you should wash yourself
                            in a bath of fragrant water and put on clean, new clothes. You should take the eight <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upāsaka</foreign> precepts and abstain from any food except sweet rice porridge. Take black and camphor incense, and place two
                            full measures on the altar. Also take white sandalwood incense or quality aloeswood incense, or camphor incense, or a combination of
                            clove incense and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kakubha</foreign> incense, and place that upon the altar. You should recite
                            the dhāraṇī over all the incense seven times, seven times a day, for seven days. On the fifteenth day of the lunar month, you should
                            abstain from taking the noontime meal, and make twenty-one small altars with saffron incense. The first should be dedicated to the
                            tathāgata, and the remaining twenty should be dedicated to the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vajrarājas</foreign>. Around
                            them you should make four small altars, dedicated to the four great kings, with incense of musk, camphor, white sandalwood, saffron,
                            and red sandalwood. Then you should make offerings to the tathāgata altar by strewing and anointing it, as well as making offerings
                            of incense to it and all the other altars in turn. Also take buttermilk, yogurt, and sugar, and, sequentially, place them in the
                            mouths of four new flasks as offerings, which should be placed separately upon the altars of the four great kings. Fill these flasks
                            with fresh water, and place in them the flowers of the twelve fruit trees. Burn ten lamps filled with fragrant oil on the altar of
                            the tathāgata, with the intention to make offerings to the buddhas of the ten directions, and burn one lamp on each of the other
                            altars. Take the incense over which you recited the dhāraṇī, as well as camphor and quality aloeswood, and burn it to honor the
                            tathāgata. Burn the remaining incense on the other altars. While the incense is burning on the altars, chant the various divine
                            dhāraṇīs. Any being who smells this incense will never die prematurely or accidentally. When the incense has burned out, the various
                            offerings should be scattered in a clean place.” <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">先當簡擇清淨之處。以栴檀末而塗其地
                                。成一方壇縱廣七肘。其人應從月初八日。香湯洗浴著新淨衣受八戒齋。唯食粳米石 蜜牛乳。取黑沈香及龍腦香。共滿一兩置於壇上。又取白檀香或沆水香。或龍腦香或 復丁香迦矩羅香。而置於壇。其人誦此陀羅尼呪。呪此諸香。於日日中皆七七遍滿于
                                七日。至十五日一日不食其日中時。以欝金香於其壇上作二十一小壇。其一處中名如 來壇。餘二十壇名金剛王壇。又於壇外作四小壇。名四天王壇復取麝香龍腦白檀欝金 之香及紫檀末。於如來壇若散若塗而為供養。自餘諸壇隨取一香而供養之。又取乳酪
                                酥及沙糖。如其次第以新瓶四口。各別盛之置四天王壇上。又以淨水著於瓶內。採十 二種果樹之花而置其中。又以香油然十支燈置如來壇。為欲供養十方佛故。自餘諸壇 各然一支。於前所呪諸香之內。取龍腦及沈水。於如來壇而燒供養。其餘壇上然自餘
                                香。將然香時其如來壇及餘壇香。復應各別誦此神呪而以呪之。若有眾生得聞此香。 非時夭橫靡不除滅。先所呪香並燒盡已。然後收彼四天王食散於淨處</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-35"/>
                    <p tid="32">When the Blessed One had spoken this, the four great kings, the entire retinue, and the world with all its gods, humans, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">asuras</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gandharvas</foreign> rejoiced and praised
                        the words of the Blessed One.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-36"/>
                    <trailer tid="33">This concludes the <title xml:lang="en">Noble Dhāraṇī Endowed with the Attributes of All the Buddhas</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="34">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-37"/>
                    <p tid="35">
                        <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.27.b" key="toh513"/>
                        <ref work="W22084" cRef="F.44.b" key="toh513" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-68"/> This was translated and edited by the Indian
                        preceptors Jinamitra and Dānaśīla and the translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé. It was then revised according to the new lexicon and
                        finalized.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="36">Notes</head>

            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="38">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-listBibl-1">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-38">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yan lag dang ldan pa zhes bya ba’i
                        gzungs</title>. (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sarva­buddhāṅgavatī­nāma­dhāraṇī</title>). Toh 513, Degé Kangyur, vol. 88 (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyud ’bum, na</foreign>), folios 26.a–27.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-39">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yan lag dang ldan pa zhes bya ba’i gzungs.
                            bka’ ’gyur</title> (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan pe
                        sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa
                        dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 88, pp 126–31.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-40">
                        <title xml:lang="zh">諸佛集會陀羅尼經. 中華電子佛典協會. 大正新脩大正藏經</title> (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Chu fo chi hui t’o lo
                            ni ching</title>). Vol. 21, no. 1346.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-41">Braarvig, Jens. “Dhāraṇī and Pratibhāna: Memory and Eloquence of the Bodhisattvas.”<title xml:lang="en">
                            Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title> 8, no.1 (1985): 17–29.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-42">Davidson, Ronald M. “Studies in Dhāraṇī Literature I: Revisiting the Meaning of the Term Dhāraṇī.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Indian Philosophy</title> 37 (2009): 97–147.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-43">_______. “Studies in dhāraṇī literature II: Pragmatics of dhāraṇīs.” <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of the
                            School of Oriental and African Studies</title> 77 (2014): 5–61.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-44">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan [/ lhan] dkar gyi chos ’gyur ro cog gi dkar
                            chag</title>). Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b - 310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-45">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische
                            übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-46">Lamotte, Étienne. <title xml:lang="en">History of Indian Buddhism: From the Origins to the Śaka
                            Era</title>. Translated from the French by Sara Webb-Boin under the supervision of Jean Dantinne. Louvain-la-Neuve: Université
                        catholique de Louvain, Institut orientaliste, 1988.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-47">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men: The Bodhisattva Path according to The Inquiry of Ugra
                            (Ugraparipṛcchā)</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawai’i Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-007-48">Nicell, Joan. 
                        <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://fpmt.org/wp-content/uploads/teachers/zopa/advice/pdf/dharani_possessing_the_limbs_c5.pdf">The 
                            Dharani Called “Possessing the Limbs of All the Buddhas.”</ref>
                        </title>
                        Portland: FPMT Inc., 2007.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-49">
                            <term>four great kings</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po chen po bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catur mahārāja</term>
                        <term type="definition">Four gods who preside over the cardinal directions: Virūḍhaka, Virūpākṣa, Dhṛtarāṣṭra, and Vaiśravaṇa. They are also referred to as the “four guardians of the world.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-50">
                            <term>four guardians of the world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten skyong ba bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catur lokapāla</term>
                        <term type="definition">See the “four great kings.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-088-007-51" type="person" mode="match">
                            <term>lord of the guhyaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang ba pa’i bdag po</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསང་བ་པའི་བདག་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhyakādhipati</term>
                            <term type="alternative">lords of the guhyaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Vaiśravaṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="UT22084-088-007-53" type="term" mode="match">
                            <term>upāsaka (precepts)</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བསྙེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāsaka</term>
                            <term type="alternative">upāsaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The upāsaka precepts for lay practitioners include the five fundamental vows (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pañcaśīla</foreign>) not to (1) kill, (2) steal, (3) commit sexual misconduct, (4) lie, or (5) use intoxicants. Additionally, three other precepts are taken on full-moon and new-moon days for a total of eight (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭāṅgaśīla</foreign>): not to (6) eat after the noon meal, (7) engage in entertainment or adorn oneself with ornaments or cosmetics, or (8) sleep on high beds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-54">
                            <term>vidyāmantra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig sngags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་སྔགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyāmantra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Knowledge or awareness mantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-55">
                            <term>Dānaśīla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dA na shI la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཱ་ན་ཤཱི་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānaśīla</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Charitable,” an Indian paṇḍita who traveled to Tibet during the time of King Trisong Detsen to serve as a
                                translator.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-56">
                            <term>Dhṛtarāṣṭra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul ’khor srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhṛtarāṣṭra</term>
                            <term type="definition"> “Protector of the Realm” (Tib.) or “Whose Realm is Stable,” (Skt.) guardian of the eastern direction. Also
                                the name of a king in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahābhārata</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-57">
                            <term>Jinamitra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Friend of the Victor,” an Indian paṇḍita who traveled to Tibet during the time of King Trisong Detsen to
                                serve as a translator.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-59">
                            <term>Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam thos kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The “Son of Viśrava (Completely Renowned),” guardian of the northern direction. He and his father are both
                                also referred to as Kubera, and he is also known as Jambhala. He rules over spirits called guhyakas (literally “secret/hidden
                                ones”), described in various capacities, giving rise to his epithet Guhyakādhipati, “Lord of the Guhyakas.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-60">
                            <term>Virūḍhaka</term>
                        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags skyes po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་སྐྱེས་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Virūḍhaka</term>
                            <term type="definition"> “Noble Birth” (Tib.) or “Sprouting/Growing Forth,” (Skt.) guardian of the southern direction. Also the name
                                of a king of Kosala during the lifetime of Śākyamuni Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-61">
                            <term>Virūpākṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig mi bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིག་མི་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Virūpākṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Deformed Eyes,” <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nāga</foreign> king and guardian of the western
                                direction. Also common epithet of Śiva, where it indicates his odd number of eyes.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-62">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Disciple of Padmasambhava and translator. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-088-007-63">
                            <term>Gaṅgā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang gA </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་གཱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṅgā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The river Ganges</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>