<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha mo gtsug tor rol pa’i tan+tra</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མོ་གཙུག་ཏོར་རོལ་པའི་ཏནྟྲ།</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Devi uṣṇīṣālalīta­tantra</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་ལྷ་མོ་གཙུག་ཏོར་རོལ་པའི་ཏནྟྲ།</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo gtsug tor rol pa’i tan+tra</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Glorious Tantra of the Play of the Goddess
          Uṣṇīṣā</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīdevi uṣṇīṣālalīta­tantra</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
        <author role="translatorMain" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-1"><!--84000 Associate Translators--></author>
        <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-2">Catherine Dalton</author>
        <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-14">Ryan Damron</editor>
        <editor role="copyEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-24">Dawn Collins</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-32">Nathaniel Rich</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-43">Martina Cotter</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0.0 <date>2025</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
          initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them
          available to everyone. </publisher>
        <availability status="1.a">
          <p type="tantricRestriction">
                        <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that
            according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are restrictions and commitments
            concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this translation
            are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading
            this text or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in
            the hands of readers.</p>
          <licence>
            <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
            <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND
              (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or
              printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage
              or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno xml:id="UT22084-101-042"/>
        <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that
          these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
        <date>2025-01-22</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl key="toh987" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 987</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 101 (gzungs ’dus, waM), folios 138.b–141.b</biblScope>
          <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="7">
            <volume number="102" start-page="276" end-page="282"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20568" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12750" work="W22084"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <notesStmt/>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-01-07T13:49:05.081Z" type="translation-status" status="3" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-3">
          <desc>3</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-01-07T13:49:05.081Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.1" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-4">
          <desc>0.0.1</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-01-07T13:49:23.013Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-5">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-01-07T13:49:39.718Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-6">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-05T09:38:52.026Z" type="translation-status" status="2.h" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-7">
          <desc>2.h</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-05T09:38:52.026Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-8">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.5" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-9">
          <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-02-15T15:10:56.206Z" type="translation-status" status="2.g" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-10">
          <desc>2.g</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-02-15T15:10:56.206Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.6" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-11">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-02-15T15:11:39.351Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.7" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-15">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-03-27T15:08:31.724Z" type="translation-status" status="2.f" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-16">
          <desc>2.f</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-03-27T15:08:31.724Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.8" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-17">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#sameer" when="2024-07-02T10:41:47.478Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.9" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-18">
          <desc>Updated vol. 101 page numbers to match the ekangyur</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-01T16:10:33.045Z" type="translation-status" status="2.d" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-19">
          <desc>2.d</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-01T16:10:33.045Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.10" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-20">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-01T16:11:05.492Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.11" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-25">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-10-14T13:38:11.533Z" type="translation-status" status="2.c" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-26">
          <desc>2.c</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-10-14T13:38:11.533Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.12" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-27">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-10-24T09:29:48.963Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.13" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-33">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-10-31T16:02:24.128Z" type="translation-status" status="2.b" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-34">
          <desc>2.b</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-10-31T16:02:24.128Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.14" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-35">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-11-15T06:08:19.781Z" type="translation-status" status="2.a" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-36">
          <desc>2.a</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-11-15T06:08:19.781Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.15" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-37">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-11-15T06:09:35.24Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.16" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-44">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-12-04T11:42:10.363Z" type="translation-status" status="2" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-297">
                    <desc>2</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-12-04T11:42:10.363Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-298">
                    <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#martina-cotter" when="2025-01-22T15:34:37.657Z" type="translation-status" status="1.a" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-299">
                    <desc>1.a</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#martina-cotter" when="2025-01-22T15:34:37.657Z" type="text-version" status="1.0.0" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-300">
                    <desc>First published version.</desc>
                </change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!--Note the "Contents" outline from the Word DOCX has not been included in the script. If the 
                    Outline to the text is quite complex, it is recommended that you paste the outlined contents from the DOCX here as a comment for
                    markup's reference. The actual table of contents will be generated in the Reading Room by the parser.-->
    <front>
      <div type="summary" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-summary">
        <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-45"/>
        <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> is a
          short tantra concerning a series of disease-causing spirits and the incantations that
          avert them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgment" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-acknowledgment">
        <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-46"/>
        <p tid="4">This publication was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
          Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-47"/>
        <p tid="5">The text was translated, edited, and introduced by the 84000 translation team.
          Catherine Dalton produced the translation and wrote the introduction. Ryan Damron edited
          the translation and the introduction, and Dawn Collins copyedited the text. Martina Cotter
          was in charge of the digital publication process.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-introduction">
        <head type="introduction" tid="7">Introduction</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-introduction-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-49"/>
          <p tid="9">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> is a
            short text concerning a series of disease-causing spirits and the incantations that
            avert them. Though titled a “tantra,” the text internally refers to itself as a
            “demon-averting dhāraṇī-sūtra” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gdon zlog pa’i mdo’i
              gzungs</title>). The text lacks the introductory narrative framework (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nidāna</foreign>) typical of sūtras and tantras and,
            indeed, has no narrative elements at all. Rather, the tantra begins with a list of names
            of these spirits, all female, who are organized into two main groups: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">grahīs</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gdon</foreign>) and a set comprised of “rulers” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang byed</foreign>) of thirteen tents (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gur</foreign>). Despite being divided into these groups, both sets of
            female deities are identified as emanations of the goddess Ekajaṭī. The tantra proceeds
            to describe different illnesses and conditions associated with the specific grahīs and
            “tent rulers,” and to teach incantations for the particular deities that serve as
            remedies for these afflictions. In the instructions for each incantation, the
            practitioner is directed to employ a specific type of ritual dagger (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kīla</foreign>), and the text provides an extensive list
            of the different daggers suitable for each purpose. The final incantations in the tantra
            are distinct for being written in a mixture of Tibetan and Sanskrit. Following the list
            of incantations and remedies, the tantra concludes with a statement of the benefits of
            reciting the text and following the proper ritual procedures (which are not taught in
            the tantra). The tantra proclaims that someone who does so will accomplish all of their
            wishes, be victorious on the battlefield, and defeat their enemies. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-50"/>
          <p tid="10">The grahīs that form the core subject of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of
              the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> are a class of disease-causing spirits that
            appear in Buddhist and non-Buddhist Indic texts alike.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-51"> In a non-Buddhist context grahas and grahīs primarily
              appear in texts related to Āyurveda, non-Buddhist Tantric systems, and astrology.
              However, illness-causing spirit possessors also appear in classical literature such as
              the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ṛgveda</title>, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atharvaveda</title>, and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahābhārata</title>. The
              interested reader is referred to <title xml:lang="en">The Self Possessed</title>,
              Frederick M. Smith’s study on possession in South Asia that deals extensively with
              this subject and includes a discussion of traditional understandings of the ontology
              of disease-causing entities like grahas and bhūtas. See especially his chapter “The
              Medicalization of Possession in Āyurveda and Tantra” (Smith 2006, pp. 471–578).</note>
            These spirits, who can be either male (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">graha</foreign>) or female (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">grahī</foreign>),<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-52"> The Tibetan
              translation of both graha and grahī is the ungendered term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gdon</foreign>, though in some texts the gender of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gdon</foreign> is specified by adding the masculine
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">pho</foreign>) or feminine (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mo</foreign>) prefix, e.g. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">pho gdon</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mo
                gdon</foreign>. In our text, however, all are referred to simply as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gdon</foreign>, with their gender determined by
              associated adjectives.</note> are understood to cause physical and mental illnesses by
            means of possessing the person.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-53"> See Smith
              2006 for a discussion of grahīs and their function in (primarily non-Buddhist) Indic
              literature. Smith writes that “[o]ne of the most prominent varieties of possession in
              Indian literature is demonic, disease-producing possession” (Smith 2006, p. 272), and
              “[t]he most common word for such invasive disease-causing spirits in Āyurveda is
              grahī…” (Smith 2006, p. 476). </note> Indeed, the very name of this class of spirits
            comes from the Sanskrit verbal root √<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">grah</foreign>, which signifies grasping or seizing. While it seems that the lists of
            such grahas remained fluid in Indic literature,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-54"> Ibid, p. 482.</note> the members of the list found in
              <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> do not map
            onto any known set of grahīs in either the Indian or the Tibetan tradition. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-55"/>
          <p tid="11">The Tibetan term for such disease-causing spirits, <distinct>dön</distinct>
              (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gdon</foreign>), is also an important term in
            Tibetan medicine, where it is used not just to refer to the spirits themselves, but also
            as a technical term for certain types of diseases associated with
              <distinct>dön</distinct>, including types of mental illness, stroke, paralysis, and
            skin disorders.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-56"> See Tidwell, Nianggajia,
              and Fjeld 2023. </note> Similar to its Indic counterpart, the Tibetan medical
            tradition describes <distinct>dön</distinct> as “grasping” or “taking hold of” those
            afflicted by their influence.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-57"> Ibid., note
              16.</note> In both traditions, the causes for such spirit-induced illnesses are
            associated with ethical transgressions, as well as offenses committed against the
            specific afflicting spirit, and the symptoms of illness often share similar
            characteristics with the afflicting spirit.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-58"> Smith 2006, Chapter 12; and Tidwell, Nianggajia, and Fjeld 2023.</note> While both
            traditions typically prescribe medical and ritual means in the treatment for such
              afflictions,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-59"> Ibid.</note>
            <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> focuses solely
            on ritual means: the use of incantations and the wielding of ritual daggers. The tantra
            does not reference the cause of being afflicted by such spirits, but it does establish a
            relationship between the offending spirits and the deity whose mantra is indicated as
            their remedy. For example, the afflictions caused by the grahī Black Yamā are overcome
            by the incantation of Mañjuśrī Yamāntaka, and the afflictions caused by the grahī Black
            Indrāṇī are overcome by the incantation of Indra. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-60"/>
          <p tid="12">The other type of disease-causing spirits described in <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> are the Tent-Ruling Ladies
              (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gur la dbang byed ma</foreign>). They do not
            appear elsewhere in the Kangyur or Tengyur and comprise one of several features of this
            text that suggest it may have been compiled in Tibet, on the basis of both Indic and
            Tibetan elements, rather than translated from an Indic source. There is no single aspect
            of the text that would definitively indicate a Tibetan rather than an Indic provenance
            for this work. However, there are a number of such features which, when taken in
            aggregate, do rather strongly suggest this to be the case. This includes the unusual
            title of the work, which appears to be a back-translation from Tibetan into Sanskrit;
            the absence of a translator’s colophon; unusual mantras that include many seemingly
            non-Indic words and rough approximations of Sanskrit terms; the inclusion of several
            spirit types like the <distinct>terang</distinct> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">te rang</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">te’u
              rang</foreign>), <distinct>tsen </distinct>(<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btsan</foreign>), and <distinct>gongpo </distinct>(<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’gong po</foreign>) that are indigenous to Tibet and lack Indic
            equivalents; the reference to the <distinct>terang</distinct> spirts of the sky, the
            “middling” area, and the earth (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gnam</foreign>,
              <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bar</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sa</foreign>); the “tent-ruling ladies,” whose tents are made of
            turquoise, coral, crystal, ox-wool, silk, or leather, all of which convey a Tibetan,
            rather than Indic, feel; the reference to a mountain-top yak spirit; and the inclusion
            of a spirit named the Lord of Order who Carries a White Staff (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skos rje drang dkar</foreign>), one of the nine male
            ancestors (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid pa ’pho dgu</foreign>) from the
            indigenous Tibetan Bonpo mythology.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-61"> See
              Norbu, p. 166 for further details on the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid
                pa ’pho dgu</foreign>.</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-62"/>
          <p tid="13">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> is
            only included in the Kangyurs from the Tshalpa line. It is found in the Compendium of
            Dhāraṇīs (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus</title>) section of the Kangyurs that
            have one, as the Degé does, and in the Tantra section of those Tshalpa Kangyurs that do
            not. It is not found in any of the Kangyurs of the Thempangma line. The canonical
            recension of this tantra, moreover, appears to be the only form in which it is extant—we
            find neither a Sanskrit text nor a Chinese translation, no record of this work in
            Dunhuang or in the imperial Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phang thang
              ma</title>) or Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan kar ma</title>) catalogs, and
            the tantra does not appear in any extracanonical collections. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-63"/>
          <p tid="14">The Dunhuang manuscript archive may, nonetheless, provide some clues that help
            us understand the context of this tantra. There are several collections of dhāraṇīs
              (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzungs ’dus</foreign>) found at Dunhuang in which the
            compiled dhāraṇīs are preceded by a short version of <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold
              Invocation Ritual</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ’dren rgyud gsum pa</title>,
            or just <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud gsum pa</title>)<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-64"> For more on <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation
                Ritual</title>, see <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation Ritual</title>
                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ’dren rgyud gsum pa</foreign>, Toh 846), <ptr target="#UT22084-100-001-introduction"/><!--Introduction-->. </note> that includes
            the invocation of a number of worldly deities and spirits to witness the ritual
            recitation of dhāraṇīs. This is followed by the main collection of texts, which then
            concludes with a series of closing prayers and dedications.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-65"> Dalton 2016, p. 204.</note> This same tripartite
            structure maps on to the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs sections found in the Kangyurs; in fact,
            the versions of <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation Ritual</title> in these
            canonical dhāraṇī collections are precisely the same as those found at the head of such
            collections from the Dunhuang archive.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-66">
              Ibid and Dalton and van Schaik 2006, p. 309, as well as <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh846.html">The Threefold Invocation
                  Ritual</ref>
                            </title> and <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh846a.html">The Threefold
                Ritual</ref>
                            </title>. Peter Skilling (1992, p. 122) has also observed a similar
              tripartite pattern among collections of Pali <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">paritta</foreign> texts used for protective ritual functions. It is therefore
              notable that none of the eighteen Sanskrit <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</title> texts cataloged and studied by Gergely Hidas (2021)
              include an opening invocation and closing dedicatory section framing the dhāraṇīs
              included in those collections. A more detailed study of the structure of Chinese
                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāranī­saṃgrahas</title>, of which there are several,
              would surely prove interesting, but the scholars who have studied these Chinese works
              have not remarked on such a structure (see Shinohara 2014). It thus appears that this
              tripartite structure in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇī­saṃgraha </title>literature
              may remain unique to Tibetan collections.</note> It is in these shared structural
            features of Tibetan dhāraṇī collections that we find interesting parallels with <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title>. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-67"/>
          <p tid="15">First, both <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess
              Uṣṇīṣā</title> and <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation Ritual</title> are
            among just a dozen works in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs section of the Degé Kangyur that
            are not additionally found elsewhere in that Kangyur. The remaining 237 texts in the
            Compendium of Dhāraṇīs section are also found in either the Sūtra or Tantra sections of
            the Degé Kangyur.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-68"> See the <ref target="https://84000.co/kb-articles/compendium-of-dharanis-kangyur-section">84000
                Knowledge Base page on the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs</ref> for further details on these
              collections and their texts. In Tshalpa Kangyurs that lack a Compendium of Dhāraṇīs
              section, most of the same texts are found at the end of the Tantra section. This is
              precisely the case with the present texts. In such Kangyurs, <title xml:lang="en">The
                Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> and both <title xml:lang="en">The
                Threefold Ritual</title> texts are found in the Tantra section. </note> Moreover,
            the translators of <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation Ritual</title> suggest
            that this work may have been compiled in Tibet on the basis of Indic elements.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-69"> See the <ptr target="#UT22084-100-002-3">introduction</ptr> to <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Ritual</title>. We also
              find a number of the very same Indic elements from <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh846.html">The Threefold Invocation
                  Ritual</ref>
                            </title> referenced in <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of
                the Goddess Uṣṇīṣa</title>:<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh987.html"/> the seven mothers, the four
              sisters, Ekajatī, Indra, Yama, Vaiśravaṇa, grahas, yakṣīnīṣ, rākṣasīs, piśācīs, nāgas,
              garuḍas, bhūtas, kumbhāṇḍas, etc. <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation
                  Ritual</title> refers to these deities and other beings as “held by the hook
              of the vidyāmantra,” (<ptr target="#UT22084-100-001-29"/>) while <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣa</title> prescribes vidyāmantras as
              methods to overcome illnesses caused by such spirits.</note> Indeed, in the Dunhuang
            archive we find a commentary on <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Invocation
              Ritual</title>, IOL Tib J 711, in which, in addition to the many Indic gods and
            spirits who are mentioned, there is also a short discussion of
              <distinct>terang</distinct> spirits—a category of spirits indigenous to Tibet—in a
            section of the text where the three worlds in Indic cosmology (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khecara</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhūcara</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nāgaloka</foreign>) are likened to the three worlds from pre-Buddhist Tibetan
            cosmology: the sky, the “middling” area, and the earth (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gnam</foreign>,<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term"> bar</foreign>,
              and<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term"> sa</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-70"> Dalton and van Schaik 2006, p. 309.</note> We will recall
            that <distinct>terang </distinct>spirits from the sky, the “middling” area, and the
            earth appear in <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess
              Uṣṇīṣā</title> as one of its seemingly Tibetan, rather than Indic, features. This
            suggests that some of the texts included in Tibetan dhāraṇī collections may have been a
            locus where Indic demonologies were merged with Tibetan demonologies. It would appear
            that this is particularly true for those texts that are unique to the Tibetan canonical
            dhāraṇī collections and not duplicated in other sections of the Kangyur.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-71"/>
          <p tid="16">While there are no known versions of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the
              Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> outside of Kangyur canonical collections, the text
            shares a significant portion of its content with another dhāraṇī text preserved under
            two different titles: <title xml:lang="en">The Play of Uṣṇīṣādevī</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor lha mo rol ma</title>; henceforth TLR) and <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī Called Uṣṇīṣā of the Playful Goddess Mahākālī</title>
              (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha mo nag mo chen mo rol par byed pa’i gtsug tor zhes bya
              ba’i gzungs</title>). This text is found in several extracanonical collections as well
            as in the small canonical collections kept in four Western Tibetan monasteries. However,
            it is not included in any of the larger Kangyur or Tengyur collections.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-72"> In two extracanonical collections, the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo rgyud gsungs rab rgya mtsho’i snying po gces par btus pa ’dod
                ’byung nor bu’i phreng ba</title> compiled by Tāranātha, and the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe rnying rtsa chen bris ma’i skor phyogs bsdus</title>
              (provenance unknown), the title is given on the title page as <title xml:lang="en">The
                Play of Uṣṇīṣādevī</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor lha mo rol
              ma</title>), but the title given in both the incipit and explicit of the text itself
              is <title xml:lang="en">The Uṣṇīṣā of the Playful Goddess Mahākālī</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha mo nag mo chen mo rol par byed pa’i gtsug tor zhes bya ba’i
                gzungs</title>). The latter is the title under which it is preserved in the Western
              Tibetan canonical collections from the monasteries at Barden, Stagrimo, Stongde, and
              Egoo. However, in the Barden collection, the only one among these four collections
              that we have had access to, the short title given by the editors at the front of the
              text is also <title xml:lang="en">The Play of Uṣṇīṣādevī</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor lha mo rol ma</title>) (<ref target="https://www.istb.univie.ac.at/kanjur/rktsneu/sub/index.php">https://www.istb.univie.ac.at/kanjur/rktsneu/sub/index.php</ref>.</note> Given the
            fact that both of these two largely parallel works have limited canonical inclusion, it
            may be that some redactors of canonical collections considered them to be Indic texts,
            while other redactors did not.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-73"> It is also
              possible that the redactors of some canonical collections simply did not have access
              to these works. </note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-74"/>
          <p tid="17">The present English translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play
              of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title> was produced on the basis of the Degé<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-294">
              <p key="toh987">This text, Toh 987, and all those contained in this same volume
                  (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus, waM</foreign>
                </foreign>), are listed as being located in volume 101 of the Degé Kangyur by the
                Buddhist Digital Resource Center (BDRC). However, several other Kangyur
                databases—including the eKangyur that supplies the digital input version displayed
                by the 84000 Reading Room—list this work as being located in volume 102. This
                discrepancy is partly due to the fact that the two volumes of the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus</foreign> section are an added supplement not
                mentioned in the original catalog, and also hinges on the fact that the compilers of
                the Tōhoku catalog placed another text—which forms a whole, very large volume—the
                  <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimala­prabhā­nāma­kālacakra­tantra­ṭīkā</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dus ’khor ’grel bshad dri med ’od</title>, Toh 845), before the
                volume 100 of the Degé Kangyur, numbering it as vol. 101, although it is almost
                certainly intended to come right at the end of the Degé Kangyur texts as volume 102;
                indeed its final fifth chapter is often carried over and wrapped in the same volume
                as the Kangyur <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chags</foreign> (catalog). Please
                note this discrepancy when using the eKangyur viewer in this translation.</p>
                        </note>
            recension of the text, in consultation with the recension found in the Qianlong Kangyur
            as well as the notes from the Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur
              ma</title>) of the Kangyur. The text is stable across all of the Kangyurs consulted,
            with the same title and only minor variants; all recensions are alike in lacking a
            translators’ colophon. The tantra appears to have some textual problems that are likely
            the result of textual corruption. As a result of this, it is sometimes difficult to
            decipher. Where applicable, the parallel passages in <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī
              Called Uṣṇīṣā of the Playful Goddess Mahākālī</title> were consulted for clarity, but
            given that that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Dhāraṇī</foreign> is not strictly
            parallel with this tantra, emendations on the basis of that text were made sparingly, and such instances are noted in the footnotes to the translation. A number of
            passages display verse segments in which one or more lines of verse have a slightly
            uneven syllable count, or where an occasional line break is not shown on the page with a
              <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shad</foreign>, despite the segment being
            properly metered. We have chosen to render these passages in verse despite these
            anomalies, because the versified structure of the passages is nonetheless clear, and we
            presume the periodic uneven syllable count and lack of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shad</foreign> are textual corruptions that have crept into the text over
            time. Because the provenance of this text is uncertain, and because the mantras and
            dhāraṇīs found herein include many non-Indic elements, we have rendered the mantra
            formulas in individual syllables rather than speculatively combining them into longer
            strings, even in cases where the intended Sanskrit term is clear. Finally, many of the
            deities and spirits listed in this text are unknown outside the witnesses identified
            above, so many of the identifications remain speculative until further resources come to
            light.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-translation">
        <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
        <head type="titleMain" tid="18">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-section-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-76"/>
          <p tid="22">
                        <ref cRef="F.138.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-295"/> Homage to the
            glorious self-arisen goddess!</p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-78"/>
          <p tid="24">These are the eighteen emanations:<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-79"> The text nonetheless lists nineteen.</note> the grahī
            Black Vetālī, the grahī Black Piśācī, the grahī Black Unmadā, the grahī Black Obscurer,
            the grahī Black Defeater, the grahī Black Seer, the grahī Black Rākṣasī, the grahī Black
            Vāyu, the grahī Black Indrāṇī, the grahī Black Revatī, the grahī Black Kumbhāṇḍī, the
            grahī Black Nāginī, the grahī Black Yakṣiṇī, the grahī Black Revatī Protectress Vetālī,
            the grahī Great Revatī the Lion-Faced Defeater, the grahī Great Revatī the Garuḍa-Winged
            Ḍākinī, the grahī Great Revatī Who Extends One Hand, the grahī One-Toothed One-Eyed
            Great Revatī, and the grahī Donkey-Riding Great Revatī. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-80"/>
          <p tid="25">There are also the additional emanations, the thirteen Ladies of the Tent who
            are great heart emanations: the grahī Ruler of the First Tent,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-81"> In this list we read the numbers as ordinal rather than
              cardinal numbers based on a list of these grahīs later in the text that uses ordinal
              numbers. </note> the grahī Ruler of the Second Tent, the grahī Ruler<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-82"> This translation follows C, J, K, Q, and Y in reading
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dbang byed</foreign>. D omits <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang</foreign>.</note> of the Third Tent, the grahī
            Ruler of the Fourth Tent, the grahī Ruler of the Fifth Tent, the grahī Ruler of the
            Sixth Tent, the grahī Ruler of the Seventh Tent, the grahī Ruler of the Eighth Tent, the
            grahī Ruler of the Ninth Tent, the grahī Ruler of the Tenth Tent, <ref cRef="F.139.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-288"/> the grahī Ruler of the Eleventh Tent, the
            grahī Ruler of the Twelfth Tent, and the grahī Ruler of the Thirteenth Tent. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-83"/>
          <p tid="26">There are the re-emanations emanated by the heart emanations: the Ruler of
            Epidemics, the Ruler of Strife, the Ruler of All Mārā Armies, the Ruler of Illness and
            Fever, the Ruler of Headaches, the Ruler of Mouth Disease, the Ruler of Blood and Throat
            Disease, the Ruler of Heart Disease, the Ruler of Internal Illness, the Ruler of Painful
            Larynx Diseases, the Ruler of Painful Thigh Diseases, the Ruler of Painful Calf
            Diseases, the Ruler of Ulcers, the Ruler of Wasting Diseases, the Ruler of Bladder
            Disease, the Ruler of Skin Diseases, the Ruler of Painful Limb Diseases, the Ruler of
            Rashes, the Ruler of Pox, the Ruler of Burning Itch, the Ruler of Abscesses, the Ruler
            of Toxic Potions,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-84">
              <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dbyigs dug</foreign>, a poison made of
              precious substances.</note> the Ruler of Poison-Derived Diseases, the Ruler of
            Dysentery, the Ruler of Stomach Illness, the Ruler of Plague, the Ruler of Latent Brain
            Disease, and the rest. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-85"/>
          <p tid="27">Know that the rulers of the four-hundred forty-four types of illnesses are
            emanations of Ekajaṭī.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-86"> While the Sanskrit
              name of this goddess is usually rendered as Ekajaṭā, all of the Tibetan translations
              here render her name Ekajaṭī, which is indeed how she is commonly referred to in
              Tibet.</note> Eliminate them all with the vidyāmantra blessed by the true vidyāmantra.
            Stab with the dagger that violently repels. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-87"/>
          <p tid="28">Eliminate a harmful graha by reciting the vidyāmantra of Black Vetālī Rākṣasī,
            destroyer of the triple city. Stab with the dagger. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-88"/>
          <p tid="29">Eliminate a harmful graha, an insanity-causing drum-riding graha, the graha of
            a dead person,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-89">
              <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">grong rgyun gi gdon</foreign>. Literally the
              “continuity” of a dead person. </note> and so forth with the vidyāmantra of Mule
              Lady,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-90"> We emend here and below to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shugs ’gro ma </foreign>from <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shugs sgrol ma</foreign> on the basis of TLR, which reads<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote"> shugs ’gro byams ma</foreign>.
            </note> since these are due to the grahī Unmadā.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-91"> We emend here to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">smyo byed gdon yin pas na</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">smyo byed gdon du za ba yin pas na</foreign>, following a structure that repeats
              itself in the subsequent passages, in which illnesses or problems are attributed to
              one of the grahīs described in the first part of this text (using the same grammatical
              pattern: X <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gyi gdon yin
              pas</foreign>…).</note> Recite the vidyāmantra and stab with the dagger. <ref cRef="F.139.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-289"/>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-92"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="30">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ a ka ra pra ma ni bhyaḥ phaṭ | śa
              tu ma ki li ki la ya huṃ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-93"/>
          <lg tid="31">
            <l>Appearing as a black woman</l>
            <l>Who sullies the yogin’s eyes</l>
            <l>Is the grahī Black Obscurer.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-94"> This
                translation follows TLR in reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sgrib
                  byed nag mo</foreign>, which better fits the description in the verse and is one
                of the grahīs mentioned at the beginning of the text. D, and all other versions of
                  <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Play of the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title>, read
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sgrol byed nag mo</foreign>, “Black
                Liberator.”</note>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-95"/>
          <p tid="32">Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the ascetic Lekden and stab
            with the dagger of the preeminent goddess Mule Lady. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-96"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="33">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarva pra ma ni bhyaḥ phaṭ | ro ti
              baṃ ki li ki la ya hūṁ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-97"/>
          <p tid="34">If someone is afflicted by a latent brain disease or an illness where their
            hands and feet are burning, this is due to the graha Black Bhūta. Therefore, eliminate
            him with the vidyāmantra of the powerful Great Glorious One and stab with the dagger of
            the great Mule Lady.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-98"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="35">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ja lar ye bhyaḥ phaṭ | pra ma ki li
              ki la ya hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-99"/>
          <p tid="36">If someone feels heavy or is afflicted by illness, or has an illness involving
            dullness, sleepiness, or forgetfulness, this is due to the grahī Black Defeater.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-100"> Here we emend to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phung byed nag mo</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bud med nag mo</foreign> following the name and sequential position of this grahī
              in the initial list of eighteen primary emanations. Most, though not all, of the
              eighteen emanations appear in order in this section of the text.</note> Therefore,
            eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the Victory Bringer and stab with the dagger of
            Madhukara. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-101"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="37">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ru tra ya na vyi śa bhyaḥ phaṭ | ka
              pa la ki li ki la ya phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-102"/>
          <p tid="38">If nothing that one does ever works out and one’s actions do not achieve their
            desired ends, this is due to the grahī Majestic Seer. Therefore eliminate her with the
            vidyāmantra of Skull Holder and stab with the dagger of Naked Mendicant.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-103"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="39">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ca ya ma me bhyaḥ phaṭ | ro ti pa ma
              ki li ki la ya hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-104"/>
          <p tid="40">If the yogin is afflicted by an illness that causes his mind to be unstable,
            unsteady, and emotional,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-105">
              <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">phya phya</foreign>. Translation
              tentative.</note> this is due to the grahī Black Rākṣasī. Therefore, eliminate her
            with the vidyāmantra of Vajrapāṇi and stab with the dagger of the protector Indra.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-106"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="41">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rakṣa ya ni bhyaḥ phaṭ | du ni rākṣa
              ki li ki la ya hūṁ drūṁ |</foreign> May whatever is unpleasing to the mind
              dissipate!<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-107">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sems la mi dga’ phya phya</foreign>. Translation tentative.</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-108"/>
          <p tid="42">An illness that involves increased wind is due to the grahī Black Vāyu.
            Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the Seven Mothers and stab with the
            dagger of the Four Sisters. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-109"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="43">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ha sa ya ni ra re bhyaḥ phaṭ | du ya
              ka sa ya ni ki li ki la ya hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-110"/>
          <p tid="44">If someone is afflicted by an illness that makes them angry, furious,
            talkative, and enraged, and their arms and legs move or cramp a lot,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-111"> Translation tentative. The Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rkang lag bya btsag mang po</foreign>, the meaning of
              which is unclear. In TLR the corresponding line reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rkang lag brkyang bskum bya smyang byed</foreign>, which roughly means,
              “their legs and arms extend, retract, and stretch out.” This suggests a condition such
              as spasms. </note> this is due to the grahī<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-112"> This reading follows K, Q, and Y in reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dbang ldan nag mo</foreign>; D reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dbang ldan nag po</foreign>. </note> Black Indrāṇī.
            Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the preeminent Indra and stab with the
            wrathful dagger of the Wrathful One from the family. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-113"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="45">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">de va lo yā bhyaḥ phaṭ | de va ki li
              ki li ya hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-114"/>
          <lg tid="46">
            <l>Being unable to sleep in the middle of the night, <ref cRef="F.140.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-290"/>
                        </l>
            <l>The occurrence of powerful sorcery, </l>
            <l>And bees appearing as pigs</l>
            <l>Are due to the grahī Black Revatī. </l>
            <l>Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the preeminent Great Glorious One </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of the Wrathful One from the family.</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-115"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="47">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">de va ki li ki la yā bhyaḥ phaṭ | de
              va dra ti ki li ki la ya hūṁ hūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-116"/>
          <p tid="48">If one is afflicted by an illness where their limbs are burning and painful,
            or if one has little appetite and feels nauseous, this is due to the grahī Black Yamā.
            Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of Mañjuśrī Yamāntaka and stab with the
            dagger of the Splendorous Invincible One.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-117"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="49">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ya ma rā ja hriḥ ṣṭi bi kri kri nad
              ma hā hūṁ drūṁ | ca ya raṃ ba ni ki li ki la ya bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-118"/>
          <lg tid="50">
            <l>When half the body becomes withered or paralyzed, </l>
            <l>When crippled, when the body is bruised and tender, </l>
            <l>Or the eyes turn dark and itchy, </l>
            <l>This is leprosy caused by sorcery </l>
            <l>And is due to the grahī Black Nāgiṇī. </l>
            <l>Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of Garuḍa He </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of the Old Seer. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-119"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="51">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nā ga le ya hūṁ hūṁ | ca ya ka bhyaḥ
              phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-120"/>
          <p tid="52">If someone is afflicted by an illness that causes their mind to feel unstable
            and vacuous, to feel pressure on their torso, experience a sense of futility, or feel as
            if their teeth are falling out, this is due to the grahī Black Yakṣiṇī.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-121"> We emend to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gnod
                sbyin nag mo</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gnod sbyin nag
                po</foreign>, given the name and sequential position of this grahī (not graha) given
              in the initial list of eighteen primary emanations. Not all of the eighteen emanations
              appear in order in this section of the text, but many of them do.</note> Therefore,
            eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of Vaiśravaṇa and stab with the dagger of the
            Emanatress. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-122"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="53">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ti ti ma ye bhyaḥ phaṭ | ku ku rā ja
              ye hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-123"/>
          <p tid="54">If someone is afflicted with skin disease, rashes, and their body itches, this
            is due to the grahī Black Revatī Protectress Vetālī. Therefore, eliminate her with the
            vidyāmantra of unimpeded Yama and stab with the dagger of the Red Lady of Desire. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-124"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="55">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">va ren he ya hūṁ hūṁ | ku ma la gur
              dang bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-125"/>
          <p tid="56">If someone is afflicted by an illness of the blood, feels heavy, cannot see
            far, or has an unstable and vacuous mind, this is due to the grahī Garuḍa-Winged Revatī.
            Therefore, eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the powerful Great Glorious One and
            stab with the dagger of blazing wrathful Hūṁchen. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-126"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="57">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">du ya kula hūṁ phaṭ | ma ma ku du ye
              bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-127"/>
          <p tid="58">If someone is afflicted by an illness that cripples their right arm <ref cRef="F.140.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-291"/> or causes rib pain, this is
            due to the grahī Revatī Who Extends One Hand. Therefore, eliminate her with the
            vidyāmantra of Expanse of Wrath and stab with the dagger of the Powerful Red Lady. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-128"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="59">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ma ma ri haya hūṁ hūṁ | ka pa la ya
              he bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-129"/>
          <p tid="60">If someone feels intoxicated, hemorrhages blood, and sees all sorts of forms
            appear before their eyes, this is due to the grahī One-Toothed One-Eyed Revatī.
            Therefore, eliminate her with the counteractive vidyāmantra of Lekden and stab with the
            dagger of the Principal Ascetic. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-130"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="61">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rākṣa se hūṁ drūṁ | rākṣa laṁ ki la
              ye bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-131"/>
          <p tid="62">As for the twelve grahīs of the lesser demons—<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-132"> According to Nebesky-Wojkowitz (1975, pp. 277 and 315),
              the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma bdud</foreign> are a Tibetan class of
              “lesser” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign>) demons, who are
              distinct from the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ya bdud</foreign>, “greater
              demons.” On the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma bdud</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ya bdud</foreign>, see also Blondeau 2009, pp. 204, n.
              13 and pp. 231–34.</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-133"/>
          <lg tid="63">
            <l>Inside a white silken tent</l>
            <l>Is the magical emanation of the sovereign woman</l>
            <l>Arisen from the White Inauspicious Lady,</l>
            <l>The powerful lady ornamented with gold and turquoise,</l>
            <l>The grahī Wisdom Samantabhadrī.</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-134"/>
          <p tid="64">Eliminate untimely rain, strife, frost, and hail caused by sorcery with the
            dharmadhātu vidyāmantra and stab with the dagger of samādhi. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-135"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="65">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ni dhar ma dhā tu sa ma ya hūṁ druṁ |
              ka ma la ca ga ye sa ma ye bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-136"/>
          <lg tid="66">
            <l>The Lady who rules the second turquoise tent</l>
            <l>Is the great and powerful Dark Blue Lady. </l>
            <l>Riding an ox, mule,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-137"> This translation
                follows TLR in reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’dre’u</foreign>; D
                reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dre</foreign>. </note> or horse.</l>
            <l>She brings disaster upon worldly yogas. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-138"/>
          <p tid="67">Eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of the great and powerful Lady and stab
            with the dagger of the great all-pervasive Lady.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-139"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="68">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">a ra li bhyaḥ phaṭ | ra du hūṁ
              druṁ || </foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-140"/>
          <lg tid="69">
            <l>The Lady who rules the third coral tent </l>
            <l>Is the ruler of the heart inside the tent. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-141"/>
          <p tid="70">Eliminate her with the offering vidyāmantra of the yellow tent and stab with
            the dagger of the Principal Ascetic.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-142"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="71">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tiṣṭa tiṣṭa ni bhyaḥ phaṭ | va pā ma
              hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-143"/>
          <p tid="72">The Lady who rules the fourth golden tent rules over all illnesses of the
            throat and ulcers. Eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of Mañjuśrī Roten<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-144">
              <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’jam dpal ro tan</foreign>. The meaning of
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ro tan</foreign> is ambiguous, and so has
              simply been phoneticized here. </note> and stab with the dagger of the Splendorous
            Invincible One. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-145"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="73">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ro ro baṁ hūṃ druṃ | ku ku ye bhyaḥ
              phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-146"/>
          <lg tid="74">
            <l>The Lady who rules the fifth dark blue tent </l>
            <l>Is the rending spike woman. </l>
            <l>Eliminate bladder and internal diseases, </l>
            <l>Blood diseases, and abscesses </l>
            <l>With the vidyāmantra of playful Yama, </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of the Playful Invincible One. <ref cRef="F.141.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-292"/>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-147"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="75">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ya go le hūṁ drūṁ | phra do phra ye
              bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-148"/>
          <lg tid="76">
            <l>The Lady who rules the sixth tent of the inconceivably large field </l>
            <l>Is the goddess of symptoms such as</l>
            <l>Vomiting blood from the mouth,</l>
            <l>The feeling of fever in the body, </l>
            <l>And contraction of the limbs. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-149"/>
          <p tid="77">Eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of compassionate Yama and stab with the
            dagger of attachment-inducing Yama. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-150"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="78">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ca ga ya baṁ bhyaḥ phaṭ | gur la de
              hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-151"/>
          <lg tid="79">
            <l>Inside the seventh oxen-hair tent </l>
            <l>Is the Mother who strikes those who speak falsely.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-152">
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khram la ’debs pa.</foreign> This phrase can
                be used to refer to suppressing those who harm the Dharma.</note>
            </l>
            <l>She inflicts illness where blood comes from the mouth, </l>
            <l>Kindles fever in the body like a great fire, </l>
            <l>And acts while brandishing a copper knife. </l>
            <l>Eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of Blazing Great Garuḍa </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of the Eliminator of Poison. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-153"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="80">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">da he ya ya hūṁ dṛūṁ | me ca ye bhyaḥ
              phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-154"/>
          <lg tid="81">
            <l>Inside the eighth elephant tent, </l>
            <l>The woman who rides a mule</l>
            <l>Rules over ulcers and lung and foot diseases. </l>
            <l>Eliminate her with the heart vidyāmantra of Yama </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of Powerful Blazing Lady.</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-155"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="82">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ca kra ki li ki la ye bhyaḥ phaṭ | ā
              ko laṁ hūṁ drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-156"/>
          <p tid="83">Inside the multicolored ninth leather tent— </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-157"/>
          <lg tid="84">
            <l>Are the nine preeminent <distinct>Dabren</distinct>
                            <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-158">
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rda bran</foreign>. The meaning of this term
                could not be determined. </note> Medicine Ladies,</l>
            <l>Who cause hail, frost, spell-caused illness, </l>
            <l>Personal ruin, house collapse, </l>
            <l>Swelling, nasal irritation, </l>
            <l>And illnesses of the nine black ones. </l>
            <l>Therefore, eliminate them with the vidyāmantra of the preeminent Lady of the Expanse </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of the Conqueror of Saṃsāra.</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-159"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="85">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ku ma la ya hūṁ drūṁ | śa ma ma ye
              bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-160"/>
          <p tid="86">Inside the dark blue tenth tent—</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-161"/>
          <lg tid="87">
            <l>Are the ten Rulers of the Tent, </l>
            <l>Who cause leprosy and itchy lesions, </l>
            <l>Make poison, cause conflict, </l>
            <l>And kill with knives. </l>
            <l>Eliminate them with the vidyāmantra of wrathful Yaśodharā </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of the All-Pervasive Mother. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-162"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="88">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">a ko śa me ra ra hūṁ drūṁ | pra du le
              bhyaḥ phaṭ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-163"/>
          <p tid="89">Inside the eleventh tent of the secret lotus—</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-164"/>
          <lg tid="90">
            <l>Is the powerful eleventh tent-ruling Lady. </l>
            <l>A great all-pervasive lady, powerful in form, </l>
            <l>She obstructs the passage of rainfall in the world by means of the planets </l>
            <l>And does not grant rainfall. </l>
            <l>Eliminate her with the vidyāmantra of Great Glorious Expanse </l>
            <l>And stab with the dagger of beautiful Gāndhārī. <ref cRef="F.141.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-293"/>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-165"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="91">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">a ko muna bhyaḥ phaṭ | ca ye ma hūṁ
              drūṁ ||</foreign>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-166"/>
          <p tid="92">Inside the camphor crystal twelfth tent—</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-167"/>
          <lg tid="93">
            <l>Is the mother of space, the sole mother Mukhale. </l>
            <l>The twelve and the fourteen are complete in you. </l>
            <l>In order to heal all beings everywhere </l>
            <l>You reside in the essence of nectar. </l>
            <l>You hold the heart-stalk of knowledge in your hand </l>
            <l>And illuminate all of existence in a single moment.</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-168"/>
          <lg tid="94">
            <l>Within the heart-maṇḍala of blazing clarity, the four māras <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śantiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                            <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-169"> This
                and the remaining mantras mix Tibetan words with transliterations of Sanskrit terms.
                The Sanskrit in each case means “pacify <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">svāhā</foreign>!” </note>
            </l>
            <l>The gongpo yak of the mountain peak<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-170">
                Emending <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ri tshe</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ri rtse</foreign>.</note>
              <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>The twelve male māras <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>The thirteen female mārās <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā
              hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>The Lord of Order who Carries a White Staff <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru
                svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>White Sky Terang <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>Colorful Terang of Intermediate Space <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā
                hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>Black Earth Terang <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>Red grahas, tsen, and red gongpo in the northeastern direction <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>Lady who Rules Epidemic and Illness <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā
                hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
            <l>Medicinal and local deities<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-171">
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yul sa</foreign>. On the equivalence of the
                terms <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yul sa</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yul lha</foreign> (local deity), see Karmay 1996, p.
                393. </note>
              <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntiṃ ku ru svā hā ||</mantra>
                        </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-172"/>
          <p tid="95">If someone clearly reads aloud three times this fundamentally beneficial
            dhāraṇī-sūtra of the Glorious Black Goddess Uṣṇīṣa that averts grahas and swears to
            perform a difficult action, they will achieve whatever they wish. If one makes five
            oblations inside a leather cup and performs the ritual according to the text, then they
            will achieve whatever they wish. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-173"/>
          <p tid="96">If someone properly upholds this graha-averting ritual for the glorious
            goddess Uṣṇīṣa, recites it again and again, follows the ritual correctly, and carries
            oblations to a great river or the top of a high mountain, then when engaged in a great
            conflict they will be victorious in battle. When performing hostile rites, direct this
            toward the heart of the enemy. If this is directed to the Rulers of the Nine Tents, the
            enemy will be defeated and destroyed. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-174"/>
          <trailer tid="97">This completes “<title xml:lang="en">The Glorious Tantra of the Play of
              the Goddess Uṣṇīṣā</title>.”</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-notes">
        <head type="notes" tid="98">Notes</head>
        <list type="abbreviations">
          <head tid="99">Abbreviations</head>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-175">
                        <abbr>C</abbr>
                        <expan> Choné</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-176">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-177">
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>Lithang</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-178">
                        <abbr>K</abbr>
                        <expan>Peking 1684/1692</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-179">
                        <abbr>Q</abbr>
                        <expan>Peking 1737
            (Qianlong)</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-180">
                        <abbr>Y</abbr>
                        <expan>Yongle</expan>
                    </item>
          <item xml:id="UT22084-101-042-181">
                        <abbr>TLR</abbr>
                        <expan>
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha mo
                nag mo chen mo rol par byed pa’i gtsug tor zhes bya ba’i
            gzungs</title>
                        </expan>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="listBibl" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-listBibl">
        <head type="listBibl" tid="100">Bibliography</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-listBibl-1">
          <head type="section" tid="102">Source Texts</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-182">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo gtsug tor rol pa’i
              tan+tra</title>. Toh 987, Degé Kangyur, vol. 101 (gzungs ’dus, waM), folios
            138.b–141.b.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-183">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo gtsug tor rol pa’i
              tan+tra</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung
            go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
            Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung
            go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 98,
            pp. 436–45.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-184">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo gtsug tor rol pa’i
              tan+tra</title>. K 612. Peking (Qianlong) Kangyur, vol. 25 (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ya</foreign>), folios 146.a–149.b.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-185">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha mo nag mo chen mo rol par
              byed pa’i gtsug tor zhes bya ba’i gzungs</title> in <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo rgyud
              gsungs rab rgya mtsho’i snying po gces par btus pa ’dod ’byung nor bu’i phreng ba,
              gnyis pa mdo phran skor</title>, vol. 1, pp. 1279–1300. Compiled by Jonang Tāranātha.
            Delhi: Dkon mchog lha bris, 1994.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-186">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha mo nag mo chen mo rol par
              byed pa’i gtsug tor zhes bya ba’i gzungs</title> in <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe
              rnying rtsa chen bris ma’i skor phyogs bsdus</title>, vol. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chi</foreign> (36), W2PD19899.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-187">
                        <ref target="https://idp.bl.uk/collection/86623249EB9143EAB175BF82E854A410/?return=%2Fcollection%2F%3Fterm%3DIOL%2520Tib%2520J%2520711">IOL Tib J 711</ref>. British Library, London. Accessed through <title xml:lang="en">The International Dunhuang Programme</title>.</bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-listBibl-2">
          <head type="section" tid="103">Other Sources</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-188">84000. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh846.html">The Threefold Invocation
                Ritual</ref>
                        </title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ’dren rgyud gsum pa</title>,
            Toh 846). Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee. Online publication.
            84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2020.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-189">84000. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh846a.html">The Threefold
              Ritual</ref>
                        </title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud gsum pa</title>, Toh 846a).
            Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee. Online publication. 84000:
            Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2020b.</bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-listBibl-3">
          <head type="section" tid="104">Secondary Sources</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-190">Blondeau, Anne-Marie. “Le Réseau des Mille Dieux et
            Démons: Mythes et Classifications.” In <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Studies in Honor of
              Samten Karmay</title>, edited by Françoise Pommaret and Jean-Luc Achard, 199–250.
            Dharamshala: Amnye Machen Institute, 2009. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-191">Dalton, Jacob P. “How Dhāraṇīs WERE Proto-Tantric:
            Liturgies, Ritual Manuals, and the Origins of the Tantras.” In <title xml:lang="en">Tantric Traditions in Transmission and Translation</title>, edited by David Gray and
            Ryan Richard Overbey, 199–229. New York: Oxford University Press, 2016. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-192">Dalton, Jacob and Sam van Schaik, eds. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Tantric Manuscripts from Dunhuang: A Descriptive Catalogue of
              the Stein Collection at the British Library</title>. Brill’s Tibetan Studies Library
            12, Leiden: Brill, 2006. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-193">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang
              ma</title>. Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang, 2003.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-194">Hidas, Gergely. <title xml:lang="en">Powers of
              Protection: The Buddhist Tradition of Spells in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</title> Collections</title>. Beyond Boundaries 9. Boston: de
            Gruyter, 2021.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-195">Karmay, Samten G. “A Comparative Study of the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yul lha</foreign> Cult in Two Areas and its Cosmological
            Aspects.” In <title xml:lang="en">Reflections of the Mountain: Essays on the History and
              Social Meaning of the Mountain Cult in Tibet and the Himalaya</title>, edited by A. M.
            Blondeau and E. Steinkellner, 383–413. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der
            Wissenschaften, 1996.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-196">Lalou, Marcelle. “Les textes bouddhiques au tempes du
            roi Khri-sroṅ-lde-bcan.” <title xml:lang="fr">Journal Asiatique</title> 241 (1953):
            313–53.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-198">Nebesky-Wojkowitz, René de. <title xml:lang="en">Oracles and Demons of Tibet: The Cult and Iconography of the Tibetan Protective
              Deities</title>. Graz: Akademische Druck, 1975. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-199">Negi, J. S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit
              Dictionary</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bod skad legs sbyar gyi tshig mdzod chen
              mo</title>). 16 vols. Sarnath: Dictionary Unit, Central Institute of Higher Tibetan
            Studies, 1993–2005. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-200">Norbu, Namkhai. <title xml:lang="en">Drung, Deu and
              Bön: Narrations, Symbolic Languages and the Bön Tradition in Ancient Tibet</title>.
            Dharamsala: Library of Tibetan Works and Archives, 1995. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-201">Shinohara, Koichi. <title xml:lang="en">Spells, Images,
              and Maṇḍalas: Tracing the Evolution of Esoteric Buddhist Rituals</title>. New York:
            Columbia University Press, 2014. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-202">Skilling, Peter (1992). “The <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Rakṣā</foreign> Literature of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Śrāvakayāna</foreign>.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the Pali Text Society</title>
            16 (1992): 109–83.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-203">Smith, Frederick M. <title xml:lang="en">The Self
              Possessed: Deity and Spirit Possession in South Asian Literature and
              Civilization</title>. New York: Columbia University Press, 2006.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-042-204">Tidwell, Tawni L., Nianggajia, and Fjeld, Heidi E.
            “Chasing <distinct>dön</distinct> spirits in Tibetan medical encounters: Transcultural
            affordances and embodied psychiatry in Amdo, Qinghai.” <title xml:lang="en">Transcultural Psychiatry </title>vol. 60, Issue 5 (2023): 799–818.</bibl>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="glossary" status="excluded" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-glossary">
        <list type="glossary">
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-206">
              <term type="translationMain">grahī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gdon </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གདོན།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">graha</term>
            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A type of female spirit understood to cause illness through
                  possession.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-207">
              <term type="translationMain">vidyāmantra</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rigs sngags </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རིགས་སྔགས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyāmantra</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A type of mantra.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-208">
              <term type="translationMain">bhūta</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’byung po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-210">
              <term type="translationMain">Mother</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ma mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མ་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>Ferocious female deities to which are attributed both
                  dangerous and protective functions. In the Indian tradition, they are often in a
                  set of seven or eight.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-211">
              <term type="translationMain">samādhi</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ting ’dzin</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཏིང་འཛིན།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">ting nge ’dzin</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-212">
              <term type="translationMain">gongpo</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’gong po</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འགོང་པོ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">’gong</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">འགོང་།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A type of Tibetan spirit.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-213">
              <term type="translationMain">terang</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">the</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཐེ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="2">the rang</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="2">ཐེ་རང་།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A type of Tibetan spirit.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-214">
              <term type="translationMain">tsen</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">btsan </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བཙན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A type of Tibetan spirit.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-216">
              <term type="translationMain">Yaśodharā</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">grags ’dzin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གྲགས་འཛིན།</term>
            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yaśodharā</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>Usually the name of Śākyamuni Buddha’s wife. Here the name
                  of a wrathful deity/mantra used to overcome disease-causing spirits. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-217">
              <term type="translationMain">Yama</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gshin rje </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yama</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Lord of Death.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-218">
              <term type="translationMain">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rnam thos </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྣམ་ཐོས།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśravaṇa</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-219">
              <term type="translationMain">Indra</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rgya byin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indra</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-220">
              <term type="translationMain">Vajrapāṇi</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">phyag na rdo rje </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajrapāṇi</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-221">
              <term type="translationMain">Mañjuśrī Yamāntaka</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’jam dpal gshin rje </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mañjuśrī­yamāntaka</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A wrathful form of Mañjuśrī.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-222">
              <term type="translationMain">Lekden</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">legs ldan </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལེགས་ལྡན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity associated with a mantra for protection and
                  healing. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-223">
              <term type="translationMain">Wisdom Samantabhadrī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ye shes kun du bzang mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀུན་དུ་བཟང་མོ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna­samantabhadrī</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>Samantabhadrī is usually the primordial female Buddha,
                  consort of the primordial Buddha Samantabhadra. Her role in this text is somewhat
                  confusing, however, because she seems here to be a type of malevolent spirit,
                  which is very much in contradistinction to her usual role.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-224">
              <term type="translationMain">Gāndhārī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sa ’dzin ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ས་འཛིན་མ།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gāndhārī</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A goddess.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-225">
              <term type="translationMain">Lord of Order who Carries a White Staff</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">skos rje drang dkar </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྐོས་རྗེ་དྲང་དཀར།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity in the Tibetan Bön tradition responsible for
                  maintaining order in the forces of nature. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-226">
              <term type="translationMain">Ekajatī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">e ka dza TI</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཨེ་ཀ་ཛ་ཊཱི།</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ekajatā</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A goddess. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-227">
              <term type="translationMain">Mukhale</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mu kha le </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མུ་ཁ་ལེ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of a powerful Tibetan female spirit. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-228">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Vetālī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ro langs nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རོ་ལངས་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-229">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Piśācī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sha za nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཤ་ཟ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-230">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Unmadā</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">smyo byed nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྨྱོ་བྱེད་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-231">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Obscurer</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sgrib byed nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྒྲིབ་བྱེད་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-232">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Defeater</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">phung byed nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཕུང་བྱེད་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-233">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Seer</term>
            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">drang srong nag mo</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">དྲང་སྲོང་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-234">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Rākṣasī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">srin mo nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྲིན་མོ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-235">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Vāyu</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rlung lha nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རླུང་ལྷ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-236">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Indrāṇī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dbang ldan nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དབང་ལྡན་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-237">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Revatī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-238">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Kumbhāṇḍī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">grul bum nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གྲུལ་བུམ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-239">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Nāginī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">klu mo nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཀླུ་མོ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-240">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Yakṣiṇī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gnod sbyin nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གནོད་སྦྱིན་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-241">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Revatī Protectress Vetālī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru skyong byed ro langs nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་སྐྱོང་བྱེད་རོ་ལངས་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-242">
              <term type="translationMain">Great Revatī the Lion-Faced Defeater</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru chen mo phung byed seng ge’i
                gdong </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ཆེན་མོ་ཕུང་བྱེད་སེང་གེའི་གདོང་།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-243">
              <term type="translationMain">Great Revatī the Garuḍa-Winged Ḍākinī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru chen mo mkha’ ’gro khyung
                gshog ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ཆེན་མོ་མཁའ་འགྲོ་ཁྱུང་གཤོག་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-244">
              <term type="translationMain">Great Revatī Who Extends One Hand</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru chen mo lag gcig nyab pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ཆེན་མོ་ལག་གཅིག་ཉབ་པ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-245">
              <term type="translationMain">One-Toothed One-Eyed Great Revatī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru chen mo so gcig mig gcig ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ཆེན་མོ་སོ་གཅིག་མིག་གཅིག་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-246">
              <term type="translationMain">Donkey-Riding Great Revatī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru chen mo bong zhon ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ཆེན་མོ་བོང་ཞོན་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of one of the eighteen primary emanations of the
                  goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-247">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Vetālī Rākṣasī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ro langs ma srin mo nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རོ་ལངས་མ་སྲིན་མོ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of a grahī. This seems to be another name for the
                  grahī otherwise called Black Vetālī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ro
                    langs nag mo</foreign>), who is identified as one of the eighteen primary
                  emanations of the goddess described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-248">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Bhūta</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">byung po nag po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བྱུང་པོ་ནག་པོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A graha. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-249">
              <term type="translationMain">Great Glorious One</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dpal chen </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དཔལ་ཆེན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is mentioned in this text. This
                  epithet is often applied to Hayagrīva or other wrathful deities.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-250">
              <term type="translationMain">Majestic Seer</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">drang srong gzi can </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དྲང་སྲོང་གཟི་ཅན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A grahī. This seems to be another name for the grahī
                  otherwise called Black Seer (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">drang srong
                    nag mo</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-251">
              <term type="translationMain">Black Yamā</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">ya ma nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཡ་མ་ནག་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A grahī.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-253">
              <term type="translationMain">Emanatress</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sprul byed ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྤྲུལ་བྱེད་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A goddess whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-254">
              <term type="translationMain">Red Lady of Desire</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’dod pa dmar mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འདོད་པ་དམར་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A goddess whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-255">
              <term type="translationMain">Garuḍa-Winged Revatī</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">nam gru khyung gshog ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ནམ་གྲུ་ཁྱུང་གཤོག་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A grahī. This seems to be another name for the grahī
                  otherwise called Great Revatī the Garuda-Winged Ḍākinī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nam gru chen mo mkha’ ’gro khyung gshog ma</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-256">
              <term type="translationMain">Hūṁchen</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">hU~M chen</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཧཱུྃ་ཆེན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A wrathful deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-257">
              <term type="translationMain">Expanse of Wrath</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dbyings kyi khro bo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་ཁྲོ་བོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A wrathful deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the
                  rituals described in this text. An alternative name may be “Great Glorious
                  Expanse” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpal chen dbyings</foreign>).
                </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-258">
              <term type="translationMain">Powerful Red Lady</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dbang mo dmar mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དབང་མོ་དམར་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A goddess whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-259">
              <term type="translationMain">Revatī Who Extends One Hand</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">lag gcig nyab pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ལག་གཅིག་ཉབ་པ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A grahī. This seems to be another name for the grahī
                  otherwise called Great Revatī Who Extends One Hand (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nam gru chen mo lag gcig nyab pa</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-260">
              <term type="translationMain">One-Toothed One-Eyed Revatī </term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">so gcig mig gcig ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སོ་གཅིག་མིག་གཅིག་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A grahī. This seems to be another name for the grahī
                  otherwise called One-Toothed One-Eyed Great Revatī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nam gru chen mo so gcig mig gcig ma</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-261">
              <term type="translationMain">Principal Ascetic</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dka’ thub gtso bo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དཀའ་ཐུབ་གཙོ་བོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-262">
              <term type="translationMain">White Inauspicious Lady</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mi bzang dkar mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མི་བཟང་དཀར་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-263">
              <term type="translationMain">Dark Blue Lady</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mthing ka chen mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མཐིང་ཀ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-264">
              <term type="translationMain">Mañjuśrī Roten</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’jam dpal ro tan </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འཇམ་དཔལ་རོ་ཏན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-265">
              <term type="translationMain">Thirteen Ladies of the Tent</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gur bdag bcu gsum</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">གུར་བདག་བཅུ་གསུམ།</term>
            <term type="translationAlternative">thirteen Ladies of the Tent</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A group of thirteen ladies who rule tents and are
                  identified as subsidiary great heart emanations of the goddess described in this
                  text. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-296">
              <term type="translationMain">Ten Rulers of the Tent </term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">gur la dbang bcu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">གུར་ལ་དབང་བཅུ།</term>
            <term type="translationAlternative">ten Rulers of the Tent</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A set of ten deities who cause disease and inflict harm.
                  They possibly overlap with the thirteen Ladies of the Tent.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-266">
              <term type="translationMain">Mule Lady</term>
            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">shugs ’gro ma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">ཤུགས་འགྲོ་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A goddess. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-267">
              <term type="translationMain">Naked Mendicant</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dge sbyong gcer bu </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དགེ་སྦྱོང་གཅེར་བུ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-268">
              <term type="translationMain">Madhukara</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sbrang rtsir byed pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྦྲང་རྩིར་བྱེད་པ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text. The word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">madhukara</foreign>
                  literally means “honey-maker” and the term can also refer to a bee. </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-269">
              <term type="translationMain">Splendorous Invincible One</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mi pham mdzes pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མི་ཕམ་མཛེས་པ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-270">
              <term type="translationMain">Skull Holder</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">thod pa can </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཐོད་པ་ཅན།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-271">
              <term type="translationMain">Garuḍa He</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">bya khyung he </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">བྱ་ཁྱུང་ཧེ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-272">
              <term type="translationMain">Playful Invincible One</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">mi pham rol ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">མི་ཕམ་རོལ་བ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-273">
              <term type="translationMain">Eliminator of Poison</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dug chen tshar gcod </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དུག་ཆེན་ཚར་གཅོད།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-274">
              <term type="translationMain">Blazing Great Garuḍa</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">khyung chen ’bar ba </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཁྱུང་ཆེན་འབར་བ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-275">
              <term type="translationMain">Powerful Blazing Lady</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’bar ma dbang </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">འབར་མ་དབང་།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-276">
              <term type="translationMain">Nine Preeminent Dabren Medicine Ladies</term>
            <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rda bran sman gyi gtso mo dgu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">རྡ་བྲན་སྨན་གྱི་གཙོ་མོ་དགུ</term>
              <term type="translationAlternative">Medicine Ladies</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A group of deities or spirits who cause illness.
                </p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-277">
              <term type="translationMain">Lady of the Expanse</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dbyings kyi gtso mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་གཙོ་མོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-278">
              <term type="translationMain">Conqueror of Saṃsāra</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">’khor ba rab ’joms </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1" status="verified">འཁོར་བ་རབ་འཇོམས།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-279">
              <term type="translationMain">All-Pervasive Mother</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">khyab pa ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཁྱབ་པ་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose dagger is employed in the rituals described
                  in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-280">
              <term type="translationMain">Great Glorious Expanse</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">dpal chen dbyings </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">དཔལ་ཆེན་དབྱིངས།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text. This may be the same deity referred to as Expanse of Wrath
                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbyings kyi khro
                bo</foreign>).</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-281">
              <term type="translationMain">Victory Bringer</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">rgyal bar byed pa </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">རྒྱལ་བར་བྱེད་པ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>A deity whose vidyāmantra is employed in the rituals
                  described in this text.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-282">
              <term type="translationMain">four sisters</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">sring mo bzhi </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">སྲིང་མོ་བཞི།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>In Indic contexts, this is typically a reference to Jayā,
                  Vijayā, Ajitā, and Aparājitā, a group of female deities who, along with their
                  brother Tumburu (an aspect of Śiva), are the focal point of a prominent cult in
                  the early Śaiva tantric tradition. They are frequently included in Buddhist
                  literature among classes of malevolent spirits.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-284">
              <term type="translationMain">triple city</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">grong khyer sum brtsegs</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">གྲོང་ཁྱེར་སུམ་བརྩེགས།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>An aspect of Śaiva mythology that was assimilated into the
                  Buddhist tradition, the “triple city” was a city of asuras built by the asura
                  architect Maya. It consisted of three levels that extended from the underworld,
                  through the earth, and up to the heavens. Brahmā blessed Tripura so that it could
                  only be destroyed by a single arrow, making it essentially indestructible.
                  However, when the asuras displeased Śiva by resuming their war with the devas, he
                  fired a divine arrow that pierced all three levels of the city, reducing them to
                  ash.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="text" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-286">
              <term type="translationMain">Tshalpa Kangyur</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">tshal pa bka’ ’gyur</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཚལ་པ་བཀའ་འགྱུར།</term>
              <term type="translationAlternative">Tshalpa</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>An edition of the Kangyur produced at Gungthang (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gung thang</foreign>) monastery in central Tibet
                  from 1347–51 under the sponsorship of the local ruler, Tshalpa Künga Dorje
                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshal pa kun dga’ rdo rje</foreign>,
                  1309–64), providing the basis for a branch of subsequent Kangyur
                editions.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="text" xml:id="UT22084-101-042-287">
              <term type="translationMain">Thempangma Kangyur</term>
              <term status="verified" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" n="1">them spangs ma bka’ ’gyur</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" n="1">ཐེམ་སྤངས་མ་བཀའ་འགྱུར།</term>
              <term type="translationAlternative">Thempangma</term>
              <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of the two textual lineages of the Kangyur. It
                  originated from a manuscript produced at Gyantsé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyal rtse</foreign>) in 1431.</p>
                            </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>