<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <!--<title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">[Note: Degé, Yongle, and Peking have gaṇu-ālaṃkārāgra°]</title>-->
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdong po rgyan gyi mchog gi gzungs</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྡོང་པོ་རྒྱན་གྱི་མཆོག་གི་གཟུངས།</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Supreme Stem Ornament</title>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇyālaṃkārāgra­dhāraṇī</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྡོང་པོ་རྒྱན་གྱི་མཆོག་ཅེས་བྱ་བའི་གཟུངས།</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sdong po rgyan gyi mchog ces bya ba’i
          gzungs</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Dhāraṇī “The Supreme Stem Ornament”</title>
        <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­gaṇyālaṃkārāgranāma­dhāraṇī</title>
        <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
        <author role="translatorMain" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-58">Translated by Catherine Dalton
          under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
        <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-59">Catherine Dalton</author>
        <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-60">John Canti</editor>
        <editor role="copyEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-61">Dawn Collins</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-62">Martina Cotter</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-63">George FitzHerbert</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.4 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
          initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them
          available to everyone. </publisher>
        <availability status="2.a">
          <licence>
            <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
            <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND
              (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or
              printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage
              or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno xml:id="UT22084-101-122"/>
        <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that
          these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
        <date>2023-07-21</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl key="toh1066" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 1066</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 101 (gzungs ’dus, waṃ), folios 236.a–236.b </biblScope>
          <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="2">
            <volume number="102" start-page="469" end-page="470"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20568" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12830" work="W22084"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <notesStmt/>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-13T13:01:17.516Z" type="translation-status" status="3" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-64">
          <desc>3</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-13T13:01:17.516Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-65">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-13T13:01:41.037Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-66">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-25T11:55:02.526Z" type="translation-status" status="2.h" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-67">
          <desc>2.h</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-04-25T11:55:02.526Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-68">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-03-16T08:43:20.081Z" type="translation-status" status="2.f" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-69">
          <desc>2.f</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-03-16T08:43:20.081Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.5" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-70">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-19T13:15:03.462Z" type="translation-status" status="2.d" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-71">
          <desc>2.d</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-19T13:15:03.462Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.6" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-72">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-19T13:15:47.399Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.7" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-73">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-22T14:07:41.461Z" type="translation-status" status="2.c" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-74">
          <desc>2.c</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-06-22T14:07:41.461Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.8" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-75">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-07-19T12:56:14.241Z" type="translation-status" status="2.a" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-76">
          <desc>2.a</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-07-19T12:56:14.241Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.9" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-77">
          <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-07-19T12:57:11.362Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.10" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-78">
          <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-79">
          <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
        </change>
        <change who="#john" when="2023-08-15T15:58:25.078Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-80">
          <desc>Reviewed and edited as communicated; not yet ready for publication.</desc>
        </change>
                <change who="#john" when="2023-08-18T09:24:26.512Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-87">
                    <desc>A few more edits.</desc>
                </change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!--Note the "Contents" outline from the Word DOCX has not been included in the script. If the 
                    Outline to the text is quite complex, it is recommended that you paste the outlined contents from the DOCX here as a comment for
                    markup's reference. The actual table of contents will be generated in the Reading Room by the parser.-->
    <front>
      <div type="summary">
        <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-1"/>
        <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Supreme Stem Ornament</title> is a short
          work that includes several prayers for protection, each of which is followed by an
          essence-mantra.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgment">
        <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-2"/>
        <p tid="4">This text was translated by Catherine Dalton and edited by the 84000 editorial
          team.</p>
        <p tid="5">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
          Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
        <lb/>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction">
        <head type="introduction" tid="8">Introduction</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-introduction-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-6"/>
          <p tid="10">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Supreme Stem Ornament</title> is a
            short text that includes several prayers for protection, each of which is followed by an
            essence-mantra (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">hṛdaya</foreign>). The prayers
            pay homage to the Three Jewels and a number of deities, requesting protection from
            astrologically inauspicious years, days, times, conjunctions, and the like, as well as
            from ghosts, bad dreams, malevolent spirits, enemies, and ill health. The final prayer
            requests protection from broken vows and samayas. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-7"/>
          <p tid="11">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Supreme Stem Ornament</title> does not
            appear to be extant in Sanskrit or in Chinese. It lacks a translator’s colophon and does
            not appear either in the Denkarma or the Phangthangma imperial catalogs, or among the
            manuscripts found in Dunhuang. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-8"/>
          <p tid="12">It is included in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs section of the Degé Kangyur and
            other Tshalpa lineage Kangyurs that have a separate Compendium of Dhāraṇīs section, and
            in the equivalent part of the Tantra section in those that do not label it as such,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-9"> An explicitly named Compendium of Dhāraṇīs
              section is found in the Degé and Urga Kangyurs as well as in the peripheral Kangyurs
              of the Tshalpa lineage (Dodedrak, Phajoding, and Ragya). In contrast, the Berlin,
              Choné, Lithang, and Peking Qianlong Kangyurs include the same collection of dhāraṇīs
              in a separate part of their Tantra sections that has no distinct label. With or
              without the label, these collections of dhāraṇīs contain many duplicates of texts also
              found in the General Sūtra or Tantra sections, and in the latter group of Kangyurs
              many dhāraṇī texts therefore appear twice in different parts of the Tantra section.
            </note> but is not included in any Thempangma lineage Kangyurs. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-10"/>
          <p tid="13">Notably, the dhāraṇī is one of only twelve works in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs
            section that is not duplicated in other sections of the Kangyur. It therefore appears
            that these twelve texts found their way into the Tshalpa lineage Kangyurs specifically
            because they were included in a Compendium of Dhāraṇīs that had been compiled on the
            basis of earlier collections of dhāraṇīs and associated ritual texts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-11"> The opening lines of the table of contents (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dkar chag</foreign>) of an independent dhāraṇī
              collection printed in Beijing in 1731, found in the Library of the Hungarian Academy
              of Sciences in Budapest and transcribed by Orosz, identify the source of all such
              dhāraṇī collections as the extracanonical collection edited by Tāranātha (Orosz 2010,
              pp. 67 and 100). This mention is also noted by Hidas 2021, p. 7, n. 56.</note> These
            collections, known in Sanskrit as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</foreign>, circulated throughout South Asia and Tibet—including in
            Dunhuang—as extracanonical dhāraṇī collections.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-12"> See J. Dalton 2016 and J. Dalton and S. van Schaik 2006
              on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</title> collections preserved in
              Dunhuang, which, like the canonical collection, contain praises and prayers as well as
              dhāraṇīs. See Hidas 2021 for the catalogs of eighteen <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</title> collections suviving in Sanskrit. </note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-13"/>
          <p tid="14">There are several factors that suggest the possibility (though it is by no
            means a certainty) that this particular work may have been translated into Tibetan from
            Chinese, rather than from Sanskrit. The first is a reference to an inauspicious
            divination result specific to a Chinese style of divination.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-14"> This is the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bdud gcod</foreign>. See the note on this term in the translation below for more
              details. </note> But there are other factors, as well: the work’s immediate proximity
            in the Kangyur to a text that was certainly translated from Chinese (Toh 1067)<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh1067.html"/>, the absence
            of a translator’s colophon, the incorrect/incoherent Sanskrit title given at the
            beginning of all of extant versions of the work, as well as the presence of at least one
            feature indicative of the older “Chinese” translation lexicon and style described by
            Stein (i.e., the vocabulary and style used to translate Buddhist texts from a variety of
            languages, including Chinese, prior to the lexical standardization imposed by the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> in 814 <hi rend="small-caps">CE</hi>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-15"> This feature is the spelling of the
              terminating particle at the end of the work: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rdzogs sho</foreign> rather than the later standard <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rdzogs so</foreign>. See Stein 2010, pp. 15–16. For further details on
              these two distinctive lexicons see Stein’s <title xml:lang="la">Tibetica
                Antiqua</title>, especially the chapter on “The Two Vocabularies in the Dunhuang
              Manuscripts.” We would also note the presence in our text of the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men </foreign>to refer to a sort of malevolent
              female spirit. This term also occurs in other manuscripts from Dunhuang that use the
              older vocabulary. See Stein 2010, p.54. In the context of one such manuscript, Stein
              translates <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’phra men ma</foreign> it as
              “witch-goddess,” and notes an association with “Bon and Yol.” We have rendered the
              term in the present text as “malevolent female spirits,” though we do think that
              Stein’s translation captures its intended sense. This term was also <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men ma </foreign>was also used to translate the
              Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ḍākinī</foreign>, usually in the sense
              of ḍākinīs as malevolent female entities, not as the “wisdom ḍākinīs” found in the
              higher tantras, where the term is usually translated as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkha’ ’gro </foreign>(<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign>). See also the note to this term below in the translation and the
              glossary entry on <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men ma </foreign>for
              further details. </note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-16"/>
          <p tid="15">The Sanskrit title and its variants do not seem to match the Tibetan title in
            meaning, and the relationship between the title in either language and the contents of
            the text remains puzzling. The transliterated Sanskrit title in the Degé and most
            Kangyurs reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ga Nu a laM ka ra a
            gra</foreign>, while the Yongle and Qianlong Kangyurs have the slightly more plausible
            variant <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ga Nya</foreign> in place of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ga Nu</foreign>. 
            The Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gaṇ</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gaṇya</foreign> 
            (“calculate” or “compute”) might conceivably relate to the theme of
            astrology present in the text, or refer to the “metrical” lines of verse that it
            contains, but both possibilities are quite unlikely. The Tibetan title, even by itself 
            without reference to the Sanskrit, is difficult to account for, as there is no mention of a “tree” or “stem” (the most
            literal meaning of the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sdong
            po</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇḍa</foreign>) in the text itself.
            Elsewhere in the Kangyur the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sdong pos
              brgyan pa</foreign> is found in the chapter colophon of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title> (the final chapter of the 
            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka­sūtra</title>, Toh 44-45) as one of several versions of that text’s
              title,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-18">See Roberts, Peter Alan. trans.,
                <title xml:lang="en">
                                <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh44-45.html">The Stem Array</ref>
                            </title>, Toh 44-45 (84000: Translating the Words of the
              Buddha, 2021).</note> but there is no obvious connection between this dhāraṇī and the
            themes of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-19">It therefore seems unlikely that this dhāraṇī could have
              been considered a condensed essence or other adjunct of that influential text—as one
              finds with other dhāraṇīs that have an explicit relationship to sūtras, a genre found
              in the groups Toh 583–589 and Toh 939–945. Indeed, such a possibility is made even
              less likely by the existence of another dhāraṇī that fulfills the “condensed essence”
              function, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdong po bkod pa’i snying po</title>, Toh 941<ref rend="pending" target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh941.html"/>.</note>
            On the one hand, to assume that the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdong po</foreign>
            translates the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇḍa</foreign>, but in its less literal
            meaning of “chief” or “excellent,” could corroborate the
            interpretation of the dhāraṇī being a supreme ornament. On the other hand, if instead of
              <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇḍa-</foreign> one takes the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇya-</foreign> 
            of the Sanskrit title found in the Yongle and Qianlong—<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ga Nya a laM ka ra a gra</foreign> 
            (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇyālaṃkārāgra</foreign>)—as part of a back-reconstruction from the Tibetan that
            could reasonably be rearranged with the word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">agra</foreign> (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog</foreign>) 
            at the beginning, the resulting <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">agragaṇyālaṃkāra</foreign> would make sense. 
            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Agragaṇya</foreign>, literally “to be counted as the foremost,”
            simply means “best,” “principal,” or “supreme,” and the title <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">agragaṇyālaṃkāra­dhāraṇī</foreign> 
            would thus mean “The Dhāraṇī that is a Supreme
            Ornament.” Overall, however, we can only remain circumspect about how the titles of this
            text as they have been preserved in different Kangyurs can be understood.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-20"/>
          <p tid="16">The present English translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the
              Supreme Stem Ornament</title> was made from the Tibetan as found in the Degé Kangyur
            recension of the work, in consultation with the notes in the <title xml:lang="en">Comparative Edition</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe sdur ma</title>). </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="translation">
        <head type="translation"> The Translation </head>
        <head type="titleHon" tid="45">The Noble</head>
        <head type="titleMain" tid="46">Dhāraṇī of the Supreme Stem Ornament</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-section-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-24"/>
          <p tid="23">
                        <ref cRef="F.236.a" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-57"/> Homage to the
            Three Jewels.</p>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-27"/>
          <lg tid="26">
            <l>May all buddhas grant their protection!</l>
            <l>I pay homage to supreme awakening;</l>
            <l>May all noble ones grant their protection!</l>
            <l>I pay homage to the supreme vajra;</l>
            <l>May all knowledge granters grant their protection!</l>
            <l>I pay homage to all the gods of the pure god realms;</l>
            <l>May all protectors grant their protection!</l>
            <l>I pay homage to the gods in the heavens;</l>
            <l>May the lords of the three worlds grant their protection!</l>
            <l>To all those who rule over the three realms of existence</l>
            <l>I pay homage and offer worship;</l>
            <l>Grant your compassionate blessings</l>
            <l>To my five aggregates and limbs! </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-28"/>
          <p tid="27">The essence-mantra of that is said to be:</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-29"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="28">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ kara kara svāhā kuru kuru svāhā
              bhara bhara svāhā bhuru bhuru svāhā dhara dhara svāhā dhuru dhuru svāhā cara cara
              svāhā curu curu svāhā </mantra>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-30"/>
          <lg tid="29">
            <l>Protect my five aggregates and limbs </l>
            <l>From inauspicious years and inauspicious months,</l>
            <l>Inauspicious days and inauspicious days of the week,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-31">“Days of the week” would more commonly be <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gza’</foreign>, rather than the reading here,
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">za</foreign>, but <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gza’</foreign> is used in the next line where it
                seems to indicate the planets (another meaning of the word). Our translation here is
                tentative.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Inauspicious planets and inauspicious stars, </l>
            <l>Inauspicious daytimes and inauspicious nighttimes,</l>
            <l>Inauspicious middays, </l>
            <l>Inauspicious mornings and inauspicious evenings, </l>
            <l>Inauspicious cardinal directions and inauspicious intermediary directions,</l>
            <l>Possession by the five ghosts,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-32"> Here the
                Degé, and most of the other Kangyurs consulted in the Pedurma edition, read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’dre lnga sdod</foreign> (“the five ghosts
                remaining”), which we understand to mean possession by the ghosts. The Yongle and
                Kangxi Kangyurs read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’dre lgna
                  gdon</foreign> (“the demonic five ghosts” or “the demons/spirits who are the five
                ghosts”), which is also a plausible reading. Given two plausible readings, we simply
                chose the one that is predominant. </note> and inauspicious divinations.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-33">
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdud gcod</foreign>. This is the name of an
                inauspicious divination result in the trigram divinations according to the Chinese
                elemental divination system. </note>
                        </l>
            <l>Grant protection from all of these! </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-34"/>
          <p tid="30">The essence-mantra of that is said to be:</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-35"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="31">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ prajñe prajñe prajñe avalokiradhati
              mani susiddhi ārya jvala nāma mañjuye svāhā</mantra>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-36"/>
          <lg tid="32">
            <l>May my five aggregates and limbs, </l>
            <l>Despite being subjected to darkness</l>
            <l>From violence<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-37">
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dmar kyi mthun</foreign>. Here we follow the
                Yongle and Kangxi Kangyurs which read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dmar
                  kyi mthun</foreign>, thus taking the phrase to mean “violence” (lit. “that which
                accords with violence”), rather than the Degé, which reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dmar kyi thun</foreign> (this might possibly be
                translated as “violent incanted substances” or “violent practices”). While we
                believe we can make most sense of the Kangxi and Yongle reading, we nonetheless
                remain unsure about the meaning of this phrase, and suspect that the passage may be
                corrupt. </note> and malevolent female spirits;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-38">
                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">phra men</foreign>. This term is one of two
                Tibetan translations of the word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ḍākinī</foreign>, the other being the more familiar <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkha’ ’gro </foreign>(<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign>). It seems the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra
                  men</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign>) was used more
                frequently to render the idea of ḍākinīs as a class of potentially malevolent female
                spirits, while the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkha’ ’gro
                  </foreign>(<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign>), while also used
                to refer to such worldly spirits, was preferred for the “wisdom” ḍākinīs in the
                higher tantras, in which context the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ḍākinī</foreign> is better known to English-speaking audiences. To avoid such
                confusion (and also because we speculate that this text may have been translated
                from Chinese rather than from Sanskrit), we have chosen to translate the word
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men </foreign>here as “malevolent
                female spirit,” since what <emph>is</emph> clear is that its referent here is a
                class of potentially harmful entities. See the glossary entry on <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men</foreign> for further uses of the
                term.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>From the onset of coughs and difficult illnesses;</l>
            <l>From obstacle years, obstacle months, obstacle days,</l>
            <l>Obstacle days of the week and the like;
              <ref cRef="F.236.b" type="folio" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-86"/>
              <!--NB There should be a folio reference here, and in any case the preceding displayed folio is 
              not the right one; it is marked (below in grey) as 236.a not 235.a but has the right Western number, yet does not appear to be 236.a either! -->
                        </l>
            <l>And from bad dreams, enemies, and hindrances,</l>
            <l>Be protected by the directional guardians</l>
            <l>Who are said to radiate light, like the sun and moon, </l>
            <l>That illuminates from the farthest reaches. </l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-39"/>
          <p tid="33">The essence-mantra of that is said to be:</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-40"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="34">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ haku hūṁ hūṁ du hūṁ hūṁ na hūṁ hūṁ
              yaṁ hūṁ hūṁ ke hūṁ hūṁ ki hūṁ hūṁ kī hūṁ hūṁ ti hūṁ hūṁ tī hūṁ hūṁ dū hūṁ hūṁ ve hūṁ
            </mantra>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-41"/>
          <lg tid="35">
            <l>From beginningless time </l>
            <l>Until being born in this life and body,</l>
            <l>I have written incorrectly, recited incorrectly, </l>
            <l>Listened incorrectly, explained incorrectly, </l>
            <l>Meditated incorrectly, and trained incorrectly. </l>
            <l>Protect my five aggregates and limbs</l>
            <l>From all such broken rules, broken vows, </l>
            <l>And broken samayas!</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-42"/>
          <p tid="36">The essence-mantra of that is:</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-43"/>
          <p rend="mantra" tid="37">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">namo bhagavata sarva dhuye duṣṭana
              svāhā</mantra>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-44"/>
          <trailer tid="38">This concludes <title xml:lang="en">“The Noble Dhāraṇī Called the
              Supreme Stem Ornament.”</title>
                    </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes">
        <head type="notes" tid="41">Notes</head>
      </div>
      <div type="listBibl">
        <head type="listBibl" tid="43">Bibliography</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-listBibl-1">
          <head type="section" tid="44">Tibetan</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-46">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sdong po rgyan gyi
              mchog ces bya ba’i gzungs</title>. Toh 1066, Degé Kangyur, vol. 101 (gzungs ’dus,
            waṃ), folios 235.a–235.b. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-47">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sdong po rgyan gyi
              mchog ces bya ba’i gzungs</title>. ka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of
            the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang
            (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
            volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing
            House), 2006–9, vol. 98, pp. 808–10.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-48">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang
              ma</title>. Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang, 2003.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-85">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang
              ldan dkar gyi chos kyi ’gyur ro cog gi dkar chag</title>. Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol.
            206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-listBibl-2">
          <head type="section" tid="47">Western</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-82">Hidas, Gergely. <title xml:lang="en">Powers of
              Protection: The Buddhist Tradition of Spells in the Dhāraṇīsaṃgraha
              Collections</title>. Boston: De Gruyter, 2021.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-83">Orosz, Gergely. <title xml:lang="en">A Catalogue of the
              Tibetan Manuscripts and Block Prints in the Library of the Hungarian Academy of
              Sciences</title>. Budapest: Library of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences, 2010. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-81">Roberts, Peter Alan, trans. (2021). <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh44-45.html">The Stem
              Array</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title>, Toh 44-45). 84000:
            Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2018.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-122-84">Stein, Rolf. A. <title xml:lang="en">Rolf Stein’s
              Tibetica Antiqua, with Additional Materials</title>. Translated and edited by Arthur
            McKeown. Boston: Brill, 2010.</bibl>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="glossary" status="excluded">
        <list type="glossary">
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-50">
              <term type="translationMain">Three Jewels</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedDictionary" status="verified">triratna</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">dkon mchog
                gsum</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ།</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-51">
              <term type="translationMain">samaya</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedDictionary" status="verified">samaya</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">dam tshig</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">དམ་ཚིག</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-52">
              <term type="translationMain">essence-mantra</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedDictionary" status="verified">hṛdaya</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">snying po</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">སྙིང་པོ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                <p>A short mantra.</p>
              </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-53">
              <term type="translationMain">dhāraṇī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedDictionary" status="verified">dhāraṇī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">gzungs</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">གཟུངས།</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-122-55">
              <term type="translationMain">malevolent female spirit</term>
              <term type="translationAlternative">malevolent female spirits</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="attestedDictionary" status="verified">ḍākinī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">phra men
                ma</term>
              <term xml:lang="bo" type="attestedSource" n="1" status="verified">ཕྲ་མེན་མ།</term>
              <note type="definition">
                <p>The term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men ma</foreign> (also
                  spelled <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phra man ma</foreign> in some texts) is one of
                  the two translations of the word <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ḍākinī</foreign> found in canonical works. In this case—as in many of the cases
                  where <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men ma </foreign>rather than the
                  other Tibetan translation of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ḍākinī</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkha’ ’gro
                    ma</foreign> is employed—it refers to a class of malevolent female spirits. The
                  higher tantras of the Nyingma tradition feature <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phra men</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma</foreign>) as a class of protective deities on the periphery of the maṇḍala
                  of wrathful deities in the Shitro (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhi
                    khro</foreign>) maṇḍala of peaceful and wrathful deities. They have female
                  bodies, animal heads, and often appear as a set of eight.</p>
              </note>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>