<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</title>
        <title key="toh1090" type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nad kyi bdag mo la bstod pa</title>
        <title key="toh1090" xml:lang="bo" type="mainTitle">ནད་ཀྱི་བདག་མོ་ལ་བསྟོད་པ།</title>
        <title key="toh1090" type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī­mahākālī­devī­stotrāṣṭaka</title>
        <title key="toh1090" type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī­mahākālī­devī­stotrāṣṭaka­nāma</title>
        <title xml:lang="zh"/>
        <!--<title key="toh1777" type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">dpal lha mo nag mo chen mo la
                    bstod pa brgyad pa</title>-->
        <!--<title key="toh1777" type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">Eight Verses Praising the
                    Glorious Goddess Mahākālī</title>-->
        <!--<title key="toh1777" type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo nag mo chen mo la bstod pa brgyad pa zhes bya ba</title>
                                <title key="toh1777" type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་ལྷ་མོ་ནག་མོ་ཆེན་མོ་ལ་བསྟོད་པ་བརྒྱད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</title>-->
        <!--<title key="toh1777" type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī­mahākālī­devī­stotrāṣṭaka</title>-->
        <!--<title key="toh1777" type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī­mahākālī­devī­stotrāṣṭaka­nāma</title>-->
        <author ref="eft:team-55" role="translatorMain">Translated by Catherine Dalton<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
          of the Buddha</author>
        <author role="translatorEng" ref="eft:person-61">Catherine Dalton</author>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="eft:person-274">Adam Krug</editor>
        <editor role="copyEditor" ref="eft:person-422">George FitzHerbert</editor>
        <editor role="projectEditor" ref="eft:person-250">Rory Lindsay</editor>
        <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="eft:person-381">Martina Cotter</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.2 <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt status="2">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern
          languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
          <p type="tantricRestriction">
                        <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are
            restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this translation are advised to consult the
            authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in
            the hands of readers.</p>
          <licence>
            <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
            <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It
              may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full
              details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-101-146"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2023-02-24</date>
            </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl key="toh1090" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 1090</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, Vol. 101 (gzungs ’dus, wa), folios 255.a–255.b.</biblScope>
          <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="2">
            <volume number="102" start-page="509" end-page="510"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20568" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12854" work="W22084"/>
        </bibl>
        <bibl key="toh1777" type="text">
          <ref>Toh 1777</ref>
          <biblScope>Degé Tengyur, Vol. 28 (rgyud ’bum, sha), folios 271.b–272.a.</biblScope>
          <author role="translatorTib">Brahmin Vararuci</author>
          <location work="UT23703" count-pages="2">
            <volume number="28" start-page="542" end-page="543"/>
          </location>
          <idno parent-id="O1JC76301JC21620" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
          <idno source-id="O1JC76301JC8330" work="W23703"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2023-03-15T16:02:26.246Z" user="admin">15/03/2023 16:02:26</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.h" date-time="2022-04-12T07:53:43.707Z" user="line-tofte">2.h</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2022-04-12T07:53:43.707Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.3" date-time="2022-04-12T08:01:52.252Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.g" date-time="2022-04-27T07:19:01.164Z" user="line-tofte">2.g</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.4" date-time="2022-04-27T07:19:01.164Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.5" date-time="2022-04-27T07:19:44.313Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.f" date-time="2022-06-16T10:17:55.018Z" user="line-tofte">2.f</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.6" date-time="2022-06-16T10:17:55.018Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2022-09-02T08:34:28.484Z" user="line-tofte">2.e</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.7" date-time="2022-09-02T08:34:28.484Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.8" date-time="2022-09-02T08:35:08.302Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2022-09-16T12:34:00.127Z" user="line-tofte">2.d</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.9" date-time="2022-09-16T12:34:00.127Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2023-01-04T10:33:49.319Z" user="line-tofte">2.c</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.10" date-time="2023-01-04T10:33:49.319Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2023-02-17T15:32:21.524Z" user="line-tofte">2.b</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.11" date-time="2023-02-17T15:32:21.524Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.12" date-time="2023-02-17T15:34:34.808Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2023-02-22T15:04:53.844Z" user="line-tofte">2.a</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.13" date-time="2023-02-22T15:04:53.844Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.14" date-time="2023-02-22T15:05:24.279Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-contributors)</note>
        <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.15" date-time="2023-02-24T13:16:32.129Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
          <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2023-03-15T16:02:21.978Z" user="line-tofte">2</note>
          <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.0.2" date-time="2023-03-15T16:02:21.978Z" user="line-tofte">Auto (update-publication-status)</note>
      </notesStmt>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!--Note the "Contents" outline from the Word DOCX has not been included in the script. If the 
                    Outline to the text is quite complex, it is recommended that you paste the outlined contents from the DOCX here as a comment for
                    markup's reference. The actual table of contents will be generated in the Reading Room by the parser.-->
    <front>
      <div type="summary">
        <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-1"/>
        <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</title>, or, as it is alternatively titled, <title xml:lang="en">Eight Verses
            Praising the Glorious Goddess Mahākālī</title>, is a short praise to the goddess Mahākālī in which she is portrayed as both a cause of human illness
          and a source of protection from it. The text is included in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs section of the Degé Kangyur as well as in the Tantra section of
          the Degé Tengyur, and it was composed by the brahmin Vararuci.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgment">
        <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-2"/>
        <p tid="4">This text was translated by Catherine Dalton and edited by the 84000 editorial team.</p>
        <p tid="5"> The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
        <lb/>
        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-5"/>
        <p tid="7">[Sponsored by XXXXXX]</p>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction">
        <head type="introduction" tid="8">Introduction</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-introduction-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-6"/>
          <p tid="10">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</title>, or, as it is alternatively titled, <title xml:lang="en">Eight Verses
              Praising the Glorious Goddess Mahākālī</title>, is a short praise to the wrathful goddess Mahākālī in which she is identified as the best source
            of protection from human illness. The text was composed by the Brahmin Vararuci, who describes Mahākālī as black, naked, terrifying, eating human
            flesh, and frequenting cremation grounds. She is described as draped in a fresh hide, holding a bell, a skull, a sword, a spear, and a lion, with a
            snake spreading its hood behind her. In this short work, Vararuci depicts Mahākālī as so large that she tramples the earth, with the sun resting at
            the level of her navel, and marvels that gods such as Indra and Yama are compelled to bow trembling at her feet.</p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-7"/>
          <p tid="11">The praise includes a striking line in which Vararuci states that Mahākālī is “present as half of Mahādeva’s body,” a reference to Śiva’s
            form as Ardhanārīśvara—the “Lord Who Is Half Female.” The female “half” of Śiva in this form is generally identified as his consort Pārvatī, and in
            the very next line of the praise Vararuci uses one of Pārvatī’s most common epithets, Gaurī, identifying Mahākālī with her as well as with the
            goddess Durgā. These passages highlight the connection and interplay between Buddhism and both Śaiva and Śākta traditions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-8"> This relationship has been studied by a number of scholars, most prominently Ronald Davidson (2002) and Alexis
              Sanderson (2009).</note>
          </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-9"/>
          <p tid="12">This praise does not appear to survive in Sanskrit or to have been translated into Chinese. The text is included in the Compendium of
            Dhāraṇīs (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus</title>) section of the Degé Kangyur and other Tshalpa-lineage Kangyurs that include a separate
            dhāraṇī section,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-10">
              <title xml:lang="en">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</title> is one of only fifteen texts in the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs section of the Degé
              Kangyur (and the other Kangyurs that include such a section) that, unlike the other 235 works in the Compendium, does <emph>not</emph> also appear
              in duplicate in other sections of the Kangyur.</note> and in the Tantra sections of Tshalpa-lineage Kangyurs that lack such a section. It is not
            found in any Kangyurs belonging to the Thempangma grouping, such as the Stok Palace Kangyur, nor do we find it in the Dunhuang collections. Since
            this text is recognized as having had a human author, the brahmin Vararuci, it is also included in all four recensions of the Tengyur. It seems
            likely that the work’s inclusion in some Kangyurs, despite clearly being an authored text, may be related to its being part of the Compendium of
            Dhāraṇīs, which seems to have been compiled on the basis of an earlier collection or collections of dhāraṇīs and associated ritual texts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-11"> Hidas notes a remark by Orosz that the Degé Kangyur catalog (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dkar
                chag</foreign>) identifies the source of the Compendium of Dhāraṇīs as the extracanonical collection edited by Tāranātha (Hidas 2021, p. 7, n.
              56).</note> These collections, known in Sanskrit as <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī­saṃgrahas</title>, appear in South Asia and Tibet—including
            at Dunhuang and as extracanonical Tibetan dhāraṇī collections—and often include praises as well as dhāraṇīs and dhāraṇī-sūtras.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-12"> See J. Dalton 2016 and J. Dalton and van Schaik 2006 on the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</foreign> collections preserved at Dunhuang, which contain praises and prayers as well as dhāraṇīs. See Hidas 2021 for the
              catalogs of eighteen <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī­saṃgraha</foreign> collections surviving in Sanskrit, many of which also
              contain praises. </note> As mentioned above, the present work has been preserved under two titles: the recension included in the Kangyurs is
            titled <title xml:lang="en">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</title>, while that in the Tengyurs is titled <title xml:lang="en">Eight Verses
              Praising the Glorious Goddess Mahākālī</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-13"> While these reflect the titles given at the incipit
              (and thus also in the catalogs) of the Kangyur and Tengyur recensions, the author’s colophons of both recensions show how it may have come to be
              known under these two different titles. The author’s colophon of the Tengyur recension reprises the title as “<title xml:lang="en">Eight Verses
                Praising the Glorious Goddess Mahākālī, the Lady Who Rules All Disease</title>,” while the author’s colophon of the Kangyur recension gives it
              as: “<title xml:lang="en">Eight Verses Praising Mahākālī, the Lady who Rules all Diseases</title>.”</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-14"/>
          <p tid="13">Not much is known about the work’s author, the brahmin Vararuci, but in addition to this praise to Mahākālī, a series of works related to
            Mahākāla included in the Tengyur—two <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sādhana</foreign>s, an empowerment rite, and a praise—are also
            attributed to him.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-15"> The four Mahākāla-related works attributed to Vararuci are two <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Mahākāla-sādhana</foreign>s (Toh 1761 and Toh 3386) <ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh1761.html"/>
                            <ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh3386.html"/>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākālābhiṣeka-vidhi</title> (Toh 1763) <ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh1763.html"/>, and a
                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Mahākāla-stotra</foreign> (Toh 1774)<ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh1774.html"/>.</note> One Vararuci (or, more probably several Vararucis) is also the author of a
            number of scientific and astrological texts composed in Sanskrit, but without further evidence it seems unlikely that those texts are authored by
            the same Vararuci as these several Buddhist works related to Mahākāla and Mahākālī that survive in translation in the Tibetan Kangyurs. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-16"/>
          <p tid="14">Neither the Kangyur nor the Tengyur recension of this praise includes a translator’s colophon, so we do not know who translated it, but
            the work is listed in the imperial Denkarma catalog (under the title found in its Kangyur recensions), so we know that it was translated prior to
            the collapse of the Tibetan empire in 843 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. At the very end of the praise, the author uses exactly the same series of
            epithets for Mahākālī—“Yama’s Queen, Mother of Māra, Sovereign Goddess of the Desire Realm”—found in <title xml:lang="en">Mahākālī’s Dhāraṇī</title>
            (Toh 670/1087), <ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh670.html"/>
                        <ref rend="pending" target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh1087.html"/> a text in the Kangyur also listed in both the Denkarma and Phangthangma imperial
            catalogs, so it is likely that Vararuci knew and was referencing that work. </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-17"/>
          <p tid="15">This English translation was completed on the basis of both the Degé Kangyur and Tengyur recensions (Toh 1090<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-175">The present text, and all those contained in this same volume (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus, wa</foreign>),
              are listed as being located in volume 100 of the Degé Kangyur by the Buddhist Digital Resource Center (BDRC). However, several other Kangyur
              databases—including the eKangyur that supplies the digital input version displayed by the 84000 Reading Room—list this work as being located in
              volume 102. This discrepancy is partly due to the fact that the two volumes of the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus</foreign> section are an
              added supplement not mentioned in the original catalog, and also hinges on the fact that the compilers of the Tōhoku catalog placed another
              text—which forms a whole, very large volume—the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā­nāmakālacakra­tantraṭīkā</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dus ’khor ’grel bshad dri med ’od</title>, Toh 845), before the present volume, numbering it as vol. 100, although it is almost certainly
              intended to come right at the end of the Degé Kangyur texts as volume 102; indeed its final fifth chapter is often carried over and wrapped in the
              same volume as the Kangyur <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chags</foreign> (catalog). Please note this discrepancy when using the eKangyur viewer
              in this translation. </note> and Toh 1777, respectively) with additional reference to the notes from the Comparative Editions (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe sdur ma</foreign>) of the Kangyur and Tengyur. While the two recensions are largely identical, the Kangyur
            recension appears to have suffered from some textual corruption during its transmission, which the textually superior Tengyur version fortunately
            helps to resolve. We have therefore generally given preference to the readings from the recension preserved in the Tengyur, although there were also
            some instances where the Kangyur recension had the better reading. All instances where the two recensions differed significantly (i.e., in a way
            that affected the meaning of the text, and therefore the translation) have been noted in the endnotes to the translation.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="translation">
        <head key="toh1090" type="translation" tid="16">The Translation</head>
        <head key="toh1090" type="titleMain" tid="18">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</head>
        <!--<head key="toh1777" type="titleMain" tid="">Eight Verses Praising the Glorious Goddess Mahākālī (Toh 1777)</head>-->
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-section-1">
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-142"/>
          <p tid="92">
                        <ref cRef="F.255.a" type="folio" key="toh1090" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-171"/>
            <ref cRef="F.271.b" type="folio" key="toh1777" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-172"/> Homage to Glorious Vajrapāṇi.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-143"> This verse of homage is found only in the Tengyur recension of the text (Toh 1777) and is absent in the Kangyur
              recension (Toh 1090).</note>
                    </p>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-144"/>
          <lb/>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-145"/>
          <lg tid="94">
            <l>O goddess, you wander in this world naked, riding a donkey,</l>
            <l>Your hair a single plait anointed with sesame oil. </l>
            <l>Seductive and adorned with every ornament,</l>
            <l>You wear lead earrings in your ears,</l>
            <l>Your feet decorated with iron shackles as anklets. </l>
            <l>Understanding your<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-146"> We have emended <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lha mo khyod nyid
                  kyis</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lha mo khyod nyid kyi</foreign>.</note> beautiful nature may allow others to see
                you,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-147"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bdag nyid mdzes par shes kyis
                  gzhan ltas</foreign>, rather than Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bdag nyid mdzes par shes kyi gzhan lta</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>But who could understand all the benefits </l>
            <l>Of the great ocean of your activity? |1|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-148"/>
          <lg tid="95">
            <l>When saṃsāra is demolished, when from human bodies<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-149"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi lus</foreign> (“human bodies”), rather than Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi rus</foreign> (“human bones”).
              </note>
            </l>
            <l>Blood and fat ooze out, and smoke issues forth,</l>
            <l>In a single instant, O goddess, you will toss </l>
            <l>All beings into your terrifying, fanged mouth.</l>
            <l>Black, holding a human skull, delighted by cremation grounds, </l>
            <l>You are what yogins seek to accomplish.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-150"> Following Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnal ’byor grub pa’i spyod yul can</foreign>, rather than Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnal ’byor grub pa’i rnal ’byor
                  can</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
            <l>As you ring your terrifying bell, you subdue all that moves, </l>
            <l>And clear and pacify<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-151"> Following Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’jigs sel zhi
                  la</foreign> and the Peking and Narthang recensions of Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’jigs pa gsal zhing zhi
                la</foreign>—both lending the meaning “clear fears and pacify”—rather than the Degé edition of Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’jigs pa bsal zhing</foreign> (“clear fears and”).</note> the fear of illness and death.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-152">
                Following Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">nad dang ’chi ba</foreign> (“illness and death”), rather than Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">nad chen ’chi ba</foreign> (“the great illness that is death”).</note> |2|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-153"/>
          <lg tid="96">
            <l>Adorned with a crown made from the heads of heroes,</l>
            <l>And a garland of heads severed on the battlefield,</l>
            <l>You dance with your delicate arms opened wide, </l>
            <l>Wearing the nāga king as a girdle across your broad hips. <ref cRef="F.272.a" type="folio" key="toh1777" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-173"/>
                        </l>
            <l>Intoxicated by the liquor of blood, </l>
            <l>In your hands you brandish a spear and sword. </l>
            <l>Your eyes bloodshot, you are seen by the host of bhūtas </l>
            <l>Who wander cremation grounds at night. |3|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-154"/>
          <lg tid="97">
            <l>Wrapped in a large, fresh hide, you wear it</l>
            <l>Half-open,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-155"> Following Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ko rlon sar pas dril te
                  brgyang ba’i gos kyis snam phyi phyed g.yogs</foreign>. Toh 1077 reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ko rlon chen po dral te
                  brgyangs pa’i gos kyis mnabs shing phyed g.yogs</foreign>.</note> bound with a belt of braided straw.</l>
            <l>Your moon-like face is adorned with the hollow tubes </l>
            <l>Of fresh human entrails, </l>
            <l>And you ring<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-156"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’khrol</foreign> (“play”),
                rather than Toh 1090<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’dril</foreign> (“wield”). </note> a bell at your cheek. </l>
            <l>Your body freshly oiled and painted with drops </l>
            <l>Of mixed blood and fat,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-157"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khrag dang zhag
                  la sogs pa’i thig les</foreign> (“drops of blood and fat and the rest”), rather than Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khrag
                  dang zhag mang ’dzag pa’i thig les</foreign> (“many drops of blood and fat that have dropped down”). </note> you carry a skull as you tear
                <ref cRef="F.255.b" type="folio" key="toh1090" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-174"/>
                        </l>
            <l>At human flesh<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-158"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi yi sha</foreign>
                (“human flesh”), rather than Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi ro’i sha</foreign> (“human corpse flesh”) The sense, of course,
                is essentially the same. </note> with your glistening teeth. Protect me! |4|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-159"/>
          <lg tid="98">
            <l>Fiercest among fierce ladies,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-160"> Following Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">drag po’i
                  drag mo</foreign> (“fiercest of the fierce ladies”), rather than Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">drag po drag mo</foreign>
                (“fierce males and fierce females”).</note>
                        </l>
            <l>Terrifying, with human flesh in your mouth, </l>
            <l>The first time they saw you even the mātṛkās were terrified </l>
            <l>As you flew into a rage, </l>
            <l>Your eyes flickering about—I bow to you!</l>
            <l>Kālī, your beautiful black body is so irresistible </l>
            <l>That even Śākra and the rest are compelled to praise you daily, </l>
            <l>And Yama himself must always bow trembling before you. |5|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-161"/>
          <lg tid="99">
            <l>You bring an end<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-162"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mjug brtul
                  ba</foreign> ([you] “bring to an end”) rather than Toh 1090 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mjug brtul bas</foreign> (“because [you]
                bring to an end”).</note> to humans and all living beings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-163"> The first line in this verse in Toh
                1090 is two syllables longer that the other three lines in the verse. However, in Toh 1777 the two “extra” syllables are present in all four
                lines, suggesting Toh 1090 may have lost the extra syllables due to textual corruption over the course of the text’s transmission. In any case,
                Toh 1777 preserves several preferable readings for this verse.</note>
            </l>
            <l>By one of your ears is a snake </l>
            <l>Whose thousand-headed hood adorns you from behind,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-164"> This line in Toh 1090, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">brang gis ’gro ba’i mgo bos gdengs ka stong dang ldan pa khyab gnas rgyan tu byas</foreign>, has multiple
                textual problems, particularly the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khyab gnas</foreign>, the problematic third-case particle in
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mgo bos</foreign>, and the lack of two metrical syllables, so we have followed the reading in Toh 1077:
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">brang gis ’gro ba ’go bo’i gdengs ka stong dang ldan pa rgyab nas rgyan du byas nas gnas</foreign>,
                with the minor modification of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’go bo’i</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote"> </foreign>to<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote"> </foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mgo bo’i</foreign>, with reference to
                Toh 1090’s reading of this one word, “head.” </note>
            </l>
            <l>And by the other, you hold a peerless lion. </l>
            <l>You trample the entire<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-165"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma lus</foreign>,
                omitted in Toh 1090. </note> ocean-encircled earth.</l>
            <l>The sun that moves above, </l>
            <l>Brilliant with a thousand rays, </l>
            <l>Rests directly at your navel.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-166"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khyod kyi
                  lte ba’i thad ka’i phyogs su gzhags</foreign>, rather than Toh 1090’s <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khyod kyis lte ba’i phyogs so
                  bzhag</foreign>, which omits <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thad ka</foreign>, “directly,” and also includes the confusing third case
                particle <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kyis</foreign>, where Toh 1777 has a much better reading with the genitive particle <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kyi</foreign>.</note> |6|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-167"/>
          <lg tid="100">
            <l>You blaze forth from the submarine fire,</l>
            <l>Able to dry up the whole of the sea.</l>
            <l>Since he can pacify all women,</l>
            <l>You are present as half of Mahādeva’s body.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-168"> This appears to be a reference to Mahākālī as the
                female half of the half-male half-female form of Śiva called Ardhanārīśvara, the “Lord Who Is Half Female.” Mahādeva is a very common epithet of
                Śiva. His other half in Ardhanārīśvara form is usually identified as his consort Pārvatī, one of whose common epithets is Gaurī. Indeed the
                half-half form is sometimes called Ardhagaurīśvara or even simply Gaurīśvara. In the following verse Vararuci identifies Mahākālī with Gaurī—an
                interesting identification since Gaurī means “Fair One,” whereas Kālī means “Black One.” The statement about Mahādeva/Śiva as one who “can
                pacify all women” is likely a reference to Śiva’s lying supine on the battlefield or appearing as a child on the battlefield in order to calm
                Kālī to prevent her from destroying the world.</note> |7|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-169"/>
          <lg tid="101">
            <l>Durgā, Gaurī, Mahākālī,</l>
            <l>To whom gods and asuras pay homage, </l>
            <l>You know all human diseases—</l>
            <l>Free us from this fear! </l>
            <l>Yama’s Queen, Mother of Māra, </l>
            <l>Sovereign Goddess of the Desire Realm—I praise you!<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-170"> Following Toh 1777 <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’dod khams dbang phyug ma la bstod</foreign>, which indicates a clear end to the composition, rather than Toh 1090<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’dod pa’i khams kyi dbang phyug ma</foreign>, which somewhat confusingly blends the verse into the author’s
                colophon. </note> |8|</l>
          </lg>
          <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-101"/>
          <trailer key="toh1090" tid="84">This concludes “<title xml:lang="en">Praising the Lady Who Rules Disease</title>”, composed by the Brahmin Vararuci.</trailer>
          <!--<trailer key="toh1777" tid="84">This concludes “<title xml:lang="en">Eight Verses Praising the
                                                  Glorious</title><note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-102"> The word <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpal</foreign>
                                                  (“glorious”) is present in Toh 1777 but absent in
                                                  Toh 1090. </note><title xml:lang="en">
                                                  Goddess Mahākālī,
                                                  the Lady Who Rules
                                                  All
                                                  Disease</title>”, composed by the Brahmin Vararuci.</trailer>
-->
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes">
        <head type="notes" tid="87">Notes</head>
      </div>
      <div type="listBibl">
        <head type="listBibl" tid="89">Bibliography</head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-listBibl-1">
          <head type="section" tid="90">Tibetan Sources</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-106">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nad kyi bdag mo la bstod pa</title>. Toh 1090, Degé Kangyur vol. 101 (gzungs ’dus, waM),
            folios 255.a–255.b. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-107">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nad kyi bdag mo la bstod pa</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the
            Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
            Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 98, pp.
            892–94.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-108">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo nag mo chen mo la bstod pa brgyad pa</title>. Toh 1777, Degé Tengyur vol. 28
            (rgyud, sha), folios 271.b–272.a.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-109">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal lha mo nag mo chen mo la bstod pa brgyad pa</title>. bstan ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
            [Comparative Edition of the Tengyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau
            of the China Tibetology Research Center). Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 14, pp.
            1714–17.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-110">Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan dkar gyi chos kyi ’gyur ro cog gi dkar
              chag</foreign>). Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-111">Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>). Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang,
            2003.</bibl>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-listBibl-2">
          <head type="section" tid="91">Secondary Sources</head>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-112">Dalton, Jacob P. “How Dhāraṇīs WERE Proto-Tantric: Liturgies, Ritual Manuals, and the Origins of the Tantras.” In
              <title xml:lang="en">Tantric Traditions in Transmission and Translation</title>, edited by David Gray and Ryan Richard Overbey, 199–229. New York:
            Oxford University Press, 2016. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-113">Dalton, Jacob and Sam van Schaik, eds. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan Tantric Manuscripts from Dunhuang: A
              Descriptive Catalogue of the Stein Collection at the British Library.</title> Brill’s Tibetan Studies Library 12. Leiden: Brill, 2006. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-114">Davidson, Ronald M. <title xml:lang="en">Indian Esoteric Buddhism: A Social History of the Tantric
              Movement.</title> New York: Columbia University Press, 2002. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-115">Hidas, Gergely. <title xml:lang="en">Powers of Protection: The Buddhist Tradition of Spells in the Dhāraṇīsaṃgraha
              Collections.</title> Beyond Boundaries 9. Boston: de Gruyter, 2021.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-116">Kawagoe, Eshin. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Dkar chag ’Phang thang ma</title>. Sendai: Tōhuku indo chibetto kenkyūkai.
            (Tohuku Society for Indo-Tibetan Studies), 2005. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-117">Lalou, Marcelle. “Les textes Bouddhiques au temps du Roi Khri-sroṅ-lde-bcan.” <title xml:lang="fr">Journal
              Asiatique </title>241 (1953): 313–52.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-118">Negi, J. S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan–Sanskrit Dictionary</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bod skad legs sbyar
              gyi tshig mdzod chen mo</title>). 16 vols. Sarnath: Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies, 1993. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="UT22084-101-146-119">Sanderson, Alexis. “The Śaiva Age: The Rise and Dominance of Śaivism during the Early Medieval Period” In <title xml:lang="en">Genesis and Development of Tantrism</title>, edited by Shingo Einoo, 41–350. Tokyo: Institute of Oriental Culture, University of
            Tokyo, 2009. </bibl>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="glossary" status="excluded">
        <list type="glossary">
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-121">
              <term>bhūta</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung po </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-122">
              <term>mātṛkā</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མ་མོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mātṛkā</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-123">
              <term>submarine fire</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya mtsho’i klong </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱ་མཚོའི་ཀློང་།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samudravahni</term>
              <term type="definition">The point of origin for the fire that consumes the universe at the end of an eon.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-124">
              <term>god</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-125">
              <term>asura</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-126">
              <term>Sovereign Goddess of the Desire Realm</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod khams dbang phyug ma </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་ཁམས་དབང་ཕྱུག་མ།</term>
              <term type="definition">Here an epithet of Mahākālī</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-127">
              <term>nāga</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-129">
              <term>Vajrapāṇi</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag na rdo rje </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajrapāṇi</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-130">
              <term>Yama</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-131">
              <term>Śākra</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
              <term type="definition">A common epithet of Indra, the lord of the gods, who dwells on the summit of Mount Sumeru and wields the thunderbolt. The
                Tibetan translation is based on an etymology that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śakra</foreign> is an abbreviation of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śata-kratu</foreign>: one who has performed a hundred sacrifices (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin</foreign>). The highest Vedic
                sacrifice was the horse sacrifice, and there is a tradition that he became the lord of the gods through performing a hundred of them.<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            </term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-132">
              <term>Śiva</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Īśvara</term>
              <term type="definition">Īśvara (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang phyug</foreign>) “Mighty One” is one of the most frequently used
                names for Śiva.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-133">
              <term>Mahādeva</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha chen </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་ཆེན།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahādeva</term>
              <term type="definition">A name of Śiva.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-134">
              <term>Gaurī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dka’ zlog </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">དཀའ་ཟློག</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaurī</term>
              <term type="definition">A goddess, an epithet of Śiva’s consort Pārvatī.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-135">
              <term>Mahākālī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag mo chen mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ནག་མོ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākālī</term>
              <term type="definition">A goddess.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-136">
              <term>Durgā</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzong </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">རྫོང་།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Durgā</term>
              <term type="definition">A goddess.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-137">
              <term>Kālī</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag mo </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">ནག་མོ།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālī</term>
              <term type="definition">A goddess.</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-138">
              <term>Māra</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-139">
              <term>Vararuci</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog srid </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོག་སྲིད།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vararuci</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
          <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-101-146-141">
              <term>Desire realm</term>
              <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod khams </term>
              <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་ཁམས།</term>
              <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāmadhātu</term>
            </gloss>
                    </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>