<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="bo" type="mainTitle">དབུ་མ་རྒྱན་གྱི་འགྲེལ་པ་དབུ་མའི་ལམ་གྲུབ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</title>
                <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="mainTitle">dbu ma rgyan gyi 'grel pa dbu ma'i lam grub pa zhes bya ba/</title>
                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mainTitle">Madhyamakālaṃkāra­vṛtti­madhyama­pratipadā­siddhi­nāma</title>
                <title xml:lang="en" type="mainTitle">A Running Commentary on the Ornament of the Middle Way, called “Establishing the Middle Way”</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.0.3 <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <availability status=""/>
                <idno xml:id="UT23703-138-003"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh4072" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 4072</ref>
                    <biblScope>ff. 102r-120v</biblScope>
                    <author xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" xml:id="UT23703-138-003-1">Ratnākaraśānti</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" xml:id="UT23703-138-003-2">lo tsa ba shakya 'od</author>
                    <location work="UT23703" count-pages="38">
                        <volume number="138" start-page="203" end-page="240"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC76301JC10703" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC76301JC10774" work="W23703"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt/>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change who="#admin" when="2022-01-20T09:14:07.444Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT23703-138-003-3">
                    <desc>Auto (correct-orphaned-attributions)</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2022-01-28T10:32:05.149Z" type="import" xml:id="UT23703-138-003-4" source="tengyur-data-4020-4085_PH_new_v2.4.xml">
                    <desc/>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2022-01-28T10:32:05.149Z" type="general" xml:id="UT23703-138-003-5" source="tengyur-data-4020-4085_PH_new_v2.4.xml">
                    <desc>Ruegg states that in the Madhyamakālaṃkāra-vṛtti (fol. 136a–b) Ratnākaraśānti turns the stages of understanding recognized by the Lankāvatarasutra into four
            bhumis of the Yogacara. The first yogabhumi consists in taking all existing dharmas as perceptual objects (ālambana). The second yogabhumi consists in understanding that there is no
            external object of knowledge (grāhya); since everything appears as mind only (cittamātra) no dharma is different from mind. The third yogabhumi consists in transcending this cittamātra and
            understanding that, because no grāhya exists, no corresponding cognizing subject (grāhaka) can exist either; cittamātra then becomes residence in the alambana of tathatā, a non-dual gnosis
            which is without the grāhaka-lakṣana. Finally the fourth yogabhumi is direct comprehension of the mahāyāna consisting in residence in gnosis absolutely free from appearance (nirābhāsa),
            and in which nāman and lakṣaṇa as well as grāhya and grāhaka have disappeared. In the same author's Upadesa (fol. 266 a) these four stages are referred to as the four bhumis having
            respectively the ālambana of the existence of things in terms of the extreme of eternalism (as opposed to nihilism), the ālambana of cittamātra, the ālambana of tathatā, and absence of
            ālambana.</desc>
                </change>
                <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT23703-138-003-6">
                    <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
    </text>
</TEI>